<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<?oxygen RNGSchema="http://libxml1a.unl.edu:8080/cocoon/scholarlyediting/scholarlyediting.rng" type="xml"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
    <teiHeader xml:lang="eng">
        <fileDesc>
            <titleStmt>
                <title level="m" type="main">The Firstling/Erstling/He Complex</title>
                <title level="m" type="sub">An Introduction</title>
                <author xml:id="tc">Tanya Clement</author>
<author xml:id="gd">Gaby Divay</author>
                
            </titleStmt>
            <editionStmt>
                <edition>
                    <date>2012</date>
                </edition>
            </editionStmt>
            <publicationStmt>
                <idno type="file">intro.baroness</idno>
                <idno type="edition">baroness</idno>
                <authority>Scholary Editing: The Annual of the Association for Documentary
                    Editing</authority>
                <address>
                    <addrLine>http://www.scholarlyediting.org</addrLine>
                </address>
                <publisher>Association for Documentary Editing</publisher>
                <publisher>University of Nebraska&#8211;Lincoln</publisher>
                <distributor>
                    <name>Center for Digital Research in the Humanities</name>
                    <address>
                        <addrLine>319 Love Library</addrLine>
                        <addrLine>University of Nebraska&#8211;Lincoln</addrLine>
                        <addrLine>Lincoln, NE 68588-4100</addrLine>
                        <addrLine>http://cdrh.unl.edu</addrLine>
                    </address>
                </distributor>
                <date>2012</date>
                <availability>
                    <p>Scholary Editing: The Annual of the Association for Documentary Editing is
                        freely distributed by the Association for Documentary Editing and the Center
                        for Digital Research in the Humanities at the University of Nebraska-Lincoln
                        and licensed under a Creative Commons Attribution-NonCommercial-ShareAlike
                        3.0 Unported License</p>
                </availability>
            </publicationStmt>
            <seriesStmt>
                <title level="j">Scholarly Editing: The Annual of the Association for Documentary
                    Editing</title>
                <respStmt>
                    <resp>editor</resp>
                    <name xml:id="ag">Amanda Gailey</name>
                </respStmt>
                <respStmt>
                    <resp>editor</resp>
                    <name xml:id="awj">Andrew Jewell</name>
                </respStmt>
                <idno type="vol">33</idno>
                <idno type="ISSN">2167-1257</idno>
            </seriesStmt>
            <sourceDesc>
                <bibl>
                    <note>Born digital.</note>
                </bibl>
            </sourceDesc>
        </fileDesc>
        <revisionDesc>
            <change when="2012-02-15" who="#lkw">proofreading / citations</change>
            <change when="2012-02-09" who="#awj">markup in TEI XML</change>
            <change when="2011" who="#tc">Initial Creation in HTML</change>
        </revisionDesc>
    </teiHeader>
    <text>
        <front><head type="main">The Firstling/Erstling/He Complex:</head>
            <head type="sub">An Introduction</head>
            <byline>Tanya Clement</byline>
            <byline>Gaby Divay</byline></front>
             <body>



<div xml:id="desc"><head type="main">Description of the Edition</head>

<p>"The Firstling/Erstling/He Complex" edition is our collaborative
 attempt to represent a complex text written by the Baroness
 Elsa von Freytag-Loringhoven (1874-1927). The edition comprises a 
cluster of works that the Baroness wrote over a twenty-year period that
 includes thirty-three versions with multiple titles
 in two languages. The "Firstling/Erstling/He" "complex" includes all of
 the works&#8212;no matter how many versions they each include&#8212;as part of this
 larger "complex" or "text" (in the Barthesian sense). According to 
Barthes, the "text" is not one object; it is  a "methodolgical field" 
that is "held only in language" and exists in the "movement of 
discourse" and in the "process of demonstration."<ptr target="#note1" xml:id="nr1" n="1" /> The 
"work," on the other hand is an actual, physical object that one might 
find in a library or an archive that can include multiple versions.<ptr target="#note2" xml:id="nr2" n="2" /> As a result of the many possibilities presented by the archive, we consider the versions included
 here as an open-ended complex "text" in this sense, one that is subject to dynamic expansion and the potential
 discovery of further related works in the Freytag-Loringhoven papers.</p> 
  
    <p>The manuscripts upon which these digital surrogates are based reside in the <ref type="url" target="http://hdl.handle.net/1903.1/1501">Papers
    of Elsa von Freytag-Loringhoven</ref> in Special Collections at the 
University of Maryland (UM), College Park, Libraries. The manuscripts 
belong to Series III, "Manuscripts,
        Drafts, Notes, and Drawings, 1919-1927." Most are found in Box 
2, Folder
        3, titled "Firstling (Erstling, He)."  Versions 13 and 14.1-4
        are in Box 3, Folder 23, titled "Pfingsten," while version
        10 was discovered in Box 2, Folder 67, titled "Liebe." Written 
over the course of twenty years, approximately one third of the poems 
are in German, tend to be composed in a conventional form, and were most
 likely written in the late 1890s before the Baroness moved from Germany
 to the United States. Two thirds are in English and are dated between 
1923-1924 when the Baroness had returned to Germany after living in the 
U.S. for many years. </p>

  <p>Our "Firstling/Erstling/He" edition includes an edited, electronic 
representation of the thirty-three versions we have identified as part 
of this complex. The underlying TEI P5 XML and the <ref type="url" target="http://v-machine.org/">Versioning Machine</ref>
 interface allow for comparisons across the complex. The transcriptions 
are accompanied by color images that further facilitate this process. 
There is a <ref type="url" target="help.baroness.html">help</ref> 
section, which describes how one might move around within the interface.
  In this introduction and the comments that accompany the edition, we 
discuss why we chose to edit this particular cluster and why the formal 
process of versioning helps reveal the shifting content of the 
Baroness's constantly revised and transformed works.</p>  
  </div>
<div xml:id="choice"><head type="main">Choosing the "Firstling/Erstling/He" Complex</head>
  <p>The Baroness's papers were found as part of Djuna Barnes's literary
 papers upon their acquisition by the University of Maryland Libraries 
in 1973. Djuna Barnes, who once wrote to a scholar interested in the 
Baroness's poetry that her manuscripts "are al [sic] sixes and sevens" 
was referring to the fact that the works within the Baroness's papers 
are composed out of numerous variants that are at times difficult for a 
reader to relate to each other. We chose to represent this particular 
complex of variants in an electronic environment because it allows us to
 show how, for the Baroness, this process of versioning was a way to 
express variant ideas as textual differences. For instance, some of the 
versions are very clean such as "Firstling" <ref type="figure">2<figure>
                    <head>Firstling 2</head>
                    <figDesc>manuscript image
        </figDesc>
                    <graphic url="./versions/images/litmss-012892-0002.jpg" />
                    </figure></ref><!--<a href="#" onclick="jkpopimage('Firstling 2', './versions/images/litmss-012892-0002.jpg', 600, 700, 'manuscript image.'); return false">2</a>-->.
 Others appear as construction sites, but once we are able to see the 
Baroness's use of different inks in the poems themselves, in marginal 
variants, or in notes (as in versions <ref type="figure">1.1-1.6<figure>
        <head>Firstling 1.1-1.6</head>
        <figDesc>manuscript image
        </figDesc>
        <graphic url="./versions/images/litmss-012892-0001.jpg" />
    </figure></ref><!--<a href="#" onclick="jkpopimage('Firstling 1.1-1.6', './versions/images/litmss-012892-0001.jpg', 600, 700, 'manuscript image.'); return false">1.1-1.6</a>--> or <ref type="figure">4.1-4.4<figure>
            <head>Firstling 4.1-4.4</head>
            <figDesc>manuscript image
            </figDesc>
            <graphic url="./versions/images/litmss-012892-0003.jpg" />
        </figure></ref><!--<a href="#" onclick="jkpopimage('4.1-4.4', './versions/images/litmss-012892-0003.jpg', 600, 700, 'manuscript image.'); return false">4.1-4.4</a>-->) her intentions for the text become clearer. Without the color images, these associations could go unnoticed.</p>

 <p>We created this edition because we believe that the Baroness has left interesting texts to explore. Considered
  at times a marginal figure, she has nevertheless had a significant impact on
  art and scholarship in three major capitals, namely Berlin, New York and Paris.<ptr target="#note3" xml:id="nr3" n="3" /> Between 1918 and 1929, the Baroness published approximately forty of her poems in little magazines such as <hi rend="italic">Broom</hi>, <hi rend="italic">Liberator</hi>, <hi rend="italic">The Little Review</hi>, <hi rend="italic">transatlantic review</hi>, <hi rend="italic">transition</hi>, and the single issue of <hi rend="italic">New York Dada</hi>.
     Born Else Hildegard Ploetz on July 12, 1874, in Swinem&#252;nde on the 
Baltic Sea, she ran away to Berlin in 1892, where she became involved in
 the Bohemian theatre circles. In 1913, she then moved to New York City where she met and married the penniless Baron Leo von 
Freytag-Loringhoven. It was in New York, after the Baron had returned to
 Germany during the war and subsequently committed suicide, that 
Freytag-Loringhoven became entrenched in the Greenwich Village artist 
movement and began her brief and successful writing career as "the 
Baroness."  Her peers, other artists and poets, consistently remarked on 
 her influences: Ernest Hemingway was her avid proponent at the <hi rend="italic">transatlantic review</hi>,
 Ezra Pound writes of her in his Cantos, William Carlos Williams 
dedicates an entire chapter of his autobiography to her, and her extant 
collection of poetry is due to Djuna Barnes diligently collecting what 
Barnes considered important in her friend's work. Despite all this 
attention from her contemporaries, until
very recently,<ptr target="#note4" xml:id="nr4" n="4" /> almost all critical attention has been directed at her Dada
  art, including her collaborations with Man Ray and Marcel Duchamp, her collages, and her spontaneous performance
  art. This edition of her "Firstling/Erstling/He" complex is an addition to the burgeoning scholarship on her poetry.</p>
</div>
<div xml:id="theory"><head type="main">Theoretical and Critical Approaches</head>     

  <p>With this edition, readers can see how the Baroness engaged the 
dialectics of time, language, and perspective as she versioned her 
poems. The Baroness's revisioning emphasizes a relationship between 
various periods of her life and the languages in which she expressed 
herself at those times. In 1923-1924, as the Baroness crafted some of 
these works, she sent them in letters to her friend Djuna Barnes in 
Paris, hoping that Barnes would get them published. In regard to the 
poems in this complex, she asked Barnes to have her German poem 
"Erstling" and her English version "Firstling" printed on one page. They
 are shown in her manuscript pages side by side as a seemingly simple 
 translation in <ref type="figure">3.1 and 3.2<figure>
         <head>Firstling 3.1-3.2</head>
         <figDesc>manuscript image
         </figDesc>
         <graphic url="./versions/images/litmss-004371-0001.jpg" />
     </figure></ref><!--<a href="#" onclick="jkpopimage('Firstling 3.1-3.2', './versions/images/litmss-004371-0001.jpg', 600, 700, 'manuscript image.'); return false">3.1 and 3.2</a>-->. The Baroness writes in her note to Barnes:
    <q rend="block">
     <p>"The German first version always was touching pathetic naiv [sic]
         &#8212; <hi rend="underline">finished</hi>. What is interesting about the <hi rend="underline">2 together</hi> is their
      vast difference of emotion &#8212; time &#8212; knowledge &#8212; pain. <hi rend="underline">That is</hi> why
      they should / be <hi rend="underline">printed together</hi>. For they are 1 + 2, the same
      poem &#8212; person &#8212; sentiment, life stretch between one &#8212; divided &#8212; assembled
      &#8212; dissembled. The German one is young &#8212; naiv &#8212; ingenious &#8212; the English
      one ripe &#8212; experienced &#8212; bitter" (Note <ref type="figure">5.3<figure>
              <head>Note 5.3</head>
              <figDesc>Note 5.3</figDesc>
              <graphic url="./versions/images/litmss-012892-0004b.jpg" />
          </figure></ref><!--<a href="#" onclick="jkpopimage('Note 5.3', './versions/images/litmss-012892-0004b.jpg', 600, 700, 'Note 5.3'); return false">5.3</a>--> / <ref type="figure">5.3 verso<figure>
                  <head>5.3 verso</head>
                  <figDesc>5.3 verso</figDesc>
                  <graphic url="./versions/images/litmss-012892-0005.jpg" />
              </figure></ref><!--<a href="#" onclick="jkpopimage('5.3 verso','./versions/images/litmss-012892-0005.jpg', 600, 700, 'manuscript image.'); return false">5.3 verso</a>-->).</p>

    </q></p>
  <p> In describing the assembling and disassembling involved in 
versioning these works, the Baroness gestures towards the communicative 
exchange or dialectic we attempt to represent with this edition. One 
textual theory that has been useful for understanding the internal 
dialectics at play within this complex is Jerome McGann's "textual 
condition" in which he understands the "text" (again, in the Barthesian 
sense of the word) to mean a gathering of moments in which "certain 
communicative interchanges are being practiced."<ptr target="#note5" xml:id="nr5" n="5" />   In the 
case of this complex, the Baroness's transformations from "Erstling" 
into "Firstling" and "[Erste] Liebe" into "He," reflects her changing 
perspectives between past and present perceptions of the same event or 
person.</p>
 </div>
   <div xml:id="vm">     <head type="main">Using TEI Encoding and the Versioning Machine </head>

<p>
  
  "Assembling and disassembling" describes the Baroness's process as she
 works and reworks her poems, but it can also describe the reader's 
experience in reading the multiple versions compared in this edition. 
The reader's experience is shaped by how the versions included in the 
edition appear in the Versioning Machine interface as both assembled and
 disassembled. To "assemble" this edition, we are using the Text 
Encoding Initiative (TEI) method for encoding and the XSLT, CSS, and 
JavaScript styles that comprise the Versioning Machine's open-source 
framework for creating the user interface. Though the edition is based 
on versions, it is not presented as a genetic edition. That is, the 
genetic critic's focus on versions is one that "accepts a teleological 
model of textuality and constantly confronts the question of authorship"
 (<hi rend="italic">Genetic Criticism</hi> 2). Because our immediate goal is not to 
represent a teleological model of this complex (though this is a 
possible reading), but to engage an evolving textual dialectic, we 
consider our approach guided by co-editor Clement's theory of textual 
performance. In this theory, the Barthesian text is always and only 
known in performance&#8212;that is, the act of reading the multiple versions 
in manuscript and print, the various notes and letters and comments of 
contemporaries or current readers is an embodied event that occurs 
within a time, a space, and with a collaborative audience  that is 
contradictory to the teleological perspective.<ptr target="#note6" xml:id="nr6" n="6" /></p>

<p> Because of these theoretical underpinnings, we are presenting this 
complex in a space that facilitates this notion of "textual 
performance"&#8212;that is, we foreground the fact that the "situated" or 
embodied reader engages the versions that comprise the text.  Assembled 
in <ref type="url" target="http://baronesselsa.org/firstling/versions/firstling.html">the VM interface</ref>
 from left to right, the versions first appear to the reader in a 
prescribed order. The Versioning Machine style sheets
    transform the TEI encoding to transform the texts into this HTML 
interface
     facilitating access to (1) all of the versions in a horizontally 
scrolling
      page; (2) the comparisons we have made between the versions;
      and (3) color JPEGs derived from archival quality TIFFs. The 
default order of the panels (each of which represent a version of a 
work) is based on the order in which these manuscript pages appear in 
their respective folders in the physical manuscript archive. Multiple 
versions appear on one manuscript page; as well, versions continue 
across multiple manuscript pages. Even so, each version appears on a 
separate panel and is numbered according to where it appears in the 
physical archival folder. In the physical archive, for example,
      the first six versions and the first note appear on the first 
manuscript page
      in the first folder that relates to this complex (from series 3, 
box 2,
folder 3). Consequently, in the edition, <ref type="figure">these versions are numbered 1.1-1.6<figure>
        <head>Firstling 1.1-1.6</head>
        <figDesc>manuscript image</figDesc>
        <graphic url="./versions/images/litmss-012892-0001.jpg" />
    </figure></ref><!--<a href="#" onclick="jkpopimage('Firstling 1.1-1.6', './versions/images/litmss-012892-0001.jpg', 600, 700, 'manuscript image.'); return false">these versions are numbered 1.1-1.6</a>-->. On the image, we can see
      1.1 in red ink; 1.2 is a typescript of "Firstling," 1.3 is another
      untitled red ink version; 1.4 is titled "Chest Apendicitis" [sic], etc. <ref type="figure">The
          next "Firstling" version<figure>
              <head>Firstling 2</head>
              <figDesc>manuscript image</figDesc>
              <graphic url="./versions/images/litmss-012892-0002.jpg" />
          </figure></ref><!--<a href="#" onclick="jkpopimage('Firstling 2', './versions/images/litmss-012892-0002.jpg', 600, 700, 'manuscript image.'); return false">The
      next "Firstling" version</a>--> is numbered 2, because it is the only version on the second page. <ref type="figure">On the next page<figure>
              <head>Erstling 3.1</head>
              <figDesc>manuscript image</figDesc>
              <graphic url="./versions/images/litmss-004371-0001.jpg" />
          </figure></ref><!--<a href="#" onclick="jkpopimage('Erstling 3.1', './versions/images/litmss-004371-0001.jpg', 600, 700, 'manuscript image.'); return false">On the next page</a>-->, an "Erstling" version is 3.1, while the next "Firstling" version is numbered 3.2 because it appears to its right, and so on. </p>

  <p>The edition is further "assembled" by the fact that we have encoded
 or marked words and phrases in the underlying XML that are related 
across works. As a result, the reader can click
    on any line to see and compare other lines in other versions that we
 have identified as related (see Figure
      1 for an example). In order to maximize this element of readerly engagement, we
      are using <ref type="url" target="http://www.tei-c.org/release/doc/tei-p5-doc/en/html/TC.html#TCAPLK">location-referenced</ref> and <ref type="url" target="http://www.tei-c.org/release/doc/tei-p5-doc/en/html/TC.html#TCAPPS">parallel
       segmentation</ref> methods described in the TEI P5 encoding 
guidelines to note the relationships between the thirty-three versions. 
The set of tags that the TEI provides for encoding these relationships 
is particularly useful: the VM interface manifests the code in 
line-by-line comparisons (with parallel segmentation encoding) alongside
 comparisons of "chunks" of text (with location-referenced encoding). 
 For example, Figure 1 shows that the two lines "BLOWN / ROSE" in version <ref type="figure">1.1<figure>
         <head>Firstling 1.1-1.6</head>
         <figDesc>manuscript image</figDesc>
         <graphic url="./versions/images/litmss-012892-0001.jpg" />
     </figure></ref><!--<a href="#" onclick="jkpopimage('Firstling 1.1-1.6','./versions/images/litmss-012892-0001.jpg', 600, 700, 'manuscript image.'); return false">1.1</a>--> expand to three lines (<del type="overstrike">BLOWN</del> ROSE / BLOWN BLOWN / ROSE") in version 1.2 and again to four lines ("ROSE <del type="overstrike">SPRAY</del> / WAY / CAST / <del type="overstrike">BLOWN</del>") in version 1.3. Figure 2 shows a snippet of this encoding in the underlying TEI document.</p> 
        



   

<figure xml:id="fig1">
<head>Figure 1</head>
<figDesc>Figure 1</figDesc>
<graphic url="./vm-images/fig1.png"/>
</figure>


    <figure xml:id="fig2">
        <head>Figure 2</head>
        <figDesc>Figure 2</figDesc>
        <graphic url="./vm-images/teifig.png"/>
    </figure>

       
    
      
    
    <p>
      A brief explanation of this encoding will help explain how the 
edition is assembled. Any words inside the "app" element (in Figure 2)
 will be highlighted together in the HTML interface. The "rdg" element, 
denoting one variant reading, includes a "wit" attribute that shows 
which version (each given a unique ID, such as "v23a") contains which 
textual variation. Also, the "app" element, which correlates the variant
 readings, includes a "loc" attribute that will associate any of these 
chunks of text with any other in the entire document, so that those 
words will also be highlighted with the words in this "app" element. 
Displayed in the interface, these encoding structures can be used to 
show poetic changes that occur over time. Changes over time mean changes
 that quite often do not fit neatly in line-by-line comparisons, such as
 changes that cross line boundaries and elude the traditionally 
hierarchical structures required by other TEI-element sets. For an 
example, see the evolution of "ROSE" in Figure 1 in the VM interface and the same information in Figure 2 as it appears within the underlying text encoded document.</p>
        
        
       <figure xml:id="fig3">
           <head>Figure 3</head>
           <figDesc>Figure 3</figDesc>
           <graphic url="./vm-images/fig3.png"/>
       </figure>
           
  
  <p>In this edition, we use images and mouse-over boxes to indicate 
points in the text that rely on non-linear space to make meaning. Figure 3, for example, shows the word "BLU<del type="overstrike">FF</del>SH"
 with a dashed line under it to indicate that there is more information 
about this point in the text. A mouseover shows a pop-up box that 
indicates that "LUSH BLO" also appears in this spot. Pulling up the 
manuscript image shows a constellation of words that is non-linear and 
therefore difficult to represent in text alone.</p>
  <p>Like the Baroness, who seems to play with the versions and cluster 
and
    recluster them, a reader of this edition can disassemble and 
reassemble
    the order by which we have chosen to present the versions. The 
interface allows users to move version panels into any sequence
    within the horizontal narrative of the page, creating an environment
 in
    which the evolution of versions (and the sequential time these 
documents
evince) is not imposed entirely by the editors. Figure 4, for instance, shows a comparison between "Firstling" <ref type="figure">1.1<figure>
        <head>Firstling 1.1-1.6</head>
        <figDesc>manuscript image</figDesc>
        <graphic url="./versions/images/litmss-012892-0001.jpg" />
    </figure></ref><!--<a href="#" onclick="jkpopimage('Firstling 1.1-1.6', './versions/images/litmss-012892-0001.jpg', 600, 700, 'manuscript image.'); return false">1.1</a>--> and "Erstling"  <ref type="figure">6<figure>
            <head>Erstling 6</head>
            <figDesc>manuscript image</figDesc>
            <graphic url="./versions/images/litmss-012892-0006.jpg" />
        </figure></ref><!--<a href="#" onclick="jkpopimage('Erstling 6', './versions/images/litmss-012892-0006.jpg', 600, 700, 'manuscript image.'); return false">6</a>--> with <ref type="figure">Note 4.5<figure>
                <head>Note 4.5</head>
                <figDesc>manuscript image</figDesc>
                <graphic url="./versions/images/litmss-012892-0003b.jpg" />
            </figure></ref><!--<a href="#" onclick="jkpopimage('Note 4.5', './versions/images/litmss-012892-0003b.jpg', 600, 700, 'manuscript image.'); return false">Note 4.5</a>--> in the middle. As explained above, clicking on any line
    shows comparisons between poems that are highlighted according to the underlying
    encoding. In the VM interface,
    the reader can reorder the panels, or highlight various, multiple clusters
    across the versions to create and identify new relationships.</p>
       <figure xml:id="fig4">
           <head>Figure 4</head>
           <figDesc>Figure 4</figDesc>
           <graphic url="./vm-images/fig2.png"/>
       </figure>
            
  
  
  
    <p>We have chosen to include annotations and images of the manuscript pages
     alongside transcriptions. Both serve to remind readers that these
     encoded transcriptions reflect a situated, edited instantiation that has
     been assembled to create a particular kind of reading experience. At the
     same time, the VM interface also introduces the reader to the disassembled
     nature of the Baroness's papers. Sometimes, the relationships between versions seem obvious. For example,
      five tentative versions written in red pen are surrounding the typed "Firstling" on
      the manuscript page comprising "Firstling" <ref type="figure">1.1-1.6<figure>
              <head>Firstling 1.1-1.6</head>
              <figDesc>manuscript image</figDesc>
              <graphic url="./versions/images/litmss-012892-0001.jpg" />
          </figure></ref><!--<a href="#" onclick="jkpopimage('Firstling 1.1-1.6', './versions/images/litmss-012892-0001.jpg', 600, 700, 'manuscript image.'); return false"> 1.1-1.6</a>-->.
     All are toying with endings like "heart flayed," "flayed
     heart," "woeful," "arid," or "woe heart." The
     Baroness, in her note to Djuna Barnes at the bottom, seems to have
     worked out "flayed heart" as her preferred expression (see Figure
     1).</p>

       <!--<figure xml:id="fig5">
           <head>Figure 5</head>
           <figDesc>Figure 5</figDesc>
           <graphic url="./vm-images/fig1.png"/>
       </figure>-->


      
    <p> On the other hand, some of the relationships between versions are not
        quite as clear. For example, in the upper right corner of the page on which we find version <ref type="figure">1.4<figure>
                <head>Firstling 1.1-1.6</head>
                <figDesc>manuscript image</figDesc>
                <graphic url="./versions/images/litmss-012892-0001.jpg" />
            </figure></ref><!--<a href="#" onclick="jkpopimage('Firstling 1.1-1.6', './versions/images/litmss-012892-0001.jpg', 600, 700, 'manuscript image.'); return false">1.4</a>-->,
 there is a unique alternative title "Chest (or: Heart) Apendicitis" 
[sic], and all six versions on this page fluctuate between "Sun" or 
"Love" as
     the agent in the opening line. Further, while preparing this 
edition,
     we discovered related versions in unrelated folders, and seemingly 
related
     folders without relevant versions. This is partly due to the fact 
that Anglophone
     scholars are unaware of earlier German drafts, while those 
interested in
     German versions find no indication that a given poem also exists in
     English. Also, messy versions
     such as "First Love" (<ref type="figure">8.3<figure>
             <head>First Love 8.3</head>
             <figDesc>manuscript image</figDesc>
             <graphic url="./versions/images/litmss-012892-0009.jpg" />
         </figure></ref><!--<a href="#" onclick="jkpopimage('First Love 8.3', './versions/images/litmss-012892-0009.jpg', 600, 700, 'manuscript image.'); return false">8.3</a>-->), "[Firstling]" (<ref type="figure">9.2<figure>
                 <head>9.1</head>
                 <figDesc>manuscript image</figDesc>
                 <graphic url="./versions/images/litmss-012892-0010.jpg" />
             </figure></ref><!--<a href="#" onclick="jkpopimage('9.1', './versions/images/litmss-012892-0010.jpg', 600, 700, 'manuscript image.'); return false">9.2</a>-->), or "He" (<ref type="figure">11<figure>
                     <head>He 11</head>
                     <figDesc>manuscript image</figDesc>
                     <graphic url="./versions/images/litmss-012916-0001.jpg" />
                 </figure></ref><!--<a href="#" onclick="jkpopimage('He 11', './versions/images/litmss-012916-0001.jpg', 600, 700, 'manuscript image.'); return false">11</a>-->) show that the Baroness used versioning to develop multiple works at the same time (See Figure 3 for an example).</p>  
  
 </div>
<div xml:id="reduct">  <head type="main">Poetic Techniques: Reduction and Translation</head>
  
  <p>Between 1910 and 1923 the Baroness moved from Germany to the United
 States and back to Germany again, all the while writing and living in 
the languages of both cultures. Upon returning to Germany in 1923, she 
wrote to Djuna Barnes saying she lamented her weakening skills in 
English: 
  
  <q rend="block">I only move in English sounds. I am homesick for 
English language, my ear declines, my taste nauseated by German 
sound&#8212;and yet I lose my facility in English, words come not easy, 
sometimes meaning is doubtful, new expressions do not present 
themselves. As much as I read English, it is not alive&#8212;living, because I
 am not, hence no fluctuation, instigation&#8212;creation . . . must again 
dream in English . . . I am left drifting old wreck&#8212;no I cannot&#8212;I 
cannot&#8212;I cannot, I am too proud!
    I cannot stand the Germans, I cannot stand their language. I am 
traitor here!<ptr target="#note7" xml:id="nr7" n="7" />
  </q></p>
  <p>In particular, the works in this edition show that the Baroness 
used reduction and translation as techniques that express her 
perspectives on both German and American cultures and languages as they 
correspond to her changing life circumstances. The difference between a 
messy, early version of "Firstling" (<ref type="figure">9.2<figure>
        <head>Erstling 9.1</head>
        <figDesc>manuscript image</figDesc>
        <graphic url="./versions/images/litmss-012892-0010.jpg" />
    </figure></ref><!--<a href="#" onclick="jkpopimage('Erstling 9.1', './versions/images/litmss-012892-0010.jpg', 600, 700, 'manuscript image.'); return false">9.2</a>-->) and the neat typescript of "Firstling" (<ref type="figure">2<figure>
            <head>Firstling 2</head>
            <figDesc>manuscript image</figDesc>
            <graphic url="./versions/images/litmss-012892-0002.jpg" />
        </figure></ref><!--<a href="#" onclick="jkpopimage('Firstling 2', './versions/images/litmss-012892-0002.jpg', 600, 700, 'manuscript image.'); return false">2</a>-->)
 indicates that the Baroness started with longer German poems, which she
 reduced considerably as she translated them into English, a process of 
reduction we can follow in the edition. </p>
  <p>Steeped in a neo-romantic movement that was popular in 
German-speaking countries around 1900, the Baroness's early poems in 
German are more like sonnets or iambic quatrains that adhere to strictly
 prescribed
    forms. The Baroness consistently "reduces" these complete lines by 
crossing out connective articles, pronouns, conjunctions and 
prepositions to achieve a simpler, more modern style. In the fourth
line in version <ref type="figure">13<figure>
        <head>[Erstling] 13</head>
        <figDesc>manuscript image</figDesc>
        <graphic url="./versions/images/litmss-012917-0001.jpg" />
    </figure></ref><!--<a href="#" onclick="jkpopimage('[Erstling] 13','./versions/images/litmss-012917-0001.jpg', 600, 700, 'manuscript image.'); return false">13</a>-->, for example, "Glieder &#8212; Blei / Limbs &#8212; Lead" undergoes a reduction from <ref type="figure">14.3<figure>
            <head>[Erstling 14]</head>
            <figDesc>manuscript image</figDesc>
            <graphic url="./versions/images/litmss-012917-0003.jpg" />
        </figure></ref><!--<a href="#" onclick="jkpopimage('[Erstling 14]','./versions/images/litmss-012917-0003.jpg', 600, 700, 'manuscript image.'); return false">14.3</a>-->,
 "Die Glieder sind schwer wie Blei / The limbs are as heavy as lead." 
With these examples, we can note how the systematic elimination of the 
article "die," the verb "sind," the attribute "schwer," and the 
conjunction "wie" leave the two nouns stripped bare in the later 
versions. Yet, these works manage to evoke the same essential 
combination of "lead" and "limbs" with intensity. Reductions of this 
sort eventually lead to the bare Dada-like word columns in "Erstling" 
and "Firstling" on image <ref type="figure">3.1<figure>
        <head>Erstling 3.1</head>
        <figDesc>manuscript image</figDesc>
        <graphic url="./versions/images/litmss-004371-0001.jpg" />
    </figure></ref><!--<a href="#" onclick="jkpopimage('Erstling 3.1', './versions/images/litmss-004371-0001.jpg', 600, 700, 'manuscript image.'); return false">3.1</a>-->. But no matter how monosyllabic these lines may have become, they still carry
    a faint echo of the original rhymes, as for instance in English "past
    &#8212; cast," and "wart &#8212; heart" in <ref type="figure">3.2<figure>
            <head>3.1 and 3.2</head>
            <figDesc>manuscript image</figDesc>
            <graphic url="./versions/images/litmss-004371-0001.jpg" />
        </figure></ref><!--<a href="#" onclick="jkpopimage('3.1 and 3.2', './versions/images/litmss-004371-0001.jpg', 600, 700, 'manuscript image.'); return false">3.2</a>-->. Another example appears in <ref type="figure">9.1<figure>
                <head>9.1</head>
                <figDesc>manuscript image</figDesc>
                <graphic url="./versions/images/litmss-012892-0010.jpg" />
            </figure></ref><!--<a href="#" onclick="jkpopimage('9.1', './versions/images/litmss-012892-0010.jpg', 600, 700, 'manuscript image.'); return false">9.1</a>--> (a
      half-sonnet), <ref type="figure">13<figure>
              <head>[Erstling] 13</head>
              <figDesc>manuscript image</figDesc>
              <graphic url="./versions/images/litmss-012917-0001.jpg" />
          </figure></ref><!--<a href="#" onclick="jkpopimage('[Erstling] 13','./versions/images/litmss-012917-0001.jpg', 600, 700, 'manuscript image.'); return false">13</a>--> (two stanzas with crossed out words), and <ref type="figure">3.1<figure>
                  <head>3.1 and 3.2</head>
                  <figDesc>manuscript image</figDesc>
                  <graphic url="./versions/images/litmss-004371-0001.jpg" />
              </figure></ref><!--<a href="#" onclick="jkpopimage('3.1 and 3.2', './versions/images/litmss-004371-0001.jpg', 600, 700, 'manuscript image.'); return false">3.1</a>--> (a column), which adheres to the Baroness's method of stripping older poems down into simpler word columns in English. </p>
  
  
  <p>As she reduced, the Baroness also translated imagery and symbols 
into a more abstract form of expression across the later versions. On 
note <ref type="figure">5.3 verso<figure>
        <head>Note 5.3</head>
        <figDesc>manuscript image</figDesc>
        <graphic url="./versions/images/litmss-012892-0005.jpg" />
    </figure></ref><!--<a href="#" onclick="jkpopimage('Note 5.3','./versions/images/litmss-012892-0005.jpg', 600, 700, 'manuscript image.'); return false">5.3 verso</a>-->, the Baroness tells Barnes that the German "Erstling" (<ref type="figure">3.1<figure>
            <head>Erstling 3.1</head>
            <figDesc>manuscript image</figDesc>
            <graphic url="./versions/images/litmss-004371-0001.jpg" />
        </figure></ref><!--<a href="#" onclick="jkpopimage('Erstling 3.1', './versions/images/litmss-004371-0001.jpg', 600, 700, 'manuscript image.'); return false">3.1</a>-->) was "touching and naiv [sic]," and the English "Firstling" (<ref type="figure">3.2<figure>
                <head>Firstling 3.2</head>
                <figDesc>manuscript image</figDesc>
                <graphic url="./versions/images/litmss-004371-0001.jpg" />
            </figure></ref><!--<a href="#" onclick="jkpopimage('Firstling 3.2','./versions/images/litmss-004371-0001.jpg', 600, 700, 'manuscript image.'); return false">3.2</a>-->)
 "bitter and grim". Indeed, these two poems represent two different 
viewpoints: one is reflecting an 1896 viewpoint, while the other has the
 hindsight perspective of 1923-24.  We can see this grimness in how the 
Baroness replaced the entire "Aderbaum" (Vein-Tree) imagery of the six 
German variants with a "cast-away rose" metaphor that remains constant 
in all "Firstling" and "He" versions. The soiled innocence of the wilted
 rose present in the English versions replaces the more immediate 
sadness or dejection of the German poems that do not use abstract 
expressions. </p>
  <p>
  Finally, the Baroness titles the poems with puns that draw on their 
biographical context: the "He" of the poems refers to her once-lover 
Ernst Hardt (1876-1947). She makes several puns out of his first and 
last names that can only be understood when read bilingually. "Ernest" 
provides the basis for wordplay such as "Erste" (or "First" in German), 
"Er" (or "He" in English), "Ernste Lieb" (or "Serious Love") and "To 
Earny/An Erni," which evokes in English what she saw as Hardt's 
materialistic, money-making ambitions.<ptr target="#note8" xml:id="nr8" n="8" /> Likewise, his surname, Hardt, 
becomes "heart" and "hard." The reductions and wordplay are lost if the 
complex is not read as a performance over time in two languages.</p>
  
  
  
  </div>
<div xml:id="concl">
<head type="main">Conclusion</head>
   <p> Ultimately, the goal of this edition is to set the multiple 
dialectics we see at work in the Baroness's "Firstling/Erstling/He" 
complex in conversation for readers. By presenting this rigorously 
encoded (and thus deeply structured) and rather complicated edition with
 many versions of the text that were written in two languages over two 
decades, we are inviting scholars and readers to explore the dialectic 
inherent to the creative process of disassembling and assembling text. 
The fact that we have presented these poems in thirty-three transcribed,
 translated, and imaged versions means that readers are not only enabled
 to do their own textual assembling and disassembling, but, in this 
process, they are invited to consider the role of documentary editing in
 the digital age. Reduction and translation were some of the Baroness's 
poetic methods and versioning is the process by which she enacted these 
methods. Versioning is also the process we have used to create this 
edition for readers. Certainly, the texts and the relationships we make 
visible in this way allow readers to explore traditional-looking 
documents (texts and images) with the kinds of advantages that a digital
 edition can afford, but the fact that we can make this complex, 
open-source text available online engages a new kind of affordance in 
digital documentary editing: we are inviting all willing readers into 
the messy performance of the textual performance of one text, to 
explore, to create, and to perform their own readings.
    </p></div></body>
<back><div type="notes">

  <note xml:id="note1">Roland Barthes, <hi rend="italic">Nouveaux essais critiques</hi> (Paris: ditions du Seuil, 1972,) 157.</note>

<note xml:id="note2">It should be noted that in some ways this Barthesian sense of "text" and "work" is contrary to how the terms are used by some in the editorial community. </note>
  
<note xml:id="note3">See the <ref type="url" target="http://hdl.handle.net/1903.1/1501">biographical introduction</ref>
 to the Elsa von Freytag-Loringhoven Papers at the University of 
Maryland. For a thorough account, see  Irene Gammel's cultural biography <hi rend="italic">Baroness Elsa: Gender, Dada, and Everyday Modernity: a Cultural
        Biography</hi>, Cambridge, Mass.: MIT Press, 2002.</note>
  
    <note xml:id="note4">Irene Gammel and Suzanne Zelaso have just published <hi rend="italic">Body Sweats</hi>, an edition of the Baroness's unpublished poems (see <hi rend="italic">Body Sweats: The Uncensored Writings of Elsa von Freytag-Loringhoven</hi>,
        edited by Irene Gammel and Suzanne Zelaso. Boston: MIT Press, 2011).</note>


<note xml:id="note5">Jerome J. McGann, <hi rend="italic">The Textual Condition</hi> (Princeton, N. J.: Princeton University Press, 1991), 21.</note>
    <note xml:id="note6">Tanya Clement, "Knowledge Representation and Digital Scholarly Editions in
        Theory and Practice." <hi rend="italic">Journal of the Text Encoding Initiative</hi> 1.1 (2011):
        2-15.</note>
<note xml:id="note7">Elsa von Freytag-Loringhoven, "Selections from the Letters of Elsa Baroness Von Freytag-Loringhoven," ed. Djuna Barnes,  <hi rend="italic">transition</hi> 11 (February 1928): 20.</note>
    <note xml:id="note8">See "To Earny/Erni," <ref type="url" target="http://hdl.handle.net/1903.1/8720">Ser. III, Box 4, Fd. 19</ref>, image 2 of 4. The Baroness also wrote a satirical poem about her affair with Ernst Hardt and his materialistic ambitions; see Elsa von Freytag-Loringhoven, "Es hat mal einen Ernst gegeben," ed. &amp; tr., Gaby Divay &amp; Jan Horner (Winnipeg: University of Manitoba, Archives &amp; Special Collections, 2000), <ref type="url" target="http://home.cc.umanitoba.ca/~divay/frl/txt_hardt.html">http://home.cc.umanitoba.ca/~divay/frl/txt_hardt.html</ref>.</note>
</div>

<!--<div xml:id="bibl">
  <list type="simple"><head type="main">Works Cited</head>       
  <item>Barthes, Roland. <hi rend="italic">Nouveaux essais critiques</hi>. Paris: ditions
    du Seuil, 1972.</item>
  <item>Bellemin-Nol, Jean. "Psychoanalytic Reading and the Avant-texte." In <hi rend="italic">Genetic
    Criticism: Texts and Avant-Textes</hi>, edited by Jed Deppman, Daniel
    Ferrer, and Michael Groden, 28-35.  Philadelphia: University
    of Pennsylvania Press, 2004.</item>
  
  <item>Clement, Tanya. "Knowledge Representation and Digital Scholarly Editions in
    Theory and Practice." <hi rend="italic">Journal of the Text Encoding Initiative</hi> 1.1 (2011):
    2-15.</item>
      <item>Divay, Gaby. "Abrechnung und Aufarbeitung im Gedicht: Else von Freytag-Loringhoven &#252;ber
          drei M&#228;nner (E. Hardt, A. Endell, F. P. Greve)." e-Ed, 2007.
      <ref target="http://home.cc.umanitoba.ca/~divay/psg/frlAbr05.html" type="url">http://home.cc.umanitoba.ca/~divay/psg/frlAbr05.html</ref></item>
  <item>&#8212;-. "Felix Paul Greve's &amp; Else von Freytag-Loringhoven's 1904/5 'Fanny
      Essler' Poems: His or Hers?" e-Ed, March 2005. <ref type="url" target="http://home.cc.umanitoba.ca/~divay/FEArt/">http://home.cc.umanitoba.ca/~divay/FEArt/</ref></item>
  
  <item>Essler, Fanny. "Gedichte. Ein Portr&#228;t: drei Sonette. Gedichte." <hi rend="italic">Die
    Freistatt </hi>(1904/5), e-edited by Gaby Divay. 2005.
      <ref target="http://home.cc.umanitoba.ca/~divay/FEPoems05/index.html#toc" type="url">http://home.cc.umanitoba.ca/~divay/FEPoems05/index.html#toc</ref></item>
  <item>Freytag-Loringhoven, Elsa von. [Autobiography]. University of Maryland, College Park, Literary Manuscripts. Typescript.</item>
  <item>&#8212;-. <hi rend="italic">Body Sweats: The Uncensored Writings of Elsa von Freytag-Loringhoven</hi>,
    edited by  Irene Gammel and Suzanne Zelaso. Boston: MIT Press, 2011.</item>
      <item>&#8212;-. "Cosmic Arithmetic." In  <hi rend="italic">In Transition</hi>, 2009. <ref type="url" target="http://digital.lib.umd.edu/transition/poem.jsp?pid=umd:55439">http://digital.lib.umd.edu/transition/poem.jsp?pid=umd:55439</ref></item>
  
  <item>&#8212;-. <hi rend="italic">The Elsa von Freytag-Loringhoven Papers</hi>. College Park, 
MD: University
    of Maryland, Literary Manuscripts. Collection. 
      <ref type="url" target="http://digital.lib.umd.edu/archivesum/actions.DisplayEADDoc.do?source=MdU.ead.litms.0009.xml&amp;style=ead">http://digital.lib.umd.edu/archivesum/actions.DisplayEADDoc.do?source=MdU.ead.litms.0009.xml&amp;style=ead</ref></item>
  <item>&#8212;-. "Es hat mal einen Ernst gegeben." Bilingual e-Ed. Feb. 2004. http://home.cc.umanitoba.ca/~divay/frl/txt_hardt.html</item>
  <item>&#8212;-. "Firstling." In <hi rend="italic"> Body Sweats: The Uncensored Writings
    of Elsa von Freytag-Loringhoven</hi>, edited by Irene Gammel and Suzanne
    Zelaso, 55. Boston: MIT Press, 2011. ["Firstling" version 3.2 in the
    present digitized edition] </item>
  <item>&#8212;-. <hi rend="italic">In Transition: Selected Poems by the
    Baroness Elsa von Freytag-Loringhoven</hi>, edited by  Tanya Clement.
      College Park, MD: University of Maryland Libraries, 2009. <ref type="url" target="http://digital.lib.umd.edu/transition/index.jsp">http://digital.lib.umd.edu/transition/index.jsp</ref></item>
  
  <item>&#8212;-. "Puckellonders sonderbare Geschichte." Bilingual
      e-Ed. 2001. <ref type="url" target="http://home.cc.umanitoba.ca/~divay/frl/txt_endell.html">http://home.cc.umanitoba.ca/~divay/frl/txt_endell.html</ref></item>
  
<item>&#8212;-. "Selections from the Letters of Elsa Baroness Von Freytag-Loringhoven." Edited by Djuna Barnes. <hi rend="italic">transition</hi> 11 (February 1928): 19-30.
</item>
   
  <item>Friedrich, Otto. <hi rend="italic">Before the Deluge: a Portrait of Berlin in the 1920s</hi>.
    New York: Harper Perennial, 1995.</item>
  <item>Gammel, Irene. <hi rend="italic">Baroness Elsa: Gender, Dada, and Everyday Modernity: a Cultural
    Biography</hi>. Cambridge, Mass.: MIT Press, 2002.</item>
  <item>Gammel, Irene, and Suzanne Zelazo. "'Harpsichords Metallic Howl': The Baroness
    Elsa von Freytag-Loringhoven's Sound Poetry." <hi rend="italic">Modernism/modernity</hi> 18.2
    (2011): 255-271.</item>
  
  <item>Greve, Felix Paul. <hi rend="italic">Fanny Essler: ein Berliner Roman</hi>. Stuttgart: A.
    Juncker, [1905].</item>
  <item>Grove, Frederick Philip. <hi rend="italic">The Papers of Frederick Philip Grove</hi>.
 Winnipeg:
    University of Manitoba, Archives &amp; Special Collections. 
Collection. 
      <ref target="http://www.umanitoba.ca/libraries/units/archives/collections/fpg/index.html" type="url">http://www.umanitoba.ca/libraries/units/archives/collections/fpg/index.html</ref></item>
  <item>  &#8212;-.<hi rend="italic"> Poems/Gedichte</hi>, edited by  Gaby Divay. Winnipeg: Wolf-Verlag,
    1993.</item>
  
      <item>&#8212;-. <hi rend="italic">Poems/Gedichte</hi>, edited by  Gaby Divay. e-Ed., 2007. <ref type="url" target="http://www.umanitoba.ca/libraries/units/archives/collections/fpg/pEd/index.html">http://www.umanitoba.ca/libraries/units/archives/collections/fpg/pEd/index.html</ref></item>
  <item>Hardt, Ernst. <hi rend="italic">Briefe an Ernst Hardt: eine Auswahl aus den Jahren
    1898-1947</hi>, edited by Tilla Goetz-Hardt, Jochen Meyer. Marbach:
    Deutsches Literaturarchiv, 1975.</item>
  <item>McGann, Jerome J. <hi rend="italic">The Textual Condition</hi>. Princeton, N. J.: Princeton
    University Press, 1991.</item>
      <item>Schrader, B&#228;rbel, and J&#252;rgen Schebera. <hi rend="italic">The Golden Twenties: Art
    and Literature in the Weimar Republic</hi>. New Haven: Yale University Press,
    1988.</item>
  
      <item>Sch&#252;ssler, Susanne. <hi rend="italic">Ernst Hardt: eine monographische Studie</hi>. Frankfurt
    ; New York: P. Lang, c1994.</item>
  <item>Richter, Hans. <hi rend="italic">Dada: Art and Anti-Art</hi>. New York: McGraw-Hill, 1965.</item>
  <item>Vanhoutte, Edward. "Prose Fiction and Modern Manuscripts." In <hi rend="italic">Electronic
    Textual Editing</hi>, edited by  Lou
    Burnard, Katherine O'Brien O'Keeffe, and John Unsworth, 161-180. New York:
    Modern Language Association of America, 2006.</item></list>
</div>-->

</back>   


    </text>
</TEI>
