<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
    <teiHeader xml:lang="eng">
        <fileDesc>
            <titleStmt>
                <title level="a" type="main">Editors' Introduction to the 2013 Issue of <hi
                        rend="italic">Scholarly Editing: The Annual of the Association for
                        Documentary Editing</hi>
                </title>

                <author>Amanda Gailey</author>
                <author>Andrew Jewell</author>
            </titleStmt>
            <editionStmt>
                <edition>
                    <date>2013</date>
                </edition>
            </editionStmt>
            <publicationStmt>
                <idno type="file">essay.v34intro</idno>
                <authority>Scholary Editing: The Annual of the Association for Documentary
                    Editing</authority>
                <address>
          <addrLine>http://www.scholarlyediting.org</addrLine>
        </address>
                <publisher>Association for Documentary Editing</publisher>
                <publisher>University of Nebraska&#8211;Lincoln</publisher>
                <distributor>
                    <name>Center for Digital Research in the Humanities</name>
                    <address>
            <addrLine>319 Love Library</addrLine>
            <addrLine>University of Nebraska&#8211;Lincoln</addrLine>
            <addrLine>Lincoln, NE 68588-4100</addrLine>
            <addrLine>http://cdrh.unl.edu</addrLine>
          </address>
                </distributor>
                <date>2013</date>
                <availability>
                    <p>Scholary Editing: The Annual of the Association for Documentary Editing is
                        freely distributed by the Association for Documentary Editing and the Center
                        for Digital Research in the Humanities at the University of Nebraska-Lincoln
                        and licensed under a Creative Commons Attribution-NonCommercial-ShareAlike
                        3.0 Unported License</p>
                </availability>
            </publicationStmt>
            <seriesStmt>
                <title level="j">Scholarly Editing: The Annual of the Association for Documentary
                    Editing</title>
                <respStmt>
                    <resp>editor</resp>
                    <name xml:id="aag">Amanda Gailey</name>
                </respStmt>
                <respStmt>
                    <resp>editor</resp>
                    <name xml:id="awj">Andrew Jewell</name>
                </respStmt>
                <idno type="vol">34</idno>
                <idno type="ISSN">2167-1257</idno>
            </seriesStmt>
            <sourceDesc>
                <bibl>
                    <note>Born digital.</note>
                </bibl>
            </sourceDesc>
        </fileDesc>
        <revisionDesc>
            <change when="2013-03-04" who="#aag">markup in TEI XML</change>
        </revisionDesc>
    </teiHeader>
    <text>
        <front>
            <head type="main">Editors' Introduction to the 2013 Issue of <hi rend="italic">Scholarly
                    Editing: The Annual of the Association for Documentary Editing</hi></head>
            <byline>Amanda Gailey</byline>
            <byline>Andrew Jewell</byline>

        </front>

        <body>
            <p>The second issue of <hi rend="italic">Scholarly Editing: The Annual of the
                    Association for Documentary Editing</hi> offers three editions that are
                remarkable in their scope. The texts range from fifteenth-century London
                to twentieth-century Omaha and are edited by scholars from Belgium, Switzerland, the
                United Kingdom, and the United States. They also implement a variety of editorial
                methodologies that evidence the rigor and interpretive significance of scholarly
                editing.</p>
            <p>Alpo Honkapohja has edited <ref type="html"
                    target="2013/editions/intro.sevenplanets">"The Trinity Seven
                        Planets,"</ref> a study of a fifteenth-century Middle English
                astrological treatise that was part of a larger set of texts bound as a portable
                physician's reference. The book, which mixes Latin and Middle English materials,
                suggests that before the printing press arrived in England, there was a commercial
                trade in medical books in London or its suburbs. In his introduction, Honkapohja offers a close
                paleographical study of the document and carefully explains his editorial methodology, which seeks to maximize flexibility so that the edition
                retains all the features necessary to make it useful to historical linguistics while
                also being richly encoded in order to be of use to more general readers. For
                instance, because the text is part of a book meant to be compact and portable, it
                includes many abbreviations that would confound modern readers, but Honkapohja
                offers expansions, as well as numerous glosses, that make the text more readable
                while losing none of the original content. The edition also offers beautiful
                full-color scans of the material, and helpful illustrations of the text's
                bibliographic relationship to other manuscripts. </p>
            <p>Elizabeth Lorang and Rebecca Weir offer <ref type="html"
                    target="2013/editions/intro.cwnewspaperpoetry">an edition that
                    focuses on the importance of newspapers in antebellum American literature</ref>,
                and through close textual scholarship they uncover fascinating connections between the
                abolitionist press and the African American press. They have selected an astonishing
                138 poems published in the <hi rend="italic">National Anti-Slavery Standard</hi> and the
                    <hi rend="italic">Anglo-African</hi>, which help illustrate not only how these historically important newspapers employed poetry
                during the Civil War but also the ways in which they were connected to each other. The edition is itself a revelatory project, and includes
                careful and thorough annotations that help contextualize the materials. But it also
                serves as a model for the kind of foundational textual scholarship that remains to
                be done on periodicals, as such editions have been generally neglected in print
                editorial work. The editors are guided by an interest in how the poems' periodical context 
                affects how they were read, and so they present scans of the entire issue
                of the newspaper in which the poems appeared.</p>
            <p>Marianne Van Remoortel is also interested in newspaper poetry, and presents <ref
                    type="html" target="2013/editions/intro.sunsetwings">a study of how
                    Dante Gabriel Rossetti's "Sunset Wings" was circulated in American
                    periodicals</ref>. Her edition is a model for how editors can use materials from
                mass digitization projects to create carefully edited small-scale editions, as well
                as use tools developed for digital humanities projects. She finds her materials
                using databases of digitized periodicals, but then repurposes them in a more careful
                scholarly edition. She tracks how newspapers across the United States reprinted the
                poem for decades, beginning with reprints that were produced before Rossetti was widely
                known, as evidenced by their frequent misspellings of his name, and continuing into
                the twentieth century. She offers different ways of accessing these reprints,
                including through a dynamic geographical representation of these newspapers by
                using <ref type="url" target="http://neatline.org/">Neatline</ref>, a tool developed
                by <ref type="url" target="http://www.scholarslab.org/">Scholars' Lab</ref> at the
                University of Virginia Library that allows users to track geographical data onto
                historical maps. Readers can also study textual differences among the reprints individually or 
                through <ref type="url" target="http://www.juxtasoftware.org/">Juxta</ref>, a text
                comparison tool developed by <ref type="url" target="http://www.nines.org/"
                    >Networked Interface for Nineteenth-century Electronic Scholarship
                (NINES)</ref>.</p>
            <p>While these editions span an array of materials and approaches, we noticed that they
                all have something in common: they each consider the material production of the
                texts as centrally important to their meaning. Honkapohja's "Trinity Seven
                    Planets" considers the book as evidence of a pre-Gutenberg book trade;
                Lorang and Weir's "Poems of the <hi rend="italic">Anglo-African</hi> and <hi rend="italic">National
                Anti-Slavery Standard</hi>, 1863-1864" establishes bedrock information about the
                material production of abolitionist texts in New York; and Van Remoortel's "A
                    Poem's Flight" views the first transatlantic reprint as a starting point for
                tracking a poem's post-authorial afterlife. The result, in each case, is an edition
                that evidences the strength and flexibility of the digital environment for enriching
                the way we read texts.</p>
            <p>This issue of <hi rend="italic">Scholarly Editing</hi> also offers essays by a range of scholars:
                Dot Porter's <ref type="html" target="2013/essays/essay.porter">"Medievalists and the Scholarly Digital Edition"</ref> studies the
                development of medieval digital editions since 2002, offering intriguing factual
                evidence about how and by whom they are used. Jane Calvert's <ref type="html" target="2013/essays/essay.calvert">"The 'Documentary
                Democracy' of the Writings of John Dickinson, Then and Now"</ref> discusses her efforts to
                edit the works of an important founder of the United States in a way that will make
                them more fully accessible to a wide readership, arguing that digital editing be
                considered a form of democratization. Finally, we offer Carol DeBoer-Langworthy's
                <ref type="html" target="2013/essays/essay.2013presidentialaddress">address as the outgoing president of the Association for Documentary Editing</ref>,
                presented at the annual meeting in 2012, in which she reflects on the role and
                significance of the documentary editor over her years of familiarity with the
                field.</p>
            <p>All this material, in combination with two reviews of new editions and the
                journal's annual list of <ref type="html" target="2013/reviews/review.recenteditions2013">"Recent Editions,"</ref> reflects the vibrant and varied world of
                editorial scholarship in both print and digital environments.</p>


        </body>




        
    </text>
</TEI>
