<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<?oxygen RNGSchema="http://www.scholarlyediting.org/scholarlyediting.rng" type="xml"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xml:lang="eng">
    <teiHeader>
        <fileDesc>
            <titleStmt>
                <title level="a" type="main">Review: <hi rend="italic">“On the Carpet: The Coming of
                        Age Letters of Penelope Skinner, 1832–1840”</hi>. Edited by Mary
                    Maillard.</title>
                <author key="Sherrer, Mary">Mary Sherrer</author>
            </titleStmt>
            <editionStmt>
                <edition>
                    <date>2016</date>
                </edition>
            </editionStmt>
            <publicationStmt>
                <idno type="file">review.sherrer</idno>
                <authority>Scholary Editing: The Annual of the Association for Documentary
                    Editing</authority>
                <address>
 <addrLine>http://www.scholarlyediting.org</addrLine>
</address>
                <publisher>Association for Documentary Editing</publisher>
                <publisher>University of Nebraska&#8211;Lincoln</publisher>
                <distributor>
                    <name>Center for Digital Research in the Humanities</name>
                    <address>
<addrLine>319 Love Library</addrLine>
<addrLine>University of Nebraska&#8211;Lincoln</addrLine>
<addrLine>Lincoln, NE 68588-4100</addrLine>
<addrLine>http://cdrh.unl.edu</addrLine>
 </address>
                </distributor>
                <date>2016</date>
                <availability>
                    <p>Scholary Editing: The Annual of the Association for Documentary Editing is
                        freely distributed by the Association for Documentary Editing and the Center
                        for Digital Research in the Humanities at the University of Nebraska-Lincoln
                        and licensed under a Creative Commons Attribution-NonCommercial-ShareAlike
                        3.0 Unported License</p>
                </availability>
            </publicationStmt>
            <seriesStmt>
                <title level="j">Scholarly Editing: The Annual of the Association for Documentary
                    Editing</title>
                <respStmt>
                    <resp>editor</resp>
                    <name xml:id="ag" key="Gailey, Amanda A.">Amanda Gailey</name>
                </respStmt>
                <respStmt>
                    <resp>editor</resp>
                    <name xml:id="awj" key="Jewell, Andrew W.">Andrew Jewell</name>
                </respStmt>
                <idno type="vol">37</idno>
                <idno type="ISSN">2167-1257</idno>
            </seriesStmt>
            <sourceDesc>
                <bibl>
                    <note>Born digital.</note>
                </bibl>
            </sourceDesc>
        </fileDesc>
        <revisionDesc>
            <change when="2016-04-14">
                <name xml:id="ga_ki" key="Kirilloff, Gabi">Gabi Kirilloff</name> markup in TEI
                XML</change>
        </revisionDesc>
    </teiHeader>
    <text>
        <body>
            <head type="main"><hi rend="italic">“On the Carpet: The Coming of Age Letters of
                    Penelope Skinner, 1832–1840”</hi>. Edited by Mary Maillard.</head>
            <p>“On the Carpet” is one of a four-part e-book series edited by independent scholar
                Mary Maillard. The series includes “Albemarle Son: The Coming of Age Letters of
                Tristrim Lowther Skinner, 1833–1849,” and “The Belles of Williamsburg: The
                Correspondence of Eliza Fisk Harwood and Tristrim Lowther Skinner, 1839–1849,” plus
                a monograph, “A Map of Time and Blood: An Introduction to the Skinner Family Papers,
                1829–1850.” These are tied together by an extensive website detailing the history of
                the family and her project, illustrated with images of family artifacts and
                portraits. The e-books can be purchased from Amazon for Kindle, Kobo, iBook, and
                other formats.</p>
            <p>Maillard’s exploration of the Skinner Family Papers from the Southern Historical
                Collection at the University of North Carolina, Chapel Hill, began as an effort to
                publish two large volumes. But when funding ran out from the North Carolina
                Department of Archives and History, she began to look at other ways to produce a
                documentary edition on her own. In turning toward digital publication, she found a
                solution that has worked for many organizations and independent scholars. Like
                others, Maillard discovered that digital editions can provide access to a wide
                audience while allowing editors to add extensive editorial material and experiment
                with creative options in the publication’s design and functionality, of which she
                has taken full advantage to guide her readers in understanding the lives of the
                Skinner family.</p>
            <p>Maillard’s concern not to be forced into a selected edition of letters encouraged her
                to adopt a digital format, and as such the volumes she produces are companions to
                one another, not discrete editions. She explains that some letters were duplicated
                in the editions, but these are few and were necessary for continuity&#8212;a
                challenge when manuscripts skip several years or significant events. While the
                collection of the Skinner family manuscripts covers the years 1770 to 1900, Maillard
                has chosen to focus on three editions of coming-of-age letters in the antebellum
                period. Expanding beyond this area, her next volume, “The Civil War Letters of
                Tristrim Lowther Skinner, 1861–1862” will be published later this year (2016).</p>
            <p>“On the Carpet” focuses on the adolescence of Penelope “Pen” Skinner (1818–1841) of
                Edenton, North Carolina, and includes her correspondence with her father, Joseph
                Blount Skinner, brother, Tristrim Lowther Skinner, and husband, Thomas Davis Warren.
                The book is divided into four chapters: Education, Coming Out, Marriage, and Death
                (although these divisions are only evident in the navigation bar at the bottom; the
                letters are not separated in the digital edition but continue seamlessly). The
                Skinner children’s mother died when they were young, and the siblings grew close as
                they were sent off to school and to relatives, sometimes together, at other times
                apart. Their father was simultaneously distant and controlling. Their correspondence
                illustrates the trials of their adolescence, and Maillard suggests, the difficulties
                Penelope Skinner particularly experienced without a close maternal figure.</p>
            <p>Maillard’s decision to publish correspondence from the Skinners’ early adulthood in
                this edition and others focuses the reader on the social lives of young, free, white
                southerners. The title of the e-book, “On the Carpet,” means under consideration or
                discussion, a direct reference to Penelope Skinner’s struggle both to present
                herself as a desirable future wife and to choose a worthy husband, or as Maillard
                aptly says, “the sheer exhausting frustration of being both pawn and agent” (24).
                After years of courtship and three engagements, Skinner finally marries at the age
                of twenty-one, and her letters suggest she is relieved to no longer be a
                “belle.”</p>
            <p>But there is much more to be found here. While the subject of courtship dominates the
                volume and Maillard’s interest as an editor, these letters cover other subjects,
                including Skinner’s pregnancy and discussions of the health of neighbors and family
                that provide an insight into medicinal practices. Perhaps because her husband was a
                physician, Skinner describes in detail the physical trials of her pregnancy, her
                exhaustion and emotions, and remedies taken for ailments. The letters are a rich
                source also for understanding not just courtship rituals but the social rules of
                visiting, attendance at religious service, gender roles, sibling relationships,
                neighbor relations, the impact of illness on a community, and the minutiae of daily
                life.</p>
            <p>“On the Carpet” also reveals much about the lives of enslaved and free people of
                color who work for the Skinner family. Maillard’s e-book notes, combined with her
                website, fill in details about, and the family history of, Annie Lowther Skinner, a
                woman enslaved by the Skinner family and a dominant figure who ran the household and
                nursery. We learn from the notes that Annie Skinner’s mother, Polly Lowther, was
                freed by the family after Annie’s birth and that Annie’s younger brother George was
                also eventually freed. But Maillard’s essay on slavery from the Skinner Family
                Papers website gives greater detail about the complicated relationship between the
                free and enslaved Skinners. While George Skinner went on to become an abolitionist
                in Boston, Penelope Skinner’s family in North Carolina still owned 185 slaves.</p>
            <p>The Skinner Family Papers website (<ref type="url"
                    target="http://skinnerfamilypapers.com">http://skinnerfamilypapers.com/</ref>)
                is a valuable and well-designed supplement to the editions and contains features to
                peruse while reading the e-books. Maillard has included sample documents, slave
                lists and family groups, essays on the family’s participation in and opposition to
                slavery, Tristrim Skinner’s role as a soldier in the Civil War, and introductions to
                each e-book. The website also features a combined index to the e-books (the index
                refers to the dates of letters rather than page numbers), so users can determine if
                the Skinner volumes will touch on subjects that interest them. For editors
                interested in the process of creating her e-books, she offers a discussion on
                different formats both for the web and e-book design.</p>
            <p>The website also includes Maillard’s editorial policies, which are straightforward.
                Transcriptions of letters faithfully represent the originals including misspellings.
                Authorial deletions and additions are included, as well as irregular spacings
                between words, most evident in the letters of Penelope and Eliza Skinner, which
                Maillard suggests “reflect the girls’ education but perhaps also some pauses in
                thought or substitution for punctuation.” Editorial notes in the text are clearly
                detectable with italics and brackets. She has also included information from
                envelopes (although not addresses), such as poetry and descriptions of sketches,
                including a drawing depicting Annie, “Tall and slender” (304), carrying a tray of
                glasses.</p>
            <p>The letters are annotated with extensive notes that explain family relationships and
                customs or terminology that may be obscure to the modern reader. Within the edition,
                it is easy to navigate between the notes and the text through hyperlinks, which take
                you from the notes, grouped together at the end, back to your page in the
                correspondence. Notes identify people and places the first time they are mentioned.
                A simple search in iBooks also turned up a complete list showing every mention of a
                name or term in the edition.</p>
            <p>Maillard states that this is the first documentary edition to be crafted specifically
                for e-books, but there are challenges in marketing a documentary edition to a wide
                audience. Although the title clearly states that this is an edited volume of
                letters, some users may not fully understand what they have purchased until they
                have downloaded the book, and may be frustrated by the length of the introductory
                essays and notes, which comprise over half the book. Others may find using the
                linked notes and referencing the web page for more information to be too cumbersome,
                preferring a straightforward narrative. And while most of her editorial material is
                easy to use and navigate, the family tree at the beginning of the book was tiny, and
                impossible to read on the iBook, a big problem in an edition focused so much on
                family relationships. However, Maillard’s choices of format create a clear and
                attractive presentation, and these issues should pose few problems to those familiar
                with digital documentary editions. Readers new to the genre will be rewarded for
                exploring all of Maillard’s editorial material and will be encouraged to examine her
                other editions.</p>
            <p>In the Skinner Family Papers web page, Maillard explains that the challenges she
                faced as an independent scholar, without institutional affiliation or funding, are
                part of the reason she turned to the e-book format rather than to traditional
                publishers or other digital publishing initiatives. Although born-digital editions
                like hers are increasingly common, there are still issues of changing technologies,
                format, design, access, and marketing. With the Skinner Papers project, Maillard has
                offered an example of a viable option to other independent scholars and
                organizations who want to create a documentary edition outside traditional
                publishers. As part of her evolving series, and on its own, “On the Carpet” offers
                much to scholars and the general public in format and substance, on topics that
                appeal to both audiences, in an accessible and enticing format.</p>

            <signed>
                <name>Mary Sherrer</name>
                <affiliation>Pinckney Papers Projects, University of South Carolina</affiliation>
            </signed>
        </body>
    </text>
</TEI>
