<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<?oxygen RNGSchema="http://www.scholarlyediting.org/scholarlyediting.rng" type="xml"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xml:lang="eng">
    <teiHeader>
        <fileDesc>
            <titleStmt>
                <title level="a" type="main">Recent Editions</title>
                <title level="a" type="sub">2014</title>
                <author key="Whitley, W. Bland">W. Bland Whitley</author>
            </titleStmt>
            <editionStmt>
                <edition>
                    <date>2014</date>
                </edition>
            </editionStmt>
            <publicationStmt>
                <idno type="file">review.recenteditions2014</idno>
                <authority>Scholary Editing: The Annual of the Association for Documentary
                    Editing</authority>
                <address>
 <addrLine>http://www.scholarlyediting.org</addrLine>
</address>
                <publisher>Association for Documentary Editing</publisher>
                <publisher>University of Nebraska&#8211;Lincoln</publisher>
                <distributor>
                    <name>Center for Digital Research in the Humanities</name>
                    <address>
<addrLine>319 Love Library</addrLine>
<addrLine>University of Nebraska&#8211;Lincoln</addrLine>
<addrLine>Lincoln, NE 68588-4100</addrLine>
<addrLine>http://cdrh.unl.edu</addrLine>
 </address>
                </distributor>
                <date>2014</date>
                <availability>
                    <p>Scholary Editing: The Annual of the Association for Documentary Editing is
                        freely distributed by the Association for Documentary Editing and the Center
                        for Digital Research in the Humanities at the University of Nebraska-Lincoln
                        and licensed under a Creative Commons Attribution-NonCommercial-ShareAlike
                        3.0 Unported License</p>
                </availability>
            </publicationStmt>
            <seriesStmt>
                <title level="j">Scholarly Editing: The Annual of the Association for Documentary
                    Editing</title>
                <respStmt>
                    <resp>editor</resp>
                    <name xml:id="ag" key="Gailey, Amanda A.">Amanda Gailey</name>
                </respStmt>
                <respStmt>
                    <resp>editor</resp>
                    <name xml:id="awj" key="Jewell, Andrew W.">Andrew Jewell</name>
                </respStmt>
                <idno type="vol">35</idno>
                <idno type="ISSN">2167-1257</idno>
            </seriesStmt>
            <sourceDesc>
                <bibl>
                    <note>Born digital.</note>
                </bibl>
            </sourceDesc>
        </fileDesc>
        <revisionDesc>
            <change when="2014-03-11"><name xml:id="lkw" key="Kirilloff, Gabi">Gabi Kirilloff</name>
                markup in TEI XML</change>
        </revisionDesc>
    </teiHeader>
    <text>

        <front>
            <head type="main">Recent Editions</head>

            <byline>Compiled by W. Bland Whitley</byline>
        </front>
        <body>
            <p>This annual bibliography of documentary editions recently published in the fields of
                American and British history, literature, and culture is generally restricted to
                scholarly first editions of English-language works.</p>


            <list type="simple">
                <item><p>ADAMS FAMILY. <hi rend="italic">Adams Family Correspondence, Volume 11:
                            July 1795–February 1797</hi>. Edited by Margaret A. Hogan, C. James
                        Taylor, Sara Martin, Neal A. Millikan, Hobson Woodward, Sara B. Sikes, and
                        Gregg L. Lint. Harvard University Press. 2013. 728 pp. $95. ISBN:
                        9780674072442. Covering the period leading up to John Adams’s inauguration,
                        when the partisan divide widened amid the fiery debate over the Jay Treaty
                        and George Washington’s impending retirement, this volume includes Abigail
                        Adams’s keen, acerbic commentary on national events, John Quincy and Thomas
                        Boylston Adams’s observations of the French Directory, the war in Europe,
                        and struggles within the Batavian government.</p></item>

                <item><p>AKRON. <hi rend="italic">The Akron Offering, a Ladies’ Literary Magazine,
                            1849–1850: A Critical Edition</hi>. Edited by Jon Miller. University of
                        Akron Press. 2013. 466 pp. $39.95. ISBN: 9781935603535. This annotated
                        edition reproduces the full run of a short-lived literary periodical written
                        by and for women of Akron, Ohio, then a bustling canal town on the cusp of
                        becoming an industrial powerhouse. While shedding light on the religious,
                        creative, and political interests of educated midwestern women, the volume
                        offers insights into their sometimes contradictory views on such events as
                        the California gold rush and the 1848 uprisings in Europe.</p></item>

                <item><p>BACON, FRANCIS. <hi rend="italic">The Oxford Francis Bacon I: Early
                            Writings, 1584–1596</hi>. Edited by Alan Stewart and Harriet Knight.
                        Oxford University Press. 2012. 1,136 pp. $299. ISBN: 9780198183136.
                        Comprised in this first volume of a new, critical edition of Bacon’s works
                        are position papers, commentaries on printed works, legal readings and
                        opinions, and discourses of advice, which were usually circulated in
                        manuscript. Although relatively informal and “occasional,” the works
                        illustrate Bacon’s developing philosophy. The edition presents the works in
                        accordance with the principles of modern textual scholarship and with full
                        commentaries and glossaries.</p></item>

                <item><p>BERLIN, ISAIAH. <hi rend="italic">Building: Letters, 1960–1975</hi>. Edited
                        by Henry Hardy and Mark Poole. Chatto &amp; Windus. 2013. 704 pp. $59.95.
                        ISBN: 9780701185763. The third volume of the English philosopher’s letters,
                            <hi rend="italic">Building</hi> covers the period when Berlin helped
                        create Wolfson College, Oxford, and published some of his most important
                        works, including his four essays on liberty—the key texts outlining his
                        thoughts on liberal pluralism. Behind these personal triumphs and his
                        observations on the turmoil of the era is a stream of gossip, commentary,
                        and acerbic humor, proving Berlin one of the most trenchant and entertaining
                        letter writers of the twentieth century.</p></item>

                <item><p>BERNSTEIN, LEONARD. <hi rend="italic">The Leonard Bernstein Letters</hi>.
                        Edited by Nigel Simeone. Yale University Press. 2013. 480 pp. $38. ISBN:
                        9780300179095. This is the first volume to present a selection of the
                        composer’s wide-ranging correspondence. It includes many never-published
                        letters to such correspondents as Aaron Copland, Stephen Sondheim, and
                        Jacqueline Kennedy Onassis. These letters reveal his complex sexuality, the
                        breadth of his musical interests, and his tremendous capacity for
                    work.</p></item>

                <item><p>BYRD, WILLIAM, II. <hi rend="italic">The Dividing Line Histories of William
                            Byrd II of Westover</hi>. Edited by Kevin Joel Berland. University of
                        North Carolina Press. 2013. 592 pp. $59.95. ISBN: 9781469606934. Collating
                        all extant manuscripts, this new edition sheds light on the historical and
                        cultural contexts of Byrd’s composition of his two distinct histories of the
                        surveying expedition on which he served: the first, a private, highly
                        satirical account, and the second, a more polished history intended for the
                        London literary market. Berland identifies for the first time many of the
                        sources Byrd used to enrich his account, raising questions about the
                        reliability and originality of Byrd’s narratives and calling for an
                        appreciation of the hybrid nature of early modern history writing.
                    </p></item>

                <item><p>CALIFORNIA. <hi rend="italic">California through Russian Eyes,
                            1806–1848</hi>. Compiled, translated, and edited by James R. Gibson.
                        Arthur H. Clark Company. 2013. 506 pp. $45. ISBN: 9780870624216. Russia
                        established a colony in California that lasted until the Russian-American
                        Company sold it in 1841. Gathered from Russian archives and journals, the
                        documents collected and translated here present detailed accounts from
                        Russian mariners, scientists, and company officials. Throughout the volume,
                        the Russians showed themselves to be acute observers of Alta California and
                        its Hispanic and Native American inhabitants.</p></item>

                <item><p>CATHER, WILLA. <hi rend="italic">The Selected Letters of Willa Cather</hi>.
                        Edited by Andrew Jewell and Janis Stout. Knopf. 2013. 752 pp. $37.50. ISBN:
                        9780307959300. The first publication of Cather’s letters (her will forbade
                        their publication), this edition collects 566 letters from throughout her
                        life. From reports of her life as a teenager in Red Cloud to her time as a
                        journalist in Pittsburgh and New York to her rise as one of America’s finest
                        novelists, these letters, mostly to close friends and family and to other
                        literary figures, reveal the confident and elegant voice that has made
                        Cather’s fiction endure.</p></item>

                <item><p>CIVIL WAR. <hi rend="italic">A Confederate Englishman: The Civil War
                            Letters of Henry Wemyss Feilden</hi>. Edited by W. Eric Emerson and
                        Karen Stokes. University of South Carolina Press. 2013. 216 pp. $29.95.
                        ISBN: 9781611171358. Feilden was a young British officer who resigned his
                        commission, ran the Union blockade, and became a staff officer of P. G. T.
                        Beauregard. During the war, he married South Carolinian Julia McCord. This
                        volume publishes for the first time his letters to her, which offer a
                        compelling view into the operations of the military headquarters in
                        Charleston and subsequently in operations in Georgia and Florida. Feilden
                        and his wife moved to Great Britain after the war, and he resumed his
                        military career there. This volume prints also a selection of letters from
                        the early twentieth century in which Feilden reflects on his career, which
                        included explorations of the Arctic.</p></item>

                <item><p>CIVIL WAR. <hi rend="italic">Diary of a Southern Refugee during the War:
                            Annotated Edition</hi>. By Judith Brokenbrough McGuire. Edited by James
                        I. Robertson Jr. University of Kentucky Press. 2013. 352 pp. $60. ISBN:
                        9780813144375. Throughout the war, McGuire wrote incisive commentaries on
                        society, detailed her hardships, and balanced reflections on her life behind
                        the battle lines with military reports and rumors. Her oft-cited journals
                        here receive for the first time meticulous annotations that furnish
                        references for poems and quotations and identify the many individuals who
                        previously have only been known by the initials McGuire gave
                    them.</p></item>

                <item><p>CIVIL WAR. <hi rend="italic">Torn by War: The Civil War Journal of Mary
                            Adelia Byers</hi>. Edited by Samuel R. Phillips. University of Oklahoma
                        Press. 2013. 248 pp. $19.95. ISBN: 9780806143958. Byers began recording her
                        thoughts and observations at the age of fifteen in 1862, during the first of
                        three Union occupations of Batesville, Arkansas. An acute observer, Byers
                        illustrated the conflicts experienced by a social elite very much dependent
                        upon slavery but situated on the fringes of the Confederacy. The volume adds
                        to the growing body of literature on civilian life during the Civil
                    War.</p></item>

                <item><p>COAL INDUSTRY. <hi rend="italic">Letters of John Buddle to Lord
                            Londonderry, 1820–1843</hi>. Edited by Anne Orde. Boydell &amp; Brewer.
                        2013. 450 pp. $90. ISBN: 978085440726. Buddle was the most eminent mining
                        engineer of his era and served as colliery manager for Charles Stewart,
                        third Marquess of Londonderry, who owned mines in northeast England.
                        Selected from the more than two thousand letters that Buddle wrote to his
                        employer, this edition offers detailed accounts of the coal trade at a time
                        when the industry was expanding rapidly and provides a window into the
                        politics, economy, and social situation of the northeast.</p></item>

                <item><p>COLONIAL MASSACHUSETTS. <hi rend="italic">The Papers of Francis Bernard,
                            Volume 3: Governor of Colonial Massachusetts, 1760–1769</hi>. Edited by
                        Colin Nicolson. University of Virginia Press. 2013. 488 pp. $49.50. ISBN:
                        9780985254315. Royal governor during the tumultuous decade that saw
                        Massachusetts set the pattern for American reactions to the Stamp Act and
                        other British measures, Bernard provided firsthand observations on the birth
                        of the American movement for independence. This third volume of a
                        four-volume set that will advance scholarship on late eighteenth-century
                        British imperial historiography covers the years 1766 and 1767.</p></item>

                <item><p>CONSTITUTION, UNITED STATES. <hi rend="italic">Documentary History of the
                            Ratification of the Constitution, Volume 26. Ratification of the
                            Constitution by the States: Rhode Island, No. 3</hi>. Edited by John P.
                        Kaminski, Gaspare J. Saladino, Jonathan M. Reid, Charles H. Schoenleber,
                        Richard Leffler, and Margaret R. Flamingo. Wisconsin Historical Society
                        Press. 2013. 1205 pp. $95. ISBN: 9780870206214. The last of three volumes
                        documenting public and private debates concerning the new US Constitution in
                        Rhode Island.</p></item>

                <item><p>DALL, CAROLINE HEALEY. <hi rend="italic">Selected Journals of Caroline
                            Healey Dall</hi>. Edited by Helen R. Deese. University of Virginia
                        Press. 2013. 752 pp. $75. ISBN: 9781936520053. The second volume of Dall’s
                        diary extends her story into the crucial period of her role in the American
                        women’s movement and in the founding of the American Social Science
                        Association. A strongly partisan New Englander, Dall is revealed also as a
                        single mother working to form a new identity as a writer, lecturer, and
                        reformer.</p></item>

                <item><p>DICKENS, CHARLES. <hi rend="italic">Dickens’s Uncollected Magazine and
                            Newspaper Sketches, as Originally Composed and Published,
                        1833–1836</hi>. Edited by Robert C. Hanna. AMS Press. 2012. 372 pp. $147.50.
                        ISBN: 9780404123456. This collection reproduces fifty-six early sketches
                        exactly as they were initially published before Dickens heavily revised them
                        for his first book, <hi rend="italic">Sketches of Boz</hi>. Authoritative
                        annotations, four rarely seen original illustrations, and authorized and
                        unauthorized versions of the sketches allow readers to encounter Dickens as
                        his first readers did.</p></item>

                <item><p>ELIOT, T. S. <hi rend="italic">The Letters of T. S. Eliot, Volume 4:
                            1928–29</hi>. Edited by Valerie Eliot and John Haffenden. Yale
                        University Press. 2013. 880 pp. $50. ISBN: 9780300187243. During the period
                        covered in this volume, Eliot sought secure financial support for his
                        periodical, the <hi rend="italic">Monthly Criterion</hi>, while tending to
                        his wife, Vivien, who had just returned from a French psychiatric hospital.
                        Corresponding as always with writers from around the world, he concluded a
                        number of writings himself, including the poem <hi rend="italic">A Song for
                            Simeon</hi> and an introduction to Wilkie Collins’s <hi rend="italic"
                            >The Moonstone</hi>.</p></item>

                <item><p>EMANCIPATION. <hi rend="italic">Freedom: A Documentary History of
                            Emancipation, 1861–1867. Series 3, Volume 2: Land and Labor,
                            1866–1867</hi>. Edited by René Hayden, Anthony E. Kaye, Kate Masur,
                        Steven F. Miller, Susan E. O’Donovan, Leslie S. Rowland, and Stephen A.
                        West. University of North Carolina Press. 2013. 1,096 pp. $99.95. ISBN:
                        9781469607429. Using documents selected from the National Archives, many of
                        them in the freedpeople’s own words, this volume examines the remaking of
                        the South’s labor system in the aftermath of emancipation. It captures the
                        efforts of freedpeople to establish their families as independent economic
                        units, the reordering of labor, migration, and new relations of credit and
                        debt.</p></item>

                <item><p>EXPLORATION. <hi rend="italic">The Strange and Dangerous Voyage of Captaine
                            Thomas James: A Critical Edition</hi>. Edited by Colleen M. Franklin.
                        McGill-Queens University Press. 2013. 360 pp. $100. ISBN: 9780773541924. A
                        British explorer, James published in 1633 an account of his attempt to find
                        the Northwest Passage and the winter he spent on an island in James Bay. For
                        two centuries, his narrative remained the British public’s primary source of
                        information for northern Canada. This new edition offers a history of the
                        text’s reception from its first publication into the nineteenth
                    century.</p></item>

                <item><p>FETHERLING, GEORGE. <hi rend="italic">The Writing Life: Journals,
                            1975–2005</hi>. Edited by Brian Busby. McGill-Queen’s University Press.
                        2013. 360 pp. $37.95. ISBN: 9780773541146. Selected from thousands of pages
                        of the journals of one of Canada’s leading literary figures, <hi
                            rend="italic">The Writing Life</hi> reveals Fetherling to be an astute
                        observer of his contemporaries as well as of himself. Figures such as
                        Margaret Atwood and Marshall McLuhan fill the journals, which begin in
                        mid-1970s Toronto before moving to Vancouver and extending into a new
                        century.</p></item>

                <item><p>FUR TRADE. <hi rend="italic">This Far-Off Land: The Upper Missouri Letters
                            of Andrew Dawson</hi>. Edited by Lesley Wischmann and Andrew Erskine
                        Dawson. Arthur H. Clark Company. 2013. 336 pp. $39.95. ISBN: 9780870624193.
                        Dawson was a young Scot who immigrated to St. Louis in 1844 and three years
                        later joined the fur trade along the upper Missouri River in what is now
                        North Dakota and Montana, where he would assume command of several trading
                        outposts and become known as the last “King of the Upper Missouri.” This
                        volume pairs a biography of Dawson with thirty-seven previously unpublished
                        letters that he sent from the frontier. The letters capture the sense of
                        isolation that characterized the fur trade and descriptions of some of the
                        least documented fur trading centers.</p></item>

                <item><p>GAYLE, SARAH HAYNSWORTH. <hi rend="italic">The Journal of Sarah Haynsworth
                            Gayle, 1827–1835: A Substitute for Social Intercourse</hi>. Edited by
                        Sarah Woolfolk Wiggins and Ruth Smith Truss. University of Alabama Press.
                        2013. 392 pp. $39.95. ISBN: 9780817313333. Long an invaluable source for
                        historians of elite southern women in the antebellum South, Gayle’s journal
                        has been frequently misinterpreted because of the ragged condition of the
                        original and the poor quality of the many transcriptions that have
                        circulated. Using archival techniques, the editors have recovered obscured
                        information and created the most reliable reading of Gayle’s journal.
                        Textual notes explain how damaged lines were restored.</p></item>

                <item><p>GOMPERS, SAMUEL. <hi rend="italic">The Samuel Gompers Papers, Volume 13:
                            Cumulative Index</hi>. Edited by Peter J. Albert and Grace Palladino.
                        University of Illinois Press. 2013. 320 pp. $50. ISBN: 9780252037429. The
                        final volume in this landmark documentary edition, the index provides a key
                        to the previous volumes, permitting scholars to recognize the emphases in
                        subject matter and locate the substantive annotations of key individuals,
                        unions, legislation, and events.</p></item>

                <item><p>HAITIAN REVOLUTION. <hi rend="italic">An Historical Account of the Black
                            Empire of Hayti</hi>. By Marcus Rainford. Edited by Paul Youngquist and
                        Grégory Pierrot. Duke University Press. 2013. 392 pp. $99.95. ISBN:
                        9780822352785. The first complete narrative in English of the Haitian
                        Revolution, Rainsford’s account was highly influential in establishing world
                        opinion of the pivotal events. Rainsford was a British officer who went to
                        Haiti to recruit black soldiers. His account supported the idea of Haitian
                        independence, praised the prowess of black troops, and recounted his
                        meetings with Toussaint Louverture and other Haitian leaders. The first
                        edition since the initial publication of 1805, this volume provides
                        contextual and historical details and includes a newly discovered miniature
                        painting of Louverture by Rainsford.</p></item>

                <item><p>HAND, LEARNED. <hi rend="italic">Reason and Imagination: The Selected
                            Correspondence of Learned Hand</hi>. Edited by Constance Jordan. Oxford
                        University Press. 2013. 480 pp. $39.95. ISBN: 9780199899104. This edition
                        offers a unique sampling of the correspondence between Hand and an array of
                        intellectual and legal giants, including Justice Oliver Wendell Holmes,
                        Theodore Roosevelt, Walter Lippmann, Felix Frankfurter, and Bernard
                        Berenson. The letters, many never before published, cover almost half a
                        century and showcase decades of original thought on American
                        jurisprudence.</p></item>

                <item><p>HARDY, THOMAS. <hi rend="italic">The Collected Letters of Thomas Hardy,
                            Volume 8: Further Letters</hi>. Edited by Michael Millgate and Keith
                        Wilson. Oxford University Press. 2013. 320 pp. $160. ISBN: 9780199607754.
                        The long-awaited supplement to Hardy’s <hi rend="italic">Collected
                            Letters</hi>, this volume contains previously unpublished letters from
                        all periods of Hardy’s career, including his earliest known letter. It
                        introduces important new correspondents and sheds light on existing
                        exchanges.</p></item>

                <item><p>HERRICK, ROBERT. <hi rend="italic">The Complete Poetry of Robert Herrick,
                            Volume 1</hi>. Edited by Tom T. Cain and Ruth Connolly. Oxford
                        University Press. 2013. 400 pp. $135. ISBN: 9780199212842. This volume
                        concentrates on Herrick’s large printed collection <hi rend="italic"
                            >Hesperides</hi>, the product of four decades of writing. Based on a
                        collation of all fifty-seven known surviving copies, the edition includes a
                        new biography. A second volume will contain extensive commentary, so that
                        readers can read it side by side with the poems.</p></item>

                <item><p>HOGG, JAMES. <hi rend="italic">Contributions to Blackwood’s Edinburgh
                            Magazine: Volume 2, 1829–1835</hi>. Edited by Thomas Richardson.
                        Edinburgh University Press. 2012. 432 pp. $95. ISBN: 9780748624898. From
                        1817 to his death in 1835, James Hogg published 115 works in <hi
                            rend="italic">Blackwood’s Edinburgh Magazine</hi>, which showcased the
                        diversity of his talent. Poems and songs, sketches of rural life, review
                        essays, short stories, and satirical pieces enlivened the journal’s pages.
                        This edition includes previously unpublished submitted work from the same
                        period and full explanatory and textual notes.
                    </p><!--I got rid of the link that was here in the word doc--></item>

                <item><p>HOGG FAMILY. <hi rend="italic">The Hoggs of Texas: Letters and Memoirs of
                            an Extraordinary Family, 1887–1906</hi>. Edited by Virginia Bernhard.
                        Texas A&amp;M University Press. 2013. 350 pp. $35. ISBN: 9781625110015.
                        Featuring more than four hundred previously unpublished letters, this volume
                        follows the family of Gov. James Stephen Hogg through the state’s late
                        nineteenth-century politics and their own ups and downs. Interspersed are
                        portions of Ima Hogg’s memoir and commentary from the editor.</p></item>

                <item><p>HOPKINS, GERARD MANLEY. <hi rend="italic">The Collected Works of Gerard
                            Manley Hopkins. Correspondence, Volume 1: 1852–1881. Volume 2:
                            1882–1889</hi>. Edited by R. K. R. Thornton and Catherine Phillips.
                        Oxford University Press. 2013. 504 pp. $299. ISBN: 9780199653706. Set out on
                        radically different lines from previous editions of the poet’s letters,
                        these two comprehensive volumes of the <hi rend="italic">Collected
                            Works</hi> provide, as far as is possible, a narrative sequence. New
                        transcriptions revise a large number of readings and include all legible
                        emendations, allowing the reader to follow the hesitancies and adjustments
                        of Hopkins’s mind. The letters provide a window into Hopkins’s thoughts on
                        his own work and on poetry in general.</p></item>

                <item><p>HUGHES, LANGSTON. <hi rend="italic">My Dear Boy: Carrie Hughes’s Letters to
                            Langston Hughes, 1926–1938</hi>. Edited by Carmaletta M. Williams and
                        John Edgar Tidwell. University of Georgia Press. 2013. 240 pp. $39.95. ISBN:
                        9780820345659. Using family systems theory, the editors introduce readers to
                        a previously unexplored aspect of Hughes’s work. The letters from Hughes’s
                        mother reveal the difficult negotiations between family and art that Hughes
                        engaged in as he attempted to sustain an elusive but enduring artistic
                        reputation. His responses to his mother’s correspondence came in his
                        artistic work, making the letters a new resource for engaging the inner self
                        that has eluded Hughes scholars.</p></item>

                <item><p>ISHERWOOD, CHRISTOPHER. <hi rend="italic">Liberation: Diaries,
                            1970–1983</hi>. Edited by Katherine Bucknell. Chatto &amp; Windus. 2012.
                        875 pp. $39.99. ISBN: 9780701169404. This edition records Isherwood’s
                        immersion in the 1970s arts scenes of Los Angeles, New York, and London,
                        when he came into contact with such figures as John Huston, David Hockney,
                        Robert Rauschenberg, and Andy Warhol. Frank and humorous reflections on the
                        dramatic events of the era and his own role in the gay liberation movement
                        are balanced with candid revelations of his fear of death.</p></item>

                <item><p>JACKSON, ANDREW. <hi rend="italic">The Papers of Andrew Jackson, Volume 9:
                            1831</hi>. Edited by Daniel Feller, Laura Eve Moss, Thomas Coens, and
                        Erik B. Alexander. University of Tennessee Press. 2013. 987 pp. $92. ISBN:
                        9871621900045. Presenting more than five hundred documents, many newly
                        discovered, this edition covers the third year of Jackson’s presidency, when
                        he cleared his contentious cabinet and pursued his feud with Vice President
                        John C. Calhoun, whom he blamed for his political troubles. Through all this
                        turmoil, Jackson continued to press his priorities: Indian removal,
                        retirement of the national debt, and opposition to the Bank of the United
                        States and to nullification.</p></item>

                <item><p>JAY, JOHN. <hi rend="italic">The Selected Papers of John Jay, Volume 3:
                            1782–1784</hi>. Edited by Elizabeth M. Nuxoll. University of Virginia
                        Press. 2013. 768 pp. $95. ISBN: 9780813932804. This volume opens with Jay’s
                        arrival in Paris for the negotiation of the peace treaty with Great Britain
                        and explores his insistence on a British recognition of American
                        independence as a precondition for negotiation and his disregard of
                        congressional instructions to take no action without the consent of France.
                        Also covered are topics such as the Jays’ social and domestic life, Jay’s
                        efforts to settle a family inheritance, and his return to America, where he
                        accepted the post of secretary of foreign affairs.</p></item>

                <item><p>JEFFERSON, THOMAS. <hi rend="italic">The Papers of Thomas Jefferson, Volume
                            39: 13 November 1802–3 March 1803</hi>. Edited by Barbara B. Oberg,
                        James P. McClure, Elaine Weber Pascu, Martha J. King, Tom Downey, and W.
                        Bland Whitley. Princeton University Press. 2012. 768 pp. $115. ISBN:
                        9780691156712. This volume contains documents connected to the closing of
                        the right of deposit in New Orleans, an act that threatened the well-being
                        of westerners and encouraged Jefferson to send his friend and ally James
                        Monroe to Paris to negotiate a permanent solution. Also included are
                        Jefferson’s request for funds for a western expedition to be led by
                        Meriwether Lewis and a visit to Washington from his daughters and two
                        grandchildren. </p></item>

                <item><p>JEFFERSON, THOMAS. <hi rend="italic">The Papers of Thomas Jefferson,
                            Retirement Series, Volume 9: 1 September 1815–30 April 1816</hi>. Edited
                        by J. Jefferson Looney, Robert F. Haggard, Julie L. Lautenschlager, Ellen C.
                        Hickman, and Christine Sternberg Patrick. Princeton University Press. 2012.
                        848 pp. $115. ISBN: 9780691156705. During the period covered in this volume,
                        Jefferson made three trips to Poplar Forest, where he also hosted the
                        returning war hero Andrew Jackson. Jefferson repurposed a letter in which he
                        indulged in a “tirade” against the pamphlet of a New England clergyman by
                        having it published anonymously in the <hi rend="italic">Richmond
                            Enquirer</hi>, and also responded anonymously to an interpretation of
                        the Constitution published in a Washington newspaper.</p></item>

                <item><p>MADISON, JAMES. <hi rend="italic">The Papers of James Madison, Retirement
                            Series, Volume 2: 1 February 1820–26 February 1823</hi>. Edited by David
                        B. Mattern, J. C. A. Stagg, Mary Parke Johnson, and Anne Mandeville Colony.
                        University of Virginia Press. 2013. 768 pp. $85. ISBN: 9780813933764. During
                        the time covered in this volume, Madison remained at his home, Montpelier,
                        other than visits to neighborhood friends and attendance at Board of Visitor
                        meetings at the University of Virginia. He corresponded with President James
                        Monroe about domestic and international politics, with Thomas Jefferson
                        about the building of the University of Virginia, and with a wide range of
                        other individuals who received Madison’s views on slavery and public
                        education.</p></item>

                <item><p>MILTON, JOHN. <hi rend="italic">The Complete Works of John Milton, Volume
                            8: De Doctrina Christiana</hi>. Edited by John K. Hale, Donald
                        Cullington, Gordon Campbell, and Thomas N. Corns. Oxford University Press.
                        2013. 1,440 pp. $375. ISBN: 9780199234516. This volume presents Milton’s
                        systematic theology, his longest work, in which he worked out his beliefs
                        directly from scripture. This definitive edition is based on a fresh
                        transcription and includes fuller textual apparatus and commentary. Of
                        particular note is the edition’s close attention to the nuances of Milton’s
                        Latin.</p></item>

                <item><p>MONTGOMERY, L. M. <hi rend="italic">The Complete Journals of L. M.
                            Montgomery: The Pei Years, 1901–1911</hi>. Edited by Mary Henley Rubio
                        and Elizabeth Hillman Waterston. Oxford University Press. 2013. 444 pp. $42.
                        ISBN: 9780199002115. The second of the complete journals to appear, this
                        volume covers Montgomery’s early adult years, including her work as a
                        newspaper editor in Halifax, Nova Scotia, the death of her grandmother, and
                        her impending marriage to a clergyman. It documents her own reflections on
                        writing, her mood swings, and her changing relationship with the world of
                        Prince Edward Island. This edition recreates the format that Montgomery
                        devised for her journals.</p></item>

                <item><p>NEHRU, JAWAHARLAL. <hi rend="italic">Selected Works of Jawaharlal Nehru,
                            Second Series, Volume 46: 1 January–28 February 1959</hi>. Edited by
                        Madhavan K. Palat. Oxford University Press. 2013. 738 pp. $60. ISBN:
                        9780198090489. With extensive annotations, this volume provides a panorama
                        of home and the world as seen from the center of power in India by a
                        sensitive observer and a skillful statesman.</p></item>

                <item><p>NEILSON, ELIZA LUCY IRION. <hi rend="italic">A New Southern Woman: The
                            Correspondence of Eliza Lucy Irion Neilson, 1871–1883</hi>. Edited by
                        Giselle Roberts. University of South Carolina Press. 2013. 352 pp. $49.95.
                        ISBN: 9781611171307. Neilson composed and preserved over 130 letters during
                        the period covered in this volume, which prints eighty letters documenting
                        family and domestic life in Columbus, Mississippi. Creating an agricultural
                        partnership with her husband under the straitened circumstances of the
                        postbellum South, Neilson also observed the efforts of one widowed sister,
                        another sister who was single, and a school-age niece. Her correspondence
                        suggests the ways that elite white women created a new southern
                        consciousness under a broader rubric of genteel postbellum
                    femininity.</p></item>

                <item><p>NIN, ANAÏS. <hi rend="italic">Mirages: The Unexpurgated Diary of Anaïs Nin,
                            1939–1947</hi>. Edited by Paul Herron. Swallow Press. 2013. 440 pp.
                        $34.95. ISBN: 9780804011464. Collecting for the first time the portion of
                        Nin’s diary that was cut from previous published editions, <hi rend="italic"
                            >Mirages</hi> covers a difficult period of Nin’s life after she fled
                        Paris and experienced a kind of delirium that fueled her search for erotic
                        fulfillment. The diary offers answers to questions concerning the end of
                        Nin’s affair with Henry Miller, her troubled marriage, and her penchant for
                        collecting devoted younger men.</p></item>

                <item><p>OLMSTED, FREDERICK LAW. <hi rend="italic">The Papers of Frederick Law
                            Olmsted, Volume 8: The Early Boston Years, 1882–1890</hi>. Edited by
                        Charles E. Beveridge, Ethan Carr, Amanda Gagel, and Michael Shapiro. Johns
                        Hopkins University Press. 2013. 928 pp. $110. ISBN: 9781421409269.
                        Relocating to Boston, where he established a modern landscape architecture
                        practice with his stepson, Olmsted during the 1880s designed the ambitious
                        park system of Boston and Brookline, public parks in New York State and
                        Detroit, and the grounds of the Biltmore Estate near Asheville. He wrote
                        frequently on the subject of landscape design, and this volume contains some
                        of his most mature and powerful statements on his art.</p></item>

                <item><p>OSAGES. <hi rend="italic">An Osage Journey to Europe, 1827–1830: Three
                            French Accounts</hi>. Edited and translated by William Least Heat-Moon
                        and James K. Wallace. University of Oklahoma Press. 2013. 168 pp. $29.95.
                        ISBN: 9780806144030. In 1827 six Osages, two of them women, traveled to
                        Europe, where they made a celebrated visit to France. Virtually lost since
                        the 1830s, the three accounts of the visit published in this volume reflect
                        European stereotypes of American Indians but nonetheless provide unique
                        insights into Osage life and are surprisingly accurate in some of their
                        depictions of Osage history, geography, and lifeways.</p></item>

                <item><p>PIERCE, WILLIAM. <hi rend="italic">William Pierce: On the Constitutional
                            Convention and the Constitution. Notes from the Convention, Sketches of
                            Delegates, and Writings on the Constitution</hi>. Edited by Richard
                        Leffler, John P. Kaminski, and Samuel K. Fore. Harlan Crow Library. 2012.
                        119 pp. Based on Pierce’s manuscript observations of the 1787 Constitutional
                        Convention, this handsome edition includes helpful annotations, brief
                        biographies of all the convention members described by Pierce, and excerpts
                        of letters Pierce wrote during the drafting and ratification of the
                        Constitution.</p></item>

                <item><p>POLK, JAMES K. <hi rend="italic">Correspondence of James K. Polk, Volume 12: January–July 1847</hi>. Edited by Tom Chaffin and Michael David Cohen. University of Tennessee Press. 2013. 567 pp. $75. ISBN: 9781572339527. The letters in this volume, most of them previously unpublished, document Polk’s prosecution of the war against Mexico, which along with his previous settlement of the Oregon controversy, increased the size of the United States by a third. During the period covered, Polk and other Americans celebrated victories at Buena Vista, Sacramento, and Veracruz, among others. The war did not eliminate, however, other foreign policy concerns also covered in the volume. Polk’s party-building efforts also emerge as a critical element of his presidency. Among personal issues exposed are Polk’s management of his Mississippi plantation and the slave trading it entailed and his interactions with family members.</p></item>

                <item><p>PORTRAITURE. <hi rend="italic">A Memoir of James De Veaux, of Charleston,
                            S.C., a Member of the National Academy of Design, New York</hi>. Edited
                        by Robert W. Gibbes, with introduction and notes by Alexander Moore.
                        University of South Carolina Press. 2013. 344 pp. $16.95. ISBN:
                        9781611170986. A promising young artist who worked up and down the East
                        Coast and throughout his native South Carolina, De Veaux became the subject
                        of a biography by Gibbes, who also printed some of the artist’s diaries and
                        letters. The <hi rend="italic">Memoir</hi> recounts De Veaux’s experiences
                        in the art world of Europe and offers insight into the artistic culture of
                        antebellum South Carolina. This edition includes textual notes and adds
                        biographical and art historical information.</p></item>

                <item><p>RELIGIOUS REVIVALS. <hi rend="italic">The McCulloch “Examinations” of the
                            Cambuslang Revival (1742): A Critical Edition</hi>. Edited by Keith
                        Edward Beebe. Boydell &amp; Brewer. 2013. Volume 1: 461 pp. $70. ISBN:
                        9780906245323. Volume 2: 355 pp. $70. ISBN: 9780906245330. Consisting of
                        more than one hundred conversion narratives from the Cambuslang revival of
                        1742 in Scotland, the McCulloch <hi rend="italic">Examinations</hi> amounted
                        to Scotland’s first large-scale oral history project. Now published in their
                        entirety for the first time, these narratives shed light on a vital chapter
                        of transatlantic religious history. The edition includes the proposed
                        redactions and marginal comments of four prominent clergymen who assisted
                        McCulloch with the project.</p></item>

                <item><p>ROLLE, RICHARD. <hi rend="italic">Two Revised Versions of Rolle’s English
                            Psalter Commentary and the Related Canticles</hi>. Edited by Anne
                        Hudson. Oxford University Press. 2013. 984 pp. $125. ISBN: 9780199674299.
                        Rolle, a fourteenth-century scholar, wrote two commentaries on the Psalms,
                        one in English and one in Latin. Some fifty years after his death, his
                        English commentary was revised by a series of Lollard writers. Presented
                        here is a full edition of the first Lollard revision, based on a full study
                        of all manuscripts of both versions. It also includes twelve canticles that
                        accompanied the commentary.</p></item>

                <item><p>SIMMS, WILLIAM GILMORE. <hi rend="italic">William Gilmore Simms’s Selected
                            Reviews on Literature and Civilization</hi>. Edited by James Everett
                        Kibler Jr. and David Moltke-Hansen. University of South Carolina Press.
                        2013. 400 pp. $44.95. ISBN: 9781611172959. Simms, in addition to his own
                        creative work, was one of the United States’ most significant literary
                        critics. This volume collects sixty-two examples of his newspaper and
                        periodical reviews as well as four critical essays. A proponent of
                        romanticism, Simms read widely, reviewing French and German works, recent
                        editions of Greek and Latin classics, and such American writers as Melville
                        and Thoreau. The editors situate Simms within the wider intellectual milieu
                        that undergirded the romantic movement.</p></item>

                <item><p>SLAVE NARRATIVES. <hi rend="italic">Narrative of James Williams, an
                            American Slave</hi>. Edited by Hank Trent. Louisiana State University
                        Press. 2013. Published in 1838 to great fanfare, James Williams’s narrative
                        was eventually disowned by its publisher, the American Anti-Slavery Society,
                        after defenders of slavery challenged its authenticity. Most historians have
                        treated it as a fraud. The editor provides new biographical information that
                        confirms the identity of the author as a man enslaved in Virginia and
                        Alabama who altered his life story to throw investigators off the track.
                        This edition draws upon court cases, advertisements, census records, and
                        estate inventories never before linked to the real-life Williams.</p></item>

                <item><p>SMITH, JOSEPH. <hi rend="italic">The Joseph Smith Papers. Documents, Volume
                            1: July 1828–June 1831</hi>. Edited by Michael Hubbard MacKay, Gerrit J.
                        Dirkmaat, Grant Underwood, Robert J. Woodford, and William J. Hartley.
                        Church Historian’s Press. 2013. 558 pp. $54.95. ISBN: 9781609075774.
                        Inaugurating the core series of the <hi rend="italic">Papers</hi>, this
                        volume includes the first three years of what survives of Smith’s papers. It
                        includes letters he sent and received, revelations, minutes of meetings he
                        participated in, ecclesiastical records, and financial papers. Subjects
                        covered include the translation and publication of the Book of Mormon, the
                        establishment of the church, and a mission to Indians in the West, led by
                        Oliver Cowdery.</p></item>

                <item><p>SMITH, JOSEPH. <hi rend="italic">The Joseph Smith Papers. Documents, Volume
                            2: July 1831–January 1833</hi>. Edited by Matthew C. Godfrey, Mark
                        Ashurst-McGee, Grant Underwood, Robert J. Woodford, and William G. Hartley.
                        Church Historian’s Press. 2013. 550 pp. $54.95. ISBN: 9781609075989. Covered
                        in this volume are administrative and doctrinal developments in the church,
                        including the organization of the United Firm and the establishment of the
                        city of Zion in Missouri. Two letters from Smith to his wife Emma offer
                        insights into Smith’s family life.</p></item>

                <item><p>SWIFT, JONATHAN. <hi rend="italic">Parodies, Hoaxes, Mock Treatises: Polite
                            Conversation, Directions to Servants, and Other Works</hi>. Edited by
                        Valerie Rumbold. Cambridge University Press. 2013. 821 pp. $130. ISBN:
                        9780521843263. Among his most fascinating works, Swift’s parodies perhaps
                        require the most explication for modern readers. The editor includes
                        discussions of the political and print contexts of Swift’s Bickerstaff
                        Papers. Each work is supplemented with a headnote and significant
                        annotation, as well as a textual account that presents and discusses changes
                        in the texts over time.</p></item>

                <item><p>TEJANOS. <hi rend="italic">Recollections of a Tejano Life: Antonio Menchaca
                            in Texas History</hi>. Edited by Timothy Matovina, Jesús F. de la Teja,
                        and Justin Poché. University of Texas Press. 2013. 202 pp. $55. ISBN:
                        9780292748651. A native of San Antonio, the prominent military veteran and
                        merchant José Antonio Menchaca was one of only a few Tejano leaders to leave
                        behind a document of recollections. Reconstructed in its entirety for the
                        first time, this annotated edition captures the social life, people, and
                        events that shaped Texas’s history during its transition from Mexican
                        hinterland to independent nation to an American, and eventually Confederate,
                        state.</p></item>

                <item><p>TEXAS RANGERS. <hi rend="italic">“Pidge,” Texas Ranger</hi>. Edited by
                        Chuck Parsons. Texas A&amp;M University Press. 2013. 224 pp. $29.95. ISBN:
                        9781603449748. Thomas C. “Pidge” Robinson moved from Virginia to Texas,
                        joining the Rangers in 1874. A learned and witty writer, Robinson sent back
                        letters, poems, and reports to Austin newspapers. Compiled from these
                        submissions, this annotated compendium offers insights into the life and
                        actions of the Rangers as well as the popular culture of postbellum
                        Texas.</p></item>

                <item><p>TUCKER, ST. GEORGE. <hi rend="italic">St. George Tucker’s Law Reports and
                            Selected Papers, 1782–1825</hi>. Edited by Charles F. Hobson. University
                        of North Carolina Press. 2013. 3 vols. 2,128 pp. $250. ISBN: 9780807837214.
                        A comprehensive set of the Virginia jurist’s law reports and selected loose
                        papers, this is an unsurpassed archive for examining the adaptation of the
                        common law during the period of the early republic. Tucker’s reports fill a
                        documentary gap caused by the 1865 fire that destroyed Virginia’s higher
                        court records. The edition includes a biographical register and
                        correspondence related to the rupture between Tucker and Spencer
                    Roane.</p></item>

                <item><p>TWAIN, MARK. <hi rend="italic">Autobiography of Mark Twain, Volume 2: The
                            Complete and Authoritative Edition</hi>. Edited by Benjamin Griffin,
                        Harriet E. Smith, Victor Fischer, Michael Barry Frank, Sharon K. Goetz, and
                        Leslie Diane Myrick. University of California Press.
                        2013.<!--This was already here--> 776 pp. $45. ISBN: 9780520272781. This
                        volume delves deeper into Twain’s life, uncovering the many roles he played.
                        Filled with his characteristic blend of humor and ire, the narrative exposes
                        his views on writing and speaking, his concerns with money, and his
                        observations on politics and politicians of the day.</p></item>

                <item><p>VIRGINIA.<hi rend="italic"> The History and Present State of Virginia</hi>.
                        By Robert Beverley. Edited by Susan Scott Parrish. University of North
                        Carolina Press. 2013.<!--In light of the email, I added this date, however it was not in the original word doc-->
                        416 pp. $45. ISBN: 9781469607948. A Virginia native, Robert Beverley
                        published his account of the colony while visiting London in 1705. The <hi
                            rend="italic">History</hi> provided English readers with information on
                        Virginia’s political economy, past, natural history, and Indians. Based on a
                        fresh transcription of the 1705 edition, this volume presents a
                        comprehensive comparison of emendations in the 1722 edition and situates its
                        author in the context of the political and cultural issues of his
                    day.</p></item>

                <item><p>WALLACE, ALFRED RUSSEL. <hi rend="italic">On the Organic Law of Change: A
                            Facsimile Edition and Annotated Transcription of Alfred Russel Wallace’s
                            Species Notebook of 1855–1859</hi>. Edited by James T. Costa. Harvard
                        University Press. 2013. 640 pp. $49.95. ISBN: 9780674724884. To mark the
                        centennial of the famous naturalist’s death, this edition presents a
                        facsimile, transcription, and annotation of Wallace’s “Species Notebook,”
                        which he kept during an expedition to Malaysia, Indonesia, and New Guinea.
                        The notebooks sketch out Wallace’s evolutionary theory, which, like
                        Darwin’s, was premised on the notion of natural selection. The edition
                        asserts Wallace’s stature as a founder of biogeography and pioneer of the
                        theory of evolution.</p></item>

                <item><p>WARREN, ROBERT PENN. <hi rend="italic">Selected Letters of Robert Penn
                            Warren, Volume 6: Toward Sunset, at a Great Height, 1980–1989</hi>.
                        Edited by Randy Hendricks and James A. Perkins. Louisiana State University
                        Press. 2013. 480 pp. $90. ISBN: 9780807152829. The sixth and final volume of
                        this selected edition, <hi rend="italic">Toward Sunset</hi> documents the
                        final decade of Warren’s life, when he published three volumes of poetry, a
                        work of nonfiction prose, and a memoir. In his last years he became
                        frustrated with the poetry he was able to write but continued to be a lively
                        correspondent, filling his letters with details of his home life and that of
                        his children. To the end he maintained a stoic attitude regarding his
                        physical decline and continued to encourage younger poets he
                    admired.</p></item>

                <item><p>WASHINGTON, GEORGE. <hi rend="italic">The Papers of George Washington,
                            Presidential Series, Volume 17: 1 October 1794–31 March 1795</hi>.
                        Edited by David R. Hoth and Carol S. Ebel. University of Virginia Press.
                        2013. 800 pp. $85. ISBN: 9780813934167. Highlighted by documents connected
                        to the suppression of the Whiskey Rebellion and the negotiation of the Jay
                        Treaty, this volume begins with Washington in the field, before his
                        determination that quelling the insurrection in western Pennsylvania no
                        longer required his presence. Letters from Alexander Hamilton kept him
                        apprised of the situation, and subsequently he entertained requests for
                        pardons for participants in the rebellion. Other issues covered include
                        Indian affairs in the wake of the Battle of Fallen Timbers and the departure
                        of Thomas Pinckney to revive stalled negotiations with Spain.</p></item>

                <item><p>WASHINGTON, GEORGE. <hi rend="italic">The Papers of George Washington,
                            Revolutionary War Series, Volume 22: 1 August–21 October 1779. Edited by
                            Benjamin L. Huggins</hi>. University of Virginia Press. 2013. 904 pp.
                        $85. ISBN: 9780813933665. During this period, Washington worked to
                        strengthen the fortifications at West Point and planned the successful
                        attack on Paulus Hook, New Jersey. He also supervised logistical support for
                        the American expedition against the Six Nations and intensified defensive
                        preparations for the expected reinforcement of British troops in the Hudson
                        area.</p></item>

                <item><p>WASHINGTON TERRITORY. <hi rend="italic">Selected Letters of A. M. A.
                            Blanchet, Bishop of Walla Walla and Nesqualy, 1847–1879</hi>. Edited by
                        Roberta Stringham Brown and Patricia O’Connell Killen. Translated by Roberta
                        Stringham Brown. University of Washington Press. 2013. 288 pp. $40. ISBN:
                        9780295992631. Named the first bishop of Walla Walla in 1846, A. M. A.
                        Blanchet spent thirty-two years in the Pacific Northwest, a time of rapid
                        change for the region. The editors have chosen forty-five of the almost nine
                        hundred letters Blanchet sent to his colleagues and superiors in Montreal,
                        Paris, and Rome, other missionaries, and US government officials. The
                        letters provide firsthand glimpses of signal events in the region’s history
                        as well as observations on ordinary settlers, native populations, and the
                        struggle to build educational and social organizations. </p></item>

                <item><p>WILDE, OSCAR. <hi rend="italic">The Complete Works of Oscar Wilde, Volume
                            5: Plays I</hi>. Edited by Joseph Donohue. Oxford University Press.
                        2013. 848 pp. $250. ISBN: 9780198119579. The first volume of a critical
                        edition of Wilde’s plays, it presents <hi rend="italic">The Duchess of
                            Padua</hi>, <hi rend="italic">Salome: Drame en un Acte</hi>, and <hi
                            rend="italic">Salome: Tragedy in One Act</hi>. Encompassing all
                        surviving manuscript material and other documents, the edition contains
                        comprehensive introductions to the plays and extensive
                    annotations.</p></item>

                <item><p>WILDE, OSCAR. <hi rend="italic">The Complete Works of Oscar Wilde, Volume
                            6: Journalism I</hi>. Edited by John Stokes and Mark Turner. Oxford
                        University Press. 2013. 1,064 pp. ISBN: 9780198119647. <hi rend="italic"
                            >Volume 7: Journalism II</hi>. 532 pp. ISBN: 9780198119630. $250. These
                        two volumes print all of Wilde’s known contributions, both signed and
                        anonymous, to periodicals and newspapers. Reviews, articles, and editorials
                        showcase Wilde’s extraordinary cultural knowledge and his witty,
                        intellectually acute style. The volumes provide an essential record of the
                        vibrant and rapidly changing journalistic culture in which Wilde played a
                        part.</p></item>

                <item><p>WOODWARD, C. VANN. <hi rend="italic">The Letters of C. Vann Woodward</hi>.
                            Edited by Michael O’Brien. Yale University Press. 2013. 480 pp.
                        $40. ISBN: 9780300185348. One of the most important American historians of
                        the twentieth century, Woodward left behind a body of wry and often funny
                        letters. Correspondents include Richard Hofstadter, John Kennedy, David
                        Riesman, and Robert Penn Warren. Woodward’s letters shed light on what it
                        meant to be an American radical and public intellectual.</p></item>
            </list>


        </body>
    </text>
</TEI>
