<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<?oxygen RNGSchema="http://www.scholarlyediting.org/scholarlyediting.rng" type="xml"?>

<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xml:lang="eng">
    <teiHeader>
        <fileDesc>
            <titleStmt>
                <title level="a" type="main">Review: <hi rend="italic">Creating a Movement with
                        Teeth: A Documentary History of the George Jackson Brigade</hi>. Edited by
                    Daniel Burton-Rose.</title>
                <title level="a" type="sub"/>
                <author key="Glick, Silvia P.">Silvia P. Glick</author>
            </titleStmt>
            <editionStmt>
                <edition>
                    <date>2014</date><!--is this right-->
                </edition>
            </editionStmt>
            <publicationStmt>
                <idno type="file">review.burton-rose</idno>
                <authority>Scholary Editing: The Annual of the Association for Documentary
                    Editing</authority>
                <address>
 <addrLine>http://www.scholarlyediting.org</addrLine>
</address>
                <publisher>Association for Documentary Editing</publisher>
                <publisher>University of Nebraska&#8211;Lincoln</publisher>
                <distributor>
                    <name>Center for Digital Research in the Humanities</name>
                    <address>
<addrLine>319 Love Library</addrLine>
<addrLine>University of Nebraska&#8211;Lincoln</addrLine>
<addrLine>Lincoln, NE 68588-4100</addrLine>
<addrLine>http://cdrh.unl.edu</addrLine>
 </address>
                </distributor>
                <date>2014</date>
                <availability>
                    <p>Scholary Editing: The Annual of the Association for Documentary Editing is
                        freely distributed by the Association for Documentary Editing and the Center
                        for Digital Research in the Humanities at the University of Nebraska-Lincoln
                        and licensed under a Creative Commons Attribution-NonCommercial-ShareAlike
                        3.0 Unported License</p>
                </availability>
            </publicationStmt>
            <seriesStmt>
                <title level="j">Scholarly Editing: The Annual of the Association for Documentary
                    Editing</title>
                <respStmt>
                    <resp>editor</resp>
                    <name xml:id="ag" key="Gailey, Amanda A.">Amanda Gailey</name>
                </respStmt>
                <respStmt>
                    <resp>editor</resp>
                    <name xml:id="awj" key="Jewell, Andrew W.">Andrew Jewell</name>
                </respStmt>
                <idno type="vol">35</idno>
                <idno type="ISSN">2167-1257</idno>
            </seriesStmt>
            <sourceDesc>
                <bibl>
                    <note>Born digital.</note>
                </bibl>
            </sourceDesc>
        </fileDesc>
        <revisionDesc>
            <change when="2014-02-26"><name xml:id="gk" key="Kirilloff, Gabi">Gabi Kirilloff</name>
                markup in TEI XML</change>
        </revisionDesc>
    </teiHeader>
    <text>
        <body>
            <head type="main"><hi rend="italic">Creating a Movement with Teeth: A Documentary
                    History of the George Jackson Brigade</hi>. Edited by Daniel Burton-Rose.
                Oakland, CA: PM Press, 2010. 315 pp. ISBN: 978-1-60486-223-2. $24.95.</head>
            <p><hi rend="italic">Creating a Movement with Teeth: A Documentary History of the George
                    Jackson Brigade</hi>, edited by Daniel Burton-Rose, contains a selection of
                documents by and about the George Jackson Brigade, the Seattle-based revolutionary
                group that was active in the 1970s. The brigade's members believed that without the
                use of arms, there would be no revolution. "The main point of unity for the Brigade
                has always been the determination to fight capitalism—with force of arms—here and
                now" (148). Although the brigade believed that the central task of revolutionaries
                was mass organizing, they also believed in developing the theory and practice of
                armed struggle (149). While an ideological division existed within the brigade
                between its Marxist-Leninist members and those who advocated anarchism, they all
                agreed on the desired outcome of their actions. They sought a "classless, stateless
                society," as they worked toward the overthrow of the U.S. government and capitalism
                (169).</p>
            <p>With only seven members, the George Jackson Brigade was exceptional for its
                diversity. Five members were "queer or bisexual," four were ex-convicts, three were
                women, and one was black (21). Their inspiration was George Jackson, a member of the
                Black Panther Party who was killed on August 21, 1971, during an attempt to escape
                from the prison in San Quentin. Jackson was clear on the need for arms: "The
                government of the U.S.A. and all that it stands for, all that it represents, must be
                destroyed. This is the starting point, and the end. We have the means to this end;
                the problem is to develop acceptance of their use" (11).</p>
            <p>The George Jackson Brigade first struck on May 31, 1975, bombing the Division of
                Corrections in the Capitol Complex Building in Olympia, Washington. Its final action
                was a robbery of a Tacoma branch of the Puget Sound National Bank on February 28,
                1978. In between, the brigade bombed two banks; offices of the FBI and the Bureau of
                Indian Affairs; a Safeway supermarket and a Safeway warehouse and distribution
                center; and a Puget Sound Power and Light substation serving a wealthy community. It
                robbed state liquor stores and more than ten banks in Washington and Oregon.<ptr
                    target="#note1" xml:id="nr1" n="1"/> The brigade's last members—Janine Bertram,
                Therese Coupez, and John Sherman—were arrested by federal agents on March 21, 1978,
                the day they planned to rob a Tacoma branch of the United Mutual Savings Bank. They
                have all since been released from prison.</p>
            <p>The selected documents, which include communiqués, newspaper articles, interviews,
                and a political statement, cover the period of the brigade's activity from 1975 to
                1977. <hi rend="italic">Creating a Movement with Teeth</hi> is intended as a
                companion volume to Burton-Rose's <hi rend="italic">Guerrilla USA: The George
                    Jackson Brigade and the Anticapitalist Underground of the 1970</hi>s (2010). In
                his short introduction, Burton-Rose sets forth his purpose in preparing the volume:
                    <q rend="block">It provides the original documents upon which [<hi rend="italic"
                        >Guerrilla USA</hi>] is in part based so that interested readers may access
                    the writings of the Brigade and their interlocutors relatively unmediated. My
                    goal in collecting these documents is not apologia: reproducing the communiqués
                    implies no more an endorsement of their contents than reprinting the
                    accompanying poems implies aesthetic appreciation. . . . Rather, I am attempting
                    to supplement an anemic record of the radical social movements of the 1970s, and
                    to preserve and pass down a collective engagement with the ever-vexing problem
                    of community self-defense and revolution in the United States.
                (23–24)</q>Indeed, it is as a companion volume to <hi rend="italic">Guerrilla
                    USA</hi> that this collection is most useful, since the introductory material,
                headnotes, and endnotes provide only limited guidance in locating the documentary
                material within the history of the brigade, and within the broader context of
                movements for social change in the 1970s.</p>
            <p>While Burton-Rose neither condemns nor outright approves the use of violence in
                pursuit of revolution, Ward Churchill, writing the book's preface, is more
                forthcoming. Churchill asserts that only through the work of Burton-Rose and others
                "can the real history of what was unquestionably the most coruscating revolutionary
                moment in recent American history be revealed, its meaning(s) honestly/accurately
                evaluated, its theoretical/tactical defects identified and corrected, its utility
                recalibrated for more effective present/future application(s)" (15). The reader may
                reasonably conclude that Burton-Rose is sympathetic to this view. His support of
                violence is barely tempered with statements such as: "If one is to have bombers
                active in one's own city, it seems desirable that they at least be ambivalent and
                self-denigrating, as Brigade members were" (23).</p>
            <p>In the short section on editorial conventions following the introduction, the editor
                states that documents are reproduced essentially as they were, although
                insignificant errors have been silently emended and punctuation has been
                standardized. Information has been provided on individuals and organizations that
                may not be immediately familiar to readers. (However, Burton-Rose assumes a good
                deal of knowledge on the part of his readers.) More explanation of the editorial
                principles that the editor followed would have been useful. For example, all the
                documents are titled, but it is not clear whether the titles are from the original
                documents or whether they have been added by the editor.</p>
            <p>The volume is arranged into four parts. Part 1 contains profiles of the brigade's
                members and is itself divided into three sections: reports of law enforcement; press
                coverage in the mainstream media; and articles in the countercultural press. Part 2
                contains the brigade's communiqués—its statements explaining the group's actions and
                goals. It is not clear what criteria the editor used in selecting the communiqués.
                Although it seems likely that Burton-Rose included all the communiqués issued by the
                brigade, clarification of this point would have been helpful. The communiqués are
                from "former Brigade members' personal papers and a file kept by the now-defunct
                Toronto-based political prisoner support collective Arm the Spirit" (25). Many of
                the communiqués are in the FBI's file on the brigade, and they are all contained in
                the files of the Seattle Police Department's Intelligence Division. Most of the
                communiqués have headnotes indicating date and place of publication (usually in the
                countercultural press). A few documents are preceded by extensive explanatory
                material, which allows the reader a fuller appreciation of a document's
                significance. "The Power of the People Is the Source of Life," the political
                statement of the George Jackson Brigade, comprises Part 3. Also included in this
                part are the brigade's chronology of its actions and an open letter to the brigade
                from the Valerian Coven, which was "an anonymous collection of politically active
                workers and students in the Seattle area."<ptr target="#note2" xml:id="nr2" n="2"
                /></p>
            <p> Part 4 is comprised of interviews, open letters, critiques of the brigade, and other
                pieces that were published in <hi rend="italic">Northwest Passage</hi>, a
                countercultural periodical based in Bellingham and Seattle from the late 1960s into
                the 1980s. Burton-Rose's preference for the countercultural press over the
                mainstream press reflects his political bent. Other than profiles of brigade members
                included in Part 1, Burton-Rose ignores the mainstream press—in his words, the
                "corporate media." He includes no articles describing the injuries to persons and
                property that were caused by the brigade's actions. The reader has no sense of the
                effect of the brigade's bombings and armed robberies on the general population.</p>
            <p>The last part of <hi rend="italic">Creating a Movement with Teeth</hi> is titled
                "Processing" and is an interview by Burton-Rose with former brigade members Bo
                Brown, Mark Cook, and Ed Mead, which took place in October 2005. When asked to give
                their perspectives on the brigade's impact, the responses of the former members show
                that none of them have any illusions about what they accomplished. "It politicized a
                lot of people," said Cook. Brown stated that they brought "the prison struggle
                closer to the forefront of regular people's minds" (264–65).</p>
            <p>Rather than separating the documents into these five parts, a chronological
                arrangement would have made the brigade's history more accessible. For example, an
                interview with Ed Mead from May 1976, in Part 4, refers to a communiqué issued on
                International Women's Day in March 1976, which is in Part 2. The brigade's political
                statement, issued on November 3, 1977, follows a communiqué issued on Easter Sunday
                1978. The placing of the notes at the end of the book, rather than following each
                document, contributes to the sense of disjointedness.</p>
            <p>As noted above, <hi rend="italic">Creating a Movement with Teeth</hi> is best
                considered together with <hi rend="italic">Guerrilla USA</hi>, which gives a
                thorough history of the George Jackson Brigade. Together, these volumes achieve
                Burton-Rose's goal of supplementing the record of the radical social movements of
                the 1970s. This is a good thing. Whether or not the editor also has achieved his
                thinly veiled goal of making readers more sympathetic to the brigade, and to the use
                of arms in bringing about a more just society, remains an open question.</p>

            <signed><name>Silvia P. Glick</name><affiliation>Boston
                University</affiliation></signed>
        </body>
        <back>
            <div type="notes">
                <note xml:id="note1">Daniel Burton-Rose, <hi rend="italic">Guerrilla USA: The George
                        Jackson Brigade and the Anticapitalist Underground of the 1970s</hi>
                    (Berkeley: University of California Press, 2010), xvi–xvii.</note>
                <note xml:id="note2">Burton-Rose, <hi rend="italic">Guerrilla USA</hi>, 70.</note>
            </div>
        </back>
    </text>
</TEI>
