<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xml:lang="eng">
    <teiHeader>
        <fileDesc>
            <titleStmt>
                <title level="a" type="main">Review: <hi rend="italic">The Papers of Eliza Lucas
                        Pinckney and Harriott Pinckney Horry: Digital Edition</hi>. Edited by
                    Constance Schulz, Robin Copp, Mary Sherrer, Nicollette Calhoun, Peggy Clark,
                    Taylor Kirton, Rachel Love, Justin McIntyre, Neal Millikan, and Benjamin
                    Sheinkin.</title>
                <title level="a" type="sub"/>
                <author key="Kierner, Cynthia A.">Cynthia A. Kierner</author>
            </titleStmt>
            <editionStmt>
                <edition>
                    <date>2014</date><!--is this right-->
                </edition>
            </editionStmt>
            <publicationStmt>
                <idno type="file">review.pinckney</idno>
                <authority>Scholary Editing: The Annual of the Association for Documentary
                    Editing</authority>
                <address>
 <addrLine>http://www.scholarlyediting.org</addrLine>
</address>
                <publisher>Association for Documentary Editing</publisher>
                <publisher>University of Nebraska&#8211;Lincoln</publisher>
                <distributor>
                    <name>Center for Digital Research in the Humanities</name>
                    <address>
<addrLine>319 Love Library</addrLine>
<addrLine>University of Nebraska&#8211;Lincoln</addrLine>
<addrLine>Lincoln, NE 68588-4100</addrLine>
<addrLine>http://cdrh.unl.edu</addrLine>
 </address>
                </distributor>
                <date>2014</date>
                <availability>
                    <p>Scholary Editing: The Annual of the Association for Documentary Editing is
                        freely distributed by the Association for Documentary Editing and the Center
                        for Digital Research in the Humanities at the University of Nebraska-Lincoln
                        and licensed under a Creative Commons Attribution-NonCommercial-ShareAlike
                        3.0 Unported License</p>
                </availability>
            </publicationStmt>
            <seriesStmt>
                <title level="j">Scholarly Editing: The Annual of the Association for Documentary
                    Editing</title>
                <respStmt>
                    <resp>editor</resp>
                    <name xml:id="ag" key="Gailey, Amanda A.">Amanda Gailey</name>
                </respStmt>
                <respStmt>
                    <resp>editor</resp>
                    <name xml:id="awj" key="Jewell, Andrew W.">Andrew Jewell</name>
                </respStmt>
                <idno type="vol">35</idno>
                <idno type="ISSN">2167-1257</idno>
            </seriesStmt>
            <sourceDesc>
                <bibl>
                    <note>Born digital.</note>
                </bibl>
            </sourceDesc>
        </fileDesc>
        <revisionDesc>
            <change when="2014-02-26"><name xml:id="gk" key="Kirilloff, Gabi">Gabi Kirilloff</name>
                markup in TEI XML</change>
        </revisionDesc>
    </teiHeader>
    <text>
        <body>
            <head type="main"><hi rend="italic">The Papers of Eliza Lucas Pinckney and Harriott
                    Pinckney Horry: Digital Edition</hi>. Edited by Constance Schulz, Robin Copp,
                Mary Sherrer, Nicollette Calhoun, Peggy Clark, Taylor Kirton, Rachel Love, Justin
                McIntyre, Neal Millikan, and Benjamin Sheinkin. Charlottesville, VA: Rotunda, 2012.
                $60 (individuals). $115–$595 (institutional).</head>
            <p>For historians of early America, Eliza Lucas Pinckney is the southern Abigail Adams:
                an erudite and well-connected female whose unusually rich surviving archive makes
                her the other go-to exemplar of white womanhood in colonial and revolutionary
                America. Known chiefly through her published letterbook as a pioneer of indigo
                cultivation in colonial South Carolina, and also as the mother of patriots—her two
                sons were prominent revolutionaries and later Federalists&#8212;Pinckney is a well-known
                and worthy subject.</p>
            <p>Her equally worthy daughter, Harriott Pinckney Horry, is less widely known today,
                though she left three fascinating travel journals and a recipe book, besides her
                significant correspondence. Like her mother, Horry was an active and knowledgeable
                plantation mistress, in part because she (also like her mother) was widowed at a
                relatively early age. As Constance Schulz observes in her introduction to this
                excellent collection, Horry's "life paralleled that of her mother in many ways, but
                also illustrates some of the profound changes which women of the South experienced
                after American independence."</p>
            <p>This born-digital edition includes every document written by or to Pinckney and
                Horry, along with some others (mostly family correspondence) that shed further light
                on their lives. Schulz divides the documents into three sections—correspondence,
                legal, and financial papers; Horry's travel journals; and recipe books from both
                women—though readers can search all these collections simultaneously. Pinckney-Horry
                family letters constitute the bulk of the documents, most of which are published
                here for the first time. A 1972 print edition of Eliza Lucas Pinckney's letterbook
                stopped in 1762, though Pinckney lived until 1793. A print edition of Harriott
                Pinckney Horry's cookbook—included here in a downloadable digital format—was
                published in 1984, but Horry's letters and travel journals have not previously been
                published.</p>
            <p>In form and spirit, this project builds on Holly Shulman's <hi rend="italic">Dolley
                    Madison Digital Edition</hi>, also published by Rotunda, the digital imprint of
                the University of Virginia Press. As Schultz explains, she shares Shulman's belief
                that female members of the founding generation of the American republic had
                compelling stories, many of which can be told through their papers. Shulman's
                digital edition of Dolley Madison's papers, which meets current scholarly standards
                for documentary editing, is the prototype for Schulz's project. In an ideal world,
                other digitized collections of women's papers will follow, published on the same
                platform to create "the possibility that scholars using such editions could search
                digitally across the writings of many women for their common experiences and
                concerns."</p>
            <p>The documents here are fully searchable by keyword, author, recipient, document type,
                date, place, and topic. The topics preloaded in the search box suggest the gendered
                nature of the documents. While the topic "health/illness" (ranked first with 333
                hits) reflects the universality of such concerns in a comparatively perilous era,
                the preponderance of documents pertaining to "family" (second with 270 hits) and
                "children" (third with 261) shows the dominant preoccupations of even these most
                cosmopolitan southern women. That said, Pinckney and Horry were also knowledgeable
                about agriculture (188 hits) and politics (46 hits), and their papers include
                letters exchanged with family members about military engagements during the
                Revolution, and also two that Horry sent to General Nathaniel Greene to request
                permission (apparently unsuccessfully) to export rice to London "for the maintenance
                and Education" of her son who attended school there during the war.</p>
            <p>Both Pinckney and Horry were accomplished plantation mistresses, and their recipe
                books offer a window onto women's work and domestic life. Perhaps not surprisingly,
                certain recipes appear in both Pinckney's and Horry's collections. Pinckney's book
                has more nonfood entries, ranging from the medicinal (including a beeswax "salve for
                corns") to the fanciful ("how to grow hair"), though Horry's book also includes some
                home remedies and instructions for household hints, such as how to use rice flour to
                make "cheap paint."</p>
            <p>Notwithstanding their domestic duties and occupations, mother and daughter were well
                traveled for women of their era. Pinckney's early letters chronicle her years in
                London as a young wife and mother. Truly a denizen of the British Atlantic world,
                she was born in Antigua, lived later in South Carolina and in London, and maintained
                transatlantic friendships for much of her life. Horry's journals record her tour of
                the northern states in 1793 (which began with a sojourn in Philadelphia, where her
                mother died of breast cancer), travels in South Carolina in 1795, and another trip
                northward in 1815. An enthusiastic and well-informed tourist, Horry readily absorbed
                (and reported) information about battlefields, religious sects, agricultural
                methods, social life, technological advances, and other subjects. Unfortunately, her
                journal is difficult to read in its original state—in other words, as one continuous
                book—because each entry is treated here as a separate document, which requires the
                reader to return to the list of contents to advance to each subsequent entry. Adding
                buttons to click for the "next" and "previous" entries would be a huge
                improvement.</p>
            <p>Overall, however, this collection is remarkably well orchestrated. Documents have
                been expertly transcribed and thoroughly annotated. Each has an accompanying sidebar
                that includes links to an impressive glossary, which identifies people, places, and
                terms as well as the relevant topics under which the document is cross-listed. Also
                included in the sidebar is a brief summary of the document. Though few in number,
                maps and illustrations are useful. The family trees are less so: difficult to read,
                they nonetheless provide essential information to readers who are patient enough to
                manipulate them effectively.</p>
            <p>Historians of the colonial, revolutionary, and early republican eras will appreciate
                this excellent collection and share my hope that more such editions of papers of the
                so-called Founding Mothers will be forthcoming. <hi rend="italic">The Papers of
                    Eliza Lucas Pinckney and Harriott Pinckney Horry</hi> is a welcome contribution
                to the fields of early American, southern, and women's history.</p>
            <signed><name>Cynthia A. Kierner</name><affiliation>George Mason
                    University</affiliation></signed>
        </body>
    </text>
</TEI>
