<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<?oxygen RNGSchema="http://www.scholarlyediting.org/scholarlyediting.rng" type="xml"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xml:lang="eng">
    <teiHeader>
        <fileDesc>
            <titleStmt>
                <title level="a" type="main">Exceptional Measures</title>
                <title level="a" type="sub">The Human Sciences in STEM
                    Worlds</title>
                <author key="McGann, Jerome">Jerome McGann</author>
            </titleStmt>
            <editionStmt>
                <edition>
                    <date>2016</date>
                </edition>
            </editionStmt>
            <publicationStmt>
                <idno type="file">essay.mcgann</idno>
                <authority>Scholary Editing: The Annual of the Association for Documentary
                    Editing</authority>
                <address>
 <addrLine>http://www.scholarlyediting.org</addrLine>
</address>
                <publisher>Association for Documentary Editing</publisher>
                <publisher>University of Nebraska&#8211;Lincoln</publisher>
                <distributor>
                    <name>Center for Digital Research in the Humanities</name>
                    <address>
<addrLine>319 Love Library</addrLine>
<addrLine>University of Nebraska&#8211;Lincoln</addrLine>
<addrLine>Lincoln, NE 68588-4100</addrLine>
<addrLine>http://cdrh.unl.edu</addrLine>
 </address>
                </distributor>
                <date>2016</date>
                <availability>
                    <p>Scholary Editing: The Annual of the Association for Documentary Editing is
                        freely distributed by the Association for Documentary Editing and the Center
                        for Digital Research in the Humanities at the University of Nebraska-Lincoln
                        and licensed under a Creative Commons Attribution-NonCommercial-ShareAlike
                        3.0 Unported License</p>
                </availability>
            </publicationStmt>
            <seriesStmt>
                <title level="j">Scholarly Editing: The Annual of the Association for Documentary
                    Editing</title>
                <respStmt>
                    <resp>editor</resp>
                    <name xml:id="ag" key="Gailey, Amanda A.">Amanda Gailey</name>
                </respStmt>
                <respStmt>
                    <resp>editor</resp>
                    <name xml:id="awj" key="Jewell, Andrew W.">Andrew Jewell</name>
                </respStmt>
                <idno type="vol">37</idno>
                <idno type="ISSN">2167-1257</idno>
            </seriesStmt>
            <sourceDesc>
                <bibl>
                    <note>Born digital.</note>
                </bibl>
            </sourceDesc>
        </fileDesc>
        <revisionDesc>
            <change when="2016-03-23"><name xml:id="gk" key="Kirilloff, Gabi"> Gabi Kirilloff</name>
                markup in TEI XML</change>
        </revisionDesc>
    </teiHeader>
    <text>
        <front>
            <head type="main">Exceptional Measures</head>
            <head type="sub">The Human Sciences in STEM Worlds</head>
            <byline>Jerome McGann</byline>
            <epigraph>
                <cit>
                    <quote>I have imagined a man who might live as the coldest scholar on
                        earth.</quote>
                    <bibl>&#8212;John Haines, <hi rend="italic">The Stars, the Snow, the Fire</hi>
                        (1989)</bibl>
                </cit>
            </epigraph>
            <epigraph>
                <cit>
                    <quote>And all that has existed in the space of six thousand years: Permanent,
                        &amp; not lost not lost nor vanishd, &amp; every little act, Word. work.
                        &amp; wish. that has existed, all remaining </quote>
                    <bibl>&#8212;William Blake, <hi rend="italic">Jerusalem</hi> (chap. 1 plate
                        13)</bibl>
                </cit>
            </epigraph>
        </front>
        <body>
            <p>Almost 2,500 years ago Socrates and Plato spent their lives promoting the thought
                that “there is nothing at the same time finer and more practical than the
                    truth.”<ptr target="#note1" xml:id="nr1" n="1"/> Their key word was
                “aletheia”&#8212;usually translated “truth,” or the disclosure of obscured or hidden
                reality. Humanists have championed and pursued the idea ever since. Most men and
                women of science share that humanist commitment.</p>
            <p>That is what I want to talk about: the education and scholarship that promotes Truth
                and Method and their everyday human practicality.<ptr target="#note2" xml:id="nr2"
                    n="2"/> Because today that subject is shaped by our online and digital
                circumstances, it is often approached as a technical problem of epistemology,
                management economics, or institutional policy. After all, we <hi rend="italic"
                    >are</hi> data-point functions in a complex internetwork of social media. But
                that is exactly why the problem of truth and method is, and has always been, an
                ethical problem, pressing for ourselves as individual moral agents, and why it has
                had certain highly charged mythic names like Socrates, Doctor Faustus, Victor
                Frankenstein, Ahab. Each brings an ethical emergency into sharp focus. Edward
                Snowden is the mythic name for an ethical emergency of our time.</p>
            <p>Most of the people I will talk about we wouldn’t call scholars, least of all
                characters of myth. All of them are Americans, a choice I make for three reasons.
                First, I am their secret sharer, for better and for worse. I see them from an inner
                standing point. Second, Americans have always had a decided yen to throw technical
                resources and solutions at every kind of problem. And third, the American empire is
                a virtual empire and Edward Snowden is the empire’s demon child.</p>
            <p>Some of the people I shall discuss are celebrated Americans, like Emerson and
                Thoreau. One is less celebrated but in my view perhaps no less glorious—the
                environmentalist Barry Lopez. And one other is more famous than he is
                celebrated—Vice President Dick Cheney. Two card-carrying scholars will also make an
                appearance. With respect to our space-time and my interests, all are what Emerson
                would call “Representative Men.” They help me think about the place of scholarship
                and education in our mediated and furiously presentist world.</p>
            <p>Scholarship and education, our particular vocational obligations, are increasingly
                organized through automated data machines and the social agents that manage them.
                This institutional effort to save, share, augment, and engineer knowledge and
                information with digital resources is alternately lamented and extolled by humanist
                scholars, and in each case with good reason.</p>
            <p>Consider the plus side. Digitization is already promoting research that would not
                have been possible using traditional so-called analog tools, and we are only
                beginning to explore the capabilities of this technology. But all technologies have
                always been machines of Enlightenment, as the history of book and other textual
                technologies themselves testify. As such, they are also all Faustian technologies.
                They underwrite those myths of mastery and control recently studied as the <hi
                    rend="italic">Dialectic of Enlightenment</hi>.<ptr target="#note3" xml:id="nr3"
                    n="3"/> We can now data mine just about everything and everyone we’ve never
                heard of. But of course that is precisely the problem. Perhaps never before have we
                been able to “know about” so much and yet to <hi rend="italic">know</hi> so little
                of what we know.<ptr target="#note4" xml:id="nr4" n="4"/> Gaining power, we become
                alienated from our weaknesses, according to the mighty working that Thomas Hardy
                long ago sketched in his reflections on the <hi rend="italic">Titanic</hi>: <quote><lg>
                        <l>And as the smart ship grew</l>
                        <l>In stature, grace, and hue,</l>
                        <l>In shadowy, silent distance, grew the iceberg too.<ptr target="#note5"
                                xml:id="nr5" n="5"/></l>
                    </lg></quote></p>
            <p>That is our situation today, as Paul Connerton, among many others, has helped us to
                see. But it is a situation with a long history, probably as long as human history
                itself. Here my pitiful American view picks up from August 1837, when Ralph Waldo
                Emerson delivered a lecture to the Phi Beta Kappa Society in Cambridge. It would be
                my country’s most influential manifesto for the scholar’s vocation. Working from an
                image of “the Soul erect and Unconquered still” (<hi rend="italic">Journal</hi>, May
                21, 1837), Emerson elaborated what he called “a theory of the Scholar’s office”: “to
                read in all books . . . the one incorruptible text of truth” (<hi rend="italic"
                    >Journal</hi>, July 29, 1837).<ptr target="#note6" xml:id="nr6" n="6"/> At the
                theory’s core was the view he had introduced in the previous year with his
                Transcendentalist testimonial, <hi rend="italic">Nature</hi>.<ptr target="#note7"
                    xml:id="nr7" n="7"/> What that essay called the “transparent eyeball” became in
                the lecture “Man Thinking.” Emerson was proposing an Enlightenment ideal of
                intellectual freedom as it was modified through Romantic ideas about organic energy:
                    <q rend="block">Free should the scholar be, &#8212;free and brave. Free even to
                    the definition of freedom, “without any hindrance that does not arise out of his
                    own constitution.”<ptr target="#note8" xml:id="nr8" n="8"/></q></p>
            <p>Not the least significant feature of Emerson’s lecture was the public context in
                which it was delivered. Three months earlier, in mid-May, the United States had
                begun its long plunge into the depression that historians call the “Panic of 1837,”
                an economic crisis that would last—like our own recent one—for seven years.
                Reflecting on that “emphatic and universal calamity” in his May <hi rend="italic"
                    >Journal</hi>, Emerson thought it presented him with a singular opportunity: to
                expose what he saw as the true “bankruptcy” of the nation. Now that “the boasted
                world [of getting and spending] had come to nothing” (<hi rend="italic"
                >Journal</hi>, May 21, 1837), Emerson decided “to inquire if the Ideal might not be
                tried” as an inspiration to a “generation . . . bankrupt of principles and hope.”
                That inquiry became his famous lecture of August 29, “The American Scholar.”</p>
            <p>Emerson was exaggerating when he suggested that the “Commodity” world of the United
                States had “come to nothing” in the financial collapse. More exactly, the crash had
                exposed yet again one of the more dismal laws driving the country’s political
                economy. So Emerson moved to make Transcendental capital from the legacy of those
                quotidian laws. He wanted Americans to embrace what he called in a later lecture the
                “Spiritual Laws” (1841) of the sovereign individual. The custodian of those Higher
                Laws is Emerson’s American Scholar, whose mission is to “master”—that is Emerson’s
                key word—the brute circumstances of daily life. As he majestically declares, “The
                true scholar [is] the only true master.” <q rend="block">He learns that he who has
                    mastered any law in his private thoughts, is master to that extent of all men
                    whose language he speaks, and of all into whose language his own can be
                        translated.<ptr target="#note9" xml:id="nr9" n="9"/></q>For Emerson, the
                Panic of 1837 was the recurrent legacy of the Commodity masters of America. Yet that
                commercial power was for Emerson not masterful but anarchic. To escape subjection to
                its anarchs, one must first recognize how “Nature” is “the first in importance of
                the influences” upon the American Scholar, or Man Thinking. This is the lecture’s
                initial move.</p>
            <p>And the question is definitely <hi rend="italic">how</hi> rather than <hi
                    rend="italic">why</hi>, for Emerson’s Nature is a force field of dynamic action.
                It is not a congeries of empirical objects&#8212;“rocks and stones and
                trees”&#8212;but an ideal system obeying “a law which is also [the] law of the human
                mind” that works to discover its law. Man Thinking turns a reciprocal attention to
                the arresting pressure of the impinging material world. In that act of attention,
                the American Scholar and Nature are reciprocal agents, “beholding and beholden.”<q
                    rend="block">To the young mind, every thing is individual, stands by itself. By
                    and by, it finds how to join two things, and see in them one nature; then three,
                    then three thousand; and so, tyrannized over by its own unifying instinct, it
                    goes on tying things together, diminishing anomalies, discovering roots running
                    under ground, whereby contrary and remote things cohere, and flower out from one
                        stem.<ptr target="#note10" xml:id="nr10" n="10"/></q>In the interchange with
                Nature, Emersonian Man discovers the “principle” that gives him mastery. It is the
                idea of an implicate order realized as Idea before it ever need be or even could be
                realized in fact. For Emerson, Man Thinking is, like Great Creating Nature, “a
                becoming creator.” “Every day, the sun; and after sunset, Night and her stars. Ever
                the wind blows, ever the grass grows.”<ptr target="#note11" xml:id="nr11" n="11"/>
                Those are, for “The American Scholar,” the very first examples of Emersonian Nature.
                They are perfectly chosen because they <hi rend="italic">define</hi> Nature, shaping
                it as an idea of a comprehensive and recurrent order. The natural world is for
                Emerson the manifestation of its subsisting Idea.</p>
            <p>Emerson will spend a lifetime generating further figures to show how “[Nature’s] laws
                are the laws of his own mind.” But his Ideal conviction concealed a real problem.
                Once Man Thinking had seized the Idea, what need of an empirical pursuit? Might Man
                    Thinking&#8212;<hi rend="italic">Emerson</hi> Thinking&#8212;actually not know
                his own Mind, or for that matter, Nature? Indeed, might the Mind’s sovereign Idea
                rather be&#8212;this was Poe’s darkly comic thought—the pursuit of its illusions, of
                    <hi rend="italic">how</hi> it is “a becoming creator” of illusions? These are
                the kinds of question lying behind the persistent judgments initially brought
                against Emerson by Poe and reinforced by later readers: that he made a false
                homology between the Human Condition and the State of Nature.</p>
            <p>Poe was Emerson’s Blakean Contrary—far less a critic of his limitations than, like
                Melville, the dark interpreter of his genius. The best critic of Emerson is his best
                and most assiduous student, Henry David Thoreau. We now see pretty clearly how
                Thoreau moved “gradually, partially, and self-conflictedly beyond the program” of
                Emersonian Transcendentalism and the scholarly ideas it promoted: <q rend="block"
                    >Thoreau became increasingly interested in defining nature’s structure, both
                    spiritual and material, for its own sake, as against how nature might subserve
                    humanity, which was Emerson’s primary consideration.<ptr target="#note12"
                        xml:id="nr12" n="12"/></q>In the late <hi rend="italic">Journals</hi> and
                the so-called Late Natural History Writings like “The Dispersion of Seeds” and <hi
                    rend="italic">Wild Fruits</hi>, we track Thoreau’s painstaking efforts to put
                acts of attention well before acts of invention&#8212;or the human encounter with
                the material world before reflection on the Order of that world.<ptr
                    target="#note13" xml:id="nr13" n="13"/></p>
            <p>And I say “painstaking” because in Thoreau we read the story of a person learning how
                to learn by submitting to a far more demanding teacher than Emerson. It was a
                teacher who, Thoreau came to understand, spoke an entirely foreign language. Bradley
                P. Dean called it “the language of trees” because Dean focused on a dialect that
                Thoreau came to study more closely than its other dialects: for instance, the
                language of fauna, of stones, of water. But Thoreau was well acquainted with
                Nature’s entire family of languages, and in his <hi rend="italic">Walden</hi>
                experiment he proved so arrested by those languages that one or another of Nature’s
                native speakers would sometimes even address him directly.</p>
            <p>For example, Walden Pond itself, according to Thoreau, speaks many dialects. All are
                in communion with the dialects of the other ponds in Walden’s neighborhood.
                Fishermen nearby, Thoreau reports, “say that the ‘thundering of the pond’ scares the
                fishes and prevents their biting,” but neither they nor Thoreau are certain what the
                ponds are saying in their winter words, or even if it is the ponds and not some
                other communicant who are speaking to the fish. But Thoreau senses that he is
                fronting, is immersed in, a scene of complex communicative action that he doesn’t
                understand. “The pond does not thunder every evening, and I cannot tell when to
                expect its thundering; but though I may perceive no difference in the weather, it
                    does.”<ptr target="#note14" xml:id="nr14" n="14"/></p>
            <p>Nature, so to speak, speaks a different language, or perhaps many different dialects
                of a single language system. So foreign is this family of languages to human
                persons, however, that a true and useful acquaintance only begins when you realize
                you will never master any of them. Consider Thoreau’s famous encounter with Mount
                    Ktaadn.<q rend="block">Vast, Titanic, inhuman Nature has got him at
                    disadvantage, caught him alone, and pilfers him of some of his divine faculty.
                    She does not smile on him as in the plains. She seems to say sternly, Why came
                    ye here before your time. This ground is not prepared for you. Is it not enough
                    that I smile in the valleys? I have never made this soil for thy feet, this air
                    for thy breathing, these rocks for thy neighbors. I cannot pity nor fondle thee
                    here, but forever relentlessly drive thee hence to where I <hi rend="italic"
                        >am</hi> kind. Why seek me where I have not called thee, and then complain
                    because you find me but a stepmother? Shouldst thou freeze or starve, or shudder
                    thy life away, here is no shrine, nor altar, nor any access to my ear. <lg>
                        <l>"Chaos and ancient Night, I come no spy</l>
                        <l>With purpose to explore or to disturb</l>
                        <l>The secrets of your realm, but . . .</l>
                        <l>. . . . . . as my way</l>
                        <l>Lies through your spacious empire up to light.”<ptr target="#note15"
                                xml:id="nr15" n="15"/></l>
                    </lg>
                </q>Thoreau summons Milton’s Satan for a language and fit reply to the obdurate
                language of Ktaadn. And Thoreau isn’t quoting Milton, he is translating the passage
                to an alienated context and occasion. The translation signals a scholarly attitude
                toward Nature that is decisively different from Emerson’s.</p>
            <p>Thoreau can translate Milton because Milton and Thoreau speak the same language.
                Thoreau cannot translate Ktaadn because Ktaadn has no knowable language. So Ktaadn’s
                words here are not Thoreau’s translation, they are his commentary on his encounter
                with the natural world. Translation is out of the question because there is no Book
                of Nature. Ktaadn’s words are thus Thoreau’s representation of an alien encounter,
                and Milton is invoked to annotate the scene.</p>
            <p>The Emersonian scholar—Man Thinking—proves his “mastery” when he realizes the
                correspondence between Mind and Nature. As <hi rend="italic">Walden</hi> shows, Man
                Thinking is equally the pivot point of Thoreau’s work. But Thoreau’s figural flights
                keep colliding with the intransigence of minute and material particulars. The
                inorganic world—Ktaadn, the ponds of <hi rend="italic">Walden</hi>, seasonal
                weather, the “clay and sand . . . flowing down the sides of a deep cut on the
                railroad”—all are Thoreau’s brute and eloquent neighbors whose grace is to overthrow
                the “Higher Laws” of the Transcendental program. In Emerson, Man Thinking takes
                communion with a mysterious Nature and discovers the mastery of metaphoric
                translation. But in Thoreau communion leads finally to translational and metaphoric
                breakdown. He is pleading for an Adamic language through “which all things and
                events speak without metaphor.”<ptr target="#note16" xml:id="nr16" n="16"/><q
                    rend="block">The distant rumbling of wagons over bridges . . . the baying of
                    dogs . . . the trump of bullfrogs . . . vainly bellowing <hi rend="italic"
                        >troonk</hi> from time to time, and pausing for a reply . . . wild cockerels
                    crow[ing] on the trees, clear and shrill for miles over the resounding earth . .
                    . sturdy pitch-pines rubbing and creaking against the shingles . . . a scuttle
                    or a blind blown off in the gale&#8212;a pine tree snapped off or torn up by the
                    roots . . . . </q><ptr target="#note17" xml:id="nr17" n="17"/></p>
            <p>So education for Thoreau is not a progress in knowledge but a repetition of primary
                encounters. The cycle of the seasons and the diurnal round locate his passage
                through “Chaos and ancient Night” on his journey to the wondrous, obdurate earth.
                The ice on Walden Pond melts in a very particular pattern every year, but each year
                the pattern unfolds so uniquely that each year it has to be rediscovered:<q
                    rend="block">In 1845 Walden was first completely open on the 1st of April; in
                    ’46, on the 25th of March; in ’47, the 8th of April; in ’51, the 28th of March;
                    in ’52, the 18th of April; in ’53, the 23rd of March; in ’54, about the 7th of
                        April.<ptr target="#note18" xml:id="nr18" n="18"/></q>Such a cunning move,
                to climax his statistical record with that word “about.” Besides, Thoreau does not
                time-stamp this record by minute and hour. And what <hi rend="italic">exactly</hi>
                does it mean to say, or to think, that the pond was “first completely open”?</p>
            <p>Or what of those red squirrels he will soon meet—creatures who,“At
                    the approach of spring” each year, would <q rend="block">[get] under my house two at a time,
                    directly under my feet as I sat reading or writing, and kept up the queerest
                    chuckling and chirruping and vocal pirouetting and gurgling sounds that ever
                    were heard; and when I stamped they only chirruped the louder, as if past all
                    fear and respect in their mad pranks, defying humanity to stop them. No, you
                    don’t—chickaree—chickaree. They were wholly deaf to my arguments, or failed to
                    perceive their force, and fell into a strain of invective that was
                        irresistible.<ptr target="#note19" xml:id="nr19" n="19"/></q>That is
                Thoreau making a reprise on one of his most celebrated reports in all of <hi
                    rend="italic">Walden</hi>: his encounter with the loon in “Brute Neighbors.”
                When he glosses the loon’s cry as a derisory laugh, the figure is itself derisory,
                marking a scene of contact where misunderstanding appears all on one side
                (Thoreau’s). So too with the red squirrels, who are, Thoreau imagines, too busy and
                preoccupied to pay any notice to their noisy neighbor upstairs. All he registers is
                a scene of existential repletion, as remote in its way as stern Ktaadn. “While he
                was thinking one thing in his brain,” Thoreau writes of the loon, “I was endeavoring
                to divine his thought in mine.”<ptr target="#note20" xml:id="nr20" n="20"/> With the
                verb “divine,” Thoreau registers the sublunar divinity of his Brute Neighbors, who
                mock at and tease out the deficiency of his understanding. In the poverty of his
                report he also reports how the implicate order of the loon’s world will always
                remain to be discovered.</p>
            <p>Where Emerson proposes “going down into the secrets of his own mind,” Thoreau’s
                catalog of particulars is outward bound to “the necessity of being forever on the
                alert”: “Instead of no path to the front-yard gate in the Great Snow&#8212;no
                gate&#8212;no front-yard&#8212;and no path to the civilized world.”<ptr
                    target="#note21" xml:id="nr21" n="21"/></p>
            <p>That out-of-bounds thought climaxes the chapter appropriately devoted to “Sounds,”
                where Thoreau invokes an order of communication that dispenses with semantics,
                syntax, and the cognitions of Man Thinking. But the decisive anti-Transcendentalist
                move is made in the paired chapters “Higher Laws” and “Brute Neighbors.” Explicitly
                invoking Emerson’s essay “Spiritual Laws” (1841), where Emerson argues that “a
                higher law . . . regulates events,” Thoreau’s study of these “Higher Laws” turns out
                a wrestling match with his Emersonian angel. The struggle makes him realize that
                “There is unquestionably this instinct in me which belongs to the lower orders of
                    creation.”<ptr target="#note22" xml:id="nr22" n="22"/></p>
            <p>The uncertainties climax in the chapter’s final paragraph, where Thoreau tells the
                story of John Farmer. Like Thoreau in his prose, John Farmer struggles to realize
                his desire “to recreate his intellectual man,” to find his sovereign Emersonian way.
                But John Farmer’s high hopes come to an uncertain end:<q rend="block">A voice said
                    to him—Why do you stay here and live this mean moiling life, when a glorious
                    existence is possible for you? Those same stars twinkle over other fields than
                    these.&#8212;But how to come out of this condition and actually migrate thither?
                    All that he could think of was to practise some new austerity, to let his mind
                    descend into his body and redeem it, and treat himself with ever increasing
                        respect.<ptr target="#note23" xml:id="nr23" n="23"/></q>The investigation of
                “Higher Laws” ends in this disturbed finale, where the impulse to redeem the brute
                body is thrown into question. The move from “Higher Laws” to “Brute Neighbors”
                signals a sharp course reversal in the quest romance of <hi rend="italic"
                    >Walden</hi>.<ptr target="#note24" xml:id="nr24" n="24"/></p>
            <p>Redemption, it turns out, is not a descent from above. The chapter opens when a
                certain Poet unexpectedly arrives to invite Thoreau—who calls himself “Hermit”—to
                leave his reflective isolation and come “a-fishing.” The invitation sets Hermit
                thinking once again on higher and lower things: “Shall I go to heaven or a-fishing?”
                he wonders. When he decides against heaven and for fishing, the event delivers him
                from new austerities to the wonders of the imbruted world: “The mice which haunted
                my house”; “A phoebe . . . a robin . . . the partridge [leading] her brood past my
                    windows.”<ptr target="#note25" xml:id="nr25" n="25"/></p>
            <p>These brief encounters draw him out further and in deeper, through the chaos and
                ancient night of the embattled ants to the “demoniac” loon. A less extravagant
                person than Thoreau might have climaxed his sojourn among the brutes with that
                famous encounter. But the episode of the loon is actually anticlimactic, for “Brute
                Neighbors” has one more paragraph of brutish revelation. Once again “on the alert,”
                Thoreau “watch[es] the ducks cunningly tack and veer and hold the middle of the
                pond, far from the sportsman.” Wise ducks, Thoreau is thinking. But the thought is
                quickly trumped when he thinks again that these are “tricks which they will have
                less need to practice in Louisiana bayous.”<ptr target="#note26" xml:id="nr26"
                    n="26"/> Beyond these thoughts of Man Thinking lie the astonishing wisdom of the
                ducks. What depths of knowledge do they possess that they understand so well how to
                manage the shifting circumstances of their migrating lives! If hunters are
                everywhere, Walden Pond and a Louisiana bayou are worlds elsewhere, and so are the
                hunters, and so are the ducks. Besides, some hunters are just going fishing.</p>
            <p>Thoreau marks his decision to go fishing with a memorandum: “Mem. There never is but
                one opportunity of a kind.”<ptr target="#note27" xml:id="nr27" n="27"/> The apothegm
                has the form of generalization or law, but its focus is entirely on differentials
                and variants. Opportunities are one of a kind, and so are experiences and all the
                singularities that comprise them.</p>
            <p>Thoreau’s studies of Nature kept drawing him toward what Alfred Jarry would soon call
                a “science of exceptions.”<ptr target="#note28" xml:id="nr28" n="28"/> Today we may
                be surprised to recognize Jarry’s pataphysical science as the shaping spirit of
                environmental studies. Listen to Barry Lopez: “The world of variables . . . is [so]
                astonishingly complex [that it] seems a reflection of that organization of energy
                that quantum mechanics predicts for the particles that compose an atom.”<ptr
                    target="#note29" xml:id="nr29" n="29"/> An “evaluation . . . of a stretch of
                land,” Lopez observes, “no matter how profound or accurate,” will always seem
                “inadequate,” for “The land retains an identity of its own, still deeper and more
                subtle than we can know” (228). So too for all the land’s creatures, flora and
                fauna, where knowledge and power abide beyond the range of our knowledge and power,
                if not beyond the range of our attention. Of the ways of the polar bear, Lopez
                remarks, “No matter how long you watch, you will not see all it can do” (96). And so
                a warning goes forth across the whole of his book: “The imposed view, however
                innocent, always obscures” (176). This is Lopez channeling Thoreau, man on the
                alert, not Emerson, the man who thought thinking was “mastery”.</p>
            <p><hi rend="italic">Arctic Dreams</hi> is thus an extended reflection on disciplines of
                knowledge, on Truth and Method. Its recurrent message is “no country, finally, is
                just like another. The generalities are abstractions” (259). But more than that,
                Lopez discovers that no country, finally, is just like itself. Arctic natives who
                are constantly dealing with their elusive, volatile, and shape-shifting world
                possess that understanding. They practice a science that is “less formal” than
                traditional western science but “not necessarily less rigorous” on that account. It
                is a science of exceptions that is “reluctan[t] to extrapolate from the individual”
                    (269n).<q rend="block">They know they can be very precise about what they do,
                    but that does not guarantee that they will be accurate. They know the behavior
                    of an individual animal may differ strikingly from the generally recognized
                    behavior of the species, and that the same species may behave quite differently
                    from place to place, from year to year. (269)</q>So when a “man from Anaktuvuk
                Pass [was asked] a question about what he did when he visited a new place,” he
                responded: “‘I listen.’ That’s all. I listen, he meant, to what the land is saying .
                . . before I, myself, ever speak a word” (257).</p>
            <p>Here the land and its brute individuals cast such a cold eye on Man Thinking that a
                scholar like myself receives a shock of recognition. <hi rend="italic">Arctic
                    Dreams</hi> is an allegory for a scholar’s life where our Emersonian commitments
                to “mastery” make a further commitment to meet their master. We are to follow “The
                Course of a Particular” and “the cry of leaves that do not transcend
                    themselves.”<ptr target="#note30" xml:id="nr30" n="30"/> We are to cultivate “a
                mind of winter” and zero-degree encounters with our culture, its Umwelt, its
                material documents.</p>
            <p>Here is what that mind of winter looks like:<q rend="block">A tundra botanist once
                    described to me her patient disassembly of a cluster of plants on a tussock, a
                    tundra mound about 18 inches high and a foot or so across. She separated live
                    from dead plant tissue and noted the number and kind of the many species of
                    plants. She examined the insects and husks of berries, down to bits of things
                    nearly too slight to see or to hold without crushing. The process took hours,
                    and her concentration and sense of passing time became fixed at that scale.
                    <!--(000) AU: please fill in page number – not needed here – the pages are indicated two lines below--></q>
                Then “at one point” her fixed attention broke and “she remembered looking up . . .
                at the tundra that rolled away in a hundred thousand tussocks toward the horizon”
                (259–60). The enormity of her studies came so sharply into focus that she could not
                resume her work, “not for long minutes.” When she left the tundra for home, we know
                the stories she would tell and how she would tell them. If she wrote them in a book
                it would be called <hi rend="italic">Arctic Dreams</hi>.</p>
            <p>That botanist was a scholar who understood both the wonder and the difficulty of her
                vocation. Only a student as implacable as that land and its little tussocks has any
                chance of approaching the land’s secrets. Mastery is out of the question. Few of us
                have been to the Arctic, much less submitted to its rigorous demands. Yet not a few
                will understand that botanist and the commitment to truth she represents. The
                subjects of the commitment are a secondary matter. No one learns to prepare good
                meals, or even some favorite dishes, without a study and care that may well turn to
                a lifelong endeavor. There are baseball fans who exhibit that botanist’s habit of
                mind, as do many gardeners, carpenters, musicians&#8212;professional and amateur.
                Lopez fashioned his Arctic botanist to an image I am especially familiar with. She
                recalls the scholar focused for hours or days on some book, some document, some
                passage or word that opens to a formidable horizon. Tennyson glimpsed “all
                experience” of this kind as “an arch where through / Gleams that untraveled world
                whose margin fades / For ever and for ever when I move.”<ptr target="#note31"
                    xml:id="nr31" n="31"/>
                <!--AU/ED: I inserted a space before and after slash--> If you travel there you
                pledge allegiance to truth: to accuracy, thoroughness, and all their stipulated
                costs. As a matter of social practice, when that scholar leaves the tundra to join
                her neighbors in the human world, her commitment to truth is called troth, which is
                every bit as demanding.</p>
            <p>We humans <hi rend="italic">will</hi> climb Mount Ktaadn and take our measure of her
                measure. We will explore the poles, go to the moon or Jupiter, and imagine&#8212;if
                only in our children’s toys&#8212;traveling, like Buzz Lightyear, “to infinity and
                beyond.” But our measures will fall short, as ancient wisdom has always known. That
                truth gets disclosed yet again&#8212;will we never learn?&#8212;by physicists and
                bioastronomers who reflect on these human endeavors and the second law of
                thermodynamics. Exploring Nature, then, we may find ourselves and take our Socratic
                measure. Or not.</p>
            <p>Arctic exploration and the quest for a Northwest Passage have furnished an archive of
                documents of “inestimable” value because the documents “expose in startling ways the
                complacency of our thoughts about land in general.” Arctic land is important because
                it “is irritatingly and uncharacteristically uncooperative” (12), so Lopez offers
                chastening examples of how to read the accounts of others who were smitten with
                Arctic dreams: Martin Frobisher, Robert Peary, Knud Rasmussen, Sir John Franklin,
                British Petroleum, Exxon Mobile. But if the work is important for reading the
                records of wilderness encounter, it has an even greater relevance for what Walter
                Benjamin called the “documents of civilization.” <hi rend="italic">Arctic
                    Dreams</hi> was written to wake up its “temperate-zone” neighbors—that’s to say,
                we who are accustomed to imagine the world as a place “where the sun actually sets
                on a summer evening, where cicadas give way in the twilight to crickets, and people
                sit on porches—none of which happens in the Arctic.” <hi rend="italic">Arctic
                    Dreams</hi> brings enlightenment to those kinds of temperate illusion, which our
                anthropocene minds have recently begun to see&#8212;‘“Thank Somebody,” as Swinburne
                liked to say&#8212;as “irritatingly and uncharacteristically uncooperative”
                (12).</p>
            <p>I have an Arctic Dream that educators and educated citizens might take that tundra
                botanist’s conscience for their monitor. Here are a few stories about why I have
                that dream.</p>
            <p>When Megyn Kelley of Fox News interviewed Dick Cheney on June 18,
                2014,<!--AU: Please fill in year--> she began by asking him to respond to the
                following passage from a recent article in the <hi rend="italic">Washington
                    Post</hi> by Paul Waldman: <q rend="block">“There is not a single person in
                    America who has been more wrong and more shamelessly dishonest on the topic of
                    Iraq than Dick Cheney, and now as the cascade of misery and death and chaos, he
                    did so much to unleash raises anew, Mr. Cheney has the unadulterated gall to
                    come before the country and tell us that it's all someone else's fault.” The
                    suggestion is that you caused this mess, Mr. Vice President. What say
                you?</q>Mr. Cheney replied: “Well, obviously I disagree.” Overriding any distinction
                between matters of fact and matters of opinion, he then remarked: “I think we went
                into Iraq for very good reasons.” He added that President Obama was responsible for
                destroying what he called a “very positive” situation that he and his people had
                created in Iraq.</p>
            <p>Kelley then pressed him further:<q rend="block">In your op-ed, you write as follows:
                    “Rarely has a US president been so wrong about so much at the expense of so
                    many.” But time and time again, history has proven that you got it wrong as well
                    in Iraq, sir. You said there were no doubts Saddam Hussein had weapons of mass
                    destruction. You said we would be greeted as liberators. You said the Iraq
                    insurgency was in the last throes back in 2005. And you said that after our
                    intervention, extremists would have to, quote, “rethink their strategy of
                    Jihad.” Now with almost a trillion dollars spent there, with 4,500 American
                    lives lost there, what do you say to those who say, you were so wrong about so
                    much at the expense of so many?</q>Mr. Cheney again replied: “I just
                fundamentally disagree, Megyn. You’ve got to go back and look at the track record.
                We inherited a situation where there was no doubt in anybody’s mind about the extent
                of Saddam’s involvement in weapons of mass destruction.”</p>
            <p>“I just fundamentally disagree.” The phrase is disturbing because its purpose is to
                blur the distinction between fact and opinion. In the interview, not all the
                relevant facts&#8212;not even perhaps the worst&#8212;were brought forward by Ms.
                Kelley. Well over 100,000 Iraqi civilians were killed between 2003 and 2008. And to
                say that “there was no doubt in anybody’s mind about the extent of Saddam’s
                involvement in WMDs” is definitely inaccurate&#8212;or to put it more truthfully,
                definitely not true. Many people at the time, as the vice president knew, expressed
                their doubts often and publicly, and some&#8212;the United Nations, most
                notably—actually tried to verify what was or wasn’t true about the American
                administration’s charges. But the administration did not allow Hans Blix’s
                inspection team to make its report in time to prevent the ensuing disaster.</p>
            <p>Because Vice President Cheney took a blithe attitude to matters of fact, he could
                take a purpose-driven approach to matters of consequence, matters of life and death.
                He practiced, and continues to practice, what Hannah Arendt called
                    “defactualization.”<ptr target="#note32" xml:id="nr32" n="32"/> He would have
                been wiser had he read <hi rend="italic">Arctic Dreams</hi> and took seriously one
                of Barry Lopez’s running themes: “The imposed view, however innocent, always
                obscures” (176). Not even the vice president would argue that his views were
                innocently imposed.</p>
            <p>But matters of fact, our brute neighbors, can be dismissed from attention in a very
                different way. This other way became widespread when humanities scholarship shifted
                from its traditional grounding in history and material culture toward literary
                philosophy and interpretive theory. For my generation, the name Paul De Man would be
                totemic for that shift. Listen to what he had to say about literary studies in 1970
                as the Theory Movement in humanities was in serious lift-off: “There is no room . .
                . for notions of accuracy and identity in the shifting world of interpretation.”<ptr
                    target="#note33" xml:id="nr33" n="33"/> Or as he remarked a few years earlier in
                an essay on the poetry of Keats, we must not think, when studying the poems, that
                they have any “positive existence.”<ptr target="#note34" xml:id="nr34" n="34"/>
                History was not exactly “bunk” for De Man, as a famous American entrepreneur once
                said, but accuracy and matters of fact were no longer “notions” that the humanist
                scholar had room for.</p>
            <p>This retreat from an empirical encounter with our documentary archive&#8212;a retreat
                from philology to theory&#8212;seems a perverse move for anyone charged with
                monitoring and preserving our cultural record. Because works of imagination fairly
                demand a science of exceptions, we recognize how and why the imposed theoretical
                view, however, innocent, always obscures. The Book of Nature is difficult and
                mysterious, but so are the Books of Men. The records of positive actions and
                singular events comprise both Natural History and Human History, but the two are
                very different. Nature is mysterious because it is absolute, human records are
                mysterious because they’re not. Fallible human beings&#8212;scientists, as we now
                say&#8212;study the Book of Nature and make both wonderful discoveries and terrible
                mistakes. But the Book of Nature, their subject, is itself perfect. Nature does not
                change, it simply mutates, as the humanly devastated State of Nature around
                Chernobyl reminds us. Or the melting of the polar ice sheets.</p>
            <p>Fallible human beings study the books and records that were made by other fallible
                human beings. Data are records and they are as prone to error as any other record.
                Worse yet, all these imperfect records are always fallibly preserved and imperfectly
                passed along to other fallible beings. Skeptics might call that a house built on
                sand. It’s actually more like a house resting on the backs of those famous turtles
                that go, as we say, all the way down. You need a lot of sympathy when you practice
                the human sciences. For the humanist, it’s human beings&#8212;natural,
                mortal&#8212;all the way down through our “Chaos and ancient night.”</p>
            <p>Socrates proposed that knowledge should be understood and pursued as complete
                self-reflection. That was an impossible proposal, as he knew. He thought he was wise
                because he knew he knew nothing for certain. We call his knowledge program the
                Hellenic vision of truth. In the West we know its complement as the (equally
                impossible) Hebrew or Christian or Islamic vision. These are the visions of the
                People of the Book, who practice an equally impossible task. The Bible is our
                normative book for studying human history. Why? Because as a book of truth it is
                also an imperfect book, full of error and evil: what Poe called “the good and the
                bad and the worst and the best.”</p>
            <p>But like the hard sciences, the human sciences have systematic methods, and you can
                see why. Humanists need as much rigor and system as we can muster because everything
                we study, including ourselves, is so unreliable. The Book of Nature is rock-solid.
                The Word of God is turtles all the way down. So are the humanities, which have to be
                prosecuted as an art: that is, less under the rule of theory or idea, and more as a
                regimen of careful practice. As one of our greatest humanities scholars once
                observed, humanistic study is like fishing. You only become good at it by patient
                and repeated experience, and by scrupulous attention to what, where, how, when, and
                why you’re doing it. Perhaps that’s even what Jesus had in mind when he urged his
                students, his disciples, to become fishers of men.</p>
            <p>Scrupulous attention to the specific and “positive existence” of the human record,
                past as well as ongoing present. Mark Twain called all of that <hi rend="italic"
                    >Life on the Mississippi</hi>. You have to know the land, the river, the
                seasonal shifts, the weather conditions, and all their unpredictable history. And
                like Twain’s river pilots, scholars have to know it at first hand, in actual contact
                with the documentary record. And you have to know it repeatedly. Finally, you also
                have to know it through the firsthand knowledge of others whom you know to have
                long-standing experiential credentials. Those are the people you go fishing with.
                Those are the people whose humanities scholarship makes a difference. In the
                shifting world of the human sciences, accuracy is imperative, as much as you can
                manage. We can’t make reliable judgments without being confident that we have
                accurate information&#8212;that’s to say, reports that mean to be candid, honest,
                and as thorough as possible. The best we can say of Vice President Cheney is that he
                was optimistic in his reports. That seems the truth. The additional truth is that he
                was dishonest&#8212;and, alas, still is.</p>
            <p>People with a commitment to knowledge and truth&#8212;people from every quarter of
                the social and political landscape&#8212;recognize dishonesty. The recognition is
                nonpartisan and interdisciplinary, a function of a common, if differently shaped,
                vocation to truth. But to give that vocation force you need more than the commitment
                of a Sovereign Individual&#8212;as Emerson, more than Thoreau, understood. The
                scholar has a pastoral office to fulfill. It is not all theology and shop talk.</p>
            <p>I like to think that Paul De Man would have been appalled at the vice president’s
                cavalier attitude toward accuracy and factual truth.<ptr target="#note35"
                    xml:id="nr35" n="35"/> But De Man’s skepticism about human knowledge&#8212;about
                the positive, factual record&#8212;was, if not dishonest, misguided. It set an
                unreliably narrow model for human studies. I know a better model, or at least a
                story about a better model. It’s a story about another scholar&#8212;a greater
                scholar than De Man, in my judgment, though one far less famous (or infamous). He
                was an assistant professor of Greek and Latin at Harvard, his name was Milman Parry,
                and he died fairly young&#8212;at thirty-three. In 1934, the year before he died, he
                delivered an address to the Board of Overseers of Harvard College. Though it bore an
                unprepossessing title, “The Historical Method in Literary Criticism,” Parry
                delivered it because he was troubled by a Crisis in Humanities.<ptr target="#note36"
                    xml:id="nr36" n="36"/></p>
            <p>Even in 1934 there was a Crisis in the Humanities? Alas, yes, as there was in 1837
                when Emerson himself engaged the crisis in a lecture to the same board. In truth, I
                think the humanities have been in a regular state of crisis at least since the
                eighteenth century. Crisis has become the modern fate of humane studies, whose
                vocation is the pursuit of social, historical, and personal truth and the
                preservation of the record of those pursuits. These are obligations that humanists
                undertake knowing they are impossible to fulfill. The historical record that comes
                down to us is a small fractional residue of the human past, and even that fraction
                is riven with holes and fragmentary, disfeatured remains. And as for the data glut
                of the present, it is being mined but not mastered. Data mining, we may want to
                remember, was what led Mr. Cheney and his accomplices to their misjudgment about
                Saddam Hussein and WMDs.</p>
            <p>Milman Parry did not know about Big Data, but he didn’t have to. His little data was
                trouble enough for someone interested in fishing for the truth. And that is what
                interested him and what he made the subject of his lecture. As with Emerson one
                hundred years before, the important context of Parry’s lecture is signaled by its
                date, 1934, when “propaganda . . . social changes and confusion” were taking such
                hold of bewildered people throughout Europe and America. Stalin had assumed control
                of the Soviets in 1923, Hitler of the Weimar Republic in 1933, and a freewheeling
                American capitalism had plunged the United States into a tormented social condition,
                worse even than the Panic of 1837. Parry reflected on that situation:<q rend="block"
                    >The chief emotional ideas to which men seem to be turning at present . . . are
                    those of nationality&#8212;for which they exploit race&#8212;and class. . . .
                    Anyone who has followed the history of the use of propaganda for political
                    purposes, with its extraordinary development of intensity and technique in the
                    past fifty years [recognizes how] those who were directing that propaganda
                    expressed their lack of concern, or even contempt, for what actually was so, or
                    actually had been so.</q>Parry went on quietly to suggest that “the European
                humanistic tradition” had something important to contribute to these benighted
                societies. He was not thinking of what Poe called “the glory that was Greece, and
                the grandeur that was Rome.” On the contrary, he was thinking about humanist
                scholars who spend their lives trying to give accurate reports about such worlds, so
                dead and far gone from the modern present, as he was reminding the Harvard
                overseers. He was also fully aware how insignificant&#8212;how <hi rend="italic"
                    >pedantic</hi>&#8212;such academic pursuits often appear to living people
                enspelled by propagandistic dreams of national glory and exceptional virtue.</p>
            <p>Parry’s heroes are not Achilles or Hector, not even Socrates or Plato. They are far
                more minor and modest. They are people who believe “that there is nothing at the
                same time finer and more practical than the truth,” and who will spend their days
                acting on that belief. You want to know what such days are like? They are days spent
                on a vast tundra studying a passage in a book few people read or perhaps have ever
                heard of&#8212;perhaps a book in a dead language&#8212;trying to say something
                accurate and truthful about it. I knew a scholar who set all his other research work
                aside for months trying to write a footnote that told the truth about a sentence in
                a letter by the poet Tennyson. Whether the document being searched has ideas with
                current social relevance is, for these adepts of truth, beside the point. Indeed,
                apparent irrelevance might be exactly <hi rend="italic">to</hi> the point for a
                people&#8212;that would be for the company I keep&#8212;surrounded by the propaganda
                and confusion of our fiercely, just-in-time present.</p>
            <p>What, then, <hi rend="italic">is</hi> the point? Simply, in Parry’s words, “that
                there is nothing at the same time finer and more practical than the truth.” That
                would be the truth <hi rend="italic">as such</hi>. Accuracy and truth are not well
                characterized as “notions” that we have&#8212;De Man’s characterization. Better to
                know them as commitments that we make. The strength of a commitment&#8212;and
                therefore its practicality&#8212;rests in how out far and how in deep it goes. The
                turtles of truth go all the way down to where there is, we trust, something we will
                never have and never know: the truth, the whole truth, and nothing but the
                truth.</p>
            <p>Scholars pledge allegiance to that impossible truth. Making the pledge is one of the
                two public functions of the humanist scholar. The other&#8212;it is closely
                related&#8212;is the obligation to protect human memory from neglect and
                erasure&#8212;as much of it as possible.<ptr target="#note37" xml:id="nr37" n="37"/>
                Both commitments resist the pressure of the consuming present, where illusions of
                sovereignty are fashioned from truthiness and memories of convenience.</p>
            <p>The quotidian realm does not cultivate habits of accuracy, thoroughness, and candor,
                and it may even&#8212;as Milman Parry remarked&#8212;hold them in contempt. In the
                fugitive and cloistered world of the scholar, however, these are predominant values.
                They monitor all quests for sovereignty and power because they recognize the
                seductive uncertainty of higher laws and the uncanny intransigence of brute fact. It
                is difficult to tell the truth, the whole truth, and nothing but the truth about a
                Tennyson letter. Yet to attempt it is both sobering and superb. Even the most
                insignificant object rests in a vast implicate order.</p>
            <p>Before the scholar’s art comes the slipping-down life of the world. To uphold that
                world’s dubious honor asks a mind of winter and a faithfulness unto all generations.
                What another poet devoted to loss called “a light to lesson ages and voluptuous
                princes.”</p>
        </body>
        <back>
            <div type="notes">
                <note xml:id="note1">See the discussion of Milman Parry below.</note>
                <note xml:id="note2">For an important context, see <hi rend="italic">Application of
                        Big Data for National Security: A Practitioner’s Guide to Emerging
                        Technologies</hi>, ed. Babak Akhgar, Gregory Saathoff, Hamid Arabnia,
                    Richard Hill, Andrew Staniforth, and Petra Saskia Bayerl (Oxford, UK:
                    Butterworth-Heinemann, 2015), and in particular chapter 6, Bethany Nowviskie and
                    Gregory Saathoff, “Interpretation and Insider Threat: Rereading the Anthrax
                    Mailings of 2001 through a ‘Big Data’ Lens,” 55–67. Preprint version available
                    at <ref type="url" target="http://libra.virginia.edu/catalog/libra-oa:8347"
                        >http://libra.virginia.edu/catalog/libra-oa:8347</ref>.</note>
                <note xml:id="note3">Theodor Adorno and Max Horkheimer, <hi rend="italic">Dialectic
                        of Enlightenment</hi>, trans. John Cumming (New York: Herder and Herder,
                    1972). <hi rend="italic">Dialectic of Enlightenment</hi> was first published in
                    1944 under the title <hi rend="italic">Philosophische Fragmente</hi>, and again
                    in 1947, revised, as <hi rend="italic">Dialektik der Aufklärung</hi>.</note>
                <note xml:id="note4">I am recalling Paul Connerton’s <hi rend="italic">How Modernity
                        Forgets</hi> (Cambridge, UK: Cambridge University Press, 2009), 32.</note>
                <note xml:id="note5">Thomas Hardy, “The Convergence of the Twain,” 22–24. <hi
                        rend="italic">The Variorum Edition of the Complete Poems of Thomas
                        Hardy</hi>, ed. James Gibson (London: Macmillan, 1979), 307.</note>
                <note xml:id="note6">Ralph Waldo Emerson, <hi rend="italic">Selected Journals</hi>,
                    1820–1842, ed. Lawrence Rosenwald (New York: Library of America, 2010).</note>
                <note xml:id="note7">Ralph Waldo Emerson, <hi rend="italic">Essays and
                    Lectures</hi>, ed. Joel Porte (New York: Library of America, 1983).</note>
                <note xml:id="note8">This “definition” actually comes from Kant, and while the
                    quotation marks suggest Emerson is quoting, he’s actually synthesizing passages
                    from <hi rend="italic">The Critique of Pure Reason</hi> and <hi rend="italic"
                        >The Philosophy of Right</hi>. This is what the lecture just called “going
                    down into the secrets of his own mind,” where Thinking Man “descend[s] into the
                    secrets of all minds” and even into the secrets of Nature itself. Before Kant
                    was, Emerson is saying, I AM.</note>
                <note xml:id="note9">Emerson, “The American Scholar,” in <hi rend="italic">Essays
                        and Lectures</hi>, 64.</note>
                <note xml:id="note10">Emerson, “The American Scholar,” 55.</note>
                <note xml:id="note11">Emerson, “The American Scholar,” 55.</note>
                <note xml:id="note12">Lawrence Buell, “Thoreau and the Natural Environment,” in <hi
                        rend="italic">The Cambridge Companion to Henry David Thoreau</hi>, ed. Joel
                    Myerson (Cambridge, UK: Cambridge University Press, 1995), 172.</note>
                <note xml:id="note13">Henry David Thoreau, <hi rend="italic">Faith in a Seed: The
                        Dispersion of Seeds and Other Late Natural History Writings</hi>, ed.
                    Bradley P. Dean (Washington, DC: Island Press/Shearwater Books, 1993), and <hi
                        rend="italic">Wild Fruits</hi>, ed. Bradley P. Dean (New York: W. W. Norton,
                    2000).</note>
                <note xml:id="note14">Henry David Thoreau, “Spring,” <hi rend="italic">Walden</hi>,
                    in <hi rend="italic">A Week on the Concord and Merrimack Rivers, Walden, The
                        Maine Woods, Cape Cod</hi>, ed. Robert F. Sayre (New York: Library of
                    America, 1985), 563.</note>
                <note xml:id="note15">Thoreau, <hi rend="italic">The Maine Woods</hi>, 641.</note>
                <note xml:id="note16">Thoreau, “Sounds,” in <hi rend="italic">Walden</hi>,
                    411.</note>
                <note xml:id="note17">Thoreau, “Sounds,” 422, 424.</note>
                <note xml:id="note18">Thoreau, “Spring,” in <hi rend="italic">Walden</hi>,
                    564.</note>
                <note xml:id="note19">Thoreau, “Spring,” 569.</note>
                <note xml:id="note20">Thoreau, “Brute Neighbors,” <hi rend="italic">Walden</hi>,
                    510.</note>
                <note xml:id="note21">Thoreau, “Sounds,” 424.</note>
                <note xml:id="note22">Thoreau, “Higher Laws,” in <hi rend="italic">Walden</hi>,
                    493.</note>
                <note xml:id="note23">Thoreau, “Higher Laws,” 499.</note>
                <note xml:id="note24">“Higher Laws” is the most stuttering episode in the book,
                    veering repeatedly between the contradictory instincts of his mortal
                    being.</note>
                <note xml:id="note25">Thoreau, “Brute Neighbors,” 503.</note>
                <note xml:id="note26">Thoreau, “Brute Neighbors,” 511.</note>
                <note xml:id="note27">Thoreau, “Brute Neighbors,” 502.</note>
                <note xml:id="note28">Roger Shattuck, introduction to <hi rend="italic">Exploits and
                        Opinions of Dr. Faustroll, Pataphysician</hi> by Alfred Jarry, trans. Simon
                    Watson Taylor (Boston: Exact Change, 1996), xi.</note>
                <note xml:id="note29">Barry Lopez, <hi rend="italic">Arctic Dreams</hi> (New York:
                    Scribner, 1986), 177. Further citations to <hi rend="italic">Arctic Dreams</hi>
                    appear in parentheses in the text.</note>
                <note xml:id="note30">Wallace Stevens, “The Course of a Particular” <hi
                        rend="italic">Wallace Stevens. Collected Poetry and Prose</hi>, ed. Frank
                    Kermode and Joan Richardson (New York: The Library of America, 1997),
                    460.</note>
                <note xml:id="note31"><hi rend="italic">Alfred Tennyson. The Major Works</hi>, ed.
                    Adam Roberts (New York: Oxford University Press, 2000), 81</note>
                <note xml:id="note32">See Hannah Arendt, “Lying in Politics: Reflections on the
                    Pentagon Papers,” <hi rend="italic">New York Review of Books</hi>, November 18,
                    1971.</note>
                <note xml:id="note33">Paul De Man, <hi rend="italic">Blindness and Insight: Essays
                        in the Rhetoric of Contemporary Criticism</hi> (New York: Oxford University
                    Press, 1971), 110.</note>
                <note xml:id="note34">De Man, introduction to <hi rend="italic">Selected Poetry of
                        John Keats</hi> (New York: New American Library, 1966), xi.</note>
                <note xml:id="note35">In this matter, Evelyn Barish’s <hi rend="italic">The Double
                        Life of Paul De Man</hi> (New York: Liveright, 2014) does give one
                    pause.</note>
                <note xml:id="note36">Milman Parry, “The Historical Method in Literary Criticism,”
                        <hi rend="italic">Harvard Alumni Bulletin</hi> 38 (1936): 778–82. Reprinted
                    in Milman Parry, <hi rend="italic">The Making of Homeric Verse: The Collected
                        Papers of Milman Parry</hi>, ed. Adam Parry (Oxford, UK: Clarendon Press,
                    1971).</note>
                <note xml:id="note37">That is the subject of my recent work <hi rend="italic">A New
                        Republic of Letters: Memory and Scholarship in the Age of Digital
                        Reproduction</hi> (Cambridge, MA: Harvard University Press, 2014).</note>
            </div>
        </back>
    </text>
</TEI>
