<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<?oxygen RNGSchema="http://www.scholarlyediting.org/scholarlyediting.rng" type="xml"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xml:lang="eng">
    <teiHeader>
        <fileDesc>
            <titleStmt>
                <title level="a" type="main">Navigating the Space-Time Continuum</title>
                <author key="Lupton, John A.">John A. Lupton</author>
            </titleStmt>
            <editionStmt>
                <edition>
                    <date>2016</date>
                </edition>
            </editionStmt>
            <publicationStmt>
                <idno type="file">essay.2016presidentialaddress</idno>
                <authority>Scholary Editing: The Annual of the Association for Documentary
                    Editing</authority>
                <address>
 <addrLine>http://www.scholarlyediting.org</addrLine>
</address>
                <publisher>Association for Documentary Editing</publisher>
                <publisher>University of Nebraska&#8211;Lincoln</publisher>
                <distributor>
                    <name>Center for Digital Research in the Humanities</name>
                    <address>
<addrLine>319 Love Library</addrLine>
<addrLine>University of Nebraska&#8211;Lincoln</addrLine>
<addrLine>Lincoln, NE 68588-4100</addrLine>
<addrLine>http://cdrh.unl.edu</addrLine>
 </address>
                </distributor>
                <date>2016</date>
                <availability>
                    <p>Scholary Editing: The Annual of the Association for Documentary Editing is
                        freely distributed by the Association for Documentary Editing and the Center
                        for Digital Research in the Humanities at the University of Nebraska-Lincoln
                        and licensed under a Creative Commons Attribution-NonCommercial-ShareAlike
                        3.0 Unported License</p>
                </availability>
            </publicationStmt>
            <seriesStmt>
                <title level="j">Scholarly Editing: The Annual of the Association for Documentary
                    Editing</title>
                <respStmt>
                    <resp>editor</resp>
                    <name xml:id="ag" key="Gailey, Amanda A.">Amanda Gailey</name>
                </respStmt>
                <respStmt>
                    <resp>editor</resp>
                    <name xml:id="awj" key="Jewell, Andrew W.">Andrew Jewell</name>
                </respStmt>
                <idno type="vol">37</idno>
                <idno type="ISSN">2167-1257</idno>
            </seriesStmt>
            <sourceDesc>
                <bibl>
                    <note>Born digital.</note>
                </bibl>
            </sourceDesc>
        </fileDesc>
        <revisionDesc>
            <change when="2016-03-23"><name xml:id="gk" key="Kirilloff, Gabi">Gabi Kirilloff</name>
                markup in TEI XML</change>
        </revisionDesc>
    </teiHeader>
    <text>
        <front>
            <head type="main">Navigating the Space-Time Continuum</head>
            <head type="sub">Presidential Address</head>
            <head type="sub">Association for Documentary Editing Annual Meeting</head>
            <head type="sub">Lincoln, Nebraska, 2015</head>
            <byline>John A. Lupton</byline>
        </front>
        <body>
            <p>Thank you. It’s been an honor to serve as your president. I’d like to thank the
                Association for Documentary Editing members, as well as committee members and
                council members, that I’ve had the pleasure to work with, not only as president, but
                over the course of the past twenty-five years I’ve been a member. I truly appreciate
                your service in our all-volunteer organization. I know and understand how busy we
                are with our real jobs, and your commitment to the Association for Documentary
                Editing is what keeps it alive.</p>
            <p>I want to begin by acknowledging a couple of people. These are people without whom I
                probably wouldn’t be standing here as a documentary editor, or as a historian, or as
                your president. First is John Y. Simon. I was an undergraduate at Southern Illinois
                University Carbondale unsure of my career path when I took history classes simply
                because I enjoyed them. John Simon’s classes led me to a path of choosing history as
                a career. When I began graduate school, I spoke to Simon and told him I wanted to be
                a Lincoln scholar. He said—and I’m not going to do the John Simon voice, but for
                those of you who know him, you can all just imagine it—“I’m going to give you some
                strange advice. You should leave SIU and transfer to Sangamon State University in
                Springfield and get involved with this new documentary editing project called the
                Lincoln Legal Papers.” I took his advice.</p>
            <p>Next is Cullom Davis who as director of the Lincoln Legal Papers gave me an
                internship as I worked on my master’s degree at Sangamon State, then shepherded me
                in my rise gradually up the ranks in the project. Cullom’s support and encouragement
                certainly helped me to gain confidence as a documentary editor as he entrusted me to
                write the briefs for more than half the 5,600 cases and nonlitigation activities in
                Lincoln’s law practice.<ptr target="#note1" xml:id="nr1" n="1"/> Last is Daniel
                Stowell who as director of the Papers of Abraham Lincoln encouraged academic
                    scholarship.<ptr target="#note2" xml:id="nr2" n="2"/> He allowed his staff to
                present scholarly papers and articles, following the philosophy of John
                Kaminsky—that we are all experts of our chosen editing subjects, and withholding the
                knowledge we have is a disservice to the public at large. Daniel not only accepted
                that premise but pushed the staff to accept it as well. Without Daniel’s guidance, I
                probably would not have been able to make the leap from associate director of the
                Lincoln Papers to leading my own historical agency for the Illinois Supreme
                    Court.<ptr target="#note3" xml:id="nr3" n="3"/></p>
            <p>After that brief look in my personal past, I wish to go further back in time. Ever
                since I was a child, I have always been fascinated by science fiction. I grew up
                reading the books of Ray Bradbury, Arthur C. Clarke, Jules Verne, H. G. Wells, and
                Isaac Asimov. The books were my gateway drug into movies and television shows like
                    <hi rend="italic">Star Wars</hi>, <hi rend="italic">Dr. Who</hi>, and <hi
                    rend="italic">Star Trek</hi>. Any time you have a <hi rend="italic">Star
                    Trek</hi> episode that features Abraham Lincoln and Captain Kirk vs. Genghis
                Khan and a Klingon, you just can’t go wrong.<ptr target="#note4" xml:id="nr4" n="4"
                /> Even today, I find myself completely engrossed in <hi rend="italic">The
                    Avengers</hi>, <hi rend="italic">X-Men</hi>, and other really well-done sci-fi
                movies. The latest trend is presenting a dystopian future with such recent examples
                as <hi rend="italic">The Hunger Games</hi> and any movie featuring a zombie
                    apocalypse.<ptr target="#note5" xml:id="nr5" n="5"/> My three daughters have
                inherited my sci-fi gene even though they roll their eyes when they can’t open a jar
                and I use my Hulk voice while opening it and calling them “puny humans.” I can do
                the Hulk—I can’t do John Simon.</p>
            <p>More specifically into the sci-fi genre, I particularly enjoy time-travel stories.
                The idea of being able to travel in time forward or backward has always been a dream
                of mine. I loved reading books such as H. G. Wells’s <hi rend="italic">The Time
                    Machine</hi> and Kurt Vonnegut’s <hi rend="italic">Slaughterhouse-Five</hi> that
                prominently feature time travel but also provide social commentary.<ptr
                    target="#note6" xml:id="nr6" n="6"/> And movies such as <hi rend="italic">The
                    Terminator</hi> and <hi rend="italic">Back to the Future</hi> not only
                enthralled me but provided larger lessons as well.<ptr target="#note7" xml:id="nr7"
                    n="7"/> I will even admit that I enjoy the time-travel love story whether it’s
                Jane Seymour and Christopher Reeve on Mackinac Island or Sandra Bullock and Keanu
                Reeves at a lake house.<ptr target="#note8" xml:id="nr8" n="8"/> When I give
                presentations to groups about Abraham Lincoln the lawyer, one question I frequently
                get is whether I’m a lawyer. I answer no, but then I add that since I’ve read the
                same books that Lincoln did when he was a lawyer, I could probably practice law in
                the 1840s and 1850s. I further add that if I ever build a time machine, I know I can
                go to antebellum Illinois to practice law and probably make a decent living. I say
                this as a joke, of course, but there’s a kernel of hope.</p>
            <p>Many physicists say that there is no possibility of time travel backward, but
                according to Albert Einstein’s theory of relativity, if I approach the speed of
                light, I can actually travel forward in time—as I move faster, the slower my time
                will pass relative to a person remaining on the Earth. So, after my very, very fast
                trip, the person on Earth has experienced months or even years while I
                simultaneously experienced only a few hours or even minutes.<ptr target="#note9"
                    xml:id="nr9" n="9"/> If you saw the movie <hi rend="italic">Interstellar</hi>,
                starring Matthew McConaughey, you understand this concept.<ptr target="#note10"
                    xml:id="nr10" n="10"/></p>
            <p>Richard Feynman built on Einstein’s work with quantum mechanics, developing his “sum
                over histories” theory in which every possible path from point A to point B is
                    considered.<ptr target="#note11" xml:id="nr11" n="11"/> The probability of an
                event is determined by summing together all the possible histories of that event.
                Time is described as a direction in space—matter moves forward in time; antimatter
                moves backward in time. But Feynman did not believe that time travel backward was
                possible using this model by simply hitching a ride on antimatter.</p>
            <p>Then we have Stephen Hawking, who popularized physics in his book <hi rend="italic">A
                    Brief History of Time</hi>.<ptr target="#note12" xml:id="nr12" n="12"/> Hawking
                attempted to merge Einstein’s theory of relativity with Feynman’s quantum theory
                into a grand unified theory, or a theory of everything.<ptr target="#note13"
                    xml:id="nr13" n="13"/> He has since changed his mind on the existence of a
                theory of everything and is now a firm believer in the many-worlds theory, that all
                possible alternate histories and futures are real, each representing an actual world
                or an actual universe. This would imply that there is a world in existence in which
                John Wilkes Booth had NOT assassinated Abraham Lincoln, for example.<ptr
                    target="#note14" xml:id="nr14" n="14"/> This is almost mind-blowing, as the
                possible number of worlds would have to be infinite!<ptr target="#note15"
                    xml:id="nr15" n="15"/></p>
            <p>Einstein, Feynman, and Hawking provide at least a glimmer of hope for us poor sci-fi
                addicts who wonder about the possibility of traveling in time. But I have a secret
                that the physicists don’t know. So, I hate to break it to them, but I actually can
                travel through time. I don’t have to have a time machine, or travel through
                wormholes, or discover bridges to alternate histories or futures, or disrupt the
                space-time continuum. My avenue of time travel is pretty simple: the document.</p>
            <p>In a general sense, not only documents allow time travel, but objects as well.
                Dinosaur bones, ice cores, and geological features all provide an avenue into a past
                period of time. Even looking at the stars, galaxies, and nebula in the sky, we are
                looking into the past. Take, for example, light, from our own sun traveling at
                186,000 miles per second, takes eight minutes to reach the Earth, so the sun we see
                when looking up in the sky is what the sun looked like eight minutes ago. We see the
                past simply by looking up.</p>
            <p>But for our purposes, the document is the secret to time travel, whether it be a
                letter, a diary, or a text. This is done in two distinct ways: first, documents
                themselves travel in time, and second, documentary editors serve as time-travel
                guides. Documents are the center of our universe as editors, and without documents,
                we have no projects, no funding, no staff, no Society for Textual Scholarship, and
                no Association for Documentary Editing.</p>
            <p>How do documents travel through time? It’s simple. A drawing by Thomas Edison travels
                in time from his hands to Paul Israel’s eyes; a letter by Margaret Sanger travels
                from her typewriter to Esther Katz’s eyes.<ptr target="#note16" xml:id="nr16" n="16"
                /></p>
            <p>Documents allow us to see and to learn about life in different eras—at least as far
                back as the written record exists. With the documentary record, we can pass
                important information down to succeeding generations. This is important. Human
                ancestors have been on Earth, according to anthropologists, for about six million
                years. Only in the last 200,000 years have modern forms of humans appeared. And
                civilization as we know it has only been in existence for the last 6,000 or so
                years. Not coincidentally, writing also made its first appearance 6,000 years
                    ago.<ptr target="#note17" xml:id="nr17" n="17"/> By transferring a knowledge
                base from generation to generation, newer generations can build upon the work of
                previous ones, allowing mankind to advance agriculturally, socially, economically,
                and technologically.<ptr target="#note18" xml:id="nr18" n="18"/> Isaac Newton best
                summarized this concept when he wrote in a letter that he had “seen further by
                standing on the shoulders of giants.”<ptr target="#note19" xml:id="nr19" n="19"/>
                With this documentary record, we can see into the past as easily as we can look up
                in the sky.</p>
            <p>There is a great deal of interest today in the documents of our collective past.
                Nearly one million people view the Declaration of Independence, the Constitution,
                and the Bill of Rights at the National Archives annually.<ptr target="#note20"
                    xml:id="nr20" n="20"/> Why do people want to stand in line, possibly for hours,
                to see something they can easily pull up on the Internet? People want to have a
                real, tangible connection with these particular documents that gave us our country
                and our freedoms. Seeing letters written by George Washington, for example, give
                people a real experience with him.</p>
            <p>I’ve noticed too how students react to documents. When I speak to elementary and
                middle school classes, I like to bring in documents—not real ones, just
                photocopies—and I see how enthralled the students are in looking at them. I will
                have the students transcribe the document and give me ideas what this document might
                be about. In addition to the content, I like to talk about the paper, the ink, the
                handwriting, the fold marks, all of which give clues as to how the document was
                created and the context in which it was created. Teachers are frequently interested
                in using documents as teaching tools, and documentary editors are best able to
                provide them.</p>
            <p>These travel-through-time experiences with documents such as the Declaration of
                Independence or George Washington’s letters, are not quantifiable. In the world of
                grant-writing and state and federal budgets, we have to quantify everything—how many
                individuals did you serve last year; how many individuals do you expect to serve
                this year? Eric Foner recently commented that the “notion that the public good can
                be measured in something other than economic terms has pretty much been
                    abandoned.”<ptr target="#note21" xml:id="nr21" n="21"/> Of course, I cannot
                testify before my state legislature’s appropriation committee that I use documents
                to travel through time, so I end up telling them the numbers they want—how many
                students I spoke to. What’s frustrating is that I can’t quantify the look on a
                fourth grader’s face when she figured out how to read a nineteenth-century letter. I
                received this note: “Mr. Lupton, I didn’t know Lincoln wrote in cursive.” I suppose
                I can submit this note and other notes I receive as evidence at my appropriation
                hearing: “Mr. Lupton, your job is so cool”; “Mr. Lupton, your job sounds super
                interesting”; and lastly, my favorite, “Mr. Lupton, I want to be a historian like
                    you.”<ptr target="#note22" xml:id="nr22" n="22"/> These are real notes. And
                documents have a power over people that isn’t quantifiable. I truly felt like I had
                taken these students to a different time, a different era, and helped them
                understand the context of nineteenth-century Illinois.</p>
            <p>And this leads to my second method of time travel, the documentary editor as guide—or
                for you <hi rend="italic">Dr. Who</hi> fans, the time lord. The principal goal of
                the documentary editor is to make documents accessible by providing authoritative
                transcriptions and contextualization. Or more simply put, we want people to read
                documents, and we want people to understand what these documents mean. Going
                further, I want people to be transported in time to meet people and understand
                society in different eras.</p>
            <p>While outreach to schools and justifying ourselves to funding sources are a part of
                our task, the root of documentary editing is in the added value we give to the
                documents. Michael Stevens once noted that “a document without explanation is
                    useless.”<ptr target="#note23" xml:id="nr23" n="23"/> As documentary editors, we
                have an obligation to contextualize these documents to readers who are not as
                experienced in time travel as we are. Editions then become large-scale time
                machines. Our immersion in these documents gives us editors an insight that few
                people have. As a result, we can bridge seemingly unconnected facts into a narrative
                that helps to explain a certain event or a certain decision. And because of our
                knowledge of a particular period of time, documentary editors can better understand
                the larger context of those facts, events, and decisions. We are, in fact, reliving
                those moments along with our chosen subject.</p>
            <p>Rich Leffler noted this tangible connection we have with our subjects: “[A]s editors,
                we become intimately involved with our subject.”<ptr target="#note24" xml:id="nr24"
                    n="24"/> Other editors have commented that they can “eavesdrop” on written
                conversations and that we editors live “simultaneously in two different worlds” of
                    time.<ptr target="#note25" xml:id="nr25" n="25"/> We editors have a rare job
                that guides people to different moments in time. When I read the Lewis and Clark
                journals, for example, I feel as though I’m transported back to 1804 looking at the
                same trees and flowers that they did along the Missouri River. Their writing is a
                time capsule that I can open whenever I want and take the same journey as they did.
                But the contextualization that accompanies it helps me to understand better what
                Lewis and Clark themselves experienced and understand better that period of
                time.</p>
            <p>In that sense, we are time-travel guides—we can watch Abraham Lincoln defend a
                slaveowner in an 1847 legal case, and we can try to explain why Lincoln, the
                antislavery advocate, might have taken this case. We can go back to the Gettysburg
                Address and note the changes among the five different texts and explain why Lincoln
                wrote all five.<ptr target="#note26" xml:id="nr26" n="26"/></p>
            <p>Our editions have been reaching wider audiences, making time travel available to the
                masses. In the past dozen or so years, accomplished authors who use our editions
                have written wonderful biographies and books.<ptr target="#note27" xml:id="nr27"
                    n="27"/> We have given students and authors the ability to travel through time
                to see not only their subject but also a range of people in different places. For
                example, one who studies a particular event in the presidency of John Adams can
                travel to the national capital to see what Adams was writing. But to add more to
                this travel, you can go and see the writings of Thomas Jefferson, Timothy Pickering,
                and John Marshall and “eavesdrop” on their conversations. Our editions serve as time
                machines, and the editor serves as the time-travel guide.</p>
            <p>Because we are guides, we cannot change what happened in the past. And my mind is
                still blown away by Hawking’s many-worlds theory, which would give us the
                opportunity to bridge these worlds to see what life would be like if history took a
                different course. In his short story “A Sound of Thunder,” Ray Bradbury explained
                the butterfly effect. In traveling to the dinosaur age, one of the characters
                stepped on and killed a butterfly, and upon his return to the present, the English
                language was different, spelling was different, and a fascist Hitleresque candidate
                had been elected president.<ptr target="#note28" xml:id="nr28" n="28"/> The
                butterfly effect describes that something as insignificant as killing a butterfly in
                the past can result in subtle or even drastic changes in the present. So, even
                though Stephen Hawking may believe there is a world in which John Wilkes Booth did
                not succeed in killing Lincoln, we still don’t have the technology to get to that
                world and see the changes the butterfly effect made in today’s alternate present.
                Historians typically don’t like to answer “what if” questions, but the butterfly
                effect, if true, would be a counterfactual historian’s dream come true.</p>
            <p>I recently watched the 1902 movie shor<hi rend="italic">t A Trip to the
                    Moon</hi>.<ptr target="#note29" xml:id="nr29" n="29"/> This is the famous movie
                by Georges Melies with the scene of the rocket landing in the man-in-the-moon’s eye.
                In 1902 we were still a year away from the Wright Brothers’ first flight. Who would
                have thought that a mere sixty-seven years later, humans actually would walk on the
                moon? The sci-fi of the past is the technology of the present. What will the sci-fi
                of the present give us for the future?</p>
            <p>According to Einstein’s theory of relativity, we can only travel to the
                future—according to Lupton’s theory of documentary editing, we can only travel into
                the past. But I do wonder what the future of the documentary editing profession will
                look like. How will future editors guide their generation back in time to our day?
                Today we have email, texts, Twitter, Facebook, and other forms of social media—how
                will this content be explained by editors of the future? I sincerely hope that our
                culture won’t be stereotyped as the Age of Kardashian. Or will it be the age of
                TMI—too much information—as people frequently post a picture to Facebook of that
                fettucine alfredo or other meals they’ve had that day. Or they post boring details
                about their lives—what flavor of gum they picked up in the checkout line at the
                grocery store, for example. We don’t care, and we may not care about the blog by the
                first-time mother who documents every tedious fact and milestone with her baby.
                Truth be told, these seemingly uninteresting tidbits come together to form a picture
                of life in the first two decades of the twenty-first century—much the same as
                mundane lawsuits over five-dollar debts in the 1840s give us a great window into the
                antebellum economy. I imagine editors of the future will love that blog by the
                first-time mother as an excellent diary of child-rearing in the early twenty-first
                century.</p>
            <p>For the future editor, we also have oral histories, which have been extremely
                important in the past to Native American cultures. With the lack of letter writing
                today, there is a growing trend for universities, historical societies, and
                libraries to have oral history programs to capture the thoughts and words of
                politicians, military veterans, business leaders, and community leaders, prominent
                or not. These oral histories are wonderful memoir pieces for the subject and his or
                her immediate family. That’s how it’s sold, but its true value will come in the
                future, when editors twenty-five, fifty, or one hundred years from now will be able
                to guide historians and researchers to travel back in time and read these oral
                histories to get into the minds of people living today and explain today’s life to
                those people in the future who did not experience it firsthand.<ptr target="#note30"
                    xml:id="nr30" n="30"/></p>
            <p>I appreciate your patience with my odd connection between science-fiction time travel
                and documentary editing, so let me close with one more trip back to my college
                years. When I was an undergraduate, I considered majoring in astrophysics because of
                my childhood interest in space exploration and time travel, and even today, I find
                myself reading articles on planetary probes, string theory vs. quantum loop gravity,
                multiverses, and the possibility of numerous dimensions. Looking back—and to use
                another time-travel metaphor, hindsight is 20/20—I made the right choice in becoming
                a documentary editor. I don’t have to prove or disprove the existence of wormholes
                or other means of time travel. By immersing myself in documents, I can transport
                myself back in time to whatever period I choose and guide others as to what the
                document is and what it means whether I’m observing great historical events or
                mundane day-to-day life. Our own personal space-time continuum is found within the
                documentary world. Physicists have nothing on us!</p>
            <p>Thank you.</p>
        </body>
        <back>
            <div type="notes">
                <note xml:id="note1">Martha L. Benner, Cullom Davis, eds., <hi rend="italic">The Law
                        Practice of Abraham Lincoln: Complete Documentary Edition</hi>, DVD edition
                    (Urbana: University of Illinois Press, 2000); Martha L. Benner and Cullom Davis,
                    eds., <hi rend="italic">The Law Practice of Abraham Lincoln: Complete
                        Documentary Edition</hi>, 2nd ed. (Springfield: Illinois Historic
                    Preservation Agency, 2009), <ref type="url"
                        target="http://www.lawpracticeofabrahamlincoln.org"
                        >http://www.lawpracticeofabrahamlincoln.org</ref>.</note>
                <note xml:id="note2">For example, see Daniel W. Stowell, ed., <hi rend="italic">In
                        Tender Consideration: Women, Families, and the Law in Abraham Lincoln’s
                        Illinois</hi> (Urbana: University of Illinois Press, 2002), in which editors
                    of the Papers of Abraham Lincoln contributed chapters on various legal topics
                    that were prominent in antebellum Illinois.</note>
                <note xml:id="note3">Illinois Supreme Court Historic Preservation Commission, <ref
                        type="url" target="http://illinoiscourthistory.org/"
                        >http://illinoiscourthistory.org/</ref>.</note>
                <note xml:id="note4">“The Savage Curtain,” <hi rend="italic">Star Trek</hi>, season
                    3, episode 22, original air date March 7, 1969.</note>
                <note xml:id="note5">The individual movies are too numerous to cite, but the <hi
                        rend="italic">X-Men</hi> franchise is produced by Twentieth Century Fox
                    Studios and has run from 2000 to the present, and the <hi rend="italic"
                        >Avengers</hi> franchise is produced by Marvel Studios and has run from 2008
                    to the present. The <hi rend="italic">Hunger Games</hi> franchise is produced by
                    Lionsgate Studios and has run from 2012 to
                    2015.<!--AU: Check whether “Studios” is official  part of names.--></note>
                <note xml:id="note6">H. G. Wells, <hi rend="italic">The Time Machine: An
                        Invention</hi> (New York: Henry Holt, 1895); Kurt Vonnegut Jr., <hi
                        rend="italic">Slaughterhouse-Five, or The Children’s Crusade: A Duty-Dance
                        with Death</hi> (New York: Delacorte, 1969).</note>
                <note xml:id="note7"><hi rend="italic">The Terminator</hi> franchise began in 1984
                    and continues to the present day. The <hi rend="italic">Back to the Future</hi>
                    franchise lasted from 1985 to 1990.</note>
                <note xml:id="note8"><hi rend="italic">Somewhere in Time</hi>, Rastar Pictures,
                    release date October 3, 1980; <hi rend="italic">The Lake House</hi>, Warner
                    Brothers, release date June 16, 2006.</note>
                <note xml:id="note9">Albert Einstein’s theory of special relativity can be read in
                    much detail in Albert Einstein, <hi rend="italic">Relativity: The Special and
                        General Theory</hi> (New York: Henry Holt, 1920), 1–68. The specific example
                    is referred to as the “twin paradox.” See Richard P. Feynman, Robert B.
                    Leighton, and Matthew Sands, <hi rend="italic">The Feynman Lectures on Physics:
                        Mainly Mechanics, Radiation, and Heat</hi> (New York: Addison-Wesley, 1963),
                    section 16-2.</note>
                <note xml:id="note10">In <hi rend="italic">Interstellar</hi>, Cooper (Matthew
                    McConaughey) and Brand (Anne Hathaway) visit a planet with a gravitational time
                    dilation in which an hour on the planet equals seven years off the planet. When
                    Cooper and Brand return to the main ship after a few hours on the planet,
                    twenty-three years had passed on the ship.</note>
                <note xml:id="note11">Richard P. Feynman, QED: <hi rend="italic">The Strange Theory
                        of Light and Matter</hi> (Princeton, NJ: Princeton University Press, 1985),
                    36–76.</note>
                <note xml:id="note12">Stephen Hawking, <hi rend="italic">A Brief History of Time:
                        From the Big Bang to Black Holes</hi> (New York: Bantam Books, 1988).</note>
                <note xml:id="note13">Stephen Hawking, <hi rend="italic">The Universe in a
                        Nutshell</hi> (New York: Bantam Books, 2001), 80.</note>
                <note xml:id="note14">Hawking uses the example of Elvis Presley still being alive;
                    see Stephen Hawking and Leonard Mlodinow, <hi rend="italic">The Grand
                        Design</hi> (New York: Bantam Books, 2010), 136.</note>
                <note xml:id="note15">Hawking notes that the “idea that the universe has multiple
                    histories may sound like science fiction, but it is now accepted as science
                    fact.” Hawking, <hi rend="italic">Universe in a Nutshell</hi>, 80.</note>
                <note xml:id="note16">Erika Holst, “About history, so what? Schools are underfunded
                    and people are sick, You want funding to study the past?” <hi rend="italic"
                        >Illinois Times</hi>, June 26, 2014. <ref type="url"
                        target="http://illinoistimes.com/article-14115-about-history,-so-what-.html"
                        >http://illinoistimes.com/article-14115-about-history,-so-what-.html</ref></note>
                <note xml:id="note17">William Howells, <hi rend="italic">Back of History</hi>
                    (Garden City, NJ: Doubleday and Company, 1954), 25–26, 86, 103; Christopher
                    Woods, ed., <hi rend="italic">Visible Language: Inventions of Writing in the
                        Ancient Middle East and Beyond</hi> (Chicago: University of Chicago Press,
                    2010), 7, 33.</note>
                <note xml:id="note18">The best statement on the advent of writing comes from James
                    H. Breasted, <hi rend="italic">The Conquest of Civilization</hi> (New York:
                    Harper and Brothers, 1926), 53–54. “The invention of writing and of a convenient
                    system of records on paper has had a greater influence in uplifting the human
                    race than any other intellectual achievement in the career of man. It was more
                    important than all the battles ever fought and all the constitutions ever
                    devised.”</note>
                <note xml:id="note19"> Louis Trenchard More, <hi rend="italic">Isaac Newton: A
                        Biography</hi> (New York: Charles Scribner’s Sons, 1934), 176–77. More notes
                    that the phrase was not original to Newton and that its use may have been a
                    social custom and not meant literally. Others have noted that Newton possibly
                    meant this phrase sarcastically; see particularly Frank Manuel, <hi
                        rend="italic">A Portrait of Isaac Newton</hi> (New York: DaCapo Press,
                    1968), 145–46.</note>
                <note xml:id="note20">Ed O’Keefe, “National Archives Bans Photos by Tourists,” <hi
                        rend="italic">Washington Post</hi>, January 25, 2010, <ref type="url"
                        target="http://voices.washingtonpost.com/federal-eye/2010/01/national_archives_bans_photos.html"
                        >http://voices.washingtonpost.com/federal-eye/2010/01/national_archives_bans_photos.html</ref>.</note>
                <note xml:id="note21">Eric Foner, “Historians as Public Figures,” session at
                    American Historical Association Annual Meeting, January 3, 2015, C-SPAN, <ref
                        type="url"
                        target="http://www.c-span.org/video/?323583-1/historians-public-figures"
                        >http://www.c-span.org/video/?323583-1/historians-public-figures</ref>.</note>
                <note xml:id="note22">Salinea to John Lupton; Michaela to John Lupton; Mykell to
                    John Lupton; Nevea to John Lupton, May 15, 2012, notes in author’s
                    possession.</note>
                <note xml:id="note23">Michael E. Stevens, “Why Documentary Editing Matters,” <hi
                        rend="italic">Documentary Editing</hi> 30 (Fall and Winter 2008–9):
                    10.</note>
                <note xml:id="note24">Richard Leffler, “Documentary Editing: Some Essential
                    Elements,” <hi rend="italic">Documentary Editing</hi> 18 (March 1996): 1.</note>
                <note xml:id="note25">Charles F. Hobson, “Keeping Company with Madison and
                    Marshall,” <hi rend="italic">Documentary Editing</hi> 19 (March 1997): 2; Phil
                    Chase, “This Editing Life: The Joys and Imperatives of Documentary Editing,” <hi
                        rend="italic">Scholarly Editing</hi> 35 (2014): 8.</note>
                <note xml:id="note26">See “Notes on the Gettysburg Address,’’ <hi rend="italic">The
                        Papers of Abraham Lincoln</hi>, <ref type="url"
                        target="http://www.papersofabrahamlincoln.org/how-you-can-help/our-search-for-documents/notes-on-the-gettysburg-address"
                        >http://www.papersofabrahamlincoln.org/how-you-can-help/our-search-for-documents/notes-on-the-gettysburg-address</ref>.</note>
                <note xml:id="note27">A frequently cited example is Pauline Maier, “The Founding
                    Revisited,” <hi rend="italic">Washington Post Book World</hi> 28 (August
                    2005).</note>
                <note xml:id="note28">Ray Bradbury, <hi rend="italic">A Sound of Thunder and Other
                        Stories</hi> (New York: HarperCollins, 1990), 203–15. The story was
                    originally published in Collier’s magazine in 1952.</note>
                <note xml:id="note29"><hi rend="italic">Le Voyage dans la Lune</hi> (<hi
                        rend="italic">A Trip to the Moon</hi>), Star Film, release date September 1,
                    1902.</note>
                <note xml:id="note30">The Oral History Association notes that “oral history
                    interviews are historical documents that are preserved and made accessible to
                    future researchers and members of the public,” <ref type="url"
                        target="http://www.oralhistory.org/"
                    >http://www.oralhistory.org/</ref>.</note>

            </div>
        </back>
    </text>
</TEI>
