<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<?oxygen RNGSchema="http://www.scholarlyediting.org/scholarlyediting.rng" type="xml"?>
<!--The poem draft in here is very tricky. I used the markup in the live oak with moss edition as a template, but this will
    probably need to be redone-->
<!--I didn't know who the author was-->
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xml:lang="eng">
    <teiHeader>
        <fileDesc>
            <titleStmt>
                <title level="a" type="main">The Letters in the Litter</title>
                <title level="a" type="sub"
                    >Messy Boundaries and Other Conundrums in Editing Walt
                    Whitman’s Correspondence</title>
                <author key="Gray, Nicole">Nicole Gray</author>
                <author key="Price, Kenneth M.">Kenneth M. Price</author>
            </titleStmt>
            <editionStmt>
                <edition> <date>2016</date> </edition>
            </editionStmt>
            <publicationStmt>
                <idno type="file">essay.grayprice</idno>
                <authority>Scholary Editing: The Annual of the Association for Documentary
                    Editing</authority>
                <address>
                    <addrLine>http://www.scholarlyediting.org</addrLine>
                </address>
                <publisher>Association for Documentary Editing</publisher>
                <publisher>University of Nebraska&#8211;Lincoln</publisher>
                <distributor> <name>Center for Digital Research in the Humanities</name> <address>
                    <addrLine>319 Love Library</addrLine>
                    <addrLine>University of Nebraska&#8211;Lincoln</addrLine>
                    <addrLine>Lincoln, NE 68588-4100</addrLine>
                    <addrLine>http://cdrh.unl.edu</addrLine>
                    </address> </distributor>
                <date>2016</date>
                <availability>
                    <p>Scholary Editing: The Annual of the Association for Documentary Editing is
                        freely distributed by the Association for Documentary Editing and the Center
                        for Digital Research in the Humanities at the University of Nebraska-Lincoln
                        and licensed under a Creative Commons Attribution-NonCommercial-ShareAlike
                        3.0 Unported License</p>
                </availability>
            </publicationStmt>
            <seriesStmt>
                <title level="j"
                    >Scholarly Editing: The Annual of the Association for Documentary
                    Editing</title>
                <respStmt>
                    <resp>editor</resp>
                    <name xml:id="ag" key="Gailey, Amanda A.">Amanda Gailey</name>
                </respStmt>
                <respStmt>
                    <resp>editor</resp>
                    <name xml:id="awj" key="Jewell, Andrew W.">Andrew Jewell</name>
                </respStmt>
                <idno type="vol">37</idno>
                <idno type="ISSN">2167-1257</idno>
            </seriesStmt>
            <sourceDesc>
                <bibl> <note>Born digital.</note> </bibl>
            </sourceDesc>
        </fileDesc>
        <revisionDesc>
            <change when="2016-03-24"><name xml:id="gk" key="Kirilloff, Gabi"
                > Gabi Kirilloff</name>
                markup in TEI XML</change>
        </revisionDesc>
    </teiHeader>
    <text>
        <front>
            <head type="main">The Letters in the Litter</head>
            <head type="sub"
                >Messy Boundaries and Other Conundrums in Editing Walt Whitman’s
                Correspondence</head>
            <byline>Nicole Gray</byline>
            <byline>Kenneth M. Price</byline>
            <epigraph>
                <cit>
                    <quote>We got talking a little about Carlyle, whereat W. produced a Burroughs
                        letter which he explained to me had “just turned up in the litter” and
                        contained “some mighty good matter&#8212;just a little of it&#8212;anent
                            Carlyle.”<ptr
                        target="#note1" xml:id="nr1" n="1" /></quote>
                </cit>
            </epigraph>
            <epigraph>
                <cit>
                    <quote>Editing the corpus of documents associated with Walt Whitman might be
                        described as a series of compromises or as a quixotic task, depending on
                        whether you are of a practical or a despairing inclination&#8212;a
                        challenging effort to impose order on a notoriously unruly set of materials.
                        An infamous picture of Whitman at the end of his life captures what appears
                        to be chaos: the elderly poet, in a chair in his house on Mickle Street in
                        Camden, surrounded by the debris of his writing life, a tossed on a sea of
                        papers that were&#8212;loosely at best&#8212;organized into piles.<ptr
                        target="#note2" xml:id="nr2" n="2" /></quote>
                </cit>
            </epigraph>
        </front>
        <body>
            <div type="section">
                <figure>
                    <head>Figure 1: Walt Whitman in his upstairs bedroom in Camden in 1891.
                        Photograph by Dr. William Reeder, Philadelphia. Library of Congress,
                        Washington, DC.</head>
                    <figDesc>Figure 1: Walt Whitman in his upstairs bedroom in Camden in 1891.
                        Photograph by Dr. William Reeder, Philadelphia. Library of Congress,
                        Washington, DC.</figDesc>
                    <graphic url="images/essay.grayprice.01.jpg" />
                </figure>
                <p>The efforts of the <hi rend="italic"
                    >Walt Whitman Archive</hi> over the course of
                    its twenty-year history have been devoted to trying to make sense out of these
                    piles and many others. Early editorial decisions that were aimed toward
                    maximizing the intelligibility of the <hi
                    rend="italic"
                    >Archive</hi> led to the
                    adoption of genre as a central organizing principle. One product of that
                    framework is that in reproducing documents on the <hi
                    rend="italic"
                    >Whitman
                        Archive</hi>, we also reproduce genre, in both text encoding and interface.
                    Genre&#8212;defined broadly as a category or type of writing “characterized by a
                    particular form, style, or purpose”&#8212;is one way of organizing the
                    information in both physical and digital archives.<ptr
                    target="#note3" xml:id="nr3" n="3"
                     /> There are others. Chronology, for example, also informs
                    the approach of the <hi
                    rend="italic"
                    >Whitman Archive</hi> and of many other
                    collections, archives, and editions engaged in organizing archival
                        materials.<ptr
                    target="#note4" xml:id="nr4" n="4" /> <hi rend="italic"
                    >Whitman Archive</hi> staff members continually make decisions
                    about boundaries between genres, documents, and texts in order to decipher the
                    materials and to facilitate users’ encounters with the <hi
                    rend="italic"
                    >Archive</hi>. But it is crucial as we impose orderliness to also honor
                    messiness, not just because that is how Whitman left&#8212;and lived
                    in&#8212;his personal archive, but also because his writings seem designed to
                    make a mess of boundaries, smudging any clear lines we (or anyone else) might
                    wish to impose by separating documents based on genre or era.<ptr
                    target="#note5" xml:id="nr5" n="5" /></p>
                <p>Whitman’s correspondence presents a useful opportunity for thinking about matters
                    of genre and order. Living at a time of rapid development in the scope and uses
                    of the postal system, Whitman offers one example of the range and intensity of
                    letter writing in the nineteenth-century United States.<ptr
                    target="#note6" xml:id="nr6" n="6"
                     /> Over the course of his life, the poet communicated by
                    post with correspondents worldwide about family, personal, and professional
                    matters. His correspondence often has complex relations to published works. In
                    some cases, Whitman would cut up incoming letters, paste them back together, and
                    write notes toward poems or prose pieces on the backs of them. In other cases,
                    letter and publication merge. Whitman’s powerfully moving letter to the mother
                    of corporal Frank Irvin following Irvin’s death, for instance, is known only as
                    it appears in <hi
                    rend="italic">Memoranda During the War</hi> and <hi rend="italic"
                    >Specimen Days</hi>; no draft or original copy of the letter
                    has been found. In this case, we encounter this letter as an integral part of
                    larger, later prose works.<ptr
                    target="#note7" xml:id="nr7" n="7"
                     /> What is a
                    letter from or to Walt Whitman? How should such documents be edited and
                    presented to readers in a digital age? What is necessary to the understanding of
                    Whitman’s correspondence and its relationship to his published and unpublished
                    poetry and prose, and what types of annotation and contextualization are
                    necessary? These fundamental, simple-sounding questions have proven to be
                    enormously complex for those of us working at the <hi
                    rend="italic">Walt Whitman
                        Archive</hi>.</p>
                <p>The question of “what is a letter” is a generic and editorial question, but it is
                    also an ontological and interpretive one.<ptr
                    target="#note8" xml:id="nr8" n="8"
                     /> For editors of printed editions of correspondence, the classification often
                    determined whether or not something made it into a published volume. For <hi
                    rend="italic"
                    >Whitman Archive</hi> editors working in a digital environment,
                    classifications like genre can determine whether or not something gets published
                    earlier rather than later; in what category it is grouped; and in which part of
                    the <hi
                    rend="italic"
                    >Archive</hi> it appears. In both cases, classification
                    shapes how the letter is experienced, the limitations of its reach and relation,
                    and the conventions of its representation.<ptr
                    target="#note9" xml:id="nr9" n="9"
                     /> In a digital environment, classification also becomes a matter of
                    what markup we use and which parts of the letter we choose to transcribe and
                        encode.<ptr
                    target="#note10" xml:id="nr10" n="10"
                     /> In our treatment and
                    representation of Whitman’s correspondence, we have borrowed from the
                    conventions of printed volumes (providing transcriptions that retain, as much as
                    possible, the original spelling and punctuation of the letters; using brackets
                    to mark illegible or unclear words; and adding footnotes as explanatory
                    apparatus). But we expect to do more in future years to update our editorial
                    policy and our display and search functionality to begin to account for the
                    complexity of many of the archival objects associated with Whitman. This process
                    has returned us to a long history of correspondence editing as well as the
                    tension between classification or order and randomness or
                    serendipity&#8212;letter or litter&#8212;as we consider what lies ahead for the
                        <hi
                    rend="italic"
                    >Whitman Archive</hi> and its ongoing engagement with what
                    Jerome McGann has called “the problem of knowledge representation.”<ptr
                    target="#note11" xml:id="nr11" n="11" /></p>
                <p>In this essay, we focus on genre as an example of one seemingly coherent
                    organizing principle that can actually disorient or needlessly limit the
                    representative possibilities for an archival object. We discuss some of the edge
                    cases of Whitman’s correspondence&#8212;documents whose generic boundaries are
                    difficult to determine&#8212;and explore their significance for editorial
                    purposes and the ways that our thinking about these objects has affected how we
                    have conceptualized and continue to conceptualize the structure of the <hi
                    rend="italic"
                    >Whitman Archive</hi> more generally. The epigraph to this
                    essay represents one of several times over the course of Whitman’s late-life
                    conversations, transcribed immediately afterward by Horace Traubel and
                    eventually published in nine volumes, when Whitman and Traubel joke about a
                    letter or another document surfacing from the litter of papers in the poet’s
                    room in Camden, New Jersey. What is the relationship of the letter to the
                        litter?<ptr
                    target="#note12" xml:id="nr12" n="12"
                     /> It is important not to
                    make negative assumptions about litter, given Whitman’s fondness for “compost,”
                    “debris,” “leaves-droppings,” and the like. Whitman’s room, like the <hi
                    rend="italic"
                    >Whitman Archive</hi>, was a broader context, an environment
                    that impacted the material form of his papers and that structures the ways they
                    can be interpreted.</p>
                <p>As we work to reorder Whitman’s piles and reproduce them in a digital
                    environment, we revisit the question of the difference between letter and litter
                    and the usefulness and intelligibility of genre-based organization. The <hi
                    rend="italic"
                    >Whitman Archive</hi> is moving toward an editorial approach
                    that embraces the potential for multiple forms of categorization and display, a
                    structure that allows objects to be both letter and litter, and many other
                    things besides. Documents that resist order point to things other than genre,
                    such as the complexities of composition and the effects of Whitman’s environment
                    and his paralysis on the shape and substance as well as the subjects of his
                    compositions in his later years. Reading Whitman’s correspondence as woven into
                    his prose and poetry illuminates both. Such complexities suggest that we may
                    need to revisit editorial commonplaces in the digital era. Ultimately we see the
                    future of the <hi
                    rend="italic"
                    >Whitman Archive</hi> as an effort to reach
                    beyond the limitations of genre or temporality or any other single organizing
                    principle by developing the framework to represent a document in multiple ways,
                    within multiple sections, with options to navigate between one document and the
                    next. In doing so we leverage new media capacities to represent process as well
                    as product, document as well as text, and to attend to the history of an
                    archival object in all its sometimes frustrating ambiguity and multitudes.</p>
            </div>
            <div type="section">
                <head type="main">What Makes a Letter?</head>
                <p>The keys to a genre are the particulars of its form, style, or purpose&#8212;the
                    characteristics or the protocols associated with it as a category of writing. We
                    might take as our starting point the definition of a letter by Edward Vanhoutte
                    and Ron Van den Branden as “a physical channel through which a communicative
                    situation is established,” defined by the distinctive features of time,
                    receiver, and sender.<ptr
                    target="#note13" xml:id="nr13" n="13"
                     /> Certainly in
                    the case of Whitman there are plenty of letters that fit such a basic
                    definition. Still, Whitman’s correspondence, like that of many literary figures,
                    can sometimes be difficult to distinguish from other kinds of writing.<ptr
                    target="#note14" xml:id="nr14" n="14" /> Though there are many documents that
                    take the conventional form of a letter&#8212;date, salutation, body,
                    signature&#8212;there are also fragments of letters, as well as iterations of
                    letters in copies or drafts. On one end of the spectrum are jottings or loose
                    notes that seem to be directed to a third party or that have some of the formal
                    features of a letter. <figure>
                    <head>Figure 2: Fragment of a Whitman letter, written on the verso of an
                            undated letter to Whitman from Joseph B. Marvin. Charles E. Feinberg
                            Collection, Library of Congress, Washington, DC. These and other images
                            from the Feinberg Collection are reproduced courtesy of the Library of
                            Congress.</head>
                    <figDesc>Figure 2: Fragment of a Whitman letter, written on the verso of an
                            undated letter to Whitman from Joseph B. Marvin. Charles E. Feinberg
                            Collection, Library of Congress, Washington, DC. These and other images
                            from the Feinberg Collection are reproduced courtesy of the Library of
                            Congress.</figDesc>
                    <graphic url="images/essay.grayprice.02.jpg" />
                    </figure> The signature at the bottom in pencil, combined with the instructions
                    to a third party&#8212;“Remember me to Coley, John Towers, Jim Sorrell, David
                    Stevens &amp; all the boys”&#8212;seem like unmistakable proof that this
                    fragment represents a line toward a letter. And, interestingly, these words
                    appear again, in a draft of a nearly complete letter from Whitman to Peter Doyle
                    dated October 14. <figure
                    type="enlargeOnClick">
                    <head>Figure 3: The second leaf of a draft letter from Whitman to Peter
                            Doyle, October 14, [1868]. Charles E. Feinberg Collection, Library of
                            Congress, Washington, DC.</head>
                    <figDesc>Figure 3: The second leaf of a draft letter from Whitman to Peter
                            Doyle, October 14, [1868]. Charles E. Feinberg Collection, Library of
                            Congress, Washington, DC.</figDesc>
                    <graphic url="images/essay.grayprice.03.jpg" />
                    </figure> In the draft, the line from the fragment appears, seemingly in a later
                    iteration, but has been crossed out. We do not have a copy of the final letter,
                    if one exists. The only evidence that this particular fragment ever made it into
                    a letter that was sent is its presence in a printed transcription by Whitman’s
                    friend and executor Richard Maurice Bucke, who edited and published a collection
                    of letters from Whitman to Peter Doyle in 1897.<ptr
                    target="#note15" xml:id="nr15" n="15"
                     /> This collection, one of several published after
                    Whitman’s death that focus on the letters between the poet and a single
                    correspondent, is framed with an introductory mention of Whitman’s “Calamus”
                    poems, and what Bucke calls the “exceptional and remarkable” friendship between
                    Whitman and Doyle.<ptr
                    target="#note16" xml:id="nr16" n="16"
                     /> In the
                    introduction, Bucke notes Whitman’s tendency in his letters to send his love to
                    a group of friends and acquaintances known by Doyle.</p>
                <p>It is unclear whether Bucke, whose collection of letters was based on a set given
                    to him by Doyle, possessed a final version of this letter that included the
                    line, or if he simply restored the line to the transcription in spite of its
                    deletion in the draft.<ptr
                    target="#note17" xml:id="nr17" n="17"
                     /> The line is
                    consistent with Bucke’s expressed intention in his edition to emphasize and
                    provide evidence of Whitman’s “calamus” friendships, and so he may have had this
                    reason to restore it if he was working from the draft. Conceivably, the line was
                    crossed out later, though neighboring corrections in Whitman’s hand in the same
                    pencil as the overstrike would suggest that Whitman was responsible for the
                    deletion. In any case, the collection of Doyle letters was republished by
                    Whitman’s executors in <hi
                    rend="italic"
                    >The Complete Writings of Walt
                        Whitman</hi> in 1902, with the excised line still included in the October 14
                        letter.<ptr
                    target="#note18" xml:id="nr18" n="18" /></p>
                <p>This document, beginning “More about William Blake,” may represent a partial
                    draft of a draft of a letter. Or it could be that Whitman copied the line onto
                    this note when he crossed it out of the draft letter to Doyle, in order to save
                    it for later. Or perhaps he wished to reproduce or remember the line in another
                    epistolary context. Is “More about William Blake” a letter, a note, a deletion,
                    or all of the above? Presumably a draft of a letter doesn’t establish a
                    communicative situation&#8212;at least not until an editor comes along to read
                    the draft! In the case of Whitman, who received at least one letter from an
                    auctioneer about the prices for which his manuscripts had sold at auction, it is
                    possible to speculate that, chaotic though the papers in his room may have
                    seemed, his decisions to retain manuscripts or hand them to his friends were
                    made with an eye to readers and editors to come.<ptr
                    target="#note19" xml:id="nr19" n="19" /> On the <hi rend="italic"
                    >Whitman Archive</hi>, we
                    have not yet begun editing drafts of letters, unless they are the only remaining
                    copy of a letter,<ptr
                    target="#note20" xml:id="nr20" n="20"
                     /> but in the future
                    we plan to present all drafts, so that users can see iterations, mark the
                    progression from draft to final copy, and sometimes better grasp nuances in his
                    writing and his relationships.</p>
                <p>At times the existence of a draft alone can be highly illuminating, as in the
                    case of Whitman’s 1890 response to John Addington Symonds’s repeated inquiries
                    about the meaning of the “Calamus” cluster of poems.<ptr
                    target="#note21" xml:id="nr21" n="21"
                     /> The final copy is no longer extant, but if it were,
                    that final copy would almost certainly convey less about Whitman’s response than
                    does a mere image of the draft. This is the famous letter in which Whitman
                    claimed: “Tho’ always unmarried I have had six children.” Equaling that whopper
                    is his final sentence, described by Edwin Haviland Miller as “artfully
                    deceptive”: “I see I have written with haste &amp; too great effusion&#8212;but
                    let it stand.”<ptr
                    target="#note22" xml:id="nr22" n="22" /> <figure type="enlargeOnClick">
                    <head>Figure 4: Recto of a draft letter from Whitman to John Addington
                            Symonds, dated August 19, 1890. Charles E. Feinberg Collection, Library
                            of Congress, Washington, DC.</head>
                    <figDesc>Figure 4: Recto of a draft letter from Whitman to John Addington
                            Symonds, dated August 19, 1890. Charles E. Feinberg Collection, Library
                            of Congress, Washington, DC.</figDesc>
                    <graphic url="images/essay.grayprice.04.jpg" />
                    </figure> Painstakingly crafted and pasted together, bearing witness to numerous
                    deletions and additions that led to the final version of the letter, this draft
                    belies Whitman’s description of writing “with haste.”<ptr
                    target="#note23" xml:id="nr23" n="23"
                     /> The material composition of this draft letter, with
                    its paste-ons and revisions, is as revelatory as the content, and the two are
                    mutually explanatory even as they contradict each other. Here an image of the
                    object, a link to Symonds’s letter, and an explanation that this is a draft as
                    well as a transcription of the text of the letter are necessary to understanding
                    Whitman’s response to Symonds’s query about “Calamus.”<ptr
                    target="#note24" xml:id="nr24" n="24" /></p>
                <p>Other explanation is necessary, too. Many have discussed the front of this draft;
                    few have mentioned the back of it.<ptr
                    target="#note25" xml:id="nr25" n="25"
                     />
                    The verso of the draft letter reveals that the draft has been pasted together
                    out of various materials, both printed and handwritten. <figure
                    type="enlargeOnClick">
                    <head>Figure 5: Verso of a draft letter from Whitman to John Addington
                            Symonds, dated August 19, 1890. Charles E. Feinberg Collection, Library
                            of Congress, Washington, DC.</head>
                    <figDesc>Figure 5: Verso of a draft letter from Whitman to John Addington
                            Symonds, dated August 19, 1890. Charles E. Feinberg Collection, Library
                            of Congress, Washington, DC.</figDesc>
                    <graphic url="images/essay.grayprice.05.jpg" />
                    </figure> One scrap is a printed poem titled “Address to the Veterans,”
                    attributed to “William Errickson.” Another is a letter from Richard Maurice
                    Bucke that can be dated between February 5 and 15, 1890, describing the death of
                    Bucke’s sister-in-law Matilda Gurd. Still another is a partial envelope with the
                    return address of Dora Warnecke, a resident of San Pablo, California.<ptr
                    target="#note26" xml:id="nr26" n="26"
                     /> A series of other letters and
                    objects have been recycled into the draft of Whitman’s letter to Symonds. How
                    are we to treat this new composite object? Typically, for publication on the <hi
                    rend="italic"
                    >Whitman Archive</hi>, we would separate out the various parts,
                    publishing each letter individually and linking them in the annotations,
                    providing images of both recto and verso. But a robust system of relation,
                    created and implemented through both the annotations and the encoding, is needed
                    to fully represent the complexity of this object, which singlehandedly muddies
                    the distinctions between incoming and outgoing letter, as well as draft and
                    final copy.</p>
                <p><hi rend="italic"
                    >Calamus</hi>, the volume of letters from Whitman to Doyle
                    edited by Bucke, itself begins with an item that may or may not be classified as
                    a letter: Bucke reproduces a note written on the flyleaf of a copy of <hi
                    rend="italic">Specimen Days</hi> that Whitman sent to Doyle in 1883. <figure
                    type="enlargeOnClick">
                    <head>Figure 6: Walt Whitman, <hi rend="italic"
                        >Calamus: A Series of Letters
                                Written During the Years 1868–1880 by Walt Whitman to a Young Friend
                                (Peter Doyle)</hi>, ed. Richard Maurice Bucke (Boston: Laurens
                            Maynard, 1897), iii. The copy of <hi
                        rend="italic"
                        >Specimen Days</hi>
                            with the original inscription to Doyle is at the Harry Ransom Center,
                            University of Texas at Austin (shelfmark PS 3220 A1 1882, copy
                            1).</head>
                    <figDesc>Figure 6: Walt Whitman, Calamus: A Series of Letters Written During
                            the Years 1868–1880 by Walt Whitman to a Young Friend (Peter Doyle), ed.
                            Richard Maurice Bucke (Boston: Laurens Maynard, 1897), iii. The copy of
                            Specimen Days with the original inscription to Doyle is at the Harry
                            Ransom Center, University of Texas at Austin (shelfmark PS 3220 A1 1882,
                            copy 1).</figDesc>
                    <graphic url="images/essay.grayprice.06.jpg" />
                    </figure> Does this inscription, headed “Pete” and signed “W.W.,” originally
                    appearing at the front of a volume that traveled, as a letter would, through the
                    mail, constitute a letter? The placement of the message in <hi
                    rend="italic"
                    >Specimen Days</hi> means the flyleaf inscription could be read as an
                    enclosure or simply as an introduction or a paratext to <hi
                    rend="italic"
                    >Specimen Days</hi>. Thinking of this inscription as a letter is useful
                    because it is clearly one in a series of communications with Doyle. As Ted
                    Genoways observes in a footnote to his transcription of the flyleaf in volume 7
                    of <hi
                    rend="italic"
                    >The Correspondence</hi>, “this note is significant, because
                    it constitutes the first correspondence from [Whitman] to Doyle since July 1880.
                    It appears that writing <hi
                    rend="italic"
                    >Specimen Days</hi> stirred [Whitman]’s
                    memories of the times he shared with Doyle in Washington” (69). Not thinking of
                    the inscription as correspondence, within a history of correspondence, puts the
                    reader at a disadvantage in interpreting the meaning of this inscription.</p>
                <p>Perhaps the most famous letter associated with Whitman, extraordinary in content
                    if traditional in form, was sent to the poet by Ralph Waldo Emerson after the
                    publication of the first edition of <hi
                    rend="italic"
                    >Leaves of Grass</hi> in
                    1855. To Emerson’s dismay, Whitman reprinted the missive with his own extended
                    reply in the “Leaves-Droppings” section of the 1856 edition of <hi
                    rend="italic"
                    >Leaves</hi>, going so far as to use part of Emerson’s letter as a blurb on
                    the spine of the book. Even before doing this, Whitman had the Emerson letter
                    printed in a newspaper, turning a private communication into a public one. Cast
                    out of the insular network of person-to-person correspondence and into the
                    public role of endorsement, Emerson’s letter changes in form and function,
                    becoming both paratext and provocation to its sender (and its numerous
                    unforeseen recipients).<ptr
                    target="#note27" xml:id="nr27" n="27"
                     />
                    Interestingly, however, the 1856 <hi rend="italic"
                    >Leaves of Grass</hi> as a
                    whole is framed in Whitman’s response as part of a letter&#8212;an enclosure, as
                    it were: “HERE are thirty-two Poems, which I send you, dear Friend and Master,
                    not having found how I could satisfy myself with sending any usual
                    acknowledgment of your letter.”<ptr
                    target="#note28" xml:id="nr28" n="28"
                     /> The
                    genre of Whitman’s extensive response letter is anything but straightforward,
                    with even the speech-act words that seem to perform gift-giving or presentation
                    (“Here are thirty-two poems”) coming <hi
                    rend="italic"
                    >after</hi> the poems in
                    the volume. The document is labeled “Letter to Ralph Waldo Emerson” and contains
                    the formal features of a letter&#8212;date, location, salutation, body, and
                    signature&#8212;but the prose of the letter, despite its frequent address to
                    “Master,” is akin to an essay along the lines of the first preface to <hi
                    rend="italic"
                    >Leaves of Grass</hi>, and of course its appearance within a
                    book (the letter was never sent as a manuscript to Emerson) takes it out of a
                    context of personal correspondence.</p>
                <p>These documents pose a challenge for the editor seeking to situate them within
                    some kind of coherent system, whether that system is based on genre, chronology,
                    or some other organizing principle. Each document can be interpreted as a letter
                    or part of a letter that was composed or sent at a particular date or time. But
                    this only tells one part of the story of the document. Each segment of a
                    repurposed object or series of notes could be classified and dated differently.
                    The publication and circulation of Emerson’s letter after it was sent and
                    received are central to the meaning of that letter. Representing these objects
                    online without collapsing the range of interpretive possibilities they introduce
                    requires both creativity and diligence. A digital environment offers new
                    potential to represent single objects in multiple ways, but also to create more
                    robust links among objects, allowing the user to move, for instance, from the
                    draft of a letter to the final version, or from a transcription of the letter as
                    Emerson sent it to its position within the 1856 <hi
                    rend="italic"
                    >Leaves of
                        Grass</hi>. Digital scans or facsimiles also help to clarify the material
                    complexities of some of these documents, even as searchable transcriptions offer
                    another way of navigating them tailored more specifically to user interests.</p>
            </div>
            <div type="section">
                <head type="main">Letters in Unexpected Places</head>
                <p>In fact, the digital scans of the letters on the <hi rend="italic"
                    >Whitman
                        Archive</hi> might come as a surprise to readers familiar with the printed
                    editions of Whitman’s correspondence. A world quite apart from the neat typeface
                    and standardized spacing of the printed letters, the manuscripts feature all
                    manner of messiness, including multiple hands, smudges, deletions, markings of
                    the holding repository, postmarks, and notes written by owners. Here the
                    messiness reflects the history of the individual document and also the history
                    of previous editors. Many of the letters include a note at the top written by
                    Horace Traubel, locating the letter within his <hi
                    rend="italic">With Walt
                        Whitman in Camden</hi>, where Traubel frequently includes complete
                    transcriptions of letters Whitman hands to him in the course of their
                    conversations. <figure>
                    <head>Figure 7: Traubel’s note at the top of a letter from James Redpath to
                            Whitman (October 5, 1886), “see notes Aug 26 &amp; 30, ’88,” points to
                            entries in <hi
                        rend="italic">With Walt Whitman in Camden</hi> dated <ref type="url"
                        target="http://whitmanarchive.org/criticism/disciples/traubel/WWWiC/2/med.00002.43.html"
                        >August 26, 1888</ref>, and <ref type="url"
                        target="http://whitmanarchive.org/criticism/disciples/traubel/WWWiC/2/med.00002.47.html"
                        >August 30, 1888</ref>. The latter includes a transcription of the
                            letter, with Whitman’s commentary. Charles E. Feinberg Collection,
                            Library of Congress, Washington, DC.</head>
                    <figDesc>Figure 7: Traubel’s note at the top of a letter from James Redpath
                            to Whitman (October 5, 1886), “see notes Aug 26 &amp; 30, ’88,” points
                            to entries in With Walt Whitman in Camden dated August 26, 1888, and
                            August 30, 1888. The latter includes a transcription of the letter, with
                            Whitman’s commentary. Charles E. Feinberg Collection, Library of
                            Congress, Washington, DC.</figDesc>
                    <graphic url="images/essay.grayprice.07.jpg" />
                    </figure> In their interactions, Traubel often reads aloud a letter to or from
                    Whitman, providing the occasion for reliving a historical moment and eliciting
                    commentary from Whitman about the sender, the situation, or the letter itself,
                    as the epigraph to this essay suggests.<ptr
                    target="#note29" xml:id="nr29" n="29" /></p>
                <p>Just as Whitman preemptively shaped the critical conversation about his poetry
                    through placement of his own anonymous reviews of <hi
                    rend="italic"
                    >Leaves of
                        Grass</hi>, here again we find him beating us to the punch: in tandem with
                    Traubel, he became the first to provide extended commentary on the
                    correspondence of Walt Whitman. In fact, Traubel’s extraordinary years-long
                    interview, peppered by transcriptions of letters, might be said to render him
                    one of the first editors of Whitman’s correspondence.<ptr
                    target="#note30" xml:id="nr30" n="30"
                     /> It is worth noting in this context Traubel’s process
                    of editorial selection, which is guided by Whitman himself. Letters seemingly
                    appear in <hi
                    rend="italic"
                    >With Walt Whitman in Camden</hi> organically, as
                    they emerge from the litter, or as they are given to Traubel by the poet. After
                    one visit, for instance, Traubel writes, “W. handed me a stained letter which he
                    wished me to read back to him.”<ptr
                    target="#note31" xml:id="nr31" n="31"
                     />
                    Acting as axes of conversation, the letters provoke reflections on the past, on
                    mutual acquaintances and friends of Whitman and Traubel, on the poet’s work, and
                    on many other topics. Set into the flow of the discussion, the letters help give
                    rise to a rich context of day-to-day rituals, reminiscences, and interactions.
                    This is no ordinary “edition” of letters, and yet in its very resistance to
                    cordoning off the archive from daily life, its openness to the combination of
                    factors that led to the unearthing of any given letter, and its careful
                    representation of the social scene of the letter’s second life and
                    rearticulation as well as the text of the letter itself, it offers a provocative
                    view of what might emerge out of an editorial approach that takes seriously the
                    conjunction of letter and litter, or that resists the ready logic of genre- and
                    chronology-based categorization.<ptr
                    target="#note32" xml:id="nr32" n="32" /></p>
                <p>Whitman did more than read and comment on his correspondence. Particularly once
                    he was less mobile, after his paralysis, he would cut some letters into pieces,
                    paste the fragments randomly back together, and use them as the scaffolding for
                    poetry or prose manuscripts. One example, currently held at the Walt Whitman
                    House in Camden, is a draft of the poem that would eventually be published as
                    “You Tides With Ceaseless Swell.” <figure
                    type="enlargeOnClick">
                    <head>Figure 8: Recto image, manuscript draft of “You Tides With Ceaseless
                            Swell.” Courtesy of Walt Whitman House, Camden, NJ. Reproduced with
                            permission.</head>
                    <figDesc>Figure 8: Recto image, manuscript draft of “You Tides With
                            Ceaseless Swell.” Courtesy of Walt Whitman House, Camden, NJ. Reproduced
                            with permission.</figDesc>
                    <graphic url="images/essay.grayprice.08.jpg" />
                    </figure> As he had with the Symonds draft, in order to create this manuscript,
                    Whitman cut apart and pasted back together several other pieces of paper. In
                    this case those pieces included four different letters: one from Whitelaw Reid,
                    dated July 17, [1878]; another from Richard J. Hinton, dated September 10, 1871;
                    yet another from William J. Sewell, dated January 8, 1884; and a final letter,
                    undated, from an unidentified sender. <figure
                    type="enlargeOnClick">
                    <head>Figure 9: Verso image, manuscript draft of “You Tides With Ceaseless
                            Swell,” constructed out of a series of letters sent to Whitman. Courtesy
                            of Walt Whitman House, Camden, NJ.</head>
                    <figDesc>Figure 9: Verso image, manuscript draft of “You Tides With
                            Ceaseless Swell,” constructed out of a series of letters sent to
                            Whitman. Courtesy of Walt Whitman House, Camden, NJ.</figDesc>
                    <graphic url="images/essay.grayprice.09.jpg" />
                    </figure> Scholars have described the importance of collaging to Whitman’s
                    poetic and composition practices, but at first glance this seems to be a
                    pasting-together that functions at the level of conscious composition only
                    depending on which side of the document one examines.<ptr
                    target="#note33" xml:id="nr33" n="33"
                     /> That is, the piecing together of the poetry lines
                    seems highly purposeful, while the shards and remains of the fragmentary letters
                    are pasted together in apparently random fashion. The content of the letters may
                    have contributed to the poetry manuscript, but if so, it is not immediately
                    apparent. The letters were probably selected not because of any content but
                    because of the available white space left on a leaf. Spanning over a decade, the
                    letters also reflect Whitman’s practice of keeping papers and letters for
                    extended periods of time, even as he eventually used them for scratch paper.<ptr
                    target="#note34" xml:id="nr34" n="34"
                     /> What literary sense can be made of
                    this practice? Certainly the letters constitute bibliographical evidence. Based
                    on the letters, we can date Whitman’s composition: if, as Geoffrey Sill argues,
                    the title and opening two lines were written first on the back of the 1878
                    letter, the poetry draft was almost certainly composed between that date and the
                    months after January 8, 1884, the latest date of one of the letters used in
                        composition.<ptr
                    target="#note35" xml:id="nr35" n="35"
                     /> The 1871 Hinton
                    letter seemingly acts only as the scaffolding for the bits as Whitman pasted
                    them together.<ptr
                    target="#note36" xml:id="nr36" n="36" /></p>
                <p>This manuscript is striking for many reasons, not least the problems it poses for
                    editorial treatment on the Whitman Archive. As a material object, it is a study:
                    in one part of the poem draft, Whitman appears to have used a piece of paper to
                    overwrite previous lines with newly composed ones, but the bulk of the
                    manuscript appears to have been written in one order, then cut to pieces,
                    shuffled, and glued back in a different order. The manuscript in its current
                    order reads: 
                    <figure>
                        <head>Figure 10: Transcription of manuscript draft of “You Tides With Ceaseless
                            Swell.” At the top left corner of the pasted-down piece of paper that
                                includes the first line under the title and the next one, there is a partial note and a series of
                                numbers written in pencil by someone other than Whitman. We have presented the line starting "What clue" with a gray background because it
                                has been crossed out with two vertical lines in the original manuscript.</head>
                        <figDesc>Figure 9: Verso image, manuscript draft of “You Tides With
                            Ceaseless Swell,” constructed out of a series of letters sent to
                            Whitman. Courtesy of Walt Whitman House, Camden, NJ.</figDesc>
                        <graphic url="images/essay.grayprice.10.jpg" />
                    </figure>


<!--I don't know what to do with this--><!--<quote> <lg>
                    <l><hi rend="underline">You tides with ceaseless swell</hi></l>
                    <l><hi rend="underline">and ebb.</hi></l>
                    <l>You<ptr target="#note37" xml:id="nr37" n="37"
                         /> tides with ceaseless
                                swell and</l>
                    <l>ebb! you <add place="supralinear" type="unmarked">power</add> <del
                        type="overstrike">law</del> that does this work!</l>
                    <l>You <del type="overstrike">unseen</del> <add place="supralinear"
                        type="unmarked">unseen</add> force, centripetal, centrifugal,</l>
                    <l>through space’s spread <add place="supralinear" type="insertion"
                        >entire!</add> ! <del type="overstrike">you systole</del></l>
                    <l><del type="overstrike">diastole!</del></l>
                    <l><del type="overstrike">What</del> <add place="supralinear" type="unmarked"
                        ><del type="overstrike">Take</del></add> <add type="insertion"
                        place="supralinear"
                        >your</add>
                                intermutual <add
                        place="supralinear" type="unmarked"><del type="overstrike"
                        >unseen</del></add> chains of</l>
                    <l>sun, <del type="overstrike">and</del> moon, <del type="overstrike"
                        >and</del> earth, and</l>
                    <l>all the <add place="supralinear" type="unmarked"><del type="overstrike"
                        >brother worlds of space?</del></add> <del type="overstrike"
                        >myriad stars?</del> constellations?</l>
                    <l>What <add place="supralinear" type="insertion"><del type="overstrike"
                        >are the</del> are the</add> messages by <add place="supralinear"
                        type="unmarked"><unclear>[law?]</unclear>of</add> <del type="overstrike"
                        >you</del> <add place="supralinear" type="unmarked"><del type="overstrike"
                        >? it you</del></add> <del type="overstrike"
                        >it</del>,
                                from</l>
                    <l>distant <del type="overstrike">worlds</del> <add place="supralinear"
                        type="unmarked">stars</add>, to us <add place="supralinear" type="insertion"
                        >through you?</add> ? What</l>
                    <l>Sirius’? What Capella’s?</l>
                    <l>What <add place="supralinear" type="insertion"><del type="overstrike"
                        >strong</del> central</add> heart <add place="supralinear" type="insertion"
                        ><del type="overstrike">within—</del></add> —and you the <add
                        place="supralinear" type="unmarked"><del type="overstrike"
                        >beating</del></add> pulse <add place="supralinear" type="unmarked"><del
                        type="overstrike"
                        >sent
                                forth—</del></add> —</l>
                    <l>vivifies all? What boundless</l>
                    <l>clue? aggregate of <add place="supralinear" type="insertion"
                        >and clue to all</add> all <add place="supralinear" type="insertion"
                        >in you</add> ? <del type="overstrike"
                        >[illegible] and
                                seen?</del></l>
                    <l>What clue to <del type="overstrike">all the</del> <add place="supralinear"
                        type="unmarked">every</add> force that</l>
                    <l>acts through <add place="supralinear" type="insertion"><del
                        rend="stirkethrough">limitless</del></add> space <add place="supralinear"
                        type="insertion">spread <del type="overstrike">of—</del></add> <del
                        type="overstrike">entire</del>—centripetal,</l>
                    <l>centrifugal?<ptr target="#note38" xml:id="nr38" n="38" /></l>
                    <l>What <del type="overstrike">liquid</del> <add place="supralinear"
                        type="unmarked">subtle</add> [illegible] indirection</l>
                    <l>and significance <add place="supralinear" type="unmarked"
                        >in you?</add> ? What fluid</l>
                    <l><add place="supralinear" type="insertion"><del type="overstrike"
                        >liquid subtle</del></add>vast identity,</l>
                    <l>Holding the universe <del type="overstrike">entire</del> <add
                        place="supralinear" type="unmarked">as</add> <del type="overstrike"
                        >and</del> one</l>
                    <l>—as sailing in a ship?<ptr target="#note39" xml:id="nr39" n="39" /></l>
                    </lg>
                    </quote>--> It is difficult to tell what the original order of the lines was, in
                    part because additional pieces of paper have been pasted on top of the letter
                    fragments used to form the bottom layer. In any event, it seems clear that the
                    first two lines&#8212;beginning with “You”&#8212;have been added later, in
                    pencil, pasted to the top of the rest of the manuscript on top of the original
                    first two lines, which like the rest of the manuscript were written in ink.
                    Further corrections have been made in purple pencil. To form the foundation for
                    the clipped lines, the letter from Hinton was cut into two pieces, and the
                    letter from Sewell pasted in between.<ptr
                    target="#note37" xml:id="nr37" n="37" /></p>
                <p>Sill has made a case for the interpretive importance of this reordering, which
                    resituates the subject of the line beginning with the word “holding” and
                    demonstrates Whitman’s close attention to the structure and prosody of his
                    lines. Another case could be made for the interpretive importance of the
                    ostensibly unrelated base materials used in Whitman’s late-life poetic
                    “collage.” Reading this poetry manuscript in relation to its material features
                    highlights its multi-generic, multi-temporal, and multidimensional
                    characteristics. Whitman had shuffled poetic lines as early as the very
                    beginning of his work as a poet, putting clipped subjects or lines in an
                    envelope or on a string and flipping them around until he was satisfied with the
                        order.<ptr
                    target="#note38" xml:id="nr38" n="38"
                     /> In his later, less mobile
                    years, this shuffling drew on the paper that surrounded him, and so letters sent
                    to him became part of his poetic constructions, recycled but not thoroughly
                    composted, visible still at least in part in the artifacts that are his poems,
                    prose, and notes toward essays, letters, and lectures. His final product here
                    reveals a temporal and material conjunction: decades-old letters are joined to
                    pieces of recent letters to form the foundation for a new composition. In the
                    case at hand, the poem has a striking resonance with its material manifestation.
                    Like the tides with “ceaseless swell and ebb,” the poet revises, acting as
                    “unseen force, centripetal, centrifugal,” pasting together a chain not in this
                    case of “sun, moon, earth, and all the constellations,” but rather of
                    near-to-hand letters, creating a new archive out of the old one that surrounds
                    him.</p>
                <p>While the content of the letters does not inform the poetry in obvious ways, it
                    does suggest the resonance of the letters as the base materials out of which the
                    poetry is wrought. Brought together to form the physical foundation for
                    Whitman’s poetry manuscript, these letters represent an intriguing cross-section
                    of nineteenth-century society. The partial letter from Sewell, a railroad
                    official, former Union general, and U.S. senator from New Jersey, reads like a
                    form letter, probably sending Whitman his annual pass to the West Jersey
                    Railroad, of which Sewell was then vice president. The letter from Hinton, a
                    journalist who met Whitman in the hospitals during the Civil War, alerts Whitman
                    to an article about the poet published in the <hi
                    rend="italic"
                    >Springfield
                        Republican</hi>. The letter from Reid, editor of the <hi
                    rend="italic"
                    >New
                        York Tribune</hi>, who, like Hinton, first met Whitman in the hospitals
                    during the Civil War, is difficult to decipher but seems to forward a check and
                    to thank Whitman for sending him a volume. These letters are practical
                    transactions that navigate major nineteenth-century industries&#8212;railroads,
                    newspapers&#8212;speaking to the poet’s transportation, publication, and
                    distribution practices, all now quite literally constituent of his poetic
                    composition practices. The world becomes the word. In pasting the letters
                    together, the poet mimics the tides in acting as “boundless aggregate,” with
                    scissors and glue “holding the universe as one.” He makes the written words and
                    voices of his correspondents integral parts of his poetic
                    project&#8212;physically, of course, but also intellectually, serving as they do
                    as evidence of the everyday concerns out of which he wove his poetry. Letters,
                    litter, and verse are all but inseparable.</p>
                <p>Again, it goes without saying that this practice of Whitman’s, fascinating though
                    it may be for contemplating his methods and materials of poetic composition,
                    complicates the project of editing his correspondence. Here, as in the case of
                    the Symonds draft, the letters used in the construction of the manuscript have
                    been reduced to fragments. Sender, recipient, and date have been removed in one
                    case. This object involves a total of five authors, writing in five different
                    hands and at least two genres on multiple scraps of paper spanning almost
                    fifteen years. In a number of provocative ways, this object contains multitudes.
                    The challenge becomes how to represent this object as a number of different,
                    mutually informing things&#8212;letters, litter, poetry&#8212;while facilitating
                    the user’s access to it through multiple channels and across multiple forms of
                    display. At stake is the “subtle indirection and significance” of such
                    documents&#8212;the ways in which seemingly disparate items, assembled through
                    cutting, pasting, and repurposing, might speak to each other and to Whitman’s
                    composition practices more generally, and how we can leverage our own processes
                    of representing them on the <hi
                    rend="italic"
                    >Whitman Archive</hi> so that such
                    meanings become accessible or at least do not get lost in remediation.</p>
            </div>
            <div type="section">
                <head type="main">Letters and their Editors</head>
                <p>In editing, as in letter writing, one engages a set of people as well as a set of
                    conventions. In the case of letter writing, as Whitman’s correspondence
                    demonstrates, those people can be contemporaries, a larger public, or imagined
                    audiences of the future. The engagement can take many forms, to which drafts and
                    material characteristics sometimes offer clues: intimacy, adulation, studied
                    nonchalance&#8212;even destruction and reconstruction, as Whitman’s repurposing
                    suggests. Twentieth-century editorial practice, which in the field of literature
                    developed with a strong sense of the significance of authorial intention and the
                    literary canon, as well as the necessity of working within the constraints of
                    print, would almost certainly have privileged the poetry manuscript part of “You
                    tides with ceaseless swell and ebb.” If the <hi
                    rend="italic"
                    >Collected Writings
                        of Walt Whitman</hi> had dealt with Whitman’s poetry manuscripts, as was the
                    original intention, the letters on the back of this manuscript would have
                    warranted a footnote; perhaps a facsimile image would even have been included,
                    because the materiality of this document has interesting implications for
                    Whitman’s composition practices and the structure of this poem. More challenging
                    may have been the question of what would have happened had the <hi
                    rend="italic"
                    >Collected Writings</hi> included incoming in addition to outgoing
                    correspondence. Would these incoming letters, partial, cut up, and repurposed,
                    have been included in a printed collection of Whitman’s correspondence? Every
                    correspondence project makes decisions about what constitutes a letter, in the
                    face of any number of ambiguities. That so few discussions of Whitman’s draft of
                    his 1890 letter to Symonds mention that it was pasted together out of other
                    things partly results from previous editorial treatment: Edwin Haviland Miller,
                    working within the constraints of a printed volume, did not provide a facsimile
                    of the letter, nor did he mention the materials out of which it was made, and he
                    limited his transcription of it to the text on the recto.<ptr
                    target="#note39" xml:id="nr39" n="39" /></p>
                <p>In treating the correspondence in a digital environment, the <hi rend="italic"
                    >Whitman Archive</hi> has benefited from editorial predecessors. The volumes
                    of outgoing Whitman correspondence compiled by Miller and supplemented by
                    Genoways have stood the test of time, representing largely accurate and
                    editorially responsible collections, and they have been invaluable resources,
                    saving <hi
                    rend="italic"
                    >Whitman Archive</hi> staff many of the headaches of
                    identifying locations of particular letters. The most apparent shortcoming of
                    those editions was something over which the editors had little control: the
                    print medium. The drawbacks of print are some of the primary limitations
                    lamented by twentieth-century editors of correspondence, and indeed there are
                    extraordinary benefits to digital collections of correspondence. These include
                    the ability to add newly discovered letters as they surface, and to put them in
                    the desired order (chronological or by correspondent, for example) rather than
                    including them in an appendix or a supplement. A digital environment also
                    affords us the space to include both incoming and outgoing letters and to render
                    enclosures in full, simplifying to some degree the process of selection by
                    expanding the bounds of publication to items that simply wouldn’t have been
                    feasible to include from the perspective of a print publisher, for whom each
                    extra page costs money.</p>
                <p>In the first section of this essay, we raised the question of what constitutes a
                    Whitman letter. From the standpoint of reading and editing in a digital
                    environment, we might ask why it matters. Restrictions of space, paper, and ink
                    no longer lend the same kind of urgency to the process of classifying and
                    selecting by genre as they did when a limited number of printed volumes could be
                    produced. On the web, given enough server space and an existing, functional
                    architecture, the number of letters to be treated can multiply quickly, and
                    anything that seems at all like a letter associated with an author could
                    conceivably be included. There are several factors that render classification
                    and selection still relevant in a digital era, however. One is the coherence and
                    navigability of the interface. Another is the structure of grant applications
                    for the letters (organized in the case of the <hi
                    rend="italic"
                    >Whitman
                        Archive</hi>, for instance, by era), which can determine publication insofar
                    as which letters appear first, and which (like undated letters) seem likely to
                    wait until the end of the project. And it is perhaps worth considering that,
                    where space is no object, time begins to loom large: waiting until the end of a
                    complete edition of Whitman’s incoming and outgoing correspondence is wait
                    enough; waiting until the end of an edition of <hi
                    rend="italic"
                    >all</hi>
                    Whitman’s writings, including the correspondence, may well be an endless
                        proposition.<ptr
                    target="#note40" xml:id="nr40" n="40" /></p>
                <p>In keeping with the loosely genre-based editorial practice we have developed for
                    the <hi
                    rend="italic">Whitman Archive</hi>, the documents published on the <hi
                    rend="italic"
                    >Archive</hi> have been sorted into categories, including
                    “Books by Whitman,” “Manuscripts,” “Notebooks,” and “Letters.” Genre lends one
                    form of coherence to a project, offering limitations, direction, and selection
                    criteria for work designed to meet a particular goal or to specify the
                    obligations associated with grant funding. As a result, <hi
                    rend="italic"
                    >Whitman Archive</hi> grant proposals have also often been organized by
                    genre or chronology (or both). Early grant applications submitted by the <hi
                    rend="italic"
                    >Archive</hi> focused on poetry manuscripts. More recently, the
                        <hi
                    rend="italic"
                    >Archive</hi> has been awarded grants devoted to
                    digitizing, cataloging, and editing prose manuscripts, fiction, journalism,
                    marginalia, and correspondence. But the examples discussed in this essay, and
                    many other such cases, have continuously presented a challenge, because genre
                    distinctions are themselves sometimes fuzzy, and individual documents may be
                    multi-generic in nature. Preserving the “subtle indirection” of the documents,
                    the messiness as well as the order, may require thinking differently about
                    genre, and instating documents within their longer and sometimes whimsical
                    histories.</p>
                <p>The archival objects discussed in this essay fit into a category of
                    correspondence, but many of them also fit comfortably into other
                    categories&#8212;poetry manuscript, published book, printed poetry, note. These
                    documents resist efforts to sort and silo by genre. Correspondence draws
                    attention to the centrality of sociability, intimacy, and connection, even as it
                    also points to publicity and mediation. Without the image of Whitman’s room in
                    Camden, it is more difficult to understand objects like the Symonds letter and
                    the “You Tides” manuscript, constructed by the poet out of the papers that
                    surrounded and at times seemed to engulf him. Without Traubel’s careful accounts
                    of his conversations with Whitman in <hi
                    rend="italic"
                    >With Walt Whitman in
                        Camden</hi>, most of Whitman’s commentary about the letters he sent and
                    received would be lacking. An advantage and a challenge of working on the <hi
                    rend="italic"
                    >Whitman Archive</hi> is that, whatever limited intentions we
                    may have had when we set out to edit a set of documents like Whitman’s
                    correspondence, we have ended up thinking much more broadly about the range of
                    documents that comprise an author-centered digital archive, and that test its
                    boundaries and coherence.</p>
                <p>As the <hi rend="italic"
                    >Archive</hi> expands, it becomes increasingly clear how
                    difficult much of Whitman’s archive is to categorize definitively. One way we
                    plan to respond to this challenge is to move toward an interface or user
                    experience that is predicated on users’ questions or searches and that allows
                    for a single object to appear in multiple sections or categories. Another way
                    forward is to think about ways to create and optimize a system of relations,
                    representing the fact that a letter can also be a poetry manuscript, as well as
                    several other letters, or to represent the publication and revision history of a
                    document, showing, for instance, that a fragment that seems like a letter could
                    point both to a draft letter, from which it has been excised, and to one of the
                    earliest edited collections of Whitman’s correspondence. Editors of the past
                    have often focused on specific items or collections of items, or on specific
                    authors; objects like the ones discussed here encourage us to think instead
                    about ongoing, transformative connections between items and authors, between
                    authors and their friends and family, and between authors and editors. Such
                    links remind us that any given item did not exist in isolation, and that a long
                    history of editing continues to affect how documents are read and re-edited in
                    different media.</p>
                <p>Editions of correspondence are themselves a genre of sorts, with their own
                    conventions, forms, purposes, and expectations. Whitman’s correspondence on the
                        <hi
                    rend="italic"
                    >Whitman Archive</hi> is, ultimately, an editorial
                    palimpsest. It, too, is an act of reconstruction. We draw heavily on and update
                    the notes and the transcriptions produced by Miller and Genoways, but we also
                    derive transcriptions from nearly all the many editions of letters to and from
                    Whitman that have been published since the nineteenth century. Like Whitman, we
                    have recycled and remediated, and like him we hope to push back against the
                    apparent rigidity of category and transform how users experience these objects
                    by creating new pathways for them to quickly shift contexts, locating items in
                    different parts of the <hi
                    rend="italic"
                    >Archive</hi> by clicking from one
                    letter to another, pulling up the digital images or our encoding, accessing
                    encyclopedia entries about particular correspondents, or navigating to the
                    version of a letter that appears in <hi
                    rend="italic"
                    >With Walt Whitman in
                        Camden</hi>. But we also intend with our reproductions of these materials to
                    extend into the future the many forms of sociability enacted by the letters,
                    inviting others to reproduce our transcriptions and the interpretations to which
                    they give rise, using the TEI encoding and other data we have created to pursue
                    still more pathways, continuing to compost and participate in the centripetal
                    and centrifugal force that is historical research and discovery.</p>
            </div>
            <div type="section">
                <head type="main">The Whitman Archive of the Future</head>
                <p>In 1888 Whitman said to Traubel, “I suppose I have done a lot less general
                    letter-writing than most men&#8212;I was not a voluminous letter writer—when I
                    wrote at all it was mainly with a very definite notion of something very
                    practical that needed to be said. . . . nothing ever came to me in a hurry: even
                    my storms came taking their time.”<ptr
                    target="#note41" xml:id="nr41" n="41"
                     />
                    Later he would remark that he was “not ‘a correspondent by nature.’”<ptr
                    target="#note42" xml:id="nr42" n="42"
                     /> While Whitman was a less
                    “voluminous” correspondent than some writers, this comment does not account for
                    those who wrote to him; we have identified over 3,000 incoming and outgoing
                    letters from 1860 to 1887 alone, ranging from postal cards to sixteen-page
                    effusions, and we expect to add many more as we embark on editing Whitman’s
                    early and late-life correspondence.</p>
                <p>McGann has called editing a creative act, and so it is&#8212;but it is also a
                    political act, with its own long history. One important feature of our work on
                    Whitman’s correspondence is that, despite the continued exertion of a
                    gravitational pull by Whitman, the incoming letters introduce a range of new
                    voices and hands to the <hi
                    rend="italic"
                    >Whitman Archive</hi>. Readers now can
                    experience the volubility and intensity of William D. O’Connor, bent on
                    identifying and reckoning with those who would attack or censor Whitman’s <hi
                    rend="italic"
                    >Leaves of Grass</hi>. They can read the thoughtful and
                    engaging letters of Whitman’s close friend and English admirer Anne Gilchrist.
                    They can peruse the reflections of Alabama farmer and philosopher John Newton
                    Johnson, who had a lengthy correspondence with Whitman and came to visit him in
                    Camden in 1887, or they can explore the connection between Whitman and various
                    friends, acquaintances, and admirers from all over the world.</p>
                <p>Editing Whitman’s correspondence for publication on the <hi rend="italic"
                    >Whitman
                        Archive</hi> turns us back to our working definition of correspondence, but
                    it also, perhaps more importantly, prompts us to consider what digitization
                    allows and requires of editors of archival materials. In one vision of the
                    future, the <hi
                    rend="italic"
                    >Whitman Archive</hi> would represent the overlap
                    between nineteenth-century (composition, revision, and archival) practices and
                    twenty-first century (editorial) practices as part of the editorial product,
                    that is, the documents that appear on the <hi
                    rend="italic"
                    >Whitman
                    Archive</hi>. These practices might be represented in how such objects are
                    defined and explained, how they are related to other documents on the <hi
                    rend="italic"
                    >Archive</hi>, and how they are navigated within the broader
                    structure of the site. The evolution in the treatment of documents by the <hi
                    rend="italic"
                    >Whitman Archive</hi> over time is moving toward an emphasis on
                    the extent to which many of these objects defy the apparent order of categories
                    of genre and question the neat hierarchy of TEI/XML tags that helps to enforce
                    that order by marking distinctions between handwriting and print, poetic line
                    and paragraph. As the digital humanities continues to work on the forms of
                    insight that can result from interpreting documents as data, the acts of
                    qualifying the apparent order of the machine-readable text and emphasizing the
                    messiness&#8212;and unpredictability, complexity, and creativity&#8212;of
                    writing and editing (and being human) become ever more pressing.</p>
                <p>As we confront the piles that were once in Whitman’s room in Camden and reorder
                    them in digital space, one way of honoring the messiness in the new medium is by
                    multiplying the representations. We have begun to move in this direction by
                    offering multiple views of a document, including facsimile images, searchable
                    transcriptions, and a view of the XML encoding. Another way is by encouraging an
                    understanding of documents and texts in relation to other documents, texts, and
                    conversations, as Traubel’s <hi
                    rend="italic"
                    >With Walt Whitman in Camden</hi>
                    insisted on doing. It may be that the seemingly marginal conjunctions of
                    editorial phenomena and oral and documentary history represented by Traubel’s
                    notes on Whitman’s letters, signaling the replication of the archive in more
                    than one place, offers a productive model for thinking about how to edit Whitman
                    documents in digital space. In the end, the <hi
                    rend="italic"
                    >Whitman
                        Archive</hi> hopes to create a richer environment for scholars, balancing
                    the project of making sense of Whitman’s archive and of thinking about our own
                    desires to make sense of the digital archive, and looking for opportunities to
                    further expand access to Whitman-related documents by creating multiple avenues
                    for users to explore the transforming and transformative relationships between
                    letters, litter, and literature.</p>
            </div>
        </body>
        <back>
            <div type="notes">
                <note xml:id="note1">Horace Traubel, <hi rend="italic"
                    >With Walt Whitman in
                        Camden</hi>, 9 vols. (various publishers, 1906–96), 1:42–43. Subsequent
                    references will be abbreviated <hi
                    rend="italic">WWWC</hi>.</note>
                <note xml:id="note2"
                    >Whitman first moved to Camden, NJ, to live with his brother
                    George in 1873 after suffering a stroke that left him partially disabled on his
                    left side. When George retired and moved outside Camden in 1884, Whitman elected
                    to stay and purchase his own house on Mickle Street, where he lived until his
                    death in 1892.</note>
                <note xml:id="note3">“Genre,” def. 1b, <hi rend="italic"
                    >The Oxford English
                        Dictionary</hi>, 2nd ed., 1989. Catalogs and finding aids of physical
                    archives often divide materials by genre, separating, for instance,
                    correspondence from manuscript material, and often including cross-reference
                    sheets in cases of documents that fit both categories.</note>
                <note xml:id="note4">On the <hi rend="italic"
                    >Whitman Archive</hi> we generally
                    offer the user an option to sort by date within a section organized by
                    genre.</note>
                <note xml:id="note5"
                    >As Ed Folsom has written, Whitman “had an ongoing battle with
                    genre,” asserting in titles and elsewhere that the units of text in <hi
                    rend="italic"
                    >Leaves of Grass</hi> were poems, but pushing the boundaries of
                    that designation. “Database as Genre: The Epic Transformation of Archives,” <hi
                    rend="italic"
                    >PMLA</hi> 122, no. 5 (October 2007): 1572. Whitman also
                    experimented in books like <hi
                    rend="italic"
                    >Two Rivulets</hi> with the
                    juxtaposition of prose and verse and the provocation to the reader produced by
                    the structural and semantic relationships between the two.</note>
                <note xml:id="note6"
                    >For a discussion of the development and increasingly widespread
                    use of the post in nineteenth-century America, as well as what he refers to as
                    “a diffuse culture of the post,” see David Henkin, <hi
                    rend="italic"
                    >The Postal
                        Age</hi> (Chicago: University of Chicago Press, 2006), 5.</note>
                <note xml:id="note7"
                    >Whitman misspelled Irvin’s name as “Irwin.” These larger prose
                    works were republished as part of <hi
                    rend="italic"
                    >The Complete Writings of
                        Walt Whitman</hi> (New York: G. P. Putnam’s Sons, 1902), 10 vols. The letter
                    about Irwin/Irvin was extracted from <hi
                    rend="italic"
                    >The Complete
                        Writings</hi> and treated as a letter by Edwin Haviland Miller in his
                    editing of Whitman’s correspondence.</note>
                <note xml:id="note8"
                    >It is also an old question, frequently asked: for an entire
                    volume of essays devoted in one way or another to this topic and many others
                    related to editing correspondence, see <hi
                    rend="italic"
                    >Editing Correspondence:
                        Papers Given at the Fourteenth Annual Conference on Editorial Problems,
                        University of Toronto, 3–4 November 1978</hi>, ed. J. A. Dainard (New York:
                    Garland, 1979).</note>
                <note xml:id="note9"
                    >The timing of publication has largely to do with grant funding.
                    Many <hi
                    rend="italic"
                    >Whitman Archive</hi> grant applications have been
                    organized around genre, typically in conjunction with chronology (we intend to
                    edit a particular set of documents from a specific time period). In the case of
                    the correspondence, for instance, support from the National Historical
                    Publications and Records Commission has allowed us to publish Whitman’s Civil
                    War, Reconstruction, and post-Reconstruction correspondence in a series of
                    grant-funded projects over the past seven years. Different grant projects have
                    been completed at different times, at different stages of technical
                    development&#8212;we are currently in the process of converting the files that
                    constitute many individual sections of the <hi
                    rend="italic"
                    >Whitman
                        Archive</hi> to the most recent P5 version of the TEI encoding
                    guidelines&#8212;so genre becomes one determining factor for where on the <hi
                    rend="italic"
                    >Archive</hi> a document is found, how it is encoded, and how
                    it is displayed.</note>
                <note xml:id="note10"
                    >Our editorial policy for the letters states that we, in this
                    first publication pass, are not transcribing and encoding deletions, although we
                    do often include scans of the original documents so that users have access to
                    revisions, deletions, and other features that are not represented in the
                    encoding or transcription. We intend to go back and transcribe and encode
                    revisions once all the letters are published. Our current treatment of
                    correspondence has differed from the way we have treated Whitman’s notebooks and
                    poetry manuscripts, for instance, for which we have been transcribing, encoding,
                    and displaying additions and deletions.</note>
                <note xml:id="note11">"Database, Interface, and Archival Fever,” <hi rend="italic"
                    >PMLA</hi> 122, no. 5 (October 2007): 1589.</note>
                <note xml:id="note12"
                    >One is reminded by this pairing of Mark Twain’s banquet speech
                    on “littery” men, a burlesque of Ralph Waldo Emerson, Henry Wadsworth
                    Longfellow, and Oliver Wendell Holmes, detailed in Richard S. Lowry’s <hi
                    rend="italic"
                    >“Littery Man”: Mark Twain and Modern Authorship</hi> (New
                    York: Oxford University Press, 1996), 24–33.</note>
                <note xml:id="note13"
                    >Edward Vanhoutte and Ron Van den Branden, “Describing,
                    Transcribing, Encoding, and Editing Modern Correspondence Material: A Textbase
                    Approach,” <hi
                    rend="italic"
                    >Literary and Linguistic Computing</hi> 24, no. 1
                    (2009): 84; written in 2002 and as qtd. in “Presentational and Representational
                    Issues in Correspondence Reconstruction and Sorting,” <hi
                    rend="italic"
                    >Literary
                        and Linguistic Computing</hi> 19, no. 1 (2004): 45–54.</note>
                <note xml:id="note14"
                    >See for instance Mark Twain, whose “Ashcroft-Lyon Manuscript”
                    has prompted Amanda Gagel’s meditation on editing and the definition of
                    correspondence in a recent issue of <hi
                    rend="italic"
                    >Scholarly Editing</hi>.
                    The Ashcroft-Lyon Manuscript, ostensibly a letter to William Dean Howells
                    consisting of several hundred pages, was unsent and unpublished. The Mark Twain
                    Project is currently editing the manuscript. See “Letters as Critical Texts,”
                        <hi
                    rend="italic">Scholarly Editing</hi> 36 (2015): 1–20.</note>
                <note xml:id="note15">See <hi rend="italic"
                    >Calamus: A Series of Letters Written
                        During the Years 1868–1880 by Walt Whitman to a Young Friend (Peter
                        Doyle)</hi>, ed. Richard Maurice Bucke (Boston: Small, Maynard,
                    1897).</note>
                <note xml:id="note16">Bucke, <hi rend="italic"
                    >Calamus</hi>, 18. For other examples
                    of such collections, see Thomas B. Harned’s <hi
                    rend="italic"
                    >The Letters of
                        Anne Gilchrist and Walt Whitman</hi> (1918); Clara Barrus’s <hi
                    rend="italic">Whitman and Burroughs: Comrades</hi> (1931); Horst Frenz’s <hi
                    rend="italic"
                    >Whitman and Rolleston: A Correspondence</hi> (1951); Artem
                    Lozynsky’s <hi
                    rend="italic"
                    >The Letters of Dr. Richard Maurice Bucke to Walt
                        Whitman</hi> (1977); and Wesley Raabe’s <ref
                    type="url"
                    target="http://www.whitmanarchive.org/biography/correspondence/lvvwintro.html"
                    ><hi rend="italic"
                    >“walter dear”: The Letters from Louisa Van Velsor
                            Whitman to Her Son Walt</hi></ref>, published on the <hi
                    rend="italic">Whitman Archive</hi> (2014). Thomas Donaldson’s <hi rend="italic"
                    >Walt
                        Whitman the Man</hi> (1896) also features a number of transcriptions and
                    facsimiles of letters, as well as other manuscripts.</note>
                <note xml:id="note17"
                    >The draft letter matches Bucke’s transcription in most other
                    particulars. There is no indication in the volume of whether the letter is a
                    draft.</note>
                <note xml:id="note18">See <hi rend="italic"
                    >The Complete Writings of Walt
                        Whitman</hi>, 5:31.</note>
                <note xml:id="note19"
                    >See the letter from W. I. Whiting to Walt Whitman of June 14,
                    1886, which Whitman forwarded to the <hi
                    rend="italic">Critic</hi> on <ref type="url"
                    target="http://www.whitmanarchive.org/biography/correspondence/tei/loc.05961.html"
                    >June 17</ref> for publication as an “item” in that magazine. In the letter,
                    Whiting wrote that “at a sale of Autographs &amp; Books a few days ago” an
                    autograph letter from Whitman had sold for eighty dollars and a first edition
                        <hi
                    rend="italic"
                    >Leaves of Grass</hi> for ten dollars, which Whiting noted
                    was “the highest paid for any similar lots.” Charles E. Feinberg Collection,
                    Library of Congress, Washington, DC. Whitman also destroyed letters,
                    particularly after his stroke, when he was concerned about his health and
                    fearful that death might be imminent. Miller, <hi
                    rend="italic">The
                        Correspondence</hi>, 2:7.</note>
                <note xml:id="note20"
                    >This is frequently the case: Whitman, after years as a
                    copyist, seems to have adopted the habit of writing drafts of letters and then
                    copying them and sending the final copy but retaining the draft, so we very
                    often only have Whitman’s draft of a letter.</note>
                <note xml:id="note21"
                    >Symonds, an English biographer, critic, and poet, was “a
                    writer of homoerotic poetry and a pioneer in the study of homosexuality.” Andrew
                    C. Higgins, “Symonds, John Addington (1840–1893),” in <hi
                    rend="italic"
                    >Walt
                        Whitman: An Encyclopedia</hi> (New York: Garland Publishing, 1998), 701–2.
                    Symonds, who later published a biography of Whitman, had asked the poet directly
                    about homosexuality in the “Calamus” poems in an August 1890 letter: “In your
                    conception of Comradeship, do you contemplate the possible intrusion of those
                    semi-sexual emotions &amp; actions which no doubt do occur between men? . . . I
                    should much like to know whether <hi
                    rend="italic"
                    >you are prepared to leave
                        them to the inclinations &amp; the conscience of the individuals
                        concerned?</hi> . . . I agree with the objections I have mentioned that,
                    human nature being what it is, &amp; some men having a strong natural bias
                    toward persons of their own sex, the enthusiasm of ‘Calamus’ is calculated to
                    encourage ardent &amp; <hi
                    rend="italic"
                    >physical</hi> intimacies. But I do not
                    agree with them in thinking that such a result would absolutely be prejudicial
                    to social interests.” Qtd. in Miller, <hi
                    rend="italic"
                    >The Correspondence</hi>,
                    5:72. Because we have not yet systematically published letters after 1887, these
                    letters are not yet available on the <hi
                    rend="italic">Whitman
                    Archive</hi>.</note>
                <note xml:id="note22">Miller, <hi rend="italic"
                    >The Correspondence</hi>, 5:73n18. Of
                    course it is impossible to prove conclusively that Whitman had no children, but
                    scholars have agreed that his claims in this letter were more likely defensive
                    than factual. David Reynolds, for instance, calls the statement about fathering
                    six children “an obvious prevarication” in <hi
                    rend="italic"
                    >Walt Whitman’s
                        America</hi> (New York: Vintage Books, 1995), 28.</note>
                <note xml:id="note23"
                    >Whitman often expressed doubts about carefully crafted and
                    refined literary letters&#8212;in his view, these suffered from a lack of
                    vitality and even a deceptiveness. He much preferred unpretentious messages such
                    as those “from sailors&#8212;stumbling, tumbling: yet full to the full of
                    expression and force” (<hi
                    rend="italic"
                    >WWWC</hi>, 6:184). Yet Whitman’s
                    reliance on drafts and intensive revision in his own letters points to the
                    (understandable) gap between his professed values and his working practice. As
                    Miller notes in his introduction to the <hi
                    rend="italic"
                    >Correspondence</hi>,
                    Whitman “was not so impulsive or spontaneous in his correspondence as he
                    implied” (1:3).</note>
                <note xml:id="note24"
                    >M. Jimmie Killingsworth notes some of the probable differences
                    between this draft and the letter that was sent to Symonds, drawing on Symonds’s
                    quotation of Whitman in a later letter to Edward Carpenter, in which Symonds
                    writes: “He rambles on about being less ‘restrained’ by temperament &amp; theory
                    than I (J. A. S.) am&#8212;‘I at moments let the spirit impulse (female) rage
                    its utmost wildest damnedest (I feel I do sometimes in L. of G. &amp; I do
                    so).’” <hi
                    rend="italic"
                    >Whitman’s Poetry of the Body: Sexuality, Politics, and
                        the Text</hi> (Chapel Hill: University of North Carolina Press, 1991), 172.
                    In the draft, Whitman wrote: “I know that while I have a horror of ranting &amp;
                    bawling, I at certain moments let the spirit, impulse, (? demon) rage its
                    utmost, its wildest, damnedest—(I feel to do so in my L of G, &amp; I do
                    so).”</note>
                <note xml:id="note25"
                    >Traubel does not include a transcription of the letter from
                    Symonds inquiring about “Calamus” in his notes in <hi
                    rend="italic"
                    >With Walt
                        Whitman in Camden</hi>, a significant omission. He does include the
                    following description of Whitman reading the letter, however: “Then W. started
                    to read the letter again, and suddenly his face paled in the strangest way and
                    he laid the letter down and said, ‘I talked with him too long: it has tired me
                    out.’ I stayed till he had recovered himself somewhat—told him he could speak of
                    it again&#8212;then left” (<hi
                    rend="italic">WWWC</hi>, 7:67).</note>
                <note xml:id="note26"
                    >The letter that arrived in this envelope has not been located,
                    nor is it listed among the “incoming letters” in the seventh volume of <hi
                    rend="italic"
                    >Walt Whitman: The Correspondence</hi>, ed. Ted Genoways (Iowa
                    City: University of Iowa Press, 2004).</note>
                <note xml:id="note27"
                    >For a discussion of Whitman’s response letter, which she
                    interprets as an expression of dissatisfaction with the genre of letter writing
                    as a mode of intimacy that (in its exclusivity) imposes hierarchy and resists a
                    more universal connection, see Elizabeth Hewitt, <hi
                    rend="italic"
                    >Correspondence and American Literature, 1770–1865</hi> (New York: Cambridge
                    University Press, 2004), 179–81. Ed Folsom also discusses Whitman’s publication
                    of this letter in conjunction with his own “epistolary poetry” in an article
                    titled “Co-Responding with Whitman,” in <hi
                    rend="italic"
                    >Companion to
                        Nineteenth-Century American Letters and Letter-Writing</hi>, ed.
                    Celeste-Marie Bernier, Judith Newman, and Matthew Pethers (Edinburgh: Edinburgh
                    University Press, forthcoming).</note>
                <note xml:id="note28">Walt Whitman, <hi rend="italic"
                    >Leaves of Grass</hi>
                    (Brooklyn, NY: n.p., 1856), 346. Wordsworth, interestingly, also invoked the
                    genre of the letter in publication of <hi
                    rend="italic"
                    >The Prelude</hi>, which
                    Gary Schmidgall notes was addressed to Coleridge “as if it were one massive
                    epistle: ‘O Friend! O Poet! brother of my soul.’” <hi
                    rend="italic"
                    >Containing
                        Multitudes: Walt Whitman and the British Literary Tradition</hi> (New York:
                    Oxford University Press, 2014), 243.</note>
                <note xml:id="note29"> See, for example, this passage from <hi rend="italic"
                    >With
                        Walt Whitman in Camden</hi>: “There were two [Bram] Stoker letters and the
                    draft of a letter from W. acknowledging them. ‘It’s a rather long story,’ I
                    said: ‘there are several chapters to it.’ I also asked him: ‘Did you read them
                    over today when you found them?’ He said: ‘No: I left that job for you: I
                    haven’t read them since they came in ’76: when I sit here, when you read to me,
                    when I have nothing to do but listen, I feel composed, at peace, more than
                    usually impressionable: I take things in without any effort,
                    then&#8212;moreover, retain them.’ I said: ‘I am willing enough to read.’ W.:
                    ‘You see&#8212;there’s method in my laziness: I’m doing the best I can in the
                    littlest ways as well as the biggest to conserve the few dribbles of vitality
                    that are left to me’” (<hi
                    rend="italic">WWWC</hi>, 4:179).</note>
                <note xml:id="note30">As Miller points out in his preface to <hi rend="italic"
                    >The
                        Correspondence</hi> (1:vii), Whitman’s literary executors (Traubel, Bucke,
                    and Thomas Harned) were the first to publish selections of his correspondence in
                    volumes like In <hi
                    rend="italic"
                    >Re Walt Whitman</hi> (Philadelphia: David
                    McKay, 1893), <hi
                    rend="italic"
                    >The Wound Dresser</hi> (Boston: Small, Maynard
                    &amp; Company, 1898), and <hi
                    rend="italic">Calamus</hi>.</note>
                <note xml:id="note31"><hi rend="italic">WWWC</hi>, 4:42.</note>
                <note xml:id="note32"
                    >Miller praises the executors for their efforts but also gently
                    notes in passing some of the shortcomings of Traubel’s transcriptions, which,
                    like many of the early publications of Whitman’s correspondence, was a “labor of
                    love” that suffered from “the absence of a consistent editorial procedure, the
                    occasionally careless transcription, the omission of a postscript or a sentence,
                    the unindicated deletion of remarks which they considered unworthy of the man
                    they venerated” (1:viii).</note>
                <note xml:id="note33">See Matt Miller, <hi rend="italic"
                    >Collage of Myself: Walt
                        Whitman and the Making of Leaves of Grass</hi> (Lincoln: University of
                    Nebraska Press, 2010). Miller discusses this manuscript briefly on pages 124–26.
                    See also Kirsten Gruesz, <hi
                    rend="italic"
                    >Ambassadors of Culture: The
                        Transamerican Origins of Latino Writing</hi> (Princeton, NJ: Princeton
                    University Press, 2002), 128.</note>
                <note xml:id="note34"
                    >For a discussion of Whitman’s reuse of letters from autograph
                    seekers, in particular for poetry manuscripts, see Eric Conrad, “‘Anything
                    Honest to Sell Books’: Walt Whitman and the Autograph Monster,” <hi
                    rend="italic"
                    >Walt Whitman Quarterly Review</hi> 32, no. 4 (2015), 192–93.
                    Conrad notes Whitman’s comment to Traubel about autograph seekers: “those
                    fellows have one virtue&#8212;they always use good paper: and on that I manage
                    to do a good deal of my writing” (<hi
                    rend="italic"
                    >WWWC</hi>, 2:45). He also
                    points out that Whitman’s repurposing is likely, in some cases, the only reason
                    the letter survived. For several points about the ways that individual
                    collections can misrepresent the phenomenon of letter writing at a given time,
                    in that letters that are preserved may not be representative of letters as a
                    whole, see Roger Chartier, “Introduction: An Ordinary Kind of Writing: Model
                    letters and letter-writing in ancient régime France,” in <hi
                    rend="italic"
                    >Correspondence: Models of Letter-writing from the Middle Ages to the
                        Nineteenth Century</hi> (Princeton: Princeton University Press, 1997),
                    18–21. Whitman’s early reuse of paper like extra wrappers from <hi
                    rend="italic"
                    >Leaves of Grass</hi> for notes and drafts likely had to do with economy.
                    Late in his life, Whitman’s repurposing may have been more a product of his lack
                    of mobility&#8212;the stacks of papers in his room seem to have provided
                    ready-to-hand material for (re)composition.</note>
                <note xml:id="note35"
                    >‘You Tides with Ceaseless Swell’: A Reading of the
                    Manuscript,” <hi
                    rend="italic"
                    >Walt Whitman Quarterly Review</hi> 6 (Spring
                    1989): 190. Sill contends that this manuscript and several others related to the
                    “Fancies at Navesink” series illustrate that Whitman was as much if not more of
                    a poetic craftsman late in his life. Three of the letters in this manuscript
                    were used for composition, in the sense that poetry lines were drafted directly
                    on them; the fourth, the 1871 letter from Hinton, seems to have been added later
                    as a way of joining the clipped lines in a different order.</note>
                <note xml:id="note36"
                    >“You Tides With Ceaseless Swell” first appeared in print as
                    part of the “Fancies at Navesink” sequence in the “Annex” to the 1884 reprinting
                    of the 1881 edition of <hi
                    rend="italic"
                    >Leaves of Grass</hi>, and in August
                    1885 the sequence was published in <hi
                    rend="italic">Nineteenth
                    Century</hi>.</note>
                <!--<note xml:id="note37"
                    > At the top left corner of the pasted-down piece of paper that
                    includes this line and the next one, there is a partial note and a series of
                    numbers written in pencil by someone other than Whitman.</note>
                <note xml:id="note38"
                    >We have presented this line with a gray background because it
                    has been crossed out with two vertical lines in the original manuscript.</note>-->
                <note xml:id="note37"
                    >This is also the order in which the lines appeared when they
                    were published in the Annex, the <hi
                    rend="italic"
                    >Nineteenth Century</hi>, and
                    later in November Boughs (1888) and the deathbed (1891–92) edition of <hi
                    rend="italic">Leaves of Grass</hi>.</note>
                <note xml:id="note38"
                    >Sill writes that a “peek beneath the pasted-on fragment”
                    reveals the original two lines.</note>
                <note xml:id="note39"
                    >For one description of this practice, see William Sloane
                    Kennedy’s relation of Whitman’s account to Harrison S. Morris in Kennedy’s <hi
                    rend="italic"
                    >Reminiscences of Walt Whitman</hi> (London: Alexander Gardner,
                    1896), 24.</note>
                <note xml:id="note40"
                    >Miller states in his editorial policy that he does not attempt
                    a diplomatic text, making some adjustments for the sake of comprehensibility and
                    omitting deletions unless they are substantive, in which case they are presented
                    in a note. The first iteration of our treatment of correspondence on the <hi
                    rend="italic"
                    >Whitman Archive</hi> has been modeled in many ways after
                    Miller’s collection: like Miller, we provide transcriptions that silently
                    incorporate additions, exclude deletions, and maintain original spellings.
                    Unlike Miller, we are also able in many cases to provide corresponding images of
                    the original letters, thus welcoming users to improve or question our
                    transcriptions. Miller does not mention the standards he used to determine what
                    constituted a letter, other than to say that he includes “all known (and
                    available) letters, post cards, and notes” (1:15).</note>
                <note xml:id="note41">The New York University Press’s <hi rend="italic"
                    >Collected
                        Writings</hi> may be taken as an example of this: even without getting to
                    the poetry manuscripts, the set spans nearly fifty years, and countless new
                    manuscripts have emerged since the final volume was published, another
                    supplement to the correspondence, in 2004.</note>
                <note xml:id="note42"><hi rend="italic">WWWC</hi>, 1:318–19.</note>
                <note xml:id="note43"><hi rend="italic">WWWC</hi>, 6:479.</note>
            </div>
        </back>
    </text>
</TEI>
