<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
    <teiHeader xml:lang="eng">
        <fileDesc>
            <titleStmt>
                <title level="a" type="main">Editors' Introduction to the 2015 Issue of <hi
                        rend="italic">Scholarly Editing: The Annual of the Association for
                        Documentary Editing</hi>
                </title>

                <author>Amanda Gailey</author>
                <author>Andrew Jewell</author>
            </titleStmt>
            <editionStmt>
                <edition>
                    <date>2016</date>
                </edition>
            </editionStmt>
            <publicationStmt>
                <idno type="file">essay.v37intro</idno>
                <authority>Scholary Editing: The Annual of the Association for Documentary
                    Editing</authority>
                <address>
          <addrLine>http://www.scholarlyediting.org</addrLine>
        </address>
                <publisher>Association for Documentary Editing</publisher>
                <publisher>University of Nebraska&#8211;Lincoln</publisher>
                <distributor>
                    <name>Center for Digital Research in the Humanities</name>
                    <address>
            <addrLine>319 Love Library</addrLine>
            <addrLine>University of Nebraska&#8211;Lincoln</addrLine>
            <addrLine>Lincoln, NE 68588-4100</addrLine>
            <addrLine>http://cdrh.unl.edu</addrLine>
          </address>
                </distributor>
                <date>2016</date>
                <availability>
                    <p>Scholary Editing: The Annual of the Association for Documentary Editing is
                        freely distributed by the Association for Documentary Editing and the Center
                        for Digital Research in the Humanities at the University of Nebraska-Lincoln
                        and licensed under a Creative Commons Attribution-NonCommercial-ShareAlike
                        3.0 Unported License</p>
                </availability>
            </publicationStmt>
            <seriesStmt>
                <title level="j">Scholarly Editing: The Annual of the Association for Documentary
                    Editing</title>
                <respStmt>
                    <resp>editor</resp>
                    <name xml:id="aag">Amanda Gailey</name>
                </respStmt>
                <respStmt>
                    <resp>editor</resp>
                    <name xml:id="awj">Andrew Jewell</name>
                </respStmt>
                <idno type="vol">37</idno>
                <idno type="ISSN">2167-1257</idno>
            </seriesStmt>
            <sourceDesc>
                <bibl>
                    <note>Born digital.</note>
                </bibl>
            </sourceDesc>
        </fileDesc>
        <revisionDesc>
            <change when="2016-05-12" who="#aag">markup in TEI XML</change>
        </revisionDesc>
    </teiHeader>
    <text>
        <front>
            <head type="main">Editors' Introduction to the 2016 Issue of <hi rend="italic">Scholarly
                    Editing: The Annual of the Association for Documentary Editing</hi></head>
            <byline>Amanda Gailey</byline>
            <byline>Andrew Jewell</byline>

        </front>

        <body>
            <p>We are pleased to announce the fifth issue of <hi rend="italic">Scholarly Editing:
                    The Annual of the Association for Documentary Editing</hi>. This issue follows
                the historic joint conference of the Association for Documentary Editing and the
                Society for Textual Scholarship at the University of Nebraska-Lincoln in the summer
                of 2015, and includes the presidential addresses from the leaders of both
                organizations, <ref target="../../2016/essays/essay.lupton.html">John A. Lupton
                    (ADE)</ref> and <ref target="../../2016/essays/essay.schulze.html">Robin G.
                    Schulze</ref>. We are also pleased to include the keynote address written by
                    <ref target="../../2016/editions/essays/essay.mcgann.html">Jerome McGann</ref>,
                who discusses “the place of scholarship and education in our mediated and furiously
                presentist world.” Other essays in this issue include Nicole Gray’s and Kenneth M.
                Price’s <ref target="../../2016/essays/essay.grayprice.html">article about the
                    complexities of editing Whitman’s correspondence</ref>, Jude Davies’s <ref
                    target="../../2016/essays/essay.davies.html">discussion of editing
                Dreiser</ref>, and Hannah Alpert-Abrams’s <ref
                    target="../../2016/essays/essay.alpertabrams.html">essay on the deterministic
                    limitations of digital representations of historical books</ref>. </p>


            <p>This issue offers several editions ranging across diverse texts. Andrew Dunning has
                edited <ref
                    target="../../2016/editions/editions/intro.dequinqueseptenis-deorationedominica.dunning.html"
                        ><hi rend="italic">De oratione dominica</hi></ref>, a thirteenth-century
                versification of a twelfth century epistolary essay, <hi rend="italic">De quinque
                    septenis</hi>, that explored high medieval thought on sin, prayer, divine gifts,
                virtue, and beatification. Through rigorous and attentive editing and markup,
                Dunning has created a dual-language edition that allows readers to deeply explore
                the text. In <ref target="../../2016/editions/editions/BinyonDestree.html">A
                    Transnational Literary Network Around 1900: The Correspondence between Laurence
                    Binyon and Olivier-Georges Destrée</ref>, Marysa Demoor, Eloise Forestier, and
                Gero Guttzeit study the multilingual correspondence between a British poet/critic
                and a Belgian advocate for the arts through the turn of the nineteenth century and
                the beginning of WWI. The edition helps illuminate transnational cultural networks
                between Britain and Belgium and sheds light on the state of the arts and publishing
                in the two nations leading up to WWI.</p>

            <p>Mary Isbell’s <ref target="../../2016/editions/editions/intro.youngidea.html"
                    >Extracts from the <hi rend="italic">Young Idea</hi></ref> presents selections
                from a handwritten newspaper produced and circulated on a nineteenth-century British
                warship, the <hi rend="italic">H.M.S. Chesapeake</hi>. Such newspapers were rare,
                and typically their editors were forbidden from publishing the texts beyond the
                ship. <hi rend="italic">The Young Idea</hi>, then, offers an unusual glimpse into
                this fascinating genre. Maire Mullins’s edition, <ref
                    target="../../2016/editions/editions/mullinswhitmanheyde.html">The Selected
                    Letters of Hannah Whitman Heyde</ref>, contributes to the record on Walt Whitman
                and offers valuable insight on domestic violence in the nineteenth century. Heyde
                was long married to a man who psychologically and physically abused her. Her
                correspondence with her mother offers a glimpse into the life of a woman surviving
                abuse at a time when the country offered little recourse or understanding for
                domestic violence victims.</p>

            <p>This issue offers an annotated list of recent scholarly editions and reviews of two
                new publications. The articles, editions, and reviews published here demonstrate the
                rich work happening today in scholarly editing.</p>

        </body>





    </text>
</TEI>
