<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<?oxygen RNGSchema="http://www.scholarlyediting.org/scholarlyediting.rng" type="xml"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xml:lang="eng">
    <teiHeader>
        <fileDesc>
            <titleStmt>
                <title level="a" type="main">Method and Judgment in the Theodore Dreiser Edition</title>
                <title level="a" type="sub">From Sister Carrie to The Titan</title>
                <author key="Davies, Jude">Jude Davies</author>
            </titleStmt>
            <editionStmt>
                <edition>
                    <date>2016</date>
                </edition>
            </editionStmt>
            <publicationStmt>
                <idno type="file">essay.davies</idno>
                <authority>Scholary Editing: The Annual of the Association for Documentary
                    Editing</authority>
                <address>
 <addrLine>http://www.scholarlyediting.org</addrLine>
</address>
                <publisher>Association for Documentary Editing</publisher>
                <publisher>University of Nebraska&#8211;Lincoln</publisher>
                <distributor>
                    <name>Center for Digital Research in the Humanities</name>
                    <address>
<addrLine>319 Love Library</addrLine>
<addrLine>University of Nebraska&#8211;Lincoln</addrLine>
<addrLine>Lincoln, NE 68588-4100</addrLine>
<addrLine>http://cdrh.unl.edu</addrLine>
 </address>
                </distributor>
                <date>2016</date>
                <availability>
                    <p>Scholary Editing: The Annual of the Association for Documentary Editing is
                        freely distributed by the Association for Documentary Editing and the Center
                        for Digital Research in the Humanities at the University of Nebraska-Lincoln
                        and licensed under a Creative Commons Attribution-NonCommercial-ShareAlike
                        3.0 Unported License</p>
                </availability>
            </publicationStmt>
            <seriesStmt>
                <title level="j">Scholarly Editing: The Annual of the Association for Documentary
                    Editing</title>
                <respStmt>
                    <resp>editor</resp>
                    <name xml:id="ag" key="Gailey, Amanda A.">Amanda Gailey</name>
                </respStmt>
                <respStmt>
                    <resp>editor</resp>
                    <name xml:id="awj" key="Jewell, Andrew W.">Andrew Jewell</name>
                </respStmt>
                <idno type="vol">37</idno>
                <idno type="ISSN">2167-1257</idno>
            </seriesStmt>
            <sourceDesc>
                <bibl>
                    <note>Born digital.</note>
                </bibl>
            </sourceDesc>
        </fileDesc>
        <revisionDesc>
            <change when="2016-03-23"><name xml:id="gk" key="Kirilloff, Gabi"> Gabi Kirilloff</name>
                markup in TEI XML</change>
        </revisionDesc>
    </teiHeader>
    <text>
        <front>
            <head type="main">Method and Judgment in the Theodore Dreiser Edition</head>
            <head type="sub">From <hi rend="italic">Sister Carrie</hi> to <hi rend="italic">The Titan</hi></head>
            <byline>Jude Davies</byline>
            <epigraph>
                <cit>
                    <quote>The history of editing has moved according to its own logic, marked, on
                        the positive side, both with methodological advances and with compelling
                        demonstrations of the importance of informed judgment. The two elements,
                        method and judgment, tend to appear on the intellectual stage as opponents,
                        and are sometimes identified, respectively, with the ideas that the past is
                        best recovered by either objective or subjective means. The tension in this
                        opposition has generated its share of pointless negativity, but like all
                        dynamic relationships the struggle has its creative potential.</quote>
                    <bibl>&#8212;Richard Bucci<ptr target="#note1" xml:id="nr1" n="1"/></bibl>
                </cit>
            </epigraph>
        </front>
        <body>
            <p>The Theodore Dreiser Edition is a project to publish the work of Theodore Dreiser
                (1871–1945), a leading and controversial literary figure of the early twentieth
                    century.<ptr target="#note2" xml:id="nr2" n="2"/> Since its inception in 1981 it
                has produced editions of novels, travel writing, and autobiography, of private
                letters and diaries, and volumes of political writings and interviews. Over that
                time the Dreiser Edition’s policies have evolved in ways that overtly reflect how
                textual editing has engaged with notions of the social text. Its first publication,
                an edition of Dreiser’s first novel, <hi rend="italic">Sister Carrie</hi>, that
                explicitly affiliated itself with the Greg-Bowers-Tanselle tradition, became a focal
                point of resistance to eclectic editing, while its most recent editions downplay
                eclecticism and announce themselves as presenting versions of texts in a continuum
                of composition. Instructive as this may be as an example of the unfolding of a logic
                in the history of editing, this essay takes the Dreiser Edition as exemplifying that
                in author editions, other dynamics are also at work. The editorial context is never
                independent from the fluctuating status and significance attributed to authors,
                while different editorial practices may be required by changes in authors’ practices
                of composition and revision as their relationships with publishers and publics
                develop over their career, and by differing archival resources. Modal differences
                between outputs also require different editorial approaches. Editorial aims may be
                conditioned by contextual changes in literary theory, criticism, and pedagogy. The
                trajectory of the Dreiser Edition may indicate general trends in scholarly editing,
                then, but this essay aims to complicate such linear narratives by reference to these
                other dynamics and contexts. The main focus is on reviewing the practices and
                rationale of the 1981 edition of <hi rend="italic">Sister Carrie</hi>, its highly
                polarized critical reception, the notions of authorship that it promoted, and the
                kinds of reading that it fostered or made possible. The essay then moves on to
                consider the subsequent development of the Edition, focusing especially on its
                latest volume, Dreiser’s fourth novel, <hi rend="italic">The Titan</hi>, which is
                forthcoming in 2016.</p>
            <p>The 1981 <hi rend="italic">Sister Carrie</hi> (known as the “Pennsylvania” text
                largely to reflect the major archival repository of Dreiser’s papers at the
                University of Pennsylvania Library, which has provided the basis of most subsequent
                Dreiser Edition volumes) elicited much praise and much criticism upon publication. A
                central but not sole cause of this controversy, as will be seen, was the decision by
                textual editor James L. W. West III to use as copy-text the holograph manuscript of
                the novel completed by Dreiser in March 1900, before it entered the processes of
                being typed, revised, and further edited. Various people, notably Dreiser’s wife,
                Sarah White Dreiser, and his friend, the minor writer Arthur Henry, contributed to
                these revisions. As well as “correcting” Dreiser’s distinctive writing style and
                removing alleged profanities, this involved cutting 36,000 words from the
                manuscript, changing and reordering the ending, fictionalizing some proper names,
                and adding chapter titles. All of this, at the time, Dreiser sought or approved in
                order to get his first novel published, and he reversed none of the revisions when
                opportunities to republish the novel arose later in his career. In his statement of
                editorial principles, West cited W. W. Greg, Fredson Bowers, and G. Thomas Tanselle
                as authorities, before using value-laden rhetoric to validate Dreiser’s holograph as
                a “serious work of art” and to state that it was the editor’s task to rescue it from
                attempts to produce a “saleable fiction.” What antagonists with different
                perspectives would view as authorial revision, or the social and historical
                processes of publication, were described by West as “damaging,” “weakening,”
                “censor[ing],” and “emasculating” Dreiser’s original vision.<ptr target="#note3"
                    xml:id="nr3" n="3"/> West justified his choice of Dreiser’s
                holograph&#8212;effectively a first draft&#8212;as his copy-text, and his editorial
                treatment of it, on the grounds of not only expunging the contributions of anyone
                other than Dreiser, but also of purifying Dreiser’s own authorship from revisions he
                made or accepted as an editor of his own work. Radically revising the notion of the
                “author’s final intentions” as developed in the copy-text tradition, West argued
                that “[i]n the strictest sense,” Dreiser’s “authorial function ceased after he
                inscribed the holograph draft of <hi rend="italic">Sister Carrie</hi>.”<ptr
                    target="#note4" xml:id="nr4" n="4"/></p>
            <p>This argument was ratcheted up in the edition’s preface by general editor Neda M.
                Westlake, which strongly evoked New Critical discourses of the verbal icon. The
                editors of the Pennsylvania Edition of <hi rend="italic">Sister Carrie</hi>,
                Westlake stated, “with recourse to the manuscript and typescript, restore the novel
                as closely as possible to the author’s original version, a more somber and
                unresolved work of art. The frame of the novel remains; within the picture, like a
                cleansed portrait, the characters assume the original clarity of the artist’s
                    design.”<ptr target="#note5" xml:id="nr5" n="5"/></p>
            <p>This was, of course, not all that the editors provided. West supplied a copious
                apparatus, including a table of “Block Cuts Marked by Arthur Henry and Accepted by
                Dreiser” as well as passages such as Dreiser’s revised ending of the novel, which
                enabled interested readers to consider the process of revision. However, at the time
                few reviewers registered this interrogative and enabling aspect of the edition. One
                such was Hershel Parker, who implied that West’s project was “bringing biographical,
                historical, and textual evidence to bear on the study of real authors creating real
                works of art.”<ptr target="#note6" xml:id="nr6" n="6"/> Most responses, though,
                accepted the self-presentation of the Pennsylvania <hi rend="italic">Sister
                    Carrie</hi> as aspiring to release the individual act of authorship from its
                social context, and were polarized between validating and contesting such a
                project.</p>
            <p>Controversy was fueled by the marketing of the Pennsylvania <hi rend="italic">Sister
                    Carrie</hi> as likely to become the “accepted standard”<ptr target="#note7"
                    xml:id="nr7" n="7"/> and the simultaneous publication of a paperback edition of
                the “unexpurgated” text <hi rend="italic">sans</hi> editorial matter in the Penguin
                American Library. In the furor, the Pennsylvania <hi rend="italic">Sister
                    Carrie</hi> became a focal point of the resistance to eclectic editing that was
                building in the American academy during the 1970s and 1980s, as Paul Eggert and
                Peter Shillingsburg have noted.<ptr target="#note8" xml:id="nr8" n="8"/> On the one
                side was a particularly extreme idealization of the author function, defended in
                reviews by Richard Lingeman, who likened the editors to “art historians cleaning a
                da Vinci fresco.” On the other side was an insistence on the “historical” text, as
                in Donald Pizer’s review in <hi rend="italic">American Literature</hi>, and later by
                Jack Stillinger, as part of his critique of “the myth of solitary genius.” Pizer had
                laid out his own view on how Dreiser’s novels should <hi rend="italic">not</hi> be
                edited as early as 1972, arguing that the circumstances of modern American
                authorship were materially different from the conditions pertaining to the
                Renaissance printed texts for which the Greg-Bowers methods were initially
                formulated. “Dreiser’s novels,” he stated, “offer an excellent example of the
                futility of applying copy-text principles to the editing of much twentieth-century
                    fiction.”<ptr target="#note10" xml:id="nr10" n="10"/></p>
            <p>Pizer had anticipated, from a perspective embedded in literary history, many of the
                criticisms of the Greg-Bowers tradition that would follow in the 1980s and 1990s,
                especially those made by Jerome J. McGann from the point of view of the “social
                    text.”<ptr target="#note11" xml:id="nr11" n="11"/> However, as Parker
                recognized, the 1981 <hi rend="italic">Sister Carrie</hi> also demonstrates a
                sensitivity to the text at hand and its various contexts, that goes beyond any
                straightforward application of editorial principles. West’s consideration of
                authorship and textual production was itself embedded in conflicts over the status
                of Dreiser and the significance of his first novel. The gestures toward idealist
                notions of authorship made by the <hi rend="italic">Sister Carrie</hi> editors and
                supportive reviewers can be fully understood only when considered in the context of
                Dreiser’s critical reputation and the trajectory of literary studies. Because of his
                style, his subject matter, and his politics, Dreiser was marginalized by New
                Criticism, and his reputation as a central literary figure was not assured in 1981.
                The affiliations with Greg-Bowers methodology and New Critical discourse were in
                part, it could be argued, a means of engaging the historical, literary, and covertly
                political debates over Dreiser’s reputation as an American author and the status of
                    <hi rend="italic">Sister Carrie</hi> within the canon of American
                literature.</p>
            <p>At one level, the projects of “cleans[ing]” and “cleaning” were directed against
                biographical “dust.” Before the publication of the Pennsylvania Edition, Dreiser’s
                literary reputation was still strongly influenced by his later biography, especially
                the left-wing political activism to which he had devoted most of his time in the
                1930s and 1940s, culminating with his support for the foreign policy of the USSR in
                1939–42, and his joining of the Communist Party shortly before he died in December
                1945. To devote the resources required to describe the composition, publication, and
                text of <hi rend="italic">Sister Carrie</hi> was not to dehistoricize but to
                rehistorize it, allowing it to be assessed independently of Dreiser’s later
                political affiliations.</p>
            <p>At another level, the editors, and reviewers such as Lingeman, were addressing issues
                of Dreiser’s style, which, while they were the focus of New Critical attention, have
                a much longer history, extending to the present. Critical views of Dreiser as a
                naïve or simply a bad writer go back to some of the first reviews of <hi
                    rend="italic">Sister Carrie</hi>, and he was the main literary target of Lionel
                Trilling’s critique of realism in the 1946 essay “Reality in America,” reprinted in
                    <hi rend="italic">The Liberal Imagination</hi> (1952), one of the most
                influential works of the New Criticism. According to Trilling, Dreiser’s works were
                overvalued (by critics such as Vernon Parrington, the primary object of Trilling’s
                critique), because they “have the awkwardness, the chaos, the heaviness which we
                associate with ‘reality.’”<ptr target="#note12" xml:id="nr12" n="12"/> More
                recently, even critics seeking to validate Dreiser’s work have sometimes done so by
                negating his sophistication, as when Joseph Epstein praises Dreiser as “a good
                boiled potato” compared to the caviar that is Henry James, or when Fredric Jameson
                frames Dreiser’s style as an artifact of American materialism and consumerism, in a
                reading first made the same year that the Pennsylvania <hi rend="italic">Sister
                    Carrie</hi> appeared, and renewed in 2015.<ptr target="#note13" xml:id="nr13"
                    n="13"/> In this context, West’s emphasis on Dreiser’s text, on the lone author
                and his aesthetic judgments, makes sense as part of the claim that Dreiser’s
                aesthetics were worthy of the same kind of attention as, say, those of Mark Twain or
                Shakespeare. As West would put it later, “I meant to present him as a disciplined
                professional and a serious young artist, not as a poorly educated rube from Indiana
                who needed chastisement with the blue pencil.”<ptr target="#note14" xml:id="nr14"
                    n="14"/> West’s insistence on the forensic attention required to isolate and
                define Dreiser’s authorship aligned him with earlier critics who had striven to
                validate Dreiser as an artist and a thinker, such as Robert H. Elias, Robert Penn
                Warren, and Ellen Moers, and with Donald Pizer’s own <hi rend="italic">The Novels of
                    Theodore Dreiser</hi> (1976), which drew upon a deep familiarity with Dreiser’s
                processes of composition and revision. In this sense Dreiser is a good example of
                how the negotiations between the disciplinary development of critical and
                documentary editing, and the changing influence on literary and historical studies
                of New Criticism, “Theory,” deconstruction, and multiculturalism, are central to any
                understanding of their trajectories.<ptr target="#note15" xml:id="nr15" n="15"/>
                What could be read as a tendency to idealize the author function in West’s
                “Editorial Principles” could equally well be understood as a strategic use of
                Greg-Bowers concepts to stake out a critical assessment of Dreiser’s work that
                avoided the polarizing debate between New Critical dismissals of his novels, and the
                framing of Dreiser’s work as directly realist portrayals of modern American urban
                society.</p>
            <p>Reconsidered in these contexts, West’s initially surprising description of his
                editorial work on <hi rend="italic">Sister Carrie</hi> as “conservative” comes into
                focus. Having insisted so strongly on the literary and artistic quality of Dreiser’s
                manuscript, West severely limited his emendations, essentially to those necessary to
                correct grammatical errors, and the very few instances where he could be certain
                that Dreiser revised alone and on purely artistic grounds. He rejected “nearly all”
                of the block cuts marked by Arthur Henry and approved by Dreiser.<ptr
                    target="#note16" xml:id="nr16" n="16"/> It would be reasonable to consider that
                some of the 36,000 words cut from the first-draft manuscript were cut for good
                “artistic” reasons&#8212;Donald Pizer’s review would suggest several
                instances&#8212;but West’s policies made it very difficult to obtain sufficient
                evidence to make such qualitative judgments. In short, the edition embraced
                eclecticism more in theory than in practice.<ptr target="#note17" xml:id="nr17"
                    n="17"/> Whether this was due to method or to judgment, there was an irony that
                so much criticism was directed toward the Edition’s presumed ahistoricism and
                idealism, given that its treatment of the holograph manuscript bore some resemblance
                to the nascent practice of versioning. West himself would go on to suggest in 1994
                that “versioning would probably work for novels such as <hi rend="italic">Sister
                    Carrie</hi>.”<ptr target="#note18" xml:id="nr18" n="18"/></p>
            <p>The Pennsylvania <hi rend="italic">Sister Carrie</hi> invited an engagement with the
                novel’s historical textualization precisely through its transparency in detailing
                editorial choices according to Greg-Bowers methods. In his “Editorial Principles”
                West explicitly ruled out the possibility of any edition of <hi rend="italic">Sister
                    Carrie</hi> being definitive and envisaged a range of possible “future
                editions,” including the use of parallel texts, facsimiles, and a variorum.<ptr
                    target="#note19" xml:id="nr19" n="19"/> The combination of this sense of textual
                possibility, West’s own “conservatism” in choosing not to selectively adopt the cuts
                proposed by Henry and agreed to by Dreiser, and his provision of tables identifying
                those cuts effectively invited readers into the editing process. As Paul Eggert
                appreciatively notes, “Because of its point of comparison” West’s “textual apparatus
                allows a more readily comprehensible study of the changes made to the manuscript
                draft by Dreiser and by his collaborators than if his edition had merely accepted
                the results of the collaboration as unchangeable.” As a result, it can be added, for
                students of literature at any level, the volume offered a practical introduction to
                questions of composition, authorship, and editing.<ptr target="#note20"
                    xml:id="nr20" n="20"/></p>
            <p>By the mid-1990s, the controversy over <hi rend="italic">Sister Carrie</hi> had died
                down, as it became apparent that the “restored” text provided a highly useful
                resource for critics and readers alongside the text published by Doubleday, Page and
                Company in 1900, and that paperbacks based on the 1900 text continued to sell
                alongside the Penguin Books edition that advertised its use of West’s text.<ptr
                    target="#note21" xml:id="nr21" n="21"/> Far from supplanting the 1900 text, as
                some critics had feared,<ptr target="#note22" xml:id="nr22" n="22"/> the
                Pennsylvania <hi rend="italic">Sister Carrie</hi> had effected what might be called
                a kind of “versioning” by the back door, helping to create a situation whereby even
                the most casual of readers cannot help but engage with the novel’s textual
                instability, at the most basic level of having to choose between what are now called
                the “complete and unexpurgated text” (Penguin) and the “author’s final version”
                (Oxford University Press). The Norton Critical Edition, edited by Donald Pizer,
                became even more textually aware than either after its second edition in 1991 added
                a comparison of the Doubleday, Page and Pennsylvania texts, and a “Textual Appendix”
                described as providing “a generous sampling of the cuts Dreiser and his friend
                Arthur Henry made in the typescript version[.]”<ptr target="#note23" xml:id="nr23"
                    n="23"/></p>
            <p>Anent the serendipity of this “versioning by the backdoor” narrative, some
                interesting questions remain. If the availability of two textual versions of <hi
                    rend="italic">Sister Carrie</hi> undoubtedly conveys welcome senses of the
                fluidity of textualization and the historical contingencies behind publication, it
                perhaps also tends to prematurely resolve those questions into a binary opposition,
                such that readers are confronted with a simple choice between (only) two texts,
                Dreiser’s original manuscript and that published in 1900. Both the Penguin and
                Oxford University Press marketing tags quoted above lay claim to a definitiveness
                which is highly questionable, hinging as they do on somewhat contingent
                interpretations of “complete,” “author’s,” and “final.” For readers without a
                background in textual editing, the immediate effect of this polarization is to
                cement an absolute distinction between a privatized conception of authorial
                creation, and the public and social process of publication. In the process, the
                questions of authorial intention and revision that give rise to eclectic editing in
                the first place are foreclosed before they have properly been registered. In this
                case, the process of revision by which Dreiser’s manuscript became the text
                published in 1900 is simplified, and any textual changes after 1900 are
                marginalized. The latter are potentially considerable, given the publication of a
                shortened version in London in 1901, whose commercial and critical success was
                crucial in encouraging and enabling Dreiser to relaunch his literary career after
                the commercial failure of the first edition, and a significant revision made for the
                second American edition (B. W. Dodge, 1907) in the first chapter of the novel to
                remove material appropriated from the humorist writer George Ade.<ptr
                    target="#note24" xml:id="nr24" n="24"/> In sum, there is still critical and
                pedagogical work to do even now, as West anticipated there would be in the
                speculations about future editions contained in his account of textual
                principles.</p>
            <p>This last point brings us back to the unresolved duality of the Pennsylvania <hi
                    rend="italic">Sister Carrie</hi>, and its implications for definitions and
                methodologies of editing more widely. On the one hand, as has just been argued, it
                invited readers into the archive to consider the processes of revision and
                publication. On the other hand, this invitation was often obscured by the strong
                claims made on behalf of its restored text, and the use of New Critical concepts to
                frame the edition. (With hindsight West explicitly distanced himself from the
                moralizing rhetoric employed in 1981, stating two decades later that if editing <hi
                    rend="italic">Sister Carrie</hi> again, “I would not be as insistent about the
                virtue of what I was doing.”<ptr target="#note25" xml:id="nr25" n="25"/>) As it was,
                the volume could be considered to exemplify what Peter Shillingsburg has described
                in a recent essay in <hi rend="italic">Ecdotica</hi> as the blurring of distinctions
                between archival editions and scholarly editions that took place in the 1980s.
                Shillingsburg regards this blurring as responsible for a great deal of confusion,
                misdirected criticism aimed between archival editors and scholarly editors, and more
                recently, for allowing a narrowly archival approach to develop in the field of
                digital editing.<ptr target="#note26" xml:id="nr26" n="26"/> Developing terms
                broached by Paul Eggert, he therefore sets about clarifying and separating the
                projects engendered by the “archival impulse,” which he summarizes as being to
                “reiterate texts,” and the “editing impulse,” to “fix texts.” This agenda draws upon
                a foundational opposition that parallels Richard Bucci’s distinction between method
                and judgment quoted in the epigraph to this essay, albeit that Bucci emphasizes the
                “creative potential” of this dynamic, while for Shillingsburg the “pointless
                negativity” looms larger. Notwithstanding this contrasting orientation, when taken
                together, both sets of distinctions usefully open up a conceptual distance around
                the familiar categories of documentary editing and critical editing. While the
                editing traditions differ as to aim and approach, which therefore must be made clear
                at all times, the relationship between them is dynamic; they are not necessarily
                bound to mutually negating ontologies. Rather, they can be seen as different
                methodologies for arbitrating between opposed modes of historicization. Reiterating
                and fixing, method and judgment, are all at work, in varying degrees, in different
                models of editing. Critical editing has its dualism of text and apparatus, while,
                for example, in the German Historical-Critical tradition the text is present
                alongside the primary aim to present an encoded archive. The relationship between
                archival and editing impulses can be and is reconceptualized according to the
                specific archival base and requirements of each project. What gives editions their
                character, then, is not their adherence to one of these impulses above the other,
                but the ways in which they arbitrate the negotiation between them, which is itself
                often manifested in the kinds of claims they make about the texts presented, and in
                turn the ways of reading that they invite or allow.</p>
            <p>In the Pennsylvania <hi rend="italic">Sister Carrie</hi>, it could be said, archival
                and editing impulses coexisted without a unifying structure. This is not to identify
                a flaw or failing so much as to indicate that it confronted head-on the conflicted
                nature of Dreiser’s reputation, notions of authorship, and editorial practice.
                Though James West does not put the matter in these terms, his reflections on the
                experience of editing novels by F. Scott Fitzgerald and William Styron as well as
                Dreiser are compatible with this sense of methodology as a product of reflection on
                the text at hand. In <hi rend="italic">Making the Archives Talk</hi> (2011) West
                argues strongly for the embedding of the editorial project in the editor’s
                open-minded immersion in the archival and biographical record from which a text is
                produced. “Narratives” justifying the text and its editorial procedures are
                constructed retrospectively.<ptr target="#note27" xml:id="nr27" n="27"/></p>
            <p>For the second novel published by the Edition, <hi rend="italic">Jennie Gerhardt</hi>
                (1992; original publication 1911), West, as he had with <hi rend="italic">Sister
                    Carrie</hi>, adopted a holograph manuscript as his copy-text on the basis of its
                embodying Dreiser’s “fair copy” text at the moment of submission, in this case in
                spring 1911, to the publisher Harper and Brothers. However, drawing upon the
                distinction between “active” and “final” authorial intention elaborated by Tanselle,
                West produced a much more eclectic text than that presented in the Pennsylvania <hi
                    rend="italic">Sister Carrie</hi>. He emended the copy-text to adopt the Harpers
                editors’ revisions where they were judged commensurate with Dreiser’s active
                    intentions.<ptr target="#note28" xml:id="nr28" n="28"/> The apparatus indicated
                the complex web of revisions and illustrated specific cruxes, giving readers
                detailed access to the process of revision within the limitations of the printed
                volume. As with <hi rend="italic">Sister Carrie</hi> the tension between editorial
                and archiving impulses was more difficult to harmonize at the level of the explicit
                claims about the “new” text. In the introduction, the “restored” text was presented
                as a “complement” to the first edition of 1911, while the statement of editorial
                principles began by emphasizing the impossibility of producing a “definitive” text
                given the complexity of the archival record, and closed by asserting that this text
                was so different from the 1911 published version that it amounted to “an edition of
                a new work of literature, heretofore unknown.”<ptr target="#note29" xml:id="nr29"
                    n="29"/> While this latter was undoubtedly an extravagant claim, it immediately
                sidelined the reductive debates over primacy that had dogged <hi rend="italic"
                    >Sister Carrie</hi>. It also had the critically useful effect of highlighting to
                readers the range of literary discourses (such as those of the “sentimental” novel
                and of realism) at play in Dreiser’s work.</p>
            <p>At this pivotal point, the trajectories of West and the Dreiser Edition diverged
                    somewhat.<ptr target="#note30" xml:id="nr30" n="30"/> While West went on to
                produce, for example, an edition of the F. Scott Fitzgerald text he published as <hi
                    rend="italic">Trimalchio: An Early Version of</hi> The Great Gatsby (2000), the
                Edition began to frame its output explicitly through an emphasis on “versioning.” In
                a 1998 second edition of <hi rend="italic">Sister Carrie</hi>, general editor Thomas
                P. Riggio described the West text as “a version in a continuum of composition.”
                Given that, as Riggio also noted, “even the harshest of critics of the Pennsylvania
                    <hi rend="italic">Sister Carrie</hi> today recognize its importance[,]” the
                claims for definitiveness which had attended the same text in 1981 were perhaps now
                unnecessary, though one may wonder whether the 1981 text would have had the same
                impact on readers if those claims had never been made. In any case, Riggio now
                emphasized that “[v]iewed together, all versions&#8212;Doubleday (1900), Dodge
                (1907), and Pennsylvania (1981)&#8212;give us a good idea of the complex process of
                writing and editing that went into making the novel.”<ptr target="#note31"
                    xml:id="nr31" n="31"/> Here Riggio began to make explicit the interest in
                “versioning,” derived in part from Donald H. Reiman,<ptr target="#note32"
                    xml:id="nr32" n="32"/> that has informed the ways in which the Dreiser Edition
                has presented subsequent work. Editions of <hi rend="italic">The Genius</hi> (edited
                by Clare Virginia Eby in 2008) and <hi rend="italic">The Financier</hi> (edited by
                Roark Mulligan, 2010) print substantial material that had been cut or revised for
                the initial publication, and present themselves as versions to be read alongside the
                published versions.</p>
            <p>It needs to be made clear that this embrace of versioning as a framework for
                understanding the function and status of Dreiser Edition volumes does not involve a
                commitment to the practices and protocols of documentary editing. A copy-text is
                identified. Emendations are made, recorded, and explained. Just as they always have,
                editors take into account the author’s intentions for the work, insofar as they are
                knowable, and examine and consider all relevant texts both pre- and
                post-publication. Volumes are often dependent on unpublished manuscripts and
                typescripts. A general statement of editorial principles, prepared by Thomas P.
                Riggio for the 2016 Dreiser Edition of <hi rend="italic">The Titan</hi>, summarizes
                current policy:<q type="block">The Dreiser Edition advocates an approach that avoids
                    the pitfalls of eclecticism and ontologies of definitiveness, while also seeking
                    as much as possible to replicate the historical presentation of a clean text to
                    readers. Accordingly, all texts are presented as one of a number of possible
                    versions in a continuum of composition. In this regard the Dreiser Edition has
                    evolved from the original formulations published in 1981 to take into account
                    the central ideas common to diverse modern textual critics (among others, Philip
                    Gaskell, Jerome J. McGann, and Donald H. Reiman).<ptr target="#note33"
                        xml:id="nr33" n="33"/></q>The named authorities might be read as each
                signaling a register of difference. Gaskell, from within the copy-text tradition,
                suggests an initial focus on the last version of the work to leave the author’s
                hands, to be selectively emended, as distinct from the original tendency in the
                Greg-Bowers tradition to prefer the authorial manuscript before the technological
                and social elements of print culture intervene. McGann’s name of course betokens an
                acknowledgment of the social text, while the citation of Reiman signals the interest
                in “versioning.” These citations function less programmatically than the appeal to
                Greg, Bowers, and Tanselle in the <hi rend="italic">Sister Carrie</hi> edition,
                which they implicitly reflect. Rather, as the “Editorial Procedures” also declares,
                though there are certain general principles, “Dreiser Edition volumes are not based
                on any fixed theory or school of thought, and editors assume that every text
                presents unique issues that shape editorial practice.”</p>
            <p>Those issues are evident in the two latest novels to appear in the Dreiser Edition,
                    <hi rend="italic">The Financier</hi>, as mentioned above, and <hi rend="italic"
                    >The Titan</hi> (forthcoming in 2016), both edited by Roark Mulligan and both of
                which use page proofs for copy-text. As Mulligan states, in the case of <hi
                    rend="italic">The Financier</hi>, “[t]his choice is based on critical and
                historical considerations” which include the sense that the 1912 published version
                had been displaced by a revised and cut version that Dreiser oversaw in 1927.
                Mulligan’s archival research revealed that some material which was cut in proof was
                reinstated by Dreiser in the later, shorter edition. For this and other reasons, he
                regarded the page proofs as “a significant stage in the novel’s production” and
                presented it accordingly.<ptr target="#note34" xml:id="nr34" n="34"/></p>
            <p>The 2016 Dreiser Edition volume of <hi rend="italic">The Titan</hi> is in many ways a
                collaborative enterprise, in which volume editor Mulligan worked closely with Riggio
                as textual editor, and with me. Here again the page proofs were chosen as copy-text,
                but this was a more difficult decision, without the specific critical and historical
                considerations that applied to <hi rend="italic">The Financier</hi>. Nevertheless,
                the historical specifics of the biographical and archival record strongly influenced
                editorial policy. For a number of reasons, the ways that Dreiser composed and
                revised changed dramatically after the publication of <hi rend="italic">Jennie
                    Gerhardt</hi>. After 1911 Dreiser, more than familiar with the active roles of
                publishers and editors, submitted his novels in forms that were clearly unfinished,
                expecting to bring them to completion in dialogue with publishers’ editors and other
                readers. (As James West has pointed out, this is a fairly common shift among
                    novelists.<ptr target="#note35" xml:id="nr35" n="35"/>) It therefore becomes
                much more difficult to identify a “fair copy” manuscript or typescript that could be
                chosen as copy-text on the grounds that it represents a completed stage in the
                development of the novel. Another set of issues derives from Dreiser’s subject
                matter. Early novels such as <hi rend="italic">Sister Carrie</hi> and <hi
                    rend="italic">Jennie Gerhardt</hi> were suggested by Dreiser’s own experiences
                and those of his close family. With the trilogy begun with <hi rend="italic">The
                    Financier</hi> and continued with <hi rend="italic">The Titan</hi>, Dreiser
                changed his way of working. He carried out lengthy and intensive historical research
                on the financier Charles Tyson Yerkes (1837–1905), consulting newspaper archives and
                traveling extensively in the United States and Europe to interview people who knew
                Yerkes. As part of his research for the Dreiser Edition volumes, Roark Mulligan
                examined the materials Dreiser had assembled for the trilogy, preserved among the
                Dreiser Papers at the University of Pennsylvania Library, including over 1,000 pages
                of notes and clippings. Having drafted his fictionalization of these materials,
                Dreiser spent months in early 1914 revising, selecting, and cutting. In his “Textual
                Commentary,” Mulligan elaborates on a range of factors that affected these
                revisions. Principal motivations were Dreiser’s aesthetic and commercial concerns to
                make the novel more concise and focused. Such cutting and revising of an initially
                lengthy draft were by now typical, integral phases in Dreiser’s habitual way of
                writing fiction. Here they were given particular impetus by his dissatisfaction with
                    <hi rend="italic">The Financier</hi>, which he already viewed as overlong. In
                addition, Dreiser’s thematic interests shifted as he moved from the first volume,
                which contextualized his protagonist Frank Cowperwood’s narrative largely with
                respect to the world of banking, to the second, which is more engaged with the city
                politics of Chicago and the Illinois legislature.</p>
            <p>Given these and additional aesthetic, literary, commercial, and legal details
                uncovered by Mulligan, even had we wanted to, it would have been very difficult to
                restore a text of <hi rend="italic">The Titan</hi> to a moment before significant
                revision took place, as was done with the <hi rend="italic">Sister Carrie</hi> and
                    <hi rend="italic">Jennie Gerhardt</hi> editions. To try to arbitrate between
                revisions would have been highly speculative. Hence it made practical as well as
                critical sense to choose the proofs as the copy text and to make minimal
                emendations.</p>
            <p>Dreiser’s use of historical research in composing <hi rend="italic">The Titan</hi>
                also influenced our conception of the apparatus. Fairly straightforwardly, since
                Dreiser’s fictionalization of specific historical material is a key element of the
                novel, Mulligan provided brief accounts of the historical personages and events in a
                series of historical notes. More difficult questions arose from the need to
                arbitrate between archival and editing impulses. Mulligan’s research at the
                University of Pennsylvania Library revealed that Dreiser had written, and
                subsequently cut, material that would be of interest to cultural historians, if not
                students of Dreiser’s work. Naturally, we wanted to make available from the
                documentary record Dreiser’s depiction of important events such as the 1893 Chicago
                World’s Fair or Great Columbian Exposition, a much-studied topic, even though the
                chapter was cut before the page-proof stage. We also wanted to indicate how
                decisions over the inclusion or exclusion of specific historical events and contexts
                were part of the process of composition. While this is true of any novel that draws
                upon historical research, the issue is sharpened here because a central theme of
                Dreiser’s trilogy is the dynamic between its protagonist’s exceptional ability to
                influence events, and wider historical forces. In <hi rend="italic">The
                    Financier</hi>, for example, Dreiser depicts Cowperwood being puzzled by the
                outbreak of “war-spirit” during the Civil War, since he views the conflict between
                Northern and Southern states almost exclusively in terms of its financial
                implications for him personally. The climax of the novel narrates Cowperwood’s
                financial ruin due to the financial panic following the Great Fire of Chicago,
                followed by the restitution of his fortunes during the stock market crash of 1873.
                Much of <hi rend="italic">The Titan</hi> deals with Cowperwood’s attempts to
                manipulate the development of streetcar lines in Chicago for his own enrichment. A
                particularly pointed example occurs in chapter 23 of the proofs, where Dreiser’s
                narrator goes out of his way to mention the 1886 Haymarket affair, explaining that
                it “changed, quite as an eruption might, the whole face of the commercial
                landscape.” After a lengthy paragraph describing this historic importance, Dreiser
                adds simply that “In the face of this, however, Cowperwood was not disturbed.” Such
                episodes provide the grounds for interpretive debate over issues such as the novel’s
                depiction of agency, and its orientation toward Cowperwood’s status as an
                exceptionally powerful individual. At the same time, they exemplify the importance
                of preserving and explaining Dreiser’s strategic depiction, or withholding, of
                historical narrative. We have sought to present and explain Dreiser’s decisions in
                the printed volume, while planning to put online selected archival material that was
                cut before proof stage.</p>
            <p>Like all authors and all works, Dreiser and <hi rend="italic">Sister Carrie</hi> and
                    <hi rend="italic">The Titan</hi> are special cases. Each volume in the Dreiser
                Edition is a product of the application of editorial practice to the archival
                record, and over the last thirty-five years editors have taken the social nature of
                textual production increasingly seriously. However, as this brief survey has
                illustrated, volumes have been shaped just as decisively by a range of other
                considerations: differing processes of composition and revision, issues of
                canonicity and reputation, the demands of readers as anticipated in the production
                of the edition and the uses to which readers put it once published, and wider
                tendencies in literary and cultural study. Bearing this in mind, the shift from an
                avowedly “eclectic” practice to one that explicitly embraces “versioning” seems to
                be directed more at influencing <hi rend="italic">how</hi> Dreiser is read than <hi
                    rend="italic">what</hi> Dreiser is read.</p>
            <div><head type="main">Acknowledgments</head>
            <p> I would like to thank Thomas P. Riggio for his guidance and intellectual generosity
                over several years, and in particular for his comments on early drafts of this
                essay. The views expressed in it, of course, are mine alone. One could not hope for
                a better collaborator than Roark Mulligan, who combines rigor and insight with
                seemingly inexhaustible patience and good humor. I am also very grateful to Andrew
                Jewell and the anonymous readers for <hi rend="italic">Scholarly Editing</hi>, whose
                comments and suggestions have been exceptionally valuable.</p></div>
        </body>
        <back>
            <div type="notes">
                <note xml:id="note1">Richard Bucci, “Tanselle’s ‘Editing without a Copy-Text’:
                    Genesis, Issues, Prospects,” <hi rend="italic">Studies in Bibliography</hi> 56
                    (2003/2004): 1–44; 7.</note>
                <note xml:id="note2">The first general editor of the Dreiser Edition was Neda M.
                    Westlake, with James L. W. West III as textual editor. Thomas P. Riggio became
                    general editor in 1986 and has been its guiding presence since, remaining as
                    textual editor after 2012, when the current author became general editor.
                    Initially at the University of Pennsylvania Press, the Edition was published by
                    Illinois University Press between 2004 and 2012, and subsequently moved to
                    University of Winchester Press, which is scheduled to publish critical editions
                    of Dreiser’s fourth novel, <hi rend="italic">The Titan</hi>, in 2016, followed
                    by his <hi rend="italic">Critical Writings</hi> and further volumes.</note>
                <note xml:id="note3">West, “Editorial Principles,” in <hi rend="italic">Sister
                        Carrie</hi> by Theodore Dreiser, Pennsylvania Edition, John C. Berkey and
                    Alice M. Winters, historical editors; James L. W. West III, textual editor; Neda
                    M. Westlake, general editor (Philadelphia: University of Pennsylvania Press,
                    1981), 580, 581, 582.</note>
                <note xml:id="note4">West, “Editorial Principles,” in Dreiser, <hi rend="italic"
                        >Sister Carrie</hi>, 580. Though an extreme definition of authorial
                    intention, West’s distinction would be elaborated in Hershel Parker, “The
                    Determinacy of the Creative Process and the ‘Authority’ of the Author’s Textual
                    Decisions,” <hi rend="italic">College Literature</hi> 10 (Spring 1983): 99–125;
                    102–3.</note>
                <note xml:id="note5">Westlake, “Preface and Acknowledgements,” in Dreiser, <hi
                        rend="italic">Sister Carrie</hi>, ix.</note>
                <note xml:id="note6">Hershel Parker, “[Review of] The Pennsylvania Edition of
                    Theodore Dreiser’s <hi rend="italic">Sister Carrie</hi>,” <hi rend="italic"
                        >Resources for American Literary Study</hi> 11 (1981): 332–36; 336. Paul
                    Eggert quotes and amplifies this argument in <hi rend="italic">Securing the
                        Past</hi>, 195.</note>
                <note xml:id="note7">See, for example, Herbert Mitgang, “After 80 Years, Publisher
                    Plans Uncut ‘Sister Carrie,’” <hi rend="italic">New York Times</hi>: Books,
                    April 17, 1981, at <ref type="url"
                        target="http://www.nytimes.com/1981/04/17/books/after-80-years-publisher-plans-uncut-sister-carrie.html?pagewanted=all"
                        >http://www.nytimes.com/1981/04/17/books/after-80-years-publisher-plans-uncut-sister-carrie.html?pagewanted=all</ref>.
                    Accessed January 10, 2016.</note>
                <note xml:id="note8">Paul Eggert, Securing the Past: Conservation in Art,
                    Architecture and Literature (Cambridge: Cambridge University Press, 2009),
                    192–98; Peter L. Shillingsburg, From Gutenberg to Google: Electronic
                    Representations of Literary Texts (Cambridge: Cambridge University Press, 2006),
                    83–84; and Shillingsburg, “Literary Documents, Texts, and Works Represented
                    Digitally,” Ecdotica 10 (2013): 76–93; 77. Eggert’s and Shillingsburg’s
                    complementary historical contextualizations of the 1981 Sister Carrie, and their
                    evident convictions that West’s project instantiates questions still vital after
                    the development of digital editing, are insights on which this essay seeks to
                    elaborate.</note>
                <note xml:id="note9">For key arguments, in addition to the Eggert, Shillingsburg,
                    and Parker cited above, see Richard Lingeman, “Sister Carrie’s Chaperones,” <hi
                        rend="italic">Nation</hi>, July 11–18, 1981, 53–57; Donald Pizer, <hi
                        rend="italic">“Sister Carrie,” American Literature</hi> 53 (January 1982):
                    731–37; and Jack Stillinger, <hi rend="italic">Multiple Authorship and the Myth
                        of Solitary Genius</hi> (New York: Oxford University Press, 1991), 157–62.
                    The debates are evenhandedly summarized by Riggio in the introduction to the
                    1998 reissue of the Pennsylvania <hi rend="italic">Sister Carrie</hi>. He also
                    notes their exhaustion, a conclusion echoed shortly afterward by both West and
                    Pizer. See Thomas P. Riggio, “Introduction,” in <hi rend="italic">Sister
                        Carrie</hi> by Theodore Dreiser (Philadelphia: University of Pennsylvania
                    Press, 1998), vi-xvi; James L. W. West III, “The <hi rend="italic">Sister
                        Carrie</hi> We’ve Come to Know,” <hi rend="italic">Dreiser Studies</hi> 32,
                    no. 2 (Fall 2001): 39–41; and Donald Pizer, “The Text of <hi rend="italic"
                        >Sister Carrie</hi>: Where We Are Now,” <hi rend="italic">Dreiser
                        Studies</hi> 32, no. 2 (Fall 2001): 42–48.</note>
                <note xml:id="note10">Donald Pizer, “Dreiser’s Novels: The Editorial Problem,” in
                        <hi rend="italic">The Editing of American Literature, 1890–1930: Essays and
                        Reviews</hi> (Lanham: Scarecrow Press, 2012), 37.</note>
                <note xml:id="note11">For their conjunction, see Donald Pizer, “Self-Censorship and
                    Textual Editing,” in <hi rend="italic">Textual Criticism and Literary
                        Interpretation</hi>, ed. Jerome J. McGann (Chicago: University of Chicago
                    Press, 1985), 144–61.</note>
                <note xml:id="note12">Lionel Trilling, “Reality in America,” in <hi rend="italic"
                        >The Liberal Imagination</hi> (New York: Viking, 1950), 13.</note>
                <note xml:id="note13">See Frederic Jameson, <hi rend="italic">The Political
                        Unconscious: Narrative as a Socially Symbolic Act</hi> (Durham, NC: Duke
                    University Press, 1981), 160, and his contribution to “Roundtable,” <hi
                        rend="italic">Journal of American Studies</hi> 48, no. 4 (2014): 1088–89;
                    and Joseph Epstein, <hi rend="italic">Partial Payments: Essays on Writers and
                        Their Lives</hi> ([1989]; New York: Norton, 1991), 260.</note>
                <note xml:id="note14">West, “The <hi rend="italic">Sister Carrie</hi> We’ve Come to
                    Know,” 41.</note>
                <note xml:id="note15">Eggert outlines these dynamics in detail in the closing three
                    chapters of <hi rend="italic">Securing the Past</hi>, 154–240.</note>
                <note xml:id="note16">West, “Textual Principles,” 581.</note>
                <note xml:id="note17">Describing the typical practices of copy-text editing, West
                    states that “The edition is therefore eclectic” (“Textual Principles,” 577), but
                    this statement of principle is balanced by his own avowedly “conservative”
                    practice as just discussed.</note>
                <note xml:id="note18">James L. W. West III, “Fair Copy, Authorial Intention, and
                    Versioning” [1994], in <hi rend="italic">Making the Archives Talk</hi>
                    (Philadelphia: Pennsylvania State University Press, 2011), 29–38; 37.</note>
                <note xml:id="note19">West, “Textual Principles,” 588–89.</note>
                <note xml:id="note20">Eggert, <hi rend="italic">Securing the Past</hi>, 195. My own
                    experience as an undergraduate in 1980s London, UK, substantiates this claim.
                    While I would never have dreamed of consulting the manuscript of <hi
                        rend="italic">Sister Carrie</hi> in the New York Public Library, or the
                    Dreiser Papers in the University of Pennsylvania Library, it seemed obvious to
                    mark up my own paperback edition with Dreiser’s cuts, using the university
                    library’s copy of the Pennsylvania <hi rend="italic">Sister Carrie</hi>.</note>
                <note xml:id="note21">The 1998 Pennsylvania version is now available as an e-book on
                    the JSTOR and Kindle platforms, regrettably without West’s textual apparatus.
                    West’s text also remains in print in the 1994 reissue of the Penguin Books
                    edition. Several editions are currently available based on the 1900 Doubleday,
                    Page text with the 1907 revision for the Dodge Edition, including significant
                    introductory and editorial matter, all of which, like the Pennsylvania and
                    Penguin Books volumes, call attention to the existence of two versions of the
                    work. The most substantial is the Norton Critical Edition, edited by Donald
                    Pizer, now in its third edition (2006). The Oxford University Press World’s
                    Classics edition, with an introduction by Lee Clark Mitchell, was reissued in
                    2009, and in the same year Signet, part of the Penguin Random House group,
                    brought out a version with an introduction by Richard Lingeman and an afterword
                    by Rachel Sarah. At time of writing (January 2016), the Schoenberg Center for
                    Electronic Text and Image at the University of Pennsylvania Library hosts online
                    digital facsimiles of three versions of the novel: the 1900 typescript used as
                    setting copy for the novel (rejected by West as copy-text in favor of Dreiser’s
                    holograph, but a document whose multiple and extensive revisions make it
                    fascinating reading), the 1900 Doubleday, Page volume, and the Pennsylvania
                    Edition. See <ref type="url"
                        target="http://www.library.upenn.edu/collections/rbm/dreiser/sc.html"
                        >http://www.library.upenn.edu/collections/rbm/dreiser/sc.html</ref>.</note>
                <note xml:id="note22">See, for example, Stillinger, <hi rend="italic">Multiple
                        Authorship</hi>, 162.</note>
                <note xml:id="note23">These phrases come from, respectively, the back cover of the
                    Penguin Books edition and the Oxford University Press catalog, both as of
                    September 2015, and the back cover of the Norton Critical Edition of <hi
                        rend="italic">Sister Carrie</hi>, 2nd edition, 1991.</note>
                <note xml:id="note24">It is also worth noting that the phrase “The Unexpurgated
                    Text,” which had featured prominently on the front cover of the Penguin Books
                    paperback edition, was relegated to the back cover when in 1994 the title
                    migrated from the Penguin American Library to the same publisher’s Classics
                    series. Perhaps a sense of unstable textuality was felt to cause some cognitive
                    dissonance with the notion of the classic.</note>
                <note xml:id="note25">West, “The <hi rend="italic">Sister Carrie</hi> We’ve Come to
                    Know,” 41.</note>
                <note xml:id="note26">Shillingsburg, “Literary Documents, Texts, and Works
                    Represented Digitally.”</note>
                <note xml:id="note27">West, <hi rend="italic">Making the Archives Talk</hi>, 1–2.
                    Also, see especially the first three essays collected in that volume: “The
                    Scholarly Editor as Biographer,” 6–16; “Editorial Theory and the Act of
                    Submission,” 17–28; and “Fair Copy, Authorial Intention, and Versioning,”
                    29–38.</note>
                <note xml:id="note28">This is a brief summary of the approach explained and
                    justified by James L. W. West III, “Editorial Principles,” in <hi rend="italic"
                        >Jennie Gerhardt</hi> by Theodore Dreiser (Philadelphia: University of
                    Pennsylvania Press, 1992), 485–96</note>
                <note xml:id="note29">James L. W. West III, “Introduction,” <hi rend="italic">Jennie
                        Gerhardt</hi>, x, and “Editorial Principles,” <hi rend="italic">Jennie
                        Gerhardt</hi>, 485, 495</note>
                <note xml:id="note30">For example, while conceding the possible validity of
                    versioning as a critical approach to <hi rend="italic">Sister Carrie</hi> and
                        <hi rend="italic">Jennie Gerhardt</hi>, West argues that later works such as
                        <hi rend="italic">The Financier</hi> and <hi rend="italic">The Titan</hi>
                    demand an eclectic approach (“Fair Copy, Authorial Intention, and Versioning,”
                    in <hi rend="italic">Making the Archives Talk</hi>, 37). On the face of it, this
                    seems in exact opposition to the Dreiser Edition’s trajectory from eclecticism
                    to versioning, but as is discussed below, the situation is more complex.</note>
                <note xml:id="note31">Riggio, “Introduction,” in <hi rend="italic">Sister
                        Carrie</hi> (1998), xi.</note>
                <note xml:id="note32">See Donald H. Reiman, <hi rend="italic">Romantic Texts and
                        Contexts</hi> (Columbia: University of Missouri Press, 1987), 180.</note>
                <note xml:id="note33">Jude Davies and Thomas P. Riggio, “Editorial Procedures,” in
                        <hi rend="italic">The Titan</hi> by Theodore Dreiser, edited by Roark
                    Mulligan; Jude Davies, general editor; Thomas P. Riggio, textual editor
                    (Winchester, UK: Winchester University Press, forthcoming, 2016).</note>
                <note xml:id="note34">Editorial Principles,” in <hi rend="italic">The Financier</hi>
                    by Theodore Dreiser, edited by Roark Mulligan; Thomas P. Riggio, general editor
                    (Urbana: University of Illinois Press, 2010), 621–24; 621, 622.</note>
                <note xml:id="note35">Making this point in “Fair Copy, Authorial Intention, and
                    Versioning,” West draws the conclusion from the absence of an authorial “fair
                    copy” for The Financier and The Titan that an eclectic approach is required. See
                    <hi rend="italic">Making the Archives Talk</hi>, 29–30, 36–37.)</note>
            </div>
        </back>
    </text>
</TEI>
