<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<?oxygen RNGSchema="http://www.scholarlyediting.org/scholarlyediting.rng" type="xml"?>
<!--I wasn't sure how to deal with the figures and the table. 
    I assume they haven't been created yet? I treated the table as an image, but you may want to change this--> 
<!--There are a number of cases in which text should be in superscript e.g. the los in "Advertencias para los 
    confessores de los Naturales " I wasn't sure how to deal with this-->
<!--The accent marks appear okay in the XML, but I'm not sure if they will display alright. Let me know
    if I need to replace them.-->
<!--I was unsure about how to deal with sections and what appeared to be subsections; these may need to be changed-->
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xml:lang="eng">
    <teiHeader>
        <fileDesc>
            <titleStmt>
                <title level="a" type="main">Representing the Long History of Early Modern Printed
                    Objects</title>
                <title level="a" type="sub">The Archaeology of a Book</title>
                <author key="Alpert-Abrams, Hannah">Hannah Alpert-Abrams</author>
            </titleStmt>
            <editionStmt>
                <edition>
                    <date>2016</date>
                </edition>
            </editionStmt>
            <publicationStmt>
                <idno type="file">essay.alpertabrams</idno>
                <authority>Scholary Editing: The Annual of the Association for Documentary
                    Editing</authority>
                <address>
 <addrLine>http://www.scholarlyediting.org</addrLine>
</address>
                <publisher>Association for Documentary Editing</publisher>
                <publisher>University of Nebraska&#8211;Lincoln</publisher>
                <distributor>
                    <name>Center for Digital Research in the Humanities</name>
                    <address>
<addrLine>319 Love Library</addrLine>
<addrLine>University of Nebraska&#8211;Lincoln</addrLine>
<addrLine>Lincoln, NE 68588-4100</addrLine>
<addrLine>http://cdrh.unl.edu</addrLine>
 </address>
                </distributor>
                <date>2016</date>
                <availability>
                    <p>Scholary Editing: The Annual of the Association for Documentary Editing is
                        freely distributed by the Association for Documentary Editing and the Center
                        for Digital Research in the Humanities at the University of Nebraska-Lincoln
                        and licensed under a Creative Commons Attribution-NonCommercial-ShareAlike
                        3.0 Unported License</p>
                </availability>
            </publicationStmt>
            <seriesStmt>
                <title level="j">Scholarly Editing: The Annual of the Association for Documentary
                    Editing</title>
                <respStmt>
                    <resp>editor</resp>
                    <name xml:id="ag" key="Gailey, Amanda A.">Amanda Gailey</name>
                </respStmt>
                <respStmt>
                    <resp>editor</resp>
                    <name xml:id="awj" key="Jewell, Andrew W.">Andrew Jewell</name>
                </respStmt>
                <idno type="vol">37</idno>
                <idno type="ISSN">2167-1257</idno>
            </seriesStmt>
            <sourceDesc>
                <bibl>
                    <note>Born digital.</note>
                </bibl>
            </sourceDesc>
        </fileDesc>
        <revisionDesc>
            <change when="2016-03-23"><name xml:id="gk" key="Kirilloff, Gabi"> Gabi Kirilloff</name>
                markup in TEI XML</change>
        </revisionDesc>
    </teiHeader>
    <text>
        <front>
            <head type="main">Representing the Long History of Early Modern Printed Objects</head>
            <head type="sub">The Archaeology of a Book</head>
            <byline>Hannah Alpert-Abrams</byline>
        </front>
        <body>
            <div type="section">
                <p>Consider the digital facsimile. Figure 1 shows the not-uncommon display of a
                    not-uncommon book: one of several dozen surviving copies of a confessional
                    manual printed in Mexico City around 1600, many of which have been made
                    available in facsimile through the Primeros Libros collection of
                    sixteenth-century Mexican imprints.<ptr target="#note1" xml:id="nr1" n="1"/> The
                    book is displayed in the web browser as though it were resting open in front of
                    us, though those who work with early books know that its physical original would
                    be gently cradled in velvet or foam if read in the archives. To navigate, the
                    reader can flip to a specific page or move sequentially through the text, as
                    though she were going to read it, page by page, from front matter to index. The
                    web interface for the book&#8212;like the web interfaces for a scanned document
                    in Google Books or HathiTrust&#8212;does not require that the reader engage with
                    the book the way she would with a print edition. But it does encourage users to
                    understand engagement with the book in the subjunctive, as a metaphor for a more
                    material reading.</p>
                <p>The book displayed in Figure 1 is a digital facsimile of the <hi rend="italic"
                        >Advertencias para los confessores de los Naturales</hi> (<hi rend="italic"
                        >Primera parte</hi>).<ptr target="#note2" xml:id="nr2" n="2"/> This
                    two-volume trilingual book is highly technical and borrows heavily from other
                    texts; despite the fact that more copies of this book survive than do those of
                    any other printed volume from the period, it is readable today only to a select
                    few. For that small audience, the reader-oriented interface of the Primeros
                    Libros website may be a useful environment for textual consumption. For the rest
                    of us, however, engagement with this printed book (or its digital facsimile)
                    happens outside the text and the reading format accessed online. Whether our
                    interest is production history, historical reading practices, aesthetics, or
                    provenance, we must conduct our research along the margins of interfaces like
                    that of the Primeros Libros website.</p>
                <figure>
                    <head>Figure 1: Screenshot of a book in the Primeros Libros collection, as
                        viewed in a web browser. (ID: pl_blac_047_98)</head>
                    <figDesc>Figure 1: Screenshot of a book in the Primeros Libros collection, as
                        viewed in a web browser. (ID: pl_blac_047_98)</figDesc>
                    <graphic url="images/essay.alpertabrams.01.jpg"/>
                </figure>
                <p>More fundamentally, even if reading is our primary goal, the reader-oriented
                    environment of the digital surrogate tends to erase the historicity of the
                    document’s construction and use. It has become a popular truth that old books
                    have a history that extends beyond the text on the page: in the words of Jerome
                    McGann, “documents are far from self-transparent. They are riven with the
                    multiple histories of their own making.”<ptr target="#note3" xml:id="nr3" n="3"
                    /> These histories embed themselves along the margins of the books, weave their
                    way into the bindings, are burned into the edges of the page. Bibliographers,
                    whose work depends on the exposition of these minute details, often find the
                    digital surrogate insufficient to the task of bibliographical display. “Put
                    briefly,” David McKitterick writes, “the two-dimensional screen cannot
                    illustrate adequately a three-dimensional object.”<ptr target="#note4"
                        xml:id="nr4" n="4"/></p>
                <p>When taken literally, McKitterick’s argument may be true: no digital interface
                    can replicate the feel, the weight, the smell of the printed book. But it
                    depends on the fallacious claim that bibliographical research is best conducted
                    in the environment of the reading room. Material engagement with rare books
                    shapes the affective framework through which we form our imaginative view of the
                    past; this can be represented but not replicated online. In contrast, other
                    aspects of the material book, like the <hi rend="italic">marcas de fuego</hi>
                    burned into the edges of books in colonial Mexican libraries, are digitally
                    representable signifiers that point directly to a book’s history of use; if they
                    are not present in most digital facsimiles today, that is not because they can’t
                    be. Indeed, some aspects of a historical book, such as damaged or revised pages,
                    are best observed through the processing power enabled by digital
                        representation.<ptr target="#note5" xml:id="nr5" n="5"/> In thinking about
                    the representation of historical books in digital facsimile, then, it is worth
                    being attentive both to how our engagement with historical books is framed, and
                    to which material qualities of the historical book are highlighted or disappear
                    within those structures. In offering a careful analysis of these structures of
                    information, this article seeks to clarify the role of the book historian in
                    paving alternative paths for engaging with digital editions.</p>
                <p>The first section of this article focuses on the frameworks that shape our
                    engagement with historical books, considering specifically the volumes in the
                    Primeros Libros collection of books printed in the first century of the Spanish
                    colonization of Mexico (1539–1601). It begins by considering how modern
                    structures for framing the historical book, from catalogue entries to web
                    interfaces and library displays, have a deterministic effect on our relationship
                    with the historical book. It argues specifically that these frameworks depend on
                    two historically determined assumptions about the nature of the early colonial
                    book: its coherence as a standalone unit and its originary status as a static
                    object fixed in time at the moment of its production.</p>
                <p>Against these frameworks, in the second section, this article describes the
                    specific material qualities of early colonial Mexican books that disrupt these
                    premises. Colophons, catchwords, title pages, woodcuts, and elisions all bring
                    into question the concept of the historical book as an atomic unit, suggesting
                    that books may have functioned as more materially and textually fluid objects in
                    sixteenth-century Mexico. Material transformations from later in a book’s
                    life&#8212;rebinding, trimming, branding, and writing marginal notes&#8212;all
                    suggest a long history of interpretive engagement with the historical book,
                    bridging the gap between the moment of production and the present day.
                    Collectively, these material qualities suggest the need for a critical reframing
                    of early modern printed books that highlights more directly the multiple,
                    historically determined ways of knowing that they contain; they also point us
                    toward interface design considerations that will enhance scholarly attempts to
                    engage those layered histories.</p>
                <p>To address this need, the final section of this article introduces the
                    “Archaeology of a Book” project, a web resource that describes the history of
                    the <hi rend="italic">Advertencias para los confessores de los Naturales</hi>.
                    “Archaeology of a Book” was designed to offer an alternative mode of engaging
                    with facsimiles in the Primeros Libros collection that would explicitly address
                    the challenges of representing a historical book’s malleability and its dynamic
                    history. Though it is neither a critical nor a documentary edition, the
                    “Archaeology of a Book” project models a critical approach to the digital
                    representation of the social history of texts that has implications for many
                    kinds of digital publication. It shares many of the concerns that Jerome McGann
                    described recently in <hi rend="italic">The New Republic of Letters</hi> when he
                    called for a New Philology that extends the social history of the book into the
                    digital domain.<ptr target="#note6" xml:id="nr6" n="6"/> The radical de-emphasis
                    of the written word in this project, however, is a point of divergence from
                    McGann’s approach. In its place, the “Archaeology of a Book” project centers the
                    virtual collation and collection made possible through digital facsimile
                    projects in order to model a dynamic exploration of the long history of the
                    book.</p>
            </div>
            <div type="section">
                <head type="main">Section 1: Frameworks for Seeing Historical Documents</head>
                <p>A printed book in sixteenth-century Mexico was a very different object from a
                    book&#8212;modern or historical&#8212;as we see it today, both because of
                    historically specific European ideas about textuality, and because of the
                    specific cultural context of New Spain. In Europe, as Jeffrey Todd Knight
                    describes, the readers and writers of Renaissance books thought of them less as
                    the unique atomic units we expect today than as what he calls “aggregations of
                    text,” a status that makes itself known through both the intertextuality and the
                    material recomposition of books during this period.<ptr target="#note7"
                        xml:id="nr7" n="7"/> In New Spain, this difference is reinforced by the fact
                    that early colonial books existed within a system of textual communication that
                    included indigenous objects of knowledge transfer (including pictographic
                    codices and other objects), scribal networks operated by both Castilian and
                    indigenous writers, and printing operations that produced a variety of document
                        types.<ptr target="#note8" xml:id="nr8" n="8"/> The printed book in Mexico
                    was thus neither the first nor the primary means of textual communication: it
                    arrived in Mexico City as a latecomer on the scene, decades after the
                    introduction of alphabetic writing, centuries after the development of
                    pictographic communication, and alongside a broad array of nontextual objects of
                    communication. Furthermore, given that most printed books from this period were
                    produced by mendicant friars as tools in the conversion of indigenous peoples,
                    these objects had a particular rhetorical function that is not easily apparent
                    today.</p>
                <p>It is not surprising, then, that early colonial books would fail to fit neatly
                    into the categories and frameworks through which we describe books today. Yet
                    surprise often characterizes the response that bibliographers have toward these
                    historical documents. As the nineteenth-century Mexican bibliographer Joaquín
                    García Icazbalceta remarked, with some consternation, of the <hi rend="italic"
                        >Advertencias</hi>, “Seis o más ejemplares de las <hi rend="italic"
                        >Advertencias</hi> he visto, y casi todos presentan diferencias entre
                        si.”<ptr target="#note9" xml:id="nr9" n="9"/> Francisco Guerra made a
                    similar&#8212;if more dramatic&#8212;comment with regard to the <hi
                        rend="italic">Opera medicinalia, in quibus quam plurima extant scitu medico
                        necessaria</hi>, a medical text printed in Mexico City in 1570, when he
                    wrote “es un libro que entre los bibliófilos ha sido temido como una plaga.”<ptr
                        target="#note10" xml:id="nr10" n="10"/> These responses suggest broader
                    anxieties over the tension between the malleability of the sixteenth-century
                    book and the rigidity of modern bibliographical frameworks. It is because we
                    expect historical books to conform to modern standards that their failure to do
                    so produces such astonishment.</p>
                <p>At the same time, by attempting to resituate the historical book in the moment of
                    its production, we run the risk of artificially imposing originary status onto
                    dynamic textual objects. By originary status I refer to the tendency to treat a
                    historical book as an original text and as a point of entry into the moment of
                    its production, rather than as a dynamic and constantly changing textual object.
                    Even as catalogue entries impose twentieth-century categories onto
                    sixteenth-century objects, they also tend to fix historical books in the time
                    and place of their production. Later transformations&#8212;like the green and
                    gold binding that Joaquín García Icazbalceta used on two exemplars of the <hi
                        rend="italic">Advertencias</hi>&#8212;disappear.</p>
                <p>This section asks the question, how do bibliographical frameworks impose textual
                    coherence and originary status onto historical books? To answer it, I turn to
                    catalogue entries and digital interfaces for the early colonial book. Digital
                    interfaces like the website for the Primeros Libros collection recreate the
                    structure of a library or special collection in ways that emphasize certain
                    kinds of textual difference (rareness, originality, fragility). At the same
                    time, they depend on catalogue entries and descriptive metadata designed
                    primarily for today’s libraries to organize their collections of modern printed
                    books. As this section will show, inconsistencies in the data represented by
                    this universal structure of information are indicative of historical transitions
                    in the ontology of the book.</p>
                <div type="subsection">
                    <head type="sub">Interfaces</head>
                    <p>At a recent event on sixteenth-century printed books at Biblioteca Lafragua
                        in Puebla, Mexico, attendees lined up to observe one of the treasures from
                        the Lafragua’s collection: an original edition of the <hi rend="italic"
                            >Opera medicinalia, in quibus quam plurima extant scitu medico
                            necessaria</hi> by Francisco Bravo.<ptr target="#note11" xml:id="nr11"
                            n="11"/> Printed in 1570 in Mexico City by Pedro Ocharte, the <hi
                            rend="italic">Opera medicinalia</hi> was the first medical text printed
                        in New Spain. Following a panel presentation detailing the history of the
                        book, during the time usually reserved for questions, the audience was
                        invited to observe firsthand one of only three surviving copies of the
                        historical text. In a ritual that one attendee described as akin to a wake
                        or a royal reception, scholars walked in a slow-moving line past the book,
                        opened to a select page and held secure in its glass case. Each visitor was
                        given a moment to observe the book, then moved on.</p>
                    <p>The event was held immediately following the annual partner meeting of the
                        Primeros Libros de las Américas consortium, of which the Biblioteca Lafragua
                        is a founding member. The consortium is a group of scholars and librarians
                        from across Spain and the Americas dedicated to producing digital facsimiles
                        of every surviving copy of the so-called American incunables&#8212;books
                        printed before 1601 in the Americas. Concurrent with the two-day symposium,
                        held at the Universidad Iberoamericana in Mexico City, a new body of texts
                        was released on the Primeros Libros website, including a digital facsimile
                        of Lafragua’s copy of the <hi rend="italic">Opera medicinalia</hi>. Even as
                        the audience traveled to Puebla to commune with the original volume, users
                        anywhere in the world were able for the first time to flip virtually through
                        the pages of the book, zoom in on difficult-to-see images, and examine this
                        book alongside hundreds of other volumes in the Primeros Libros digital
                        collection.</p>
                    <p>Though it might be easy to see this moment as the ironic juxtaposition of two
                        ways of engaging with a book, I would suggest that these two moments
                        represent the continuation of a single way of thinking about historical
                        documents. In the glass-encased copy of the <hi rend="italic">Opera
                            medicinalia</hi>, we see a book that has been stripped almost completely
                        of its value as a textual object (no reading allowed). It signifies,
                        instead, through the aesthetic of its presentation. The glass frame reminds
                        us that the book is valuable because it is rare (one of three surviving
                        copies), original (the first medical text printed in the Americas), and
                        fragile (protected by glass). Though we know that medical knowledge was
                        recorded and communicated by other means long before the arrival of the
                        Spaniards in Tenochtitlan, and though we know that at least some of the
                        information in the <hi rend="italic">Opera medicinalia</hi> is the
                        near-duplication of medical information already printed elsewhere, the
                        combination of place, technology, and content allows this book to signify a
                        certain kind of historical origin. The fragility of the book itself
                        reinforces the idea that reading this book would bring us back to the
                        beginning of Mexican intellectual history.</p>
                    <p>To read the book, however, we’ll have to turn to the digital
                        facsimile&#8212;another book preserved under glass. The Primeros Libros
                        website, where the book is hosted, opens with a splash page that visualizes
                        a nineteenth-century library: sixteenth-century Mexican books rebound and
                        shelved according to nineteenth-century conventions. This historical shift
                        relocates the books in the context not of the moment of their production,
                        but rather of the moment when the bibliographical work of Joaquín García
                        Icazbalceta and others first described the category of the Mexican
                        incunabula and its importance in recording the origins of Mexican
                        historiography. The website’s affective framework, in other words, is one
                        that reinforces the originary status of the early colonial printed
                        books.</p>
                    <p>Upon entering the website, the user is reoriented toward a more
                        twentieth-century way of accessing documents. Browsing is enabled according
                        to the categories commonly used for cataloguing (by owning institution,
                        language, year, printer, author, keyword). Upon selecting a book, the user
                        is led to a descriptive catalogue entry; a link in the description then
                        opens an e-book display, as shown in Figure 1. The primary effect of this
                        structure is to mimic precisely the sequence of decisions that a library
                        user would go through in accessing a book from the library stacks. At the
                        same time, this modernizing apparatus functions as another layer of
                        protection for the document itself: like the glass case, its very
                        replicability reinforces the vulnerability of the original form.</p>
                    <p>The display for the Primeros Libros website is not unique: it mimics other
                        book readers like Google Books, HathiTrust, or even Kindle, all designed for
                        indiscriminate use across production periods. There is no differentiation
                        between the sixteenth-century textual object and one produced today. The
                        result is a book that is viewed according to a unique textual mythology, and
                        read from an ahistorical perspective</p>
                </div>
                <div type="subsection">
                    <head type="sub">Catalogues</head>
                    <p>Because library catalogues are utilitarian and ubiquitous, it is easy to
                        overlook the important role they play in framing textual consumption. Most
                        scholarly interest in library catalogues is based on practical objectives:
                        improving interoperability, discoverability, and information retrieval.
                        Nevertheless, some researchers have made a case for closer attention to the
                        catalogue by questioning the epistemological implications of catalogues as
                        classification systems. Jens-Erik Mai, for example, argues that all library
                        classification systems are harmful because each applies a single
                        interpretive framework to information that is diverse and often
                        incompatible, writing “One challenge for information professionals [. . .]
                        is to provide access tools that minimize the harm done by
                            classifications.”<ptr target="#note12" xml:id="nr12" n="12"/> Rather
                        than evaluating the harm done (or good enacted) by catalogue entries, my
                        purpose here is to understand the interpretive work that these structures
                        perform in shaping our engagement with the colonial book.</p>
                    <p>Table 1, which shows entries for the <hi rend="italic">Advertencias</hi>
                        taken from online catalogues for institutions in the United States, Mexico,
                        Chile, and Spain, illustrates the structures of information that shape
                        access to both printed volumes and digital facsimiles. The entries in Table
                        1 have been selected from a larger data set at random for brevity, and the
                        table collapses multiple attributes into a single category&#8212;an attempt
                        to manage the extensive incompatibilities across catalogues for this
                        document. A brief survey of this table makes clear that, while the presence
                        of competing international metadata standards makes compatibility across
                        political and linguistic boundaries challenging, seemingly fundamental
                        categories like author, title, place, and date are inconsistent even within
                        a single country.</p>
                    <table rows="13" cols="6">
                        <head type="main">Table 1: Select Catalogue Entries for Original Exemplars of the <hi
                                rend="italic">Advertencias</hi></head>
                        <!--1-->
                        <row role="label">
                            <cell role="data">Library</cell>
                            <cell role="data">Author/autor</cell>
                            <cell role="data">Title/titulo</cell>
                            <cell role="data">Publisher / editorial / published / pie impren /
                                publicación</cell>
                            <cell role="data">Lugar de publicación / place of publication</cell>
                            <cell role="data">date / año</cell>
                        </row>
                        <!--2-->
                        <row role="data">
                            <cell role="data">Arizona State University Libraries</cell>
                            <cell role="data">Juan Bautista, fray, 1555-ca. 1613</cell>
                            <cell role="data">Advertencias. Para los confessores de los naturales
                                [electronic resource]/ Compvestas por el padre fray Ioan Baptista,
                                de la Orden del seraphico padre sanct Francisco, lector de
                                theologia, y guardian del Conuento de Sactiago Tlatilulco: dela
                                Prouincia del sancto euangelio. Primera- [segunda] parte. Con
                                priuilegio.</cell>
                            <cell role="data">[publisher] En Mexico: Enel conuento de Sanctiago
                                Tlatilulco, Por M. Ocharte / año 1600.</cell>
                            <cell role="data">[hierarchical place] Mexico -- Mexico City</cell>
                            <cell role="data">none</cell>
                        </row>
                        <!--3-->
                        <row role="data">
                            <cell role="data">UC Berkeley Library (Bancroft)</cell>
                            <cell role="data">Juan Bautista de la Concepción, Saint, 1561-1613 ¶
                                Ocharte, Melchior, 1571-1616? Book producer ¶ Ocharte Figueros,
                                Ludouicus. Book producer</cell>
                            <cell role="data">Advertencias. Para los confessores de los naturales.
                                Compvestas por el padre fray Ioan Baptista, de la Orden del
                                seraphico padre sanct Francisco, lector de theologia, y guardian del
                                Conuento de Sanctiago Tlatilulco: dela Prouincia del sancto
                                euangelio. Primera- [segunda] parte. Con priuilegio.</cell>
                            <cell role="data">[published] En Mexico, Enel Conuento de Sanctiago
                                Tlatilulco, Por M. Ocharte. Año 1600.</cell>
                            <cell role="data">Mexico City Mexico</cell>
                            <cell role="data">none</cell>
                        </row>
                        <!--4-->
                        <row role="data">
                            <cell role="data">Bibliotecas del Tencológico de Monterrey
                                [cervantina]</cell>
                            <cell role="data">Juan Bautista, 1660-1700</cell>
                            <cell role="data">Advertencias para los Confessores de los Naturales /
                                Compvestas por el padre fray Ioan Baptista, de la Orden del
                                seraphico padre sanct Francisco, lector de theologia, y guardian del
                                Conuento de Sanctiago Tlatilulco: dela Prouincia del sancto
                                euangelio. Primera­ [segunda] parte. Con priuilegio</cell>
                            <cell role="data">[pie impren] En Mexico : En el Conuento de Sanctiago
                                Tlatilulco, Por M. Ocharte, 1600.</cell>
                            <cell role="data">none</cell>
                            <cell role="data">none</cell>
                        </row>
                        <!--5-->
                        <row role="data">
                            <cell role="data">Biblioteca nacional de antropología e Historia</cell>
                            <cell role="data">Juan Bautista, fray, 1555-ca. 1613.</cell>
                            <cell role="data">Confessionario en lengva mexicana y castellana : con
                                muchas advertencias muy neceffarias para los c</cell>
                            <cell role="data">Melchior Ochiarte</cell>
                            <cell role="data">Sanctiago Taltilulco [México]</cell>
                            <cell role="data">none</cell>
                        </row>
                        <!--6-->
                        <row role="data">
                            <cell role="data">Biblioteca nacional de antropología e Historia</cell>
                            <cell role="data">Juan Bautista, fray, 1555-ca. 1613.</cell>
                            <cell role="data">Advertencias para los confessores de los naturales /
                                compuestas por el Padre Fray Juan Bautista de la Orden del Seráfico
                                Padre San Francisco…</cell>
                            <cell role="data">[area de Publicación] México: En el convento de
                                Sanctiago Tlatilulco, por M. Ocharte, 1600</cell>
                        </row>
                        <!--7-->
                        <row role="data">
                            <cell role="data">Biblioteca Nacional de España</cell>
                            <cell role="data">Juan Bautista (O.F.M.) (1555-ca. 1613) ¶ Ocharte,
                                Melchor, imp. ; ¶ ocharte figueroa I</cell>
                            <cell role="data">Aduertencias para los confessores de los Naturales
                                [Texto impreso]/ compuestas por el padre Fray Ioan Baptista, de la
                                Orden del seraphico Padre Sanct Francisco…; primera [-segunda]
                                parte</cell>
                            <cell role="data">[publicación] En Mexico : en el conuento de Sanctiago
                                Tlatilulco, por M. Ocharte, 1600(excudebat Ludouicis Ocharte
                                Figueroa ...), 1601</cell>
                        </row>
                        <!--8-->
                        <row role="data">
                            <cell role="data">Centro de Estudios de Historia de México</cell>
                            <cell role="data">BAUTISTA, Fray Juan</cell>
                            <cell role="data">Advertencias para los Confessores de los
                                naturales.</cell>
                            <cell role="data">[pie de imprenta] MEXICO: M. Ocharte, 1600</cell>
                            <cell role="data">none</cell>
                        </row>
                        <!--9-->
                        <row role="data">
                            <cell role="data">Kroch Library, Cornell</cell>
                            <cell role="data">Juan Bautista, fray, 1555-aproximately 1613</cell>
                            <cell role="data">Advertencias para los confessores de los naturales
                                compuestas por el padre fray Joan Baptista.</cell>
                            <cell role="data">[published] Convento de Sanctiago Tlatilulco, Mexico :
                                M. Ocharte, 1600.</cell>
                            <cell role="data">none</cell>
                        </row>
                        <!--10-->
                        <row role="data">
                            <cell role="data">Rubenstein Library, Duke</cell>
                            <cell role="data">compuestas por el padre fray Joan Baptista. ¶ Juan
                                Bautista, fray, 1555­approximately 1613.</cell>
                            <cell role="data">Advertencias para los confessores de los naturales
                                compuestas por el padre fray Joan Baptista.</cell>
                            <cell role="data">Mexico, en el conuento de Sanctiago Tlatilulco, por M.
                                Ocharte, 1600.</cell>
                            <cell role="data">none</cell>
                        </row>
                        <!--11-->
                        <row role="data">
                            <cell role="data">Gordon College: Jenks Library</cell>
                            <cell role="data">Juan Bautista, 1555­ (Author).</cell>
                            <cell role="data">Advertencias. Para los confessores de los naturales.
                                Compvestas por el padre fray Ioan Baptista, de la Orden del
                                seraphico padre Sanct Francisco, lector de theologia, y guardian del
                                conuento de Sanctiago Tlatilulco: dela Prouincia del Sancto
                                Euangelio ... Con priuilegio.</cell>
                            <cell role="data">[publisher] En Mexico, En el Conuento de Sanctiago
                                Tlatilulco, Por M. Ocharte, ano 1600­[01]</cell>
                            <cell role="data">none</cell>
                            <cell role="data">[date] año 1600 [i.e. 1601] </cell>
                        </row>
                        <!--12-->
                        <row role="data">
                            <cell role="data">Dumbarton Oaks</cell>
                            <cell role="data">Juan Bautista, fray, 1555-approximately 1613. ¶
                                Ocharte, Melchior, 1571-1616?, printer. ¶ Ocharte Figueros, Luís,
                                printer. ¶ Montt, Luis, 1848-1909, former owner.</cell>
                            <cell role="data">Advertencias para los confessores de los naturales /
                                compvestas por el padre Ioan Baptista, de la Orden del seraphico
                                padre sanct Francisco, lector de theologia, y guardian del Conuento
                                de Sanctiago Tlatilulco: dela Prouincia del sancto euangelio.</cell>
                            <cell role="data">[published]: En Mexico : Enel Conuento de Sanctiago
                                Tlatilulco, por M. Ocharte, año 1600 [i.e. 1601] </cell>
                            <cell role="data">none</cell>
                        </row>
                        <!--13-->
                        <row role="data">
                            <cell role="data">UNAM</cell>
                            <cell role="data">Juan Bautista, fray, 1555-ca. 1613</cell>
                            <cell role="data">Advertencias para los confessores de los naturales /
                                compvestas por el padre fray Ioan Baptista, de la Orden del
                                Seraphico Padre Sanct Francisco…</cell>
                            <cell role="data">En el Convento de Santiago Tlatilulco, por M.
                                Ocharte,</cell>
                            <cell role="data">En México</cell>
                            <cell role="data">[año] 1600</cell>
                        </row>
                    </table>
                    <p>What this reveals, as metadata specialists have long known, is that the
                        categories through which we orient ourselves to even the most
                        straightforward entities are difficult to pin down. Even with the help of
                        controlled vocabularies, and despite the fact that most entries are drawn
                        directly from the title page of the book (shown in Figure 2), not a single
                        element was replicated perfectly across all catalogues.<ptr target="#note13"
                            xml:id="nr13" n="13"/> The introduction of human error multiplies these
                        variations, which serves as an opportunity to reflect on the important,
                        difficult, and undervalued labor of cataloguers. But the errors in this
                        catalogue are not random; they point to underlying uncertainties about the
                        nature of the historical book.</p>
                    <figure>
                        <head>Figure 2: Three known title pages for the <hi rend="italic"
                                >Advertencias</hi>. The images on the left and right are from
                            exemplars held by the Benson Latin American Collection. The image in the
                            center is from an exemplar held by the Biblioteca Palafoxiana. All
                            images from the Primeros Libros collection. (IDs: pl_blac_047_7;
                            pl_plfx_011_3; pl_blac_048_7) </head>
                        <figDesc>Figure 2: Three known title pages for the Advertencias. The images
                            on the left and right are from exemplars held by the Benson Latin
                            American Collection. The image in the center is from an exemplar held by
                            the Biblioteca Palafoxiana. All images from the Primeros Libros
                            collection. (IDs: pl_blac_047_7; pl_plfx_011_3; pl_blac_048_7)</figDesc>
                        <graphic url="images/essay.alpertabrams.02.jpg"/>
                    </figure>
                    <p>This is apparent, for example, in the spelling variations of the many
                        “titles” for the <hi rend="italic">Advertencias</hi>. In some cases,
                        historical orthography (<hi rend="italic">compvesta, Ioan</hi>) has been
                        replaced with a modern equivalent (<hi rend="italic">compuesta, Juan</hi>);
                        in other cases, modern orthography (<hi rend="italic">Advertencias</hi>) has
                        been replaced with a historical variant not present in the book (<hi
                            rend="italic">Aduertencias</hi>). Capitalization and punctuation reveal
                        similar inconsistencies: while the decorative capitalization of the title
                        page is never kept intact in the catalogue entry, several Mexican libraries
                        have introduced capitalizations that conform to the Anglophone standard
                        (capitalizing <hi rend="italic">Confessores</hi>), while many North American
                        libraries maintain the standard Mexican form (capitalizing only the first
                        word in the title). Despite their simplicity, these orthographic differences
                        mark an underlying uncertainty about the standards to which the text should
                        conform. According to whose parameters do we demarcate the author, title,
                        and place of publication for a historical document? What kind of
                        interpretive work happens when we produce catalogue entries for historical
                        documents? The implication here is that catalogue entries don’t merely
                        describe the documents they represent; they also contain ways of
                        understanding the document that go beyond the metadata structure.</p>
                    <p>A still more fundamental incompatibility between historical books and modern
                        cataloguing practices is obscured by these inconsistencies. The familiar
                        categories of catalogue entries&#8212;author, title, place,
                        publisher&#8212;combine to describe a single, unique textual entity: a book.
                        As Knight observes, however, “books have not always existed in discrete,
                        self-enclosed units. In the early handpress era, the printed work was
                        relatively malleable and experimental&#8212;a thing to actively shape,
                        expand, and resituate as one desired.”<ptr target="#note14" xml:id="nr14"
                            n="14"/> The malleability of the historical book is embedded in the
                        documents as they come down to us, and shows itself in the insufficiencies
                        of catalogue entries. For example, though almost all catalogues name the
                        author of the <hi rend="italic">Advertencias</hi> as “Juan Bautista, fray,
                        1555–approximately 1613,” as suggested by the Library of Congress Name
                        Authority File, several include a separate or third “author” entry to
                        account for the other individuals involved in the production of the book,
                        including Melch[i]or Ocharte, the printer credited on the title page, and L.
                        Figueroa Ocharte, the printer credited in the colophon.<ptr target="#note15"
                            xml:id="nr15" n="15"/> In other cases, entries include additional titles
                        to represent the binding of multiple books in one skin.<ptr target="#note16"
                            xml:id="nr16" n="16"/> As in the case of the orthographic variation, in
                        these examples catalogue categories reveal the malleability of the
                        historical book relative to the terms we use to describe it.</p>
                    <p>This malleability is even more pronounced when we consider the interpretive
                        changes that books tend to undergo over the long history of their use. As
                        books move between religious libraries, private collections, public
                        libraries, and international archives, they play strikingly different roles
                        in the public imagination. This social dimension of the historical book is
                        often recorded through the catalogue element of “provenance” or “notes” or
                        even “author”&#8212;if it is recorded at all. As the Table 1 shows,
                        catalogues only occasionally provide ownership dates, and are never explicit
                        about gaps in the known provenance of the book. Furthermore, though
                        catalogues will sometimes alert the user to the presence of ownership marks
                        on the body of the book, they only occasionally describe more significant
                        transformations, such as rebinding, trimming, or editing the document. In
                        omitting this information, like the glass case for the <hi rend="italic"
                            >Opera medicinalia</hi>, they impose a static condition on the book that
                        I have been referring to as “originary.” As the subsequent sections will
                        show, however, alternate frameworks for understanding the historical textual
                        object can allow us to recenter the dynamism of the book over time.</p>
                </div>
            </div>
            <div type="section">
                <head type="main">Section 2: Reframing the Early Colonial Book</head>
                <p>In the prior section, I suggested that interfaces and catalogue entries reinforce
                    structures of information that tend to erase the historical significance of
                    early colonial books by replicating modern book forms. In this section, I
                    propose an alternative model for analyzing the parameters of the historical book
                    based on two axes: malleability and historicity. In this context, the term
                    malleability is contrasted with the coherence of a modern printed book as an
                    atomic unit. It refers to the ways that the boundaries of colonial books blur
                    and shift throughout their production, and is determined by the processes that
                    bring a book into being during the (sometimes long) period of its development as
                    a textual object, from composition to printing and binding. This can include the
                    borrowing of earlier texts; acts of coauthorship, transcription, and
                    translation; the production of front matter and errata; and the censorship
                    processes. Historicity, in this context, is contrasted with the ahistorical or
                    originary status embedded in modern frameworks for historical books. It refers
                    to the long, dynamic social history that colonial books underwent as they moved
                    across libraries, cities, and nations according to political, social, and market
                    forces. It is traced through marks of provenance, and it is understood in terms
                    of the discursive field that a document occupies and the affective sphere
                    through which it is read. Turning to the <hi rend="italic">Advertencias</hi> and
                    the <hi rend="italic">Opera medicinalia</hi> as case studies, I consider how
                    these two axes allow for a more dynamic understanding of historical books than
                    the modern frameworks through which they are commonly accessed and read.</p>
                <div type="subsection">
                    <head type="sub">Malleability</head>
                    <p>The malleability of an early colonial book relative to the rigid frameworks
                        in which it is commonly placed can be understood by digging down into the
                        categories of authorship, printer, and title—three categories that
                        collectively shape the boundaries of the modern book. In the case of the <hi
                            rend="italic">Advertencias</hi> and the <hi rend="italic">Opera
                            medicinalia</hi>, this excavation will indicate how the names associated
                        with these entries diverge, converge, bifurcate, and meld, suggesting a
                        fluid form of textuality that crosses the boundaries of binding, paper, and
                            text.<ptr target="#note17" xml:id="nr17" n="17"/></p>
                    <p>The Franciscan friar known as Juan Bautista, director of the Colegio de la
                        Santa Cruz de Tlatelolco, Mexico, was certainly the composer of the <hi
                            rend="italic">Advertencias</hi>. His status as “author” in the catalogue
                        entries for the book applies to him what we might call a modern author
                        function: it allows us to understand the book as his intellectual property,
                        and to attribute its composition primarily to his genius. Yet as we saw in
                        the prior section, this author function collapses in the colonial context.
                        The orthographic uncertainty of the author’s name (Juan Bautista? Ioan
                        Baptista?) reveals an underlying doubt about the identity of this man and
                        his position as a historical subject. The presence of multiple names under
                        the category of author&#8212;including that of the printer and former
                        owners&#8212;suggests that in the case of a historical book, the author
                        function may be shared by multiple individuals.</p>
                    <p>Further examination of the composition of the <hi rend="italic"
                            >Advertencias</hi> supports this argument. As was common in the early
                        modern period, large sections of the <hi rend="italic">Advertencias</hi> are
                        copied from other books or manuscripts. In one famous example, Bautista
                        lifts a long passage directly from the appendix to the fifth book of
                        Bernardino de Sahagún’s <hi rend="italic">Historia general</hi>, which had
                        been circulating in manuscript form in New Spain during the period that the
                            <hi rend="italic">Advertencias</hi> was composed. Other citations, as
                        Verónica Murillo Gallegos has shown, refer to documents that do not seem to
                        correspond to any surviving manuscripts: they now serve as the only evidence
                        we have of these historical texts.<ptr target="#note18" xml:id="nr18" n="18"
                        /> Indeed, Murillo argues that the significance of the <hi rend="italic"
                            >Advertencias</hi> today rests in the way it brings together for the
                        first time the circulating manuscripts of the new generation of Mexican
                        creoles. As a composition, then, it functions more as a window into textual
                        circulation among a group of associated thinkers than as a unique and
                        isolated textual object, a status which is not reflected on the title page
                        or in the catalogue entries for the book.</p>
                    <p>Authorship in the <hi rend="italic">Advertencias</hi> is further expanded by
                        the fact that the Franciscan friars commonly worked with indigenous scribes,
                        informants, or translators to produce their texts, especially when writing
                        in indigenous languages. In his 1606 <hi rend="italic">Sermonario</hi>,
                        Bautista directly credits eight students from Tlatelolco who served as
                            assistants.<ptr target="#note19" xml:id="nr19" n="19"/> In place of a
                        modern author, then, in this colonial context we may find what Kathryn
                        Burns, referring to Peruvian notaries, describes as a “blended, composite
                        agency” underlying the text.<ptr target="#note20" xml:id="nr20" n="20"/>
                        While we don’t know the precise role that indigenous writers had in
                        composing the <hi rend="italic">Advertencias</hi>, to lose sight of this
                        composite authorship is effectively to erase the intellectual contribution
                        of indigenous participants, and to flatten the heterogeneous intellectual
                        atmosphere of the Colegio de la Santa Cruz where the book was produced. The
                        stakes of rethinking colonial composition are higher than they may appear:
                        authorship in this context is directly associated with the historiography of
                        indigenous intellectual labor.</p>
                    <p>Social and political changes during the long period of textual composition
                        can also shape the dynamic category of authorship in a colonial text, as is
                        the case for the <hi rend="italic">Opera medicinalia</hi>. As described by
                        José Gaspar Rodolfo Cortés Riveroll, a scholar and translator of the <hi
                            rend="italic">Opera medicinalia</hi>, the text is divided into four
                        books with an epistle in the middle. The first two books, dedicated to the
                        viceroy of New Spain, were likely written while the author was in Spain. The
                        subsequent two books, dedicated to the president of the Real Audiencia de
                        México, were likely written in Mexico. Even this division, however, is
                        overly simple: Cortés Riveroll observes that in the twelfth chapter of the
                        second book, for example, the language changes enough to suggest either a
                        significant passage of time or a new writer.<ptr target="#note21"
                            xml:id="nr21" n="21"/> These additions, Cortés Riveroll argues, were
                        added later “para darles contexto local.”<ptr target="#note22" xml:id="nr22"
                            n="22"/> A long and multinational composition process, combined with the
                        possible introduction of a second author, is significant enough to produce
                        textual disunity or a kind of discursive malleability. At the same time, it
                        is a reminder that the composition of a historical book can extend across
                        the length of the composer’s lifetime&#8212;and beyond the process of print
                        production and binding.</p>
                    <p>Textual production in the early colonial period, like production today, is
                        often thought of as separate from but complementary to the process of
                        composition. The printing press is supposed to provide fixity, in the words
                        of Elizabeth Eisenstein, to an otherwise malleable textual object. Yet as we
                        consider the categories of printer and printing, it becomes clear that in
                        these cases production introduces new occasions for textual and material
                        malleability, once again broadening the boundaries of the textual object. As
                        the previous section illustrated, textual production is described in
                        catalogue entries through the figure of the printer, who can appear variably
                        under the entry for author or publisher/editorial, or in the note. This
                        variability reveals uncertainty regarding the role of the printer in shaping
                        the textual object, as well as a more fundamental uncertainty about the
                        printer himself.</p>
                    <p>Though the title pages shown in Figure 2 inform us that Melchor Ocharte
                        printed both volumes of the <hi rend="italic">Advertencias</hi> in 1600, the
                        colophon on the final page of the <hi rend="italic">Segunda parte</hi>
                        credits his half brother Luis Ocharte Figueroa with printing the book; this
                        colophon is dated 1601. (Juan Pascoe has convincingly argued for a third
                        possibility, that the book was printed by the uncredited Cornelio Adrián
                            César).<ptr target="#note23" xml:id="nr23" n="23"/> This is indicative
                        of the long and unstable printing process, which may have been drawn out
                        over more than one year and involved more than one printer, as veiled
                        comments in Bautista’s dedication suggest. It also draws attention to the
                        complex scene of production in early colonial Mexico, where religious
                        leaders like Bautista, creole printers like Ocharte, and European immigrants
                        like Adrián César vied for control over communication technologies. As in
                        the case of the author, the printer attribution on the title page obscures a
                        multifaceted process that involved numerous individuals and stages of
                        production.</p>
                    <p>The confusion of the printer attribution in the catalogue entries also
                        reveals some uncertainty regarding the role of the printer in shaping the
                        final book. It was during the printing process that aesthetic coherence
                        across books was established through shared typefaces, layouts,
                        orthographies, and, more notably, shared images. The woodcut used in the
                        title page of the <hi rend="italic">Opera medicinalia</hi>, for example, was
                        also used in the <hi rend="italic">Diálogos</hi> of Cervantes de Salazar
                        (printed in Mexico, 1554) as well as in an edition of the <hi rend="italic"
                            >Vulgata</hi> printed in Lyon by Balthazar Arnoullet in 1545.<ptr
                            target="#note24" xml:id="nr24" n="24"/> Despite the anxiety that this
                        reuse of images has caused bibliographers of the <hi rend="italic">Opera
                            medicinalia</hi>, of course, it is a well-documented characteristic of
                        printing in the early modern period. It suggests that in this context, the
                        boundaries of printed books may expand to include other documents with
                        shared images, as well as those with shared texts.</p>
                    <p>Just as some aspects of the production process replicate material across
                        books, other parts of the process introduce significant distinctions between
                        multiple exemplars of what modern readers would think of as the same book.
                        Excisions, revisions, and other postproduction modifications (such as the
                        removal of three leaves from the <hi rend="italic">Advertencias</hi>, for
                        example) are unevenly replicated across exemplars and are of dubious origin:
                        was it the author who produced the excision? The printer? The Inquisition?
                        The reader? In the case of the <hi rend="italic">Advertencias</hi>, a more
                        obvious inconsistency is found in the presence and order of front matter
                        associated with the book. It was this inconsistency that caused García
                        Icazbalceta to comment despairingly on the differences between the
                        exemplars. Some exemplars are missing elements, including licenses, while
                        others include an additional set of indulgences dated 1603. Some exemplars,
                        furthermore, seem to have indulgences of different lengths. The extensive
                        documentation that makes up the front matter is uniquely characteristic of
                        the context of New Spain in the late sixteenth century, where both imported
                        and locally printed books went through a complex regulation process. The
                        haphazard survival of the front matter is thus a symbol&#8212;if not a
                        direct representation&#8212;of the gap between rules and practice in the
                        circulation of texts in New Spain.</p>
                    <p>At the same time, the front matter marks the fluid boundaries between the
                        exemplars that make up the <hi rend="italic">Advertencias</hi>. According to
                        the title pages, the <hi rend="italic">Advertencias</hi> is a single book
                        made up of two separately bound volumes (<hi rend="italic">Primera
                            parte</hi> and <hi rend="italic">Segunda parte</hi>). Yet binding
                        practices suggest otherwise: in a number of cases, the <hi rend="italic"
                            >Primera parte</hi> was bound with Bautista’s earlier <hi rend="italic"
                            >Confessionario</hi>, a process of compilation that replicates the
                        composition process described earlier, and suggests some flexibility even
                        toward the bound volume as a unit of measure for textual objects. Comparison
                        of the front matter among these exemplars shows that some of the licenses
                        are duplicated between the two books. Binding and compilation thus further
                        multiply the variant shapes that a book as a textual unit might hold, even
                        as they give form to the otherwise fluid structures of intertextual
                        reproduction.</p>
                </div>
                <div type="subsection">
                    <head type="sub">Historicity</head>
                    <p>By examining the composition and production of early colonial Mexican books,
                        we can better understand their malleability as textual objects. These books
                        do not ossify, however, at the moment that they are bound into a coherent
                        unit. Instead, the historical book has a long and dynamic history as it
                        moves from the site of its production, through multiple libraries, regions,
                        and historical moments, to arrive at the present day.<ptr target="#note25"
                            xml:id="nr25" n="25"/> This movement, often referred to in terms of
                        provenance&#8212;a book’s history of ownership&#8212;can leave a material
                        mark on exemplars, playing an interpretive role in shaping the book as a
                        signifying object. Like Bonnie Mak, whose study of digitization projects
                        emphasizes the long interpretive history of the medieval manuscript, I find
                        the metaphor of the palimpsest, with its complex history of records and
                        erasures, useful in representing the multiple layers of meaning embedded in
                        a single exemplar.<ptr target="#note26" xml:id="nr26" n="26"/> Unlike the
                        static palimpsest, in this section I propose that historical books can be
                        better understood as dynamic material objects that carry with them the
                        multiple, often diverging contexts of their meaning and use.</p>
                    <p>By examining library catalogues and other sources, I have located more than
                        seventy exemplars associated with the <hi rend="italic">Advertencias</hi>
                        (including the <hi rend="italic">Primera parte</hi>, <hi rend="italic"
                            >Segunda parte</hi>, and exemplars co-bound with the <hi rend="italic"
                            >Confessionario</hi>). The case of just one of these exemplars, a copy
                        of the <hi rend="italic">Primera parte</hi> currently held by the Biblioteca
                        Francisco Xavier Clavigero at the Universidad Iberoamericana in Mexico City,
                        illustrates how changing historical contexts carry with them shifting
                        interpretive contexts as the books move through distinct discursive spheres
                        and historical moments. Changes in ownership are influenced by the complex
                        interaction among different dimensions of the book: as a source of
                        information, as a cultural heritage item, and as a collectible artifact.
                        They are often triggered by large-scale changes in political and economic
                        power within Mexico or internationally.</p>
                    <p>The exemplar at the Iberoamericana emblematizes this dynamic. Bound together
                        with Bautista’s earlier <hi rend="italic">Confessionario</hi>, the volume
                        stands out for the many ownership marks that have been made over the years
                        of its circulation, from the brand on the edge of the book to multiple
                        handwritten notations and bookplates in the interior. Collectively, these
                        marks show the long trajectory of the exemplar, which in this case parallels
                        closely the dominant narrative about Mexico’s cultural heritage.</p>
                    <figure>
                        <head>Figure 3: Bottom edge of a copy of the <hi rend="italic"
                                >Advertencias</hi> from the Biblioteca Francisco Xavier Clavigero.
                            Image from the Catálogo Colectivo de Marcas de Fuego website. (ID:
                            BFXC-16039)</head>
                        <figDesc>Figure 3: Bottom edge of a copy of the Advertencias from the
                            Biblioteca Francisco Xavier Clavigero. Image from the Catálogo Colectivo
                            de Marcas de Fuego website. (ID: BFXC-16039)</figDesc>
                        <graphic url="images/essay.alpertabrams.03.jpg"/>
                    </figure>
                    <p>Brands made with iron or ink on the edges of books, like the one shown in
                        Figure 3, were used by religious orders during the colonial period to mark
                        ownership of a book. Careful work on the taxonomy of these <hi rend="italic"
                            >marcas</hi> by scholars involved with the <hi rend="italic">Catálogo
                            Colectivo de Marcas de Fuego</hi> project makes it possible for us to
                        identify, in many cases, the library that held a given copy of the <hi
                            rend="italic">Advertencias</hi>, and in some cases to date the
                        acquisition of that copy. Individually, a <hi rend="italic">marca</hi> can
                        give us a hint about who may have had access to a given exemplar.
                        Collectively, the <hi rend="italic">marcas</hi> offer a partial view of the
                        movement of the <hi rend="italic">Advertencias</hi> during the period,
                        allowing us to understand its role in the intellectual culture of the
                        religious orders. They also suggest a culture of book loaning in which
                        marking ownership helped libraries retain possession of these valuable
                        commodities while alerting users to the cultural capital of the owning
                        institution. In this case, unfortunately, the <hi rend="italic">marca</hi>
                        has not been identified, though the catalogue entry speculates that it may
                        be affiliated with the Convento de Santiago Tlatelolco, located near the
                        Colegio de la Santa Cruz, where the <hi rend="italic">Advertencias</hi> was
                            printed.<ptr target="#note27" xml:id="nr27" n="27"/></p>
                    <p>The reference to the convent at Tlatelolco allows us reconstruct part of the
                        discursive context that framed the <hi rend="italic">Advertencias</hi> at
                        this time. Though this work is speculative, we know enough to say with some
                        certainty that this library would have held at least one copy of the <hi
                            rend="italic">Advertencias</hi>&#8212;taken, perhaps, from the defunct
                        library at the Colegio sometime in the mid-seventeenth century. As the
                        introduction to Michael Mathes’s important study of that original library
                        describes, the library and the school that it supported was a “verdadero
                        semillero” (a true seedbed) for intellectual and cultural development.<ptr
                            target="#note28" xml:id="nr28" n="28"/> At this time the <hi
                            rend="italic">Advertencias</hi> would have been held alongside volumes
                        of Plutarch and Virgil, printed American texts like the <hi rend="italic"
                            >Arte de la lengua mexicana y castellana</hi> by Alonso de Molina, and
                        the manuscripts of Sahagún and others. By the end of the seventeenth
                        century, however, the school was in ruins, the manuscripts had been sent
                        abroad for safekeeping (where they would be all but forgotten for over a
                        century), and the library, now located at the Convento de Santiago
                        Tlatelolco, served a narrower form of intellectual service. Though we have
                        little assurance that this exemplar underwent this precise trajectory, it is
                        likely that at least one copy of the <hi rend="italic">Advertencias</hi>
                        did.</p>
                    <p>Additional ownership marks allow us to continue tracing the history of this
                        particular exemplar. As in many other cases, evidence here suggests that
                        this exemplar first began to circulate at the politically unstable end of
                        the eighteenth century. A note on the title page of the <hi rend="italic"
                            >Confessionario</hi> dated 1797&#8212;some thirty years before military
                        troops occupied the convent and used the books as mattresses<ptr
                            target="#note29" xml:id="nr29" n="29"/>&#8212;attributes the volume to a
                        “B[achille]r. Juan Antonio Moreno de Abalos.” A later note on the pastedown
                        suggests that it was acquired along with another volume by a book dealer in
                        1803. In 1833, it was likely sold to the British and Foreign Bible Society.
                        By this point, it would have shed its utilitarian purpose as a resource for
                        Spanish missionaries working among indigenous populations in New Spain.
                        Instead, it was now associated with an institution established in 1804 to
                        translate and distribute vernacular bibles to missionaries and growing
                        Christian communities around the world.</p>
                    <p>This period of circulation and subsequent acquisition abroad is just one of
                        many cases in which documents once held by Mexican religious orders entered
                        the global books and antiquities marketplace during the political
                        disruptions of the late colonial period, the Mexican wars of independence,
                        and subsequent turmoil. In his <hi rend="italic">Breve historia del libro en
                            Mexico</hi>, Ernesto de la Torre Villar describes this period as the
                        beginning of the cultural decline of Mexico and of the loss of its
                        bibliographic patrimony.<ptr target="#note30" xml:id="nr30" n="30"/> Others
                        have described the movement of books out of Mexico during this period as an
                        “exodus,” similarly bemoaning Mexico’s loss.<ptr target="#note31"
                            xml:id="nr31" n="31"/> From a different perspective, the Bible Society
                        acquisition points to a new life for the <hi rend="italic">Advertencias</hi>
                        as it shifts from serving as a record of Spanish conquest to becoming part
                        of a larger history centering on the global spread of religion through
                        European colonization. It also draws attention to the rise of British
                        economic investment in Mexico during the first part of the nineteenth
                        century, embedded materially in this exemplar through the manuscript
                        notation.</p>
                    <p>This exemplar underwent another important shift when it was acquired by the
                        Mexican businessman and bibliophile Manuel Arango Arias. On his many trips
                        abroad for business, Arango worked to locate and acquire Mexican heritage
                        items and bring them home. In 1996, he donated his collection to the
                        Biblioteca Francisco Xavier Clavigero in Mexico City.<ptr target="#note32"
                            xml:id="nr32" n="32"/> Thus this exemplar participated in the broader
                        process of cultural return, whereby heritage items that were taken from
                        their sites of origin under colonial or imperial conditions are brought back
                        to their homelands. We might notice, of course, that this “return” is only
                        partial. The library where the book was first collected no longer exists,
                        the religious orders are largely dismantled, and the rare books collection
                        at the Iberoamericana serves an entirely different public: scholars and
                        bibliophiles with documented institutional affiliations and an interest in
                        early colonial Mexico.</p>
                </div>
            </div>
            <div type="section">
                <head type="main">Section 3: Modeling New Approaches to Editing Early Colonial
                    Books</head>
                <p>LLILAS Benson Latin American Studies and Collections at the University of Texas
                    at Austin is a founding member of the Primeros Libros project, dedicated to
                    producing freely available facsimile editions (and, soon, transcriptions) of all
                    books printed before 1601 in the Americas. The interface for this project
                    employs traditional cataloguing categories like author, title, date, and
                    printer; it is designed primarily to promote the readability of the books. As an
                    employee of LLILAS Benson in 2014, I became interested in developing another
                    model for approaching these digital objects. Working with Kent Norsworthy, then
                    LLILAS Benson’s digital scholarship coordinator, I developed a digital project
                    for exploring one book in that collection&#8212;the <hi rend="italic"
                        >Advertencias para los confessores de los Naturales</hi>&#8212;that would be
                    based on the two dimensions of malleability and historicity described above.
                    This project was designed specifically to decenter the textual content of the
                    book&#8212;still freely available on the Primeros Libros website&#8212;in favor
                    of object and context. At the same time, the project offered an alternative to
                    traditional models for communicating book history.</p>
                <p>For the Archaeology of a Book project, as it came to be called, we chose to use
                    the Scalar platform, a “free, open source authoring and publishing platform
                    that’s designed to make it easy for authors to write long-form, born-digital
                    scholarship online.” We were attracted to Scalar because its mission, as
                    articulated by Tara McPherson, aligned with our own: “to formulate new ways of
                    working with digitized archival materials within the humanities and to continue
                    to model emerging genres of digital scholarly publishing.” Scalar was ideal
                    because it allowed us to experiment with new structures for scholarly publishing
                    without first developing extensive programming skills or finding funding for a
                    development team—a priority when modeling a platform that we hoped would be
                    widely applicable to students and faculty across institutions.</p>
                <p>For the <hi rend="italic">Archaeology of a Book</hi> project, as it came to be
                    called, we chose to use the Scalar platform, a “free, open source authoring and
                    publishing platform that’s designed to make it easy for authors to write
                    long-form, born-digital scholarship online.”<ptr target="#note33" xml:id="nr33"
                        n="33"/> We were attracted to Scalar because its mission, as articulated by
                    Tara McPherson, aligned with our own: “to formulate new ways of working with
                    digitized archival materials within the humanities and to continue to model
                    emerging genres of digital scholarly publishing.”<ptr target="#note34"
                        xml:id="nr34" n="34"/> Scalar was ideal because it allowed us to experiment
                    with new structures for scholarly publishing without first developing extensive
                    programming skills or finding funding for a development team&#8212;a priority
                    when modeling a platform that we hoped would be widely applicable to students
                    and faculty across institutions.</p>
                <p>Two particular features of Scalar make it particularly well suited to our
                    project. First, its organizational structure is based on paths and networks,
                    rather than the linear model of a traditional printed book. This suited our
                    interest in reframing our approach to textual objects using a multidimensional
                    model. Second, it is designed to interface smoothly with preexisting digital
                    facsimile collections, archives, and media databases, a feature that enables us
                    to display textual or material contexts that crossed collections. The <hi
                        rend="italic">Archaeology of a Book</hi> project, which continues to evolve,
                    is currently available <ref type="url"
                        target="http://scalar.usc.edu/works/advertencias/index.">online</ref>; in
                    what remains of this article, I will describe some of the principles and
                    technologies that we used to produce this project, and how it has allowed us to
                    see new possibilities for describing digital facsimiles.</p>
                <figure type="enlargeOnClick">
                    <head>Figure 4: Two visualizations showing the organizational structure of <hi
                            rend="italic">Archaeology of a Book</hi>. “Visualization,” <hi
                            rend="italic">Archaeology of a Book</hi>, Scalar, accessed December 31,
                        2015, http://scalar.usc.edu/works/advertencias/index.</head>
                    <figDesc>Figure 4: Two visualizations showing the organizational structure of
                        Archaeology of a Book. “Visualization,” Archaeology of a Book, Scalar,
                        accessed December 31, 2015,
                        http://scalar.usc.edu/works/advertencias/index.</figDesc>
                    <graphic url="images/essay.alpertabrams.04.jpg"/>
                </figure>
                <p>The <hi rend="italic">Archaeology of a Book</hi> project was designed around a
                    series of branching paths, as shown in the visualizations in Figure 4. Each path
                    is oriented around a different dimension of book analysis: the introduction
                    focuses on composition and reception; the production path focuses on printing
                    and binding; the collection and acquisition paths focus on provenance; and the
                    concluding path focuses on digitization. Though these paths differ slightly from
                    the organizational schema described earlier in this article, they follow the
                    same basic principles in emphasizing the malleability of the historical book and
                    the long and changing history of its use. While they can be read linearly to
                    produce an essay-like reading experience, the images in Figure 4 show that there
                    are a number of ways to orient to the content of the project. This
                    organizational flexibility allows us to step outside the rigid or hierarchical
                    categories of the traditional catalogue.</p>
                <figure type="enlargeOnClick">
                    <head>Figure 5: Facsimiles of pages from the <hi rend="italic">Advertencias</hi>
                        (left, from Primeros Libros) and the <hi rend="italic">Florentine</hi> Codex
                        (right, from the World Digital Library) show how Bautista borrowed text from
                        his predecessor. (IDs: pl_blac_047_00234; 10616 [1/31])</head>
                    <figDesc>Figure 5: Facsimiles of pages from the Advertencias (left, from
                        Primeros Libros) and the Florentine Codex (right, from the World Digital
                        Library) show how Bautista borrowed text from his predecessor. (IDs:
                        pl_blac_047_00234; 10616 [1/31])</figDesc>
                    <graphic url="images/essay.alpertabrams.05.jpg"/>
                </figure>
                <p>As described in this article, the malleability associated with the composition
                    and production of early colonial Mexican books was reflected in the sharing of
                    texts and images across documents and in the variation within and between copies
                    of a single book. Using the Primeros Libros collection and the Scalar interface,
                    we were able to highlight both of these features. One unique quality of the
                    Primeros Libros project is that it brings together for the first time a set of
                    contemporaneous but geographically distant exemplars. This feature was extended
                    by Scalar’s unique association with online databases like the Internet Archive,
                    which allowed us to make visual associations between largely disparate
                    documents. In <ref type="url"
                        target="http://scalar.usc.edu/works/advertencias/writing-the-advertencias">a
                        section dedicated to the process of composition</ref>, for example, we were
                    able to bring together a facsimile image of a page from Bernardino de Sahagún’s
                        <hi rend="italic">Florentine Codex</hi> with the identical page as it
                    appears printed in the <hi rend="italic">Advertencias</hi> (Figure 5). It is
                    unlikely that these texts have been together (even virtually) since Sahagún’s
                    manuscript left Mexico sometime in the seventeenth century. In fact, a closer
                    examination shows that Bautista has revised the original, describing a causal
                    relationship between the flower Omixuchitl and an associated illness that
                    remains implicit in Sahagún’s manuscript. The Scalar interface makes it easy for
                    the user to visualize these pages side by side, or to move between the project
                    and complete facsimiles hosted by the World Digital Library and the Primeros
                    Libros project. Ultimately, pages like this portray the expanding definition of
                    early modern authorship that a traditional organizational schema might
                    elide.</p>
                <p>Sections dedicated to the production of the <hi rend="italic">Advertencias</hi>
                    take further advantage of the fact that the <hi rend="italic">Primeros
                        Libros</hi> project hosts multiple copies of each book in its collection to
                    identify differences among exemplars. Collation across multiple libraries can be
                    costly and slow, but when the books are brought together as facsimiles, it
                    becomes relatively easy. Use of Cobre, a comparative book reader designed by
                    Texas A&amp;M (and <ref type="url"
                        target="http://scalar.usc.edu/works/advertencias/digital-projects">featured
                        in the digital path of <hi rend="italic">Archaeology</hi></ref>) made it
                    easy to identify the differences in front matter between exemplars, as shown in
                    Figure 6; by linking to the Cobre reader, we also encourage users to conduct
                    their own document comparisons. Other variations associated with the production
                    of the book, such as excised pages or lines, can be uncovered through the same
                    process of collation and displayed on the Scalar page. Again, the pathways work
                    against the grain of standard cataloguing categories like title or publisher in
                    order to disrupt the sense of the book as an atomic unit.</p>
                <figure>
                    <head>Figure 6: A comparison of two exemplars of the <hi rend="italic"
                            >Advertencias</hi>, as seen in the Cobre comparative reader. (ID: “Cobre
                        Reader comparing frontmatter of the Advertencias”)</head>
                    <figDesc>Figure 6: A comparison of two exemplars of the Advertencias, as seen in
                        the Cobre comparative reader. (ID: “Cobre Reader comparing frontmatter of
                        the Advertencias”)</figDesc>
                    <graphic url="images/essay.alpertabrams.06.jpg"/>
                </figure>
                <p>The multiple textual meanings that a book engages as it circulates across
                    historical contexts are made visible through material signals of provenance like
                    firebrands, marginal notes, and nameplates. Unfortunately, these details are not
                    preserved in the Primeros Libros collection; they were collected, instead,
                    through my own research or through other online projects like the <hi
                        rend="italic">Catálogo Colectivo de Marcas de Fuego</hi>. Bringing these
                    details to bear on the facsimiles, however, emphasizes the dynamism of these
                    otherwise static historical documents. It shows how documents from the sixteenth
                    century reappear throughout Mexico’s intellectual history. It also, I hope,
                    emphasizes the importance of preserving these marginal or material details when
                    constructing online facsimile collections.</p>
                <p>Provenance marks serve as a point of access that can provide valuable information
                    about the history of ownership for an exemplar. We can expand this context by
                    tracing the discursive sphere in which the book existed, examining the ways that
                    an owner may have refigured the book, the library in which that book was
                    present, and the aesthetic space that the book occupied. As was shown above in
                    the example of the Tlatelolco library, the books in a collection can provide
                    insight into the intellectual community that would have accessed or read the <hi
                        rend="italic">Advertencias</hi>: through library catalogues, we can
                    partially reconstruct those collections. With Scalar, it is possible to <ref
                        type="url"
                        target="http://scalar.usc.edu/works/advertencias/printing-at-tlatelolco"
                        >bring those books back together</ref>, a project that I hope to extend in
                    future iterations as I construct a digital “library at Tlatelolco” and a list of
                    Bautista’s collected works.</p>
                <figure>
                    <head>Figure 7: An interactive Story Map display of the distribution of the <hi
                            rend="italic">Advertencias. Archaeology of a Book</hi>, Scalar, accessed
                        December 25, 2015,
                        http://scalar.usc.edu/works/advertencias/twentieth--twenty-first-centuries.</head>
                    <figDesc>Figure 7: An interactive Story Map display of the distribution of the
                        Advertencias. Archaeology of a Book, Scalar, accessed December 25, 2015,
                        http://scalar.usc.edu/works/advertencias/twentieth--twenty-first-centuries.</figDesc>
                    <graphic url="images/essay.alpertabrams.07.jpg"/>
                </figure>
                <p>In <ref type="url"
                        target="http://scalar.usc.edu/works/advertencias/twentieth--twenty-first-centuries"
                        >a page on twenty-first century collections</ref>, I sought to introduce two
                    additional elements to the narrative of provenance: the dynamic geographical
                    movement of the <hi rend="italic">Advertencias</hi> and the affective experience
                    of the architectural contexts in which they are currently held. To achieve this,
                    I used Story Maps, a third-party application for producing interactive maps.<ptr
                        target="#note35" xml:id="nr35" n="35"/> This map, shown in Figure 7,
                    visually represents the geographic distribution of exemplars through the world,
                    revealing patterns of distribution or consumption. Linking points on the map to
                    photographs and brief prose narratives illustrates the affective experience of
                    the library, archive, museum, or special collection where the book is held. The
                    goal is to draw attention to the ways that atmosphere and access provide a
                    framework for a reading experience, and to show how local and regional
                    differences play a significant role in our relationship to textual objects. As
                    these historical books are read with decreasing frequency, their role as
                    artifacts embedded in a curated environment comes to the forefront of their
                    social value. Mapping the current distribution of the <hi rend="italic"
                        >Advertencias</hi> seeks to communicate these diverse affective experiences,
                    while recording the current landscape of the exemplars for future study.</p>
                <div type="subsection">
                    <head type="sub">Looking Forward</head>
                    <p>In this article, I have sought to describe an approach to digital critical
                        editions that engages with the shifting status of books in the early modern
                        period, changes in their status over time, and the material traces that
                        history leaves on the books themselves. Just as I have described the history
                        of the book as dynamic and historical, I sought with <hi rend="italic"
                            >Archaeology of a Book</hi> to produce a dynamic project that would
                        embody the future of this historical book as well as its past.</p>
                    <p>For the future of <hi rend="italic">Archaeology of a Book</hi>, I look toward
                        new scholarship and new platforms. Using Scalar, a stable and user-friendly
                        interface, allowed us to design a project that can be infinitely expandable,
                        enabling both collaborations and pedagogical opportunities. Scholars working
                        with books from the Primeros Libros collection can add their own pages or
                        pathways to expand the scope of the resource. Teachers may also invite
                        undergraduate and graduate students to add their scholarship to the
                        project.</p>
                    <p>While this new research may simply replicate the model set forth by the
                        existing project, it could also expand in new dimensions that take advantage
                        of other technologies. Incorporating more dynamic mapping and timeline
                        platforms like Neatline Omeka, for example, would open new ways of
                        understanding the history of the collection. Three-dimensional facsimiles
                        and other forms of data visualization could expand the scope of book history
                        even further, while developing resources for the history of these books as
                        historical records, as living objects, and as valued world heritage
                        documents.</p>
                    <p>The future of <hi rend="italic">Archaeology of a Book</hi> and projects like
                        it is also tied up in the future of scholarly communication. Book history
                        has long been told in book form, a convention that carries its own
                        structures of information delivery and organization. With digital platforms
                        for scholarly writing, it is possible to unbind the history from the book,
                        producing new objects of information delivery that engage the shape of the
                        historical book as well as its content. This poses an opportunity for book
                        historians to engage critically with the structures through which we see
                        historical books as well as with the history of those books themselves.</p>
                </div>
            </div>
        </body>
        <back>
            <div type="notes">
                <note xml:id="note1">Primeros Libros (2014), <ref type="url"
                        target="www.primeroslibros.org">www.primeroslibros.org</ref> (accessed
                    December 25, 2015).</note>
                <note xml:id="note2">Juan Bautista, <hi rend="italic">Advertencias para los
                        confessores de los Naturales</hi> (Tlatelolco: Melchor Ocharte,
                    1600).</note>
                <note xml:id="note3">Jerome McGann, <hi rend="italic">A New Republic of Letters</hi>
                    (Cambridge: Harvard University Press, 2014), 45.</note>
                <note xml:id="note4">David McKitterick, <hi rend="italic">Old Books, New
                        Technologies: The Representation, Conservation and Transformation of Books
                        Since 1700</hi> (Cambridge: Cambridge University Press, 2013), 4.</note>
                <note xml:id="note5">Sarah Werner articulates the contours of this debate clearly
                    when she writes, “Digital facsimiles appear to be flat, made up of pages without
                    depth or relationship to other pages, part of a sequence that is made up of bits
                    rather than bindings. But this is not because such flatness is inherent to
                    digitization. It is because of the limited ways in which digitization has been
                    put to use for us.” Given the extensive resources necessary to produce truly
                    multidimensional facsimiles, however, these ideal digitization projects may not
                    always be possible, and the critiques of current digital editions are not
                    invalid. Matt Kirschenbaum and Sarah Werner, “Digital Scholarship and Digital
                    Studies: The State of the Discipline,” <hi rend="italic">Book History</hi> 17
                    (2014): 420. </note>
                <note xml:id="note6">McGann, <hi rend="italic">New Republic</hi>.</note>
                <note xml:id="note7">Jeffrey Todd Knight, <hi rend="italic">Bound to Read:
                        Compilations, Collections, and the Making of Renaissance Literature</hi>
                    (Philadelphia: University of Pennsylvania Press, 2013), 8.</note>
                <note xml:id="note8">Germaine Warkentin, “Dead Metaphor or Working Model: ‘The Book’
                    in Native America,” in <hi rend="italic">Colonial Mediascapes</hi>, ed. Matt
                    Cohen and Jeffrey Glover (Lincoln: University of Nebraska Press, 2014).</note>
                <note xml:id="note9">“I have seen six or more exemplars of the Advertencias, and
                    almost all of them display differences between them” (all trans. mine unless
                    otherwise noted). Joaquín García Icazbalceta, <hi rend="italic">Bibliografía
                        mexicana del siglo XVI.: Primera parte</hi> (Mexico: Imprenta de Francisco
                    Diaz de Leon, 1886), 353.</note>
                <note xml:id="note10">“It is a book that among bibliophiles has been feared like the
                    plague.” Francisco Guerra, “La portada de la ‘Opera Medicinalia,’ Mexico, 1570,”
                        <hi rend="italic">Revista de Indias</hi> 52.194 (1992): 159.</note>
                <note xml:id="note11">Francisco Bravo, <hi rend="italic">Opera Medicinalia</hi>
                    (Mexico: Pedro Ocharte, 1570), <ref type="url" target="www.primeroslibros.org"
                        >www.primeroslibros.org</ref>. For a thorough study of the history of this
                    book, refer to Rodrigo Martínez Baracs, <hi rend="italic">El largo
                        descubrimiento del Opera medicinalia de Francisco Bravo</hi> (Fondo de
                    Cultura Económica, 2015).</note>
                <note xml:id="note12">Jens-Erik Mai, “Ethics, Values and Morality in Contemporary
                    Library Classifications,” <hi rend="italic">Knowledge Organization</hi> 40, no.
                    4 (2013): 242.</note>
                <note xml:id="note13">The introduction of bibliographic error is not reserved for
                    early modern books&#8212;modern catalogue entries are notoriously difficult. Nor
                    are these inconsistencies reserved for catalogues; even Rosa María Fernández de
                    Zamora’s bibliography of early Mexican printed books, the newest authority in
                    the field, introduces orthographic differences in its transcription of the two
                    primary title pages, reminding us again of the difficulty of maintaining
                    consistency in bibliographic record keeping. Rosa María Fernández de Zamora, <hi
                        rend="italic">Los impresos mexicanos del siglo XVI: Su presencia en el
                        patrimonio cultural del nuevo siglo</hi> (Ciudad de Mexico: UNAM,
                    2009).</note>
                <note xml:id="note14">Knight, <hi rend="italic">Bound to Read</hi>, 4.</note>
                <note xml:id="note15">Library of Congress, “Juan Bautista, fray, 1555–approximately
                    1613,” <hi rend="italic">Library of Congress Name Authority File</hi>, May 13,
                    2015, <ref type="url"
                        target="http://id.loc.gov/authorities/names/no98094250.html"
                        >http://id.loc.gov/authorities/names/no98094250.html</ref>.</note>
                <note xml:id="note16">Consider, for example, the variations between entries in the
                    “title/título” category. The titles, all taken directly from the title page,
                    nevertheless vary in length from seven words to forty-three. Where, in the case
                    of an early colonial printed book, does the title begin&#8212;and where does it
                    end?</note>
                <note xml:id="note17">For the language of excavation&#8212;among other
                    things&#8212;I am indebted to Bonnie Mak, “Archaeology of a Digitization,” <hi
                        rend="italic">Journal of the Association for Information Science and
                        Technology</hi> 65, no. 8 (2014): 1515–26.</note>
                <note xml:id="note18">Verónica Murillo Gallegos, “Obras de personajes novohispanos
                    en las <hi rend="italic">Advertencias para los confesores de los naturales</hi>
                    de fray Juan Bautista de Viseo,” <hi rend="italic">Anuario de Historia de la
                        Iglesia</hi> 20 (2011): 362.</note>
                <note xml:id="note19">Mark Christensen, <hi rend="italic">Nahua and Maya
                        Catholicisms</hi> (Palo Alto: Stanford University Press, 2013), 33.</note>
                <note xml:id="note20">Kathryn Burns, <hi rend="italic">Into the Archive</hi>
                    (Durham: Duke University Press, 2010), 39.</note>
                <note xml:id="note21">José Gaspar Rodolfo Cortés Riveroll, “Francisco Bravo y el
                    primer libro de medicina impreso en América,” in <hi rend="italic">Autores de
                        obra médica en la Nueva España: vida y obras, 1552–1618</hi>, ed. María
                    Luisa Rodríguez-Sala, Enrique Delgado López, and José Gaspar Rodolfo Cortés
                    Riveroll (México: Benemérita Universidad Autónoma de Puebla, 2011), 106.</note>
                <note xml:id="note22">“To give them local context.” Cortés Riveroll, “Francisco
                    Bravo,” 95.</note>
                <note xml:id="note23">Juan Pascoe, “Primeros años en la nueva españa septiembre de
                    1596 hasta octubre de 1598” (unpublished manuscript, 2014).</note>
                <note xml:id="note24">Guerra, “La portada de la ‘Opera Medicinalia,’” 159–63.</note>
                <note xml:id="note25">Nor do all historical books begin with their production, of
                    course&#8212;many have long prehistories that all but disappear in the process
                    of binding and cataloguing.</note>
                <note xml:id="note26">Mak, “Archaeology of a Digitization.”</note>
                <note xml:id="note27">The catalogue description reads: <hi rend="italic">“Monograma
                        formada por las iniciales “A”, “C”, “F”, “R”, “U”, “I”, “J”, “S” y una “O”
                        como tilde coronando las anteriores.”</hi> (Monogram formed from the
                    initials A, C, F, R, U, I, J, S, and an O like a tilde crowning the previous
                    letters.) Observations remark, “<hi rend="italic">Monograma con las iniciales
                        entrelazadas, las cuales podrían referirse al Convento de Santiago
                        Tlatelolco. &#8212;Dado que no se ha localizado un ejemplar que nos permita
                        conocer la identidad del antiguo poseedor, se mantiene como marca no
                        identificada. &#8212;No aparece en los catálogos previos.</hi>” (Monogram
                    with the initials intertwined, which may refer to the Convent of Santiago
                    Tlatelolco. &#8212;Given that an exemplar has not been located which allows us
                    to know the identity of the historical owner, it remains an unidentified mark.
                    &#8212;It does not appear in previous catalogues.) “BFXC-16039,” <hi
                        rend="italic">Catálogo colectivo de marcas de fuego</hi>, <ref type="url"
                        target="http://www.marcasdefuego.buap.mx:8180/mafu-img//db/xmlibris/marcas_de_fuego/no_identificadas/16039-canto_orig.jpg"
                        >http://www.marcasdefuego.buap.mx:8180/mafu-img//db/xmlibris/marcas_de_fuego/no_identificadas/16039-canto_orig.jpg</ref>
                    (accessed December 31, 2015).</note>
                <note xml:id="note28">Published in English as <hi rend="italic">The America’s First
                        Academic Library: Santa Cruz de Tlatelolco</hi> (1985). Miguel Mathes, <hi
                        rend="italic">Santa Cruz de Tlatelolco: La primera biblioteca académica de
                        las Américas</hi> (Mexico: Archivo Histórico Diplomático Mexicano,
                    1982).</note>
                <note xml:id="note29">Mathes, <hi rend="italic">Santa Cruz de Tlatelolco</hi>,
                    41</note>
                <note xml:id="note30">Ernesto de la Torre Villar, <hi rend="italic">Breve historia
                        del libro en México</hi> (Mexico: Universidad Nacional Autónoma de México,
                    1990), 119. </note>
                <note xml:id="note31">Rosa María Fernández de Zamora, “Presencia de los impresos
                    mexicanos del Siglo XVI en las bibliotecas del siglo XXI,” <hi rend="italic"
                        >Investigación Bibliotecológica</hi> 19, no. 36 (Enero/Junio 2004):
                    7–26.</note>
                <note xml:id="note32"><hi rend="italic">Catálogo de la Colección Biblioteca Manuel
                        Arango Arias</hi> (Mexico: Universidad Iberoamericana, 2000), 13.</note>
                <note xml:id="note33"> Alliance for Networking Visual Culture, “About Scalar,”
                    scalar.usc.edu (accessed December 25, 2015).</note>
                <note xml:id="note34">Tara McPherson, “Designing for Difference,” <hi rend="italic"
                        >Differences</hi> 25, no. 1 (2014): 183.</note>
                <note xml:id="note35"> Esri, “Story Maps,” <ref type="url"
                        target="http://storymaps.arcgis.com/en/"
                        >http://storymaps.arcgis.com/en/</ref> (accessed December 25, 2015).</note>
            </div>
        </back>
    </text>
</TEI>
