<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<?oxygen RNGSchema="http://www.scholarlyediting.org/scholarlyediting.rng" type="xml"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xml:lang="eng">
    <teiHeader>
        <fileDesc>
            <titleStmt>
                <title level="a" type="main">Stories that Work</title>
                <title level="a" type="sub">Our Philological Future</title>
                <author key="Schulze, Robin G.">Robin G. Schulze</author>
            </titleStmt>
            <editionStmt>
                <edition>
                    <date>2016</date>
                </edition>
            </editionStmt>
            <publicationStmt>
                <idno type="file">essay.schulze</idno>
                <authority>Scholary Editing: The Annual of the Association for Documentary
                    Editing</authority>
                <address>
 <addrLine>http://www.scholarlyediting.org</addrLine>
</address>
                <publisher>Association for Documentary Editing</publisher>
                <publisher>University of Nebraska&#8211;Lincoln</publisher>
                <distributor>
                    <name>Center for Digital Research in the Humanities</name>
                    <address>
<addrLine>319 Love Library</addrLine>
<addrLine>University of Nebraska&#8211;Lincoln</addrLine>
<addrLine>Lincoln, NE 68588-4100</addrLine>
<addrLine>http://cdrh.unl.edu</addrLine>
 </address>
                </distributor>
                <date>2016</date>
                <availability>
                    <p>Scholary Editing: The Annual of the Association for Documentary Editing is
                        freely distributed by the Association for Documentary Editing and the Center
                        for Digital Research in the Humanities at the University of Nebraska-Lincoln
                        and licensed under a Creative Commons Attribution-NonCommercial-ShareAlike
                        3.0 Unported License</p>
                </availability>
            </publicationStmt>
            <seriesStmt>
                <title level="j">Scholarly Editing: The Annual of the Association for Documentary
                    Editing</title>
                <respStmt>
                    <resp>editor</resp>
                    <name xml:id="ag" key="Gailey, Amanda A.">Amanda Gailey</name>
                </respStmt>
                <respStmt>
                    <resp>editor</resp>
                    <name xml:id="awj" key="Jewell, Andrew W.">Andrew Jewell</name>
                </respStmt>
                <idno type="vol">37</idno>
                <idno type="ISSN">2167-1257</idno>
            </seriesStmt>
            <sourceDesc>
                <bibl>
                    <note>Born digital.</note>
                </bibl>
            </sourceDesc>
        </fileDesc>
        <revisionDesc>
            <change when="2016-03-23"><name xml:id="gk" key="Kirilloff, Gabi"> Gabi Kirilloff</name>
                markup in TEI XML</change>
        </revisionDesc>
    </teiHeader>
    <text>
        <front>
            <head type="main">Stories that Work</head>
            <head type="sub">Our Philological Future</head>
            <head type="sub">Presidential Address, Society for Textual Scholarship</head>
            <head type="sub">Joint Conference of the Association for Documentary Editing and the Society for Textual Scholarship</head>
            <head type="sub">Lincoln, Nebraska, 2015</head>
            <byline>Robin G. Schulze</byline>
        </front>
        <body>
            <p>Can I have an AMEN?</p>
            <p>No, really, can I have an AMEN!</p>
            <p>I say, AMEN, my brothers and sisters in the disciplines of documentary and textual
                and literary editing, because our time has come. The winds of scholarship are, I
                think, finally blowing our way. It is time to ride the current as far as we can.</p>
            <p>Lest you all think I have lost my mind, let me admit that I am surprised to hear
                myself say such a thing. Indeed, when I finished my edition of Marianne Moore’s
                poetry in 2002, <hi rend="italic">Becoming Marianne Moore: The Early Poems,
                    1907–1924</hi> (Berkeley: University of California Press, 2002), I pretty much
                vowed that I would never edit anything again. As all of us in this room know,
                editing and archiving are very hard work. My attempt to show Marianne Moore’s poetry
                in all of her goofy textual splendor cost me gray hairs, stomach upsets, and legal
                fees. My edition ran into copyright changes that nearly scotched years of work. My
                edition was orphaned at my press and almost left for dead. In spite of hundreds of
                pages of discursive, classically interpretive material, it nearly failed to get me
                promoted. The whole experience left me exhausted.</p>
            <p>As it turns out, I am headed back to the well of editing Marianne Moore—a well I
                thought I would never visit again. And fifteen years later, the well and its
                surroundings look very different. Since my edition appeared, many of the basic tools
                that scholars need to navigate Moore’s verse have made their way into the world.
                There are a series of wonderful editions by Heather White, who picked up where I
                left off, granting access to Moore’s poems in multiple versions from 1924 to
                    1941.<ptr target="#note1" xml:id="nr1" n="1"/> There is a brilliantly edited and
                selected collection of letters.<ptr target="#note2" xml:id="nr2" n="2"/> There is a
                masterful, beautiful, poignant, and accurate biography that gives Moore’s life a
                narrative arc.<ptr target="#note3" xml:id="nr3" n="3"/> Some of the most important
                Moore materials in the Rosenbach Museum and Library in Philadelphia have finally
                been digitized in the process of basic conservation. The Moore estate has changed
                hands. And of course, the world of digital technology has changed dramatically.
                First generations of digital projects and products have tobogganed into second and
                third. The Smart Phone and iPad have changed computer interfaces and the portability
                and pourability of content. The E-ink technology, the basis for the easily readable
                Kindle screen that I reported on to the Society for Textual Scholarship community in
                1999(!) has changed the ways in which people read and think about reading.</p>
            <p>So I am going back to create, in concert with some of my favorite colleagues
                (Elizabeth Gregory, Cristanne Miller, and Heather White), a digital edition of
                Marianne Moore’s notebooks—one of the holy grails of modernism. Moore’s notebooks
                contain an exquisite record of a mind at work—drafts of poems, copious notes from
                her daily reading and research, a host of almost impossibly catholic materials that
                range from quotes snagged from high-toned critical commentary to snippets of
                advertisements for number 2 pencils and Johnnie Walker Scotch. Moore also mined her
                own life for poetic material on a regular basis, but not in ways that later poets
                would deem “confessional.” Instead, like Harriet the Spy, she recorded what other
                people said. Her notebooks are filled with comments by her modernist peers—pieces of
                monologue and dialog from just about every modernist writer who passed through the
                New York scene in the early decades of the twentieth century. In part, I am going
                back because this documentary material poses every challenge possible. The notebooks
                are profoundly visual as well as linguistic in content. They contain multiple genres
                of writing. They are private and public. They contain quotes from all sorts of
                contemporary print sources that constitute Moore’s quirky representation of the
                chaotic intellectual culture of the early twentieth century. They challenge the
                whole notion of how and why and what we annotate. To edit these notebooks, Elizabeth
                and Cris and Heather and I are going to have to create a “knowledge site,” to use
                Peter Shillingsburg’s phrase, that can make sense of many, many different ways to
                use and interpret this material.<ptr target="#note4" xml:id="nr4" n="4"/></p>
            <p>I know that this edition might be a fool’s errand. But I am also going back because I
                have a sense of mission. I am going back to the notebooks in the full knowledge that
                this damn project might take the rest of my life. It might never get off the
                self-sustaining funding launching pad. It might crash and burn on still-lurking
                issues of copyright. It might be obsolete by the time it goes live. I have none of
                the certainties that I have when publishing in print. Everything is a risk. I know
                why scholars don’t take on these kinds of projects. And yet, I think this is a good
                time for me, and for all of us, to really lean in. Here’s why.</p>
            <p>In September of 2014, I was brave enough, or dumb enough, to take a position as an
                academic associate dean of the humanities at the University of Delaware. The post
                has been, to say the least, a challenge. Delaware is a good midsized research
                institution. It is, however, facing some major challenges. UD was insulated from the
                titanic financial meltdown of 2008. Endowments and DuPont contributions kept the
                school sailing on a tide of easy money that started to dry up just when the current
                (and exiting) president put a new “resource-based budgeting” model in place seven
                years ago. The long and the short is that the chickens of limited resources are just
                now coming home to roost in the UD College of Arts and Sciences—an odd scenario for
                those who have worked at Delaware for any length of time. The current budget
                restrictions have sent everyone scrambling, and competition for resources has become
                fierce. I have had to gear up arguments for the humanities that resonate with
                physicists, mechanical engineers, and professors of finance. I have had to sell my
                priorities to the parents of kids who would rather cut off their arms than send them
                to school to study art history, history, philosophy, or English. I’ve had to
                convince donors that their hard-earned money is best spent on culture.</p>
            <p>All this may seem impossible. But I am happy to report that some of my arguments have
                been winning. So take heart. I have been carrying the day because it is just the
                sorts of work that those of us in this room are doing that is the most exciting to
                people who wouldn’t know a humanity if it bit them in the rear. It is time for all
                of us to take advantage of a cultural moment that is now emerging. To that end, I’d
                like to share with you some real-life arguments that have helped me sell philology
                to the sharks.</p>
            <p>I start my pitch with a basic premise—that no one sets out in this life to edit,
                curate, exhibit, or archive anything without a sense of the importance of, to use
                Jerome McGann’s elegant phrase, “preserving the precious remains of our own
                alienated lives.”<ptr target="#note5" xml:id="nr5" n="5"/> I also begin with the
                premise that such preserving is basic human activity in the modern world. Every
                person on the planet understands the act of saving material things as a means to
                access memory. We are all curators and editors and archivists of our own lives. We
                decide which material objects to save and which to toss out as we move through the
                years. Each time we revisit our stuff we narrate once again for ourselves and others
                who we are and what we value. Acts of private curation are powerful. When I moved to
                Delaware and downsized my home, I faced the problem of my lifelong library of paper
                books. I had to decide which volumes to keep and which to give away, a task that
                immediately got tied up with so much more than the needs of my current scholarly
                life. So many of the books had notes and highlights and marginalia and traces of who
                I was at the time I read them. They were material mnemonic devices that stored
                memories of my entire adulthood, a physical record of the life I have lived inside
                my head. Sorting through them, I had to decide which memories were important enough
                to hold on to in that material form. I had to re-narrate, re-edit, re-curate my life
                to date.</p>
            <p>Even those who see the humanities as the educational grasshopper that sponges off the
                ant of the sciences understand the activities of personal archiving. And they also
                understand that acts of editing, curating, archiving, exhibiting, and narrating with
                material objects take place on levels far beyond the personal where the stakes are
                indeed very high. We are the keepers and, more importantly, creators of our material
                cultural heritage through acts of editing, curating, and archiving. I have managed
                to pull down large amounts of cash by explaining to my institution that those of us
                who edit are in the business of telling vital cultural stories with material objects
                and that we are training others every day to do the same. Newsflash: academic
                administrators at all levels are officially sick of supporting scholars in the
                humanities who seem determined to talk only to other scholars. Forms of
                hyper-professionalized humanities research have always had a slim purchase in
                academia. We aren’t, after all, out curing cancer or creating patents. Most
                administrators, however, understand that what we do as editors is important public
                work. They get museums and preserving and collecting things. They have watched <hi
                    rend="italic">Antiques Roadshow</hi> and understand that stuff, particularly
                material documentary stuff, matters to people and that stuff tells stories about who
                we are as a people and a nation. Editors and archivists are the original public
                humanists, and it is time for all of us to stand up and claim that role loud and
                strong.</p>
            <p>So even if you don’t feel comfortable doing it, you need to make claims for the
                public significance of your work. You need to tell people that your research and
                scholarship is pitched not just to other scholars but to a wider public—that you are
                involved directly in the sorts of preserving, conserving, curating, and editing
                activities that make culture available and accessible to people beyond the six
                scholars who will probably read your next monograph. You need to be able to explain,
                in one breath, on the elevator between first and third floor, why the texts or
                artifacts or documents you are presenting to the world are important, and you need
                to do it in such a way that not only your students but also the parents of your
                students can understand you. You need to trace the second life of your scholarship
                because this is important to administrators and donors. Where and how is what you
                are doing making news? Making the world better? And you need to do all this with
                style and flair.</p>
            <p>Our time has come as well because we are not only public humanists but also at the
                forefront of new forms of humanities education that make administrators sit up and
                take notice. The words to use here are “project-based learning.” Those of us engaged
                in large editorial and archival projects, be they in cyberspace or physical space,
                can offer our students classroom experiences that others can’t by engaging them
                directly in the work we are doing. When you talk to your administrators, you need to
                tell them that project-based classes ensure that students are getting real-world
                experience in complex, team project planning with real-world consequences. You need
                to tell them that students in such classes learn to negotiate the difficult
                relationship between the material and the digital, that they gain skills as well as
                content knowledge, that they, too, are engaging in important acts of public
                scholarship. You need to emphasize the footprints that such projects create for
                institutions, the way they help advertise and brand the student experience as
                innovative and outward looking. Project-based classes sound a lot like internships,
                and that is a plus for administrators. The difference is that they are internships
                that we control, that we make into deeply intellectual experiences that ask all the
                vital questions about history, about text, about materiality, about our digital
                future—questions that haunt our work. Even if you are used to doing your work by
                yourself, hunkered down in whatever archive drives your passion, you need to
                re-conceive of yourself as a team leader. You need to talk about your “lab” without
                flinching. And you need to do this with style and flair.</p>
            <p>A sidebar: As a deanlette, I am inclined to ask my humanities faculty members a
                pointed question: “How bored are you?” Seriously, if the academic major in which you
                teach looks like one that you could have taken when you were in college—or worse,
                one your mom or dad could have taken—what does that say about the humanities? All of
                us in this room are doing work that is SO much more interesting than most of what I
                see listed in course catalogs. The challenge is to remake the experience of our
                undergraduate learners in ways that show them the public significance of what we do.
                That, I think, will do more than anything else to ensure our cultural future.</p>
            <p>I will end by sharing a story that I use with parents, administrators, and donors
                that is a bit more abstract but, for me, lies at the heart of what we do as public
                humanists. When I get up before the masses, I say this: that being trapped in a
                world of literal meaning is the equivalent of being trapped in hell. If we are
                generating students who have no access to or understanding of symbolic content or
                its history, transmission, and creation—students who can’t make the leap between the
                literal and the figurative—we are producing sad and desperate souls who have no
                access to the deeper meaning of anything in life. We are making kids who live in two
                dimensions, who confuse surface for depth, who never ask why people are using one
                set of words and images to communicate rather than another. Abandon all hope, ye who
                enter here—there is no joy, no enlightenment, no creativity.</p>
            <p>I am happy to tell you that everything you do every day, in terms of your scholarship
                and your teaching, is vitally important, and that, yes, there are people out there
                who will listen and nod. And yes, if you get your story straight and speak clearly,
                with style and flair, they will open their pocketbooks.</p>
        </body>
        <back>
            <div type="notes">
                <note xml:id="note1">Marianne Moore, <hi rend="italic">A-Quiver with Significance:
                        Marianne Moore, 1932–1936</hi>, ed. Heather White (Victoria, CA: ELS
                    Editions, 2008); Marianne Moore, <hi rend="italic">Adversity &amp; Grace:
                        Marianne Moore, 1936–1941</hi>, ed. Heather White (Victoria, CA: ELS
                    Editions, 2012).</note>
                <note xml:id="note2">Marianne Moore, <hi rend="italic">The Selected Letters of
                        Marianne Moore</hi>, ed. Bonnie Costello, Celeste Goodridge, and Cristanne
                    Miller (New York: Alfred Knopf, 1997).</note>
                <note xml:id="note3">Linda Leavell, <hi rend="italic">Holding on Upside Down: The
                        Life and Work of Marianne Moore</hi> (New York: Farrar, Straus, Giroux,
                    2013).</note>
                <note xml:id="note4">For Shillingsburg’s in-depth definition of the “knowledge
                    site,” see Peter Shillingsburg, <hi rend="italic">From Gutenberg to Google:
                        Electronic Representations of Literary Texts</hi> (Cambridge, UK: Cambridge
                    University Press, 2006), 80–125.</note>
                <note xml:id="note5">Jerome McGann, <hi rend="italic">A New Republic of Letters:
                        Memory and Scholarship in the Age of Digital Reproduction</hi> (Cambridge,
                    MA: Harvard University Press, 2014), 47.</note>
            </div>
        </back>
    </text>
</TEI>
