<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<?xml-model href="http://www.tei-c.org/release/xml/tei/custom/schema/relaxng/tei_all.rng" type="application/xml" schematypens="http://relaxng.org/ns/structure/1.0"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
    <teiHeader xml:lang="eng">
        <fileDesc>
            <titleStmt>
                <title level="m">Introduction</title>
              
                <author>Rebecca Nesvet</author>
                <respStmt>
                    <resp>Transcription and encoding</resp>
                    <name xml:id="RN">Rebecca Nesvet</name>
                </respStmt>
            </titleStmt>
            <editionStmt>
                <edition>
                    <date>2017</date>
                </edition>
            </editionStmt>
            <publicationStmt>
                <authority>Scholarly Editing: The Annual of the Association for Documentary
                    Editing</authority>
                <address>
                    <addrLine>http://www.scholarlyediting.org</addrLine>
                </address>
                <publisher>Association for Documentary Editing</publisher>
                <publisher>University of Nebraska&#8211;Lincoln</publisher>
                <distributor>
                    <name>Center for Digital Research in the Humanities</name>
                    <address>
                        <addrLine>319 Love Library</addrLine>
                        <addrLine>University of Nebraska&#8211;Lincoln</addrLine>
                        <addrLine>Lincoln, NE 68588-4100</addrLine>
                        <addrLine>http://cdrh.unl.edu</addrLine>
                    </address>
                </distributor>
                <date>2017</date>
                <idno type="file">intro.scienceart</idno>
                <idno type="edition">scienceart</idno>
                <availability>
                    <p>Scholarly Editing: The Annual of the Association for Documentary Editing is
                        freely distributed by the Association for Documentary Editing and the Center for
                        Digital Research in the Humanities at the University of Nebraska-Lincoln and
                        licensed under a Creative Commons Attribution-NonCommercial-ShareAlike 3.0
                        Unported License</p>
                </availability>
            </publicationStmt>
            <seriesStmt>
                <title level="j">Scholarly Editing: The Annual of the Association for Documentary
                    Editing</title>
                <respStmt>
                    <resp>2017 issue editor</resp>
                    <name xml:id="nhg">Nicole Gray</name>
                </respStmt>
                <respStmt>
                    <resp>editor</resp>
                    <name xml:id="ag">Amanda Gailey</name>
                </respStmt>
                <respStmt>
                    <resp>editor</resp>
                    <name xml:id="awj">Andrew Jewell</name>
                </respStmt>
                <idno type="vol">38</idno>
                <idno type="ISSN">2167-1257</idno>
            </seriesStmt>
            <sourceDesc>
                <bibl>
                    <note>Born digital.</note>
                </bibl>
            </sourceDesc>
            
        </fileDesc>
        <revisionDesc status="embargoed">
            <change when="2016-10-19" who="#rn"> made minor encoding corrections suggested by #nhg.</change>
            <change when="2016-11-12" who="#rn">major revisions due to discovery of the annotated volume described below.</change> 
            <change when="2016-11-21" who="#rn">minor line edits; added Briggs quote; edited encoding of block quotes.</change>
            <change when="2016-11-29" who="rn">edited Introduction to account for bolding of
                “supplied” text (in the script file.)</change>
            <change when="2016-12-07" who="rn">various edits in response to draft workup and nhg questions; section moved.</change>
            <change when="2016-12-16" who="rn">edited header of Figure 2 to credit Thomas Onwhyn.</change>
            <change when="2016-12-22" who="rn">added Stedman Jones quote; standardized all dates to British style.</change>
            <change when="2016-12-27" who="rn">changed faulty hyperlinks.</change>
            <change when="2017-01-05" who="rn">rewrote handwriting evidence paragraph, corrected acknowledgement of the Rare Book Collection, Wilson Special Collections Library, in accordance with their policy.</change>
            <change when="2017-01-17" who="rn">updated citation of forthcoming <hi rend="italic">Notes and Queries</hi> article in response to 1/16/2017 receipt of page proofs; added reference to <hi rend="italic">Mazeppa</hi>.</change>
            <change when="2017-04-09" who="#rn">in previous draft copy, edited description of QM in accordance with viewing of all of UNC copy</change>
            <change when="2017-04-19" who="#rn">began to implement edits and proofreading as described in editor and reviewer feedback. Completed <date when="2017-05-08">2017-05-08</date>.</change>
            <change when="2017-05-24" who="#rn">line edits: (1) insertion of "Rymer's novel" (line 297) and substitution of "that" for "to" (line 761), (3) corrected mixed up numbering of footnotes 5-7, (4) added missing # to 3 note# tags so that links will work, (4) added missing comma to one citation. </change></revisionDesc>
    </teiHeader>
    <text>
        <front/>        
        <body>
        <div>
                <figure type="enlargeOnClick" n="1">
                    <head>Figure 1</head>
                    <graphic url="Nesvet_190_0012.jpg"/>
                    <figDesc><hi rend="italic">Science and Art</hi> in the <hi rend="italic">Queen’s
                            Magazine</hi> 1 no. 5 (August, 1842), 190. Photograph courtesy of
                        the Rare Book Collection, Wilson Special Collections Library, University of North Carolina, Chapel Hill, 2016.</figDesc>
                </figure>
                <head>Introduction</head>
            <byline>by Rebecca Nesvet</byline>
                <p>On 24 July, 1820, an advertisement in the <hi rend="italic">London Morning
                        Post</hi> announced “The Triumph of Mechanism.” In an exhibition room in the
                    Western Exchange, Bond Street, a man&#8211;shaped machine called “PROSOPOGRAPHUS, the
                    AUTOMATON ARTIST” was reportedly drawing perfect silhouettes of astonished
                    visitors and strategically placed portrait busts. European spectators had seen
                    other automata write their inventor’s name, play music, or make sounds, but
                    Prosopographus was different. This automaton’s output seemed neither
                    predetermined by its inventor nor limited to a narrow range of options. “[T]he
                    only Automaton in the world that takes Likenesses,” Prosopographus could
                    complete “a Profile Likeness in one minute.”<ptr target="#note1" xml:id="nr1"
                        n="1"/> By 1825, the advertising presented Prosopographus as an existential
                    threat to the human artist. An ad placed in the <hi rend="italic">Theatrical
                        Observer and Daily Bills of the Play</hi> claimed that the “Automaton Artist
                    [...] draws Likenesses with more certainty,” or accuracy, “than is in the power
                    of the living hand to execute.”<ptr target="#note2" xml:id="nr2"
                        n="2"/></p>
                <p>These ads played upon widespread fears. In 1815, during the Luddite rebellion
                    against the imposition of labor&#8211;saving machines upon the weaving industry,
                    the utopian reformer Robert Owen had condemned the emerging factory economy and
                    the machines that made it possible. The son&#8211;in&#8211;law of a Scottish
                    industrialist, Owen saw firsthand the effects of the “manufacturing system” upon
                    the children who constituted much of his father&#8211;in&#8211;law’s workforce.
                    “Is it to be imagined,” Owen asked, “that the British Government will ever put
                    the chance of a trivial pecuniary gain of a few, in competition with the solid
                    welfare of so many millions of human beings?”<ptr target="#note3" xml:id="nr3"
                        n="3"/> The answer was affirmative. The Luddites were suppressed, and
                    Prosopographus warned middle&#8211;class Londoners that even skilled artists
                    could find themselves replaced by machines.</p>
                <p>A similar warning is issued in an obscure playscript of 1820. <hi rend="italic"
                        >Science and Art, A Farce, in Two Acts</hi> concerns a young London lawyer,
                    Jack Freeman, who falls in love with Maria, the ward of an inventor of automata,
                    Peter Patent. This industrial&#8211;age Pantalone intends to save the British
                    nation a great deal of money by replacing various entire professions with his
                    patent automata. Freeman gains access to Patent’s home by masquerading as an
                    automaton, in a performance choreographed by his friend Dick Lobby, another
                    unscrupulous lawyer. When Lobby brings the pseudo&#8211;automaton to Patent, the
                    confusion of machine with human creates comic mayhem, and forces Patent to
                    question his previous dismissal of the human in favor of the machine. Meanwhile,
                    the <hi rend="italic">denouément</hi> hints that Freeman is not a self&#8211;acting individual, or free
                    man, but a part of a social machine, for he has unwittingly pursued Maria in
                    accordance with a plan designed by others.</p>
                <p>Written by the critically neglected working&#8211;class London novelist, poet,
                    and engraver Malcolm Rymer (ca. 1775&#8211;1835), <hi rend="italic">Science and
                        Art</hi> is here republished for the first time since the nineteenth
                    century. It deserves scholarly attention not only for its commentary on the
                    Industrial Revolution, but for the story of the editor who facilitated its
                    initial publication, the author’s son James Malcolm Rymer (1814&#8211;84). In
                    the 1840s&#8211;60s, this Rymer achieved considerable literary success by
                    prolifically penning “penny bloods,” or cheap fiction serials targeting
                    working&#8211;class readers. His bloods included the <hi rend="italic"
                        >Dracula</hi> precursor <hi rend="italic">Varney, the Vampyre; or, the Feast
                        of Blood</hi> and <hi rend="italic">The String of Pearls; or, the Barber of
                        Fleet&#8211;Street</hi>, the earliest tale of the fictional entrepreneur,
                    machine&#8211;inventor, murderer, and food&#8211;processing magnate Sweeney
                        Todd.<ptr target="#note4" xml:id="nr4" n="4"/> Before these triumphs, Rymer
                    published his late father’s play <hi rend="italic">Science and Art,</hi> without
                    attribution, in the August, 1842 fifth and final number of the <hi rend="italic"
                        >Queen’s Magazine</hi>.<ptr target="#note5" xml:id="nr5" n="5"/>
                </p>
                <p>This edition aims to reveal <hi rend="italic">Science and Art</hi>’s place in the
                    neglected history of the Rymers of London. Scholars of nineteenth&#8211;century
                    literature are familiar with prominent literary families, such as the Shelleys,
                    Brontës, Brownings, and Wildes. Whereas these luminaries are all upper&#8211; or
                    middle&#8211;class families, the Rymers were working&#8211;class men and women.
                    Furthermore, the Rymers’ creative activity spanned the Romantic and Victorian
                    eras, presenting a challenge to the longstanding periodization of
                    nineteenth&#8211;century British literature. Advocating for scholars of
                    nineteenth&#8211;century poetry to read across period boundaries, Charles
                    Laporte (2003) has pointed out that “highbrow Romantic theory tended … to shape
                    Victorian poetic practice” and that “its influence entered all facets of
                    Victorian high culture.”<ptr target="#note6" xml:id="nr6" n="6"/> However,
                    Romantic&#8211;era writing that was not considered “highbrow” also shaped the
                    generation that followed it. For instance, Gregory Dart (2012) has traced the
                    development of “Cockneyism” from Leigh Hunt (and Keats, and Hazlitt) to
                        Dickens.<ptr target="#note7" xml:id="nr7" n="7"/> A similar process informs
                    the overlooked journey to print of <hi rend="italic">Science and Art</hi>. Its
                    composition by Malcolm Rymer and its publication by his son both contribute to a
                    century-spanning discourse about industrialization, labor, and human dignity. I
                    hope that widening access to the text of <hi rend="italic">Science and Art</hi>
                    and some of its contexts will help to facilitate greater understanding of
                    Malcolm and James Malcolm Rymer’s shared and individual contributions to
                    nineteenth&#8211;century literature and will expedite their incorporation
                    into the canon and curriculum.</p>
            </div>
            <div>
                <head>“By Mr. M. Rymer&#8212;1820”</head>
                
                <p>It has very recently become possible to identify Malcolm Rymer as the author of
                        <hi rend="italic">Science and Art</hi> and the composition date as 1820. The
                    play was unattributed and undated until October 2016, when the Rare Book
                    Collection, Wilson Special Collections Library, University of North Carolina,
                    Chapel Hill acquired from the London antiquarian book dealer Jarndyce and
                    Company an incomplete copy of the first and only volume of the <hi rend="italic"
                        >Queen’s Magazine</hi> (1842), edited by James Malcolm Rymer. Bound into
                    this book are the five numbers of the volume, dated April through August 1842,
                    and the magazine’s Prospectus. However, some components are missing. The first
                    number has no contents page. An engraved portrait of Rymer has been excised from
                    the second  number. From the fourth, the pages containing one complete article
                    (“Why is the Queen’s Life Attempted?”) are missing.<ptr target="#note8" xml:id="nr8" n="8"/> It is unknown who defaced the volume, nor at what
                    point(s) in its history. </p>
                <p>According to Jarndyce cataloguer and penny bloods scholar Helen R. Smith, this
                    particular copy of the <hi rend="italic">Queen’s Magazine</hi> had once been in
                    James Malcolm Rymer’s possession. Smith also points out that some of its
                    contents bear handwritten corrections or annotations, and one hand is Rymer’s.
                    In the first number, his signature adorns a review of the play “Acis and
                    Galatea,” which the celebrated actor&#8211;manager William Macready was then
                    mounting at the theatre at Drury Lane. In the third, a handwritten annotation
                    identifies Rymer as the poet of “Love’s Fables,” correcting the printed
                    attribution to “George Hillier Fantome.”<ptr target="#note9" xml:id="nr9" n="9"/>
                    This pseudonym combines the name of the publisher George Hillier (1815&#8211;66)
                    with the French word for ghost. In the fifth number, at the top of the first
                    page of <hi rend="italic">Science and Art,</hi> another handwritten note reads
                    “By Mr. M. Rymer&#8212;1820” (Figure 1).<ptr target="#note10" xml:id="nr10"
                        n="10"/></p>
                <p>I propose that this author is Malcolm Rymer. As I have shown in a contribution to
                        <hi rend="italic">Notes and Queries</hi> (2017), Malcolm Rymer, born in
                    Edinburgh, was active in the London literary community of the early nineteenth
                    century. He used the abbreviation “Mr. Rymer” for the bylines of two poems he
                    published in the <hi rend="italic">Monthly Magazine</hi> in 1815 and 1818. On
                    the title&#8211;page of his 1806 novel <hi rend="italic">The Spaniard, or the
                        Pride of Birth, A Tale</hi>, he styled himself “M. Rymer.” As he was the
                    only male imaginative writer called “M. Rymer” who was active during the Regency
                    or the early Victorian era, it is highly unlikely that a “Mr. M. Rymer”
                    published by Malcolm Rymer’s son could be anybody else.<ptr target="#note11" xml:id="nr11"
                        n="11"/></p>
                <p>The manuscript attribution of <hi rend="italic">Science and Art</hi> to Malcolm
                    Rymer is likely accurate because it apparently was scrawled by his son. The hand
                    differs significantly from James Malcolm Rymer’s signature on the review of
                    “Acis and Galatea,” but it closely resembles another of his signatures, that
                    with which he solemnized his marriage to Caroline Huttly in the St. James,
                    Clerkenwell parish record on April 27, 1839.<ptr target="#note12" xml:id="nr12"
                        n="12"/> This signature and the <hi rend="italic">Queen’s Magazine</hi>
                    inscription share similar capital and lowercase <hi rend="italic">m</hi>’s and
                    large, loose lowercase <hi rend="italic">er</hi>’s that appear somewhat like
                    uppercase letters. In each example, a strikethrough nearly bisects at least some
                    of the letters horizontally. This evidence combined with James Malcolm Rymer’s
                    connection to the UNC copy of his magazine suggests that the attribution is his
                    holograph annotation.</p>
               
                <p>Could <hi rend="italic">Science and Art</hi> actually have been written in the
                    1840s by James Malcolm Rymer and misattributed to his father? This is
                    improbable, as the play seems indeed to have been written in 1820, when James
                    Malcolm Rymer was only six years old. It appears to allude to topical events of 1820. In that year, Prosopographus was on
                    display. The play also includes a recurring topical joke that involves Lobby’s
                    claim that Patent, the London&#8211;based inventor of automata, is famous in
                    Asia and particularly celebrated in China. This joke would have made sense in
                    the early years of the nineteenth century because in the late
                    eighteenth and early nineteenth century, London was the global export center for
                    automata, largely on account of the activity of a few automaton&#8211;makers.
                    They included James Cox and the Swiss expatriates Henri&#8211;Louis
                    Jaquet&#8211;Droz and his foster brother Frédéric Leschot. Although some
                    Jaquet&#8211;Droz&#8211;Leschot wares were produced in their London workshop and
                    some in Switzerland, Leschot confessed that eventually, all new ones were
                    “engraved as though [made] in England, because it is the general opinion that
                    every thing of this kind [automata] made in that country is of better
                        workmanship.”<ptr target="#note13" xml:id="nr13" n="13"/> It was also a
                    common belief that the most zealous appreciators of such things were Chinese. In
                    the 1770s&#8211;90s, the Qianlong Emperor (d. 1799) was a frequent client of
                    this community of artisans. He became famous in Europe for his “apparently
                    insatiable” desire for automata and other mechanical “toys”<ptr target="#note14"
                        xml:id="nr14" n="14"/> Long before 1842, the deaths of the Qianlong Emperor
                    and the inventors here named had evaporated this international trade
                    network.</p>
                <p>Additional circumstantial evidence that <hi rend="italic">Science and Art</hi>
                    dates to the early nineteenth century is the reference to “those who march into
                    the field at the arbitrary pleasure of a despot.”<ptr target="#note15"
                        xml:id="nr15" n="15"/> In 1820, Napoléon’s <hi rend="italic">Grande
                        Armée</hi> was a vivid living memory, but in 1842, Britain demonized no
                    singular martial despot. Also, the elderly Patent seems more likely to have been
                    a child of the eighteenth century than the nineteenth, as he wears a wig long
                    enough to appear to be caught up by the fake “automaton.”<ptr target="#note16"
                        xml:id="nr16" n="16"/> Wigs were worn by upper&#8211;class men throughout
                    the eighteenth century, but, after the 1795 imposition of a tax on the white
                    powder with which the wigs were adorned, the style fell out of favor. “Cropped,
                    natural” hairstyles then predominated, while “wigs were increasingly stigmatized
                    as old&#8211;fashioned.”<ptr target="#note17" xml:id="nr17" n="17"/> An old man
                    in 1820, as Patent is, could be accustomed to wigs; not so a Victorian. These
                    details suggest that <hi rend="italic">Science and Art</hi> was more likely
                    composed in 1820, as the inscription claims, than in 1842. </p>
            </div>
        <div>
            <head>“Those Self&#8211;Moving Machines”</head>
            <p><hi rend="italic">Science and Art</hi> deserves contemporary attention for its
                    contribution to the nineteenth&#8211;century British conversation about the
                    increasing automation of industry. Malcolm Rymer seems to have been concerned
                    throughout his career about conflicts between man and machine, science and art.
                    His novel <hi rend="italic">The Spaniard</hi> shows an industrious, honest
                    sixteenth&#8211;century Madrid barber persecuted by the Inquisition.
                    Temperamentally unsuited to the tonsorial trade on account of his aversion to
                    shedding blood or causing pain, Pedrosa de Leandrez eventually finds refuge in a
                    more liberal country: either England or Holland.<ptr target="#note18"
                        xml:id="nr18" n="18"/> A closer look at this tale reveals a timely political
                    agenda. In a significant departure from its source, Richard Cumberland’s <hi
                        rend="italic">The History of Nicolas Pedrosa, The Spaniard</hi> (1798), Rymer’s novel pits
                    a feeling artisan against the theory&#8211;driven proverbial machine of the
                    Inquisition, with its literal instruments of torture, suggesting a criticism of
                    the nascent Industrial Revolution.</p>
            <p>In <hi rend="italic">Science and Art</hi>, Malcolm Rymer more clearly represents
                    conflict between mechanical ingenuity and traditional labor. “One would imagine
                    that [Patent] thought nothing right in this world, as his invention,” or
                    ingenuity, “is continually on the rack to make it better,” Lobby says. “I don’t
                    know how many machines he has invented,” nor “how many schemes he has proposed
                    for the good of the public.”<ptr target="#note19" xml:id="nr19" n="19"/> In
                    practice, Patent’s “machines” and “schemes” seem unlikely to improve most
                    people’s lives. Instead, they threaten human labor, dignity, thought, and
                    creativity. The first example of Patent’s ingenuity introduced in the script
                    seems capable of disenfranchising quite a lot of human labor and also of rapidly
                    industrializing warfare. In the first scene, Lobby tells Freeman that Patent:
                        <quote>[...] not long ago [...] published proposals for an automaton
                        manufactory, in which he explained the variety of uses those self–moving
                        machines might be put to, and what an immense saving of expense to the
                        nation to employ them. In the first place he contended, that the business of
                        an army, according to the system of modern tactics, might as well be managed
                        by automatons as real soldiers; this would be a wonderful saving, as it
                        would render [...] unnecessary almost the whole host of army agents, army
                        contractors, and barrack masters. </quote>In this monologue, Lobby concedes
                    that an automaton army would save lives, as its soldiers would not die and could
                    be “repaired.”<ptr target="#note20" xml:id="nr20" n="20"/> However, Patent’s
                    rhetoric is primarily economic. He rejoices in the “saving of expense to the
                    nation,” the “wonderful saving,” and is not concerned for the livelihoods of the
                    “whole host” of men rendered “unnecessary” by his innovation.</p>
                <p>Patent’s subsequent scheme attacks the livelihood of members of an institution
                    even more deeply revered than the army: the Royal Navy. “When Old Patent went
                    down to the fleet at <placeName>Portsmouth</placeName> to publish his
                    proposals,” Lobby relates, “our brave tars [sailors] would have him thrown
                    overboard for a a rascal who wanted the enemy to get all the fighting to
                    themselves.” Patent then tries to market his automata to “a few wealthy noblemen
                    [...] who told him that if he could conceive to make them say aye and nay, they
                    would probably take a dozen or two, as they might have use for them upon the
                    dissolution of Parliament.”<ptr target="#note21" xml:id="nr21" n="21"/> In other
                    words, the aristocracy wants automated voters and representatives, whom they
                    could control more easily than the already small and privileged pre&#8211;Reform
                    electorate. This anecdote suggests that Patent’s automata cannot improve
                    society, so long as the power to commission, purchase, and operate them remains
                    with those who resist humane reform. </p>
                <p>Malcolm Rymer reinforces this idea by making Patent wrest technological power
                    away from the upper class, although only for a moment. Rymer’s lawyer characters
                    are unconcerned about Patent’s disruptive potential until they realize that his
                    inventions could threaten their own livelihoods. When Patent tells his friend,
                    Freeman’s lawyer uncle (“Old Freeman”), that he intends to develop a “scheme” to
                    settle law cases “without delay or expense,” thereby making lawyers unnecessary,
                    Old Freeman erupts in self&#8211;concerned outrage. “What? where would be the
                    traffic, if all mankind were to settle their disputes themselves? I say, where
                    would be the cash?”<ptr target="#note22" xml:id="nr22" n="22"/> Lawyers would
                    need to become Luddites were the professions to become the targets of industrial
                    improvement. </p>
                <p>The play’s comic resolution implies that mechanical innovation is not inherently
                    evil and that the boundary between human and machine is quite hazy. Young
                    Freeman and his uncle each don the automaton costume and, by the art of
                    play&#8211;acting, persuade Patent that they are the wondrous machine. Art
                    triumphs over mechanical genius, but when the ruse is exposed, Patent happily
                    accepts his ward’s marriage to Young Freeman, as it is the exact match he had
                    intended for her. This resolution uncomfortably implies that the rebellious
                    young <hi rend="italic">innamorati</hi> ultimately behave as their elders
                    designed, like machines. As the characters commemorate the nuptials by dancing,
                    Patent offers to accompany them on his “newly invented hurdy&#8211;gurdy,” a
                    traditional Welsh musical instrument that contains a wheel mechanism reminiscent
                    of clockwork.<ptr target="#note23" xml:id="nr23" n="23"/> When Patent has learnt
                    the pseudo&#8211;automaton’s secret&#8212;that “the most perfect machine the world ever
                    saw” is the human being&#8212;he is able to use his powers of invention to celebrate
                        love.<ptr target="#note24" xml:id="nr24" n="24"/> He learns to rejoice that
                    two humans might appreciate each other more than all other living and nonliving
                    machines.</p>
                
                </div>
            
            <div>
                <head>Audience and Actors</head>
                <p>Who, if anyone, was expected to perform <hi rend="italic">Science and Art</hi>,
                    and what was its target audience? Malcolm Rymer appears to have designed <hi
                        rend="italic">Science and Art</hi> for domestic consumption, not
                    professional performance. It seems never to have been produced in the commercial
                    theatre, as journalism from 1819&#8211;60 records no notices for any public
                    performance. It also was not published in its author’s lifetime, for reasons
                    that I do not know. However, Regency Britain had a culture of home theatricals,
                    such as those described in Austen’s novel <hi rend="italic">Mansfield Park</hi>
                    (1814). <hi rend="italic">Science and Art</hi> appears suited by design to this
                    performance mode. The specified settings are all either vague and featureless or
                    domestic. For instance, the first scene takes place in the high&#8211;living
                    Freeman’s “lodgings at the Temple.” This impressive landmark is represented by
                    merely a “two chairs and [a] table.”<ptr target="#note25" xml:id="nr25" n="25"/>
                    Likewise, Freeman meets Maria at the Opera at Covent Garden, but we do not see
                    this momentous meeting. Instead, it is described in retrospect in Freeman’s
                    dialogue with his servant Tom. </p>
                <p>The play’s depiction of Patent’s premises also suggests authorial acquiescence to
                    the limitations of domestic theatricals. The home of an eccentric inventor of
                    anthropomorphic automata would seem ripe for scenographic creativity. Many of us
                    have grown up entranced by the uncanny clutter of the ersatz automaton workshops
                    in films such as Fritz Lang’s <hi rend="italic">Metropolis</hi> (1927), Ridley
                    Scott’s <hi rend="italic">Blade Runner</hi> (1982), or Tim Burton’s <hi
                        rend="italic">Edward Scissorhands</hi> (1990). Conversely, <hi rend="italic"
                        >Science and Art</hi> calls for only “The House of Mr. Patent.”<ptr
                        target="#note26" xml:id="nr26" n="26"/> No automata, parts, nor tools are
                    explicitly prescribed, excepting the pseudo&#8211;automaton, and even the
                    automaton costume seems amateur&#8211;proofed. It consists of a “mask and
                    domino,” and the automaton’s mechanical nature appears merely via his stilted
                        walk.<ptr target="#note27" xml:id="nr27" n="27"/> Regency home thespians
                    would have been able to realize this simple effect. </p>
                <p>Nineteenth&#8211;century domestic performers would also have been able to cope
                    with the musical requirements of the piece. The script calls for Maria’s song to
                    be performed by or as a “symphony.”<ptr target="#note28" xml:id="nr28" n="28"/>
                    In the early nineteenth century, this word did not necessarily imply a full
                    orchestra. Another common meaning was “music in parts,” involving multiple
                    performers, or simply “concerted or harmonious music.”<ptr target="#note29"
                        xml:id="nr29" n="29"/> A few members of a family and their guests could
                    easily provide this incidental music. Intended for such a domestic setting, the
                    play encourages households and families to consider the plight of artisans and
                    other workers disenfranchised by the automation of their trades.</p>
                
            </div>
            
            
            <div>
                <head>The Editor’s Tale</head>
                <figure type="enlargeOnClick" n="2">
                    <head>Figure 2</head>
                    <graphic
                        url="p76.CUL.cropped.jpg"/>
                    <figDesc>Thomas Onwhyn, “The Spirit of the Age,” <hi rend="italic">Queen’s
                            Magazine</hi> 1, no. 2 (May, 1842), 76. Photograph by Cambridge
                        University Library, 2016. Onwhyn’s initials appear on the cover of one of
                        the books on the floor.</figDesc>
                </figure>
                <p>As Malcolm Rymer never saw <hi rend="italic">Science and Art</hi> published, what
                    alignment of the proverbial stars permits us to read it now? The solution to
                    that mystery is itself noteworthy. As the historian James P. McClure observed in
                    a 2014 Presidential address to the Association for Documentary Editing, scholars
                    need to pay attention to how manuscript sources find their way into print. To do
                    so, we must understand the lives, contexts, and motivations of editors,
                    especially documentary editors. As McClure explains: <quote>There is always a
                        second story about a published primary text … it always involves at least
                        one textual scholar or documentary editor (whether or not so&#8211;called)
                        [...] As far as the users of the texts are concerned, the second story is
                        often invisible, and its creators [...] are anonymous.<ptr target="#note30"
                            xml:id="nr30" n="30"/></quote>One “second story” of <hi rend="italic"
                        >Science and Art</hi> is mine. My previously explained objectives in
                    choosing to transcribe, contextualize, and circulate this text to a new
                    generation of readers, along with the priorities of <hi rend="italic">Scholarly
                        Editing</hi>’s editors, bring <hi rend="italic">Science and Art</hi> to your
                    screen today. Also critical to its appearance there is the twenty-first century
                    digital revolution, with its cataclysmic renegotation of the relationships
                    between science and art, machine and human. This renegotiation helpfully
                    democratizes the production and consumption of knowledge and story, yet presents
                    the navigators of the digital world with unprecedented
                    challenges&#8212;demanding exploration of the very questions that are central to
                        <hi rend="italic">Science and Art</hi>. However, this is not that play’s
                    only “second story.” I could not have read the script had an earlier editorial
                    process not taken place: that of <hi rend="italic">Science and Art</hi>’s first
                    editor, James Malcolm Rymer. </p>
                <p>What aspects of Malcolm Rymer’s play could have persuaded his son to publish it?
                    What external factors might have made its recovery appealing? The manuscript may
                    have spoken to James Malcolm Rymer on a thematic level. From early adulthood, he
                    evidently found himself torn between vocations in applied science and
                    imaginative art. As I have noted, he was raised by a creative family. Malcolm
                    Rymer wrote literature and produced engravings. Malcolm’s wife Louisa Rymer (<hi
                        rend="italic">née</hi> Dixon), James Malcolm’s mother, worked as a milliner,
                    making hats and accessories. Several of their children were artists, too. James
                    Malcolm Rymer’s brothers Chadwick and Gavin (or Gaven) were visual artists and
                    engravers. Three original engravings signed by Gavin Rymer (1834) reside in the
                    collection of the Guildhall.<ptr target="#note31" xml:id="nr31" n="31"/>
                </p>
                <p>Another engraver brother, Thomas, James Malcolm’s junior by two years, achieved
                    considerable artistic fame on two continents. In 1838, he stood trial for
                    forgery at the Old Bailey, London’s central criminal court. He was accused of
                    engraving a one&#8211;pound banknote to create a fiver&#8212;a considerable sum
                    in those days. He was found guilty and transported to Van Diemen’s Land for
                    life. There and on the Australian mainland, he intermittently practiced
                    engraving and forgery for decades. Repeatedly convicted of using his engraving
                    knowledge to forge banknotes, he essentially dared the authorities to catch and
                    keep him.<ptr target="#note32" xml:id="nr32"
                        n="32"/> In 1865, during his final
                    criminal trial, <hi rend="italic">Bell’s Life in Sydney and Sporting
                        Chronicle</hi> facetiously called him “an artist of great <hi rend="italic"
                        >note</hi>,” but this was not far from the truth, given his oft&#8211;tested
                    ingenuity.<ptr target="#note33" xml:id="nr33"
                        n="33"/> Via criminal
                    creativity, Thomas Rymer fit into the artistic, fiction&#8211;making family that
                    he would never again see. </p>
                <p>Like Malcolm, Chadwick, Gavin, and Thomas Rymer, James Malcolm Rymer initially
                    learned the art and science of engraving. In 1839, he further entrenched himself
                    in the Rymer clan by marrying a paternal cousin, Caroline Huttly, but he was
                    also carving out a new path. He became a civil engineer, and in 1840, registered
                    a patent for engraved furniture castors. Engraving the castors, he argued, would
                    increase their friction, making it harder for the furniture to shift about the
                        floor.<ptr target="#note34" xml:id="nr34" n="34"/> In this patent, Rymer
                    demonstrates his knowledge of engraving, but distinguishes himself from his
                    father and brothers by fashioning himself an inventor. He devises a new purpose
                    for a traditional artistic process, refusing to let it become obsolete. </p>
                <p>Rymer’s patent castor did not take off, but he soon entered a new vocation:
                    literature. In 1842, the twenty&#8211;eight&#8211;year&#8211;old Rymer embraced
                    his father’s calling by founding the <hi rend="italic">Queen’s Magazine</hi>. He
                    wrote much of the content himself, under his own name, the alias “the Editor,”
                    and several less transparent pseudonyms. The second number includes an engraving
                    of him as a man of letters (Figure 2). Provided by the illustrator Thomas
                    Onwhyn, this portrait shows Rymer sitting in a wing chair before a pile of
                    books, including a volume of Shakespeare, and conversing with an ethereal,
                    hovering, female “Spirit of the Age,” perhaps in homage to William Hazlitt’s
                    1825 literary caricature series of the same title. In this image, Rymer is a
                    well&#8211;read writer and canny editor: a Leigh Hunt type for a new generation
                    of London readers and writers. He also presented himself as an imaginative
                    writer, as the magazine includes his original fiction. Each number features an
                    instalment of one of his earliest bloods, <hi rend="italic">Jane Shore, an
                        Historical Romance</hi>, credited to him as “the Editor.”<ptr
                        target="#note35" xml:id="nr35" n="35"/></p>
                
                    <p>In compiling this periodical, Rymer followed in his father’s footsteps by
                    championing reform. Although Rymer <hi rend="italic">fils </hi>ultimately
                    achieved literary fame and some degree of financial solvency by supplying
                    fiction to newspapers priced at one penny, an expense affordable to
                    working&#8211;class readers, the <hi rend="italic">Queen’s Magazine</hi> cost a
                    shilling per number, as its title&#8211;page advertises. Its textual contents
                    corroborate that Rymer envisioned it as middle&#8211;class aspirational
                    literature that also reached out to other demographics. The Prospectus
                    identifies it as “A Family Magazine of the Highest Class,” and informs
                    “respectable Advertisers” that it will have: 
                <quote>
                    a <hi rend="italic">certain</hi> large circulation in a high class of
                        society, quite independent of the popular patronage it is fairly presumed it
                        will receive from a Public, who at no period of English history were so
                        fitted as now to judge of sterling literary pretensions.
                </quote></p>
                <p>In the magazine’s first number, Rymer exhorts his middle&#8211;class readers to
                    pursue reform and oppose aristocratic tyranny. In the first instalment of <hi
                        rend="italic">Jane Shore, </hi> he contends that “with an intelligent and
                    educated people,” the “incessant petty jealousies” and “eternal feuds” of the
                    “nobility [...] would [...] ensure [...] their extinction as a class.”<ptr
                        target="#note36" xml:id="nr36" n="36"/> This sort of rhetoric renders the
                    shilling periodical a tool of general political reform, which was needed in the
                    run&#8211;up to the May 1842 presentation of the Second Chartist Petition (the
                    “National Petition of the Industrious Classes”) to Parliament. The title of <hi
                        rend="italic">Queen’s Magazine</hi> hints that Victoria herself supported
                    the periodical and its agenda, though in fact she has no discernible connection
                    to it.</p>
                <p>The <hi rend="italic">Queen’s Magazine</hi> also examines the impact of
                    mechanical innovation on existing vocations and industries, which may help to
                    explain why James Malcolm Rymer chose to publish the play in that periodical. As
                    the published Prospectus of the <hi rend="italic">Queen’s Magazine</hi> states,
                    he intended a regular column on “Useful and Important Inventions.” In the first
                    number, Rymer reports that he “feel[s] much pleasure in commencing this feature
                    of our Miscellany with the admirable invention of Mr. Palmer,” the “Patent
                    Electrotint.” With this technology, which enlisted electricity to transfer
                    images directly to metal plates for printing, “the process of engraving or
                    etching is wholly superseded.” This might be perceived as a threat to the
                    livelihood of engravers, but only if they fail to innovate. Rymer presents the
                    electrotint process as an “[i]nvention which is calculated to confer the
                    greatest benefit upon the Fine Arts.”<ptr target="#note37" xml:id="nr37" n="37"
                    /> By embracing new technologies, artists might advance their medium and
                    engravers might avoid obsolescence.</p>
                <p>More worrying than Palmer’s Patent Electrotint to the British workers of the
                    1840s was the automation of vast industries. This fact makes <hi rend="italic"
                        >Science and Art</hi>’s concern with the displacement of the human worker by
                    machines as immediate in James Malcolm Rymer’s time as it had been in his
                    father’s. On March 16, 1839, an editorial in the Chartist newspaper <hi
                        rend="italic">The Northern Star</hi> articulated the widely held conviction
                    that “the progress of machinery has been so rapid, so unchecked, and so
                    self&#8211;protecting [...] that those who have been engaged in the pursuit
                    have, as if by magic, become the monied aristocracy of the country.”<ptr
                        target="#note38" xml:id="nr38" n="38"/> On February 21, 1846, the same
                    newspaper looked back across the 1840s and pronounced that “machinery had
                    pounced upon us with such an unexpected hop, step, and jump that society was
                    compelled to submit to such laws as regulations that its owners thought proper
                    to impose.”<ptr target="#note39" xml:id="nr39" n="39"/> The aforementioned
                    Chartist National Petition, signed by over three million people, explicitly
                    blamed automation (among other ills) for the workers’ dispossession, condemning
                    “monopolies of suffrage, of paper money, of <hi rend="italic">machinery</hi>, of
                    land, of the public press ... all arising from class legislation” (<hi
                        rend="italic">emphasis mine</hi>).<ptr target="#note40" xml:id="nr40" n="40"
                    /> After the petition’s May 1842 rejection by Parliament, a wave of general
                    strikes saw workers defend their livelihoods by sabotaging machinery. In June,
                    Staffordshire coal miners:

                    <quote>rak[ed] out the fires of colliery engines and pull[ed] out the plugs from
                        the steam chambers. As boiling water cascaded onto engine&#8211;room floors,
                        steam engines were rendered instantly inoperable&#8212;a dramatic form of
                        protest but without risk of permanent damage to the plant.<ptr
                            target="#note41" xml:id="nr41" n="41"/></quote>
                </p>
                <p>Nor were only collieries affected. Throughout the summer of 1842, strikers
                    “marched from factory to factory, removing the boiler&#8211;plugs in order to
                    bring steam engines to a stand,” and vowing to abstain from paid work until the
                    passage of the rejected Charter. In consequence of this strike wave, prominent
                    Chartists were arrested, to the obvious detriment of the movement.<ptr
                        target="#note42" xml:id="nr42" n="42"/> These events reveal <hi rend="italic"
                        >Science and Art</hi> as a timely contribution to a periodical of 
                    August, 1842.</p>
                <p>James Malcolm Rymer might also have chosen to dust off <hi rend="italic">Science
                        and Art</hi> when he did on account of the script’s accidental germaneness
                    to another topical controversy of the same summer. To Rymer, Patent might have
                    recalled the inventor Charles Babbage (1791&#8211;1871), whose “calculating
                    engines,” the “Difference Engine” and “Analytical Engine,” were then in
                    development. In mid&#8211;1842, Babbage publicly faced the greatest challenge of
                    his career, as the government considered whether to renew the funding of his
                    calculating engines project, which they had begun to support financially in
                    1833. Notably, the engines were known as automata. In a letter of 1823, Home
                    Secretary Robert Peel called the Difference Engine a “scientific automaton.”<ptr
                        target="#note43" xml:id="nr43" n="43"/> Therefore, Babbage and Patent invent
                    the same sort of machine. Indeed, while Patent “invents the wheels” and “axes”
                    and the automaton&#8211;Freeman walks as if “full of wheels,” the science
                    popularizer Dionysius Lardner, describing the calculating engines in an <hi
                        rend="italic">Edinburgh Review</hi> article that Babbage helped him to
                    prepare, claimed that the “project of a Calculating Engine” aimed to “substitute
                    an automaton for a compositor” and to “throw the powers of wheel&#8211;work into
                    thought,” which “could not fail to awaken the attention of the world.”<ptr
                        target="#note44" xml:id="nr44" n="44"/> In Babbage’s two major Difference
                    Engine models, writes the computer scientist Allan G. Bromley, the originator of
                    the Science Museum’s 1985&#8211;91 construction of the first complete functional
                    Difference Engine, “the digits of numbers are represented by the positions of
                    wheels (figure wheels) rotating on vertical axes.”<ptr target="#note45"
                        xml:id="nr45" n="45"/>
                </p>
                <p>Babbage’s utopian dreaming and overtures to the government also distinguish
                    Patent. His plans to make the army, navy, and legal system more efficient by
                    replacing human labor with automata recalls the critic Tamara Ketabgian’s apt
                    2011 characterization of Babbage as an “technophilia[c]” who “idealizes the
                    machine as an empowering prosthesis for humans.” Babbage’s <hi rend="italic">On
                        the Economy of Machinery and Manufactures</hi>, Ketabgian observes,
                    problematically “bases its guiding principle on the substitution of machinery
                    for human limbs.”<ptr target="#note46" xml:id="nr46" n="46"/> We have seen that
                    the sailors stationed at Portsmouth threaten to throw Patent “overboard for a
                        rascal.”<ptr target="#note47" xml:id="nr47" n="47"/> No doubt some
                    early&#8211;1830s compilers of nautical tables would similarly have eagerly
                    dunked Babbage. Rymer may have expected scientifically literate readers of the
                        <hi rend="italic">Queen’s Magazine</hi> to see Babbage in <hi rend="italic"
                        >Science and Art</hi>. In this context, James Malcolm Rymer’s publication of
                    his father’s work twenty&#8211;two years after its composition transforms that
                    work, investing it with new meaning. </p>
                <p>Of course, if we choose to read <hi rend="italic">Science and Art</hi>’s pompous,
                    bumbling Patent as an accidental <hi rend="italic">doppelgänger </hi>of Babbage,
                    the play might appear a short&#8211;sighted vision of scientific revolution.
                    Patent stands in stark contrast to Babbage’s most famous literary doubling, in
                    Charles Dickens’s <hi rend="italic">Little Dorrit</hi> (1857). This novel shows
                    the genius inventor Daniel Doyce vanquished by the bureaucratic idiocy of the
                    government “Circumlocution Office,” which finds Doyce a “notorious rascal,”
                    “guilty” of being “ingenious” and of “trying to turn his ingenuity to his
                    country’s service,” which “makes him a public offender directly.”<ptr
                        target="#note48" xml:id="nr48" n="48"/> However, Babbage may have deserved
                    the Patent treatment. The entire 1840s has long been known as the ‘Hungry
                    Forties’. As Peter J. Gurney has pointed out, the term was coined only in the
                    early twentieth century.<ptr target="#note49" xml:id="nr49" n="49"/> Still, it
                    is apt. Widespread working&#8211;class and indigent hunger preceded the Irish
                    Potato Famine (1845&#8211;7), and dominated both the nation and the national
                    consciousness throughout the period 1840&#8211;9. We cannot “underestimate the
                    political centrality of the debate on hunger” throughout this decade, writes
                        Gurney.<ptr target="#note50" xml:id="nr50" n="50"/> Charlotte Boyce adds
                    that it was not only the working&#8211;class and radical press that debated
                    hunger in this decade: it was the entire nation.<ptr target="#note51"
                        xml:id="nr51" n="51"/> The causes were many: rural to urban migration that
                    obliterated many workers’ and children’s access to home&#8211;grown food; the
                    oppressive Poor Law and Corn Laws, the latter the target of the Anti&#8211;Corn
                    Law League; a series of crop failures, and of course the three failed potato
                    harvests of the mid&#8211;1840s. </p>
                <p>The food crisis was impossible to ignore&#8212;unless, perhaps, one had designed
                    a wondrous machine and was monomaniacally focused on getting it built. That was
                    Babbage’s public image in many quarters, whether or not it was his reality. In
                        <hi rend="italic">Charles Babbage: Pioneer of the Computer</hi> (1982),
                    Babbage’s preeminent modern biographer Anthony Hyman claims that “Babbage’s
                    industrial interests and the possibilities of commercial application of his
                    calculating machines were quite unattractive” to Peel.<ptr target="#note52"
                        xml:id="nr52" n="52"/> This Prime Minister (1834&#8211;5 and 1841&#8211;6)
                    had never liked the idea of a government&#8211; funded calculating engine
                    project. His 1823 letter to Croker had derided Babbage as an inhabitant of
                    “Laputa,” the levitating island of impractical mathematicians in Jonathan
                    Swift’s <hi rend="italic">Gulliver’s Travels</hi> (1726).<ptr target="#note53"
                        xml:id="nr53" n="53"/></p>
                <p>This was a charitable interpretation of Babbage’s political outlook, for he was
                    not a Laputian, but an outspoken political conservative. As Hyman points out,
                    Babbage’s published writings demonstrate that his idea of the “manufacturing
                    class […] included factory workers and factory owners’ collaborating to form a
                    “free market.”<ptr target="#note54" xml:id="nr54" n="54"/> His <hi rend="italic"
                        >Economy of Manufactures</hi> appeared “during the most widespread class
                    struggles in England in the whole of the eighteenth and nineteenth centuries.”
                    During those struggles, Babbage “insist[ed] that working men should realize that
                    their interests and those of their masters were essentially in harmony.”<ptr
                        target="#note55" xml:id="nr55" n="55"/> Unsurprisingly, then, the government
                    only took measures to encourage Babbage’s completion of his engines, to the tune
                    of £17,000 of public money, during relatively conservative periods. The Duke of
                    Wellington proved his champion, but during the Peelite era, Babbage’s political
                    backing vanished.<ptr target="#note56" xml:id="nr56" n="56"/> In 1842, when he
                    requested more funding, it may have seemed that, surrounded by his fragmentary
                    wheel&#8211;work, he could not see suffering humanity beyond. Neither can <hi
                        rend="italic">Science and Art</hi>’s Patent until he learns that the most
                    “perfect machine” in history is the human. </p>
                <p>Despite the urgency of this message, <hi rend="italic">Science and Art</hi> and
                    the periodical in which it appeared immediately vanished into obscurity. The
                    play was not republished and the <hi rend="italic">Queen’s Magazine</hi> folded
                    after its fifth number, the one in which <hi rend="italic">Science and Art
                    </hi>had appeared. The critic Louis James (1963) states that the <hi
                        rend="italic">Queen’s Magazine</hi> “failed,” which would not have been
                        unusual.<ptr target="#note57" xml:id="nr57" n="57"/> Periodicals that were
                    founded and terminated in 1842&#8211;3 include <hi rend="italic">The Hackney
                        Journal </hi>(1842), <hi rend="italic">The Journal of the Working Classes
                        </hi>(1842),<hi rend="italic">The North of England Magazine</hi>
                    (1842&#8211;3), and the ethical vegetarian magazine <hi rend="italic">The
                        Healthian</hi> (1842&#8211;3). It seems as if the <hi rend="italic">Queen’s
                        Magazine</hi> did in fact prove unsustainable, as it clearly faced
                    unanticipated financial setbacks. The Prospectus announces advertising rates,
                    but the five numbers carry no advertisements, and we may assume that Rymer
                    failed to bring in anticipated advertising revenue. Likewise, his failure to
                    secure reviews of the <hi rend="italic">Queen’s Magazine</hi> in any other
                    periodical cannot have helped its circulation. </p>
                <p>However, no evidence confirms that Rymer was forced by financial difficulty alone
                    to terminate it. Discontinuation might also have been wise given the suppression
                    of Chartism that immediately followed the strikes and demonstrations of
                    June&#8211;August 1842. Alternately, Rymer might simply have decided to shift
                    his available time and energy to a more promising literary venture. By the end
                    of 1843, he was vigorously churning out fiction serials and other compositions
                    for the emerging publishing magnate Edward Lloyd, including his (Rymer’s) first
                    bestseller, the penny blood <hi rend="italic">Ada, the Betrayed. </hi> He also
                    edited periodicals for Lloyd and, later, the sometime Chartist G.W.M. Reynolds.
                    It is possible that in 1842, Rymer saw in Lloyd’s publishing firm a better
                    opportunity than the editorship of the <hi rend="italic">Queen’s Magazine</hi>
                    provided, and consequently jumped ship. In any case, as Rymer’s debut
                    publication, at least under his own name, the magazine served a vital purpose in
                    his literary development.</p>
            </div>
            
            <div>
                <head>Common Concerns</head>
                <p>After August 1842, in the penny bloods that Rymer produced for Lloyd, he
                    continued to share literary imagery and sociopolitical concerns with his late
                    father, while achieving a measure of success that Malcolm Rymer never enjoyed.
                    In <hi rend="italic">The Lady in Black, or, the Widow and the Wife</hi> (1847),
                    when the ghostly heroine, Sarah Whitehead, is first introduced, “[h]er thoughts
                    were far away from the busy, bustling crowd among which she moved, like some
                    automaton that had been made to walk wonderfully well.”<ptr target="#note58"
                        xml:id="nr58" n="58"/> Her ambulation recalls that of Young Freeman when he
                    portrays the automaton. Like the machine he pretends to be, Sarah is not a
                    thinking, feeling member of the metropolitan community. She only impersonates
                    one.</p>
                <p>Rymer portrays technology producing superfluous commodities and threatening
                    traditional culture in <hi rend="italic">Mazeppa; or, the Wild Horse of the
                        Ukraine </hi> (1850). This work departs from its Byronic source by
                    foregrounding a new character, a pompous London inventor reminiscent of Patent.
                    Mr. Peter Lumpus of High Holborn, the self&#8211;described “original inventor of
                    the royal patent no&#8211;lace&#8211;anti&#8211;tag stays,” and “inflexible
                    cravat” travels through Mazeppa’s exotic Eastern principality to peddle these
                    wares to the rumored nine hundred wives of the Sultan of Turkey.<ptr
                        target="#note59" xml:id="nr59" n="59"/> Like Patent, Lumpus is distinguished
                    by great confidence in his questionable inventions and a belief that they will
                    captivate an Oriental market. As in <hi rend="italic">Science and Art,</hi> this
                    ideology is held up to ridicule and threatens traditional ways of life. However,
                    Lumpus also repeatedly steps in to rescue the other characters, and invariably
                    succeeds. He makes the traditional hero, Mazeppa, all but effectively redundant,
                    yet also arguably presents British metropolitan innovation in a positive light.
                    He rises to the opportunity to risk his life to save his new friends and, as he
                    often points out, brings glory to High Holborn.</p>
                <p>Rymer’s most enduring penny blood, <hi rend="italic">The String of Pearls</hi>
                    (1846&#8211;7, republished in an expanded edition in 1850) speculates upon the
                    effects of industrialization on society in general and the working population in
                    particular. We have seen that in <hi rend="italic">Science and Art,</hi> Patent
                    is willing to upend society and destroy many people’s livelihoods in the name of
                    “saving.” When he speaks of technological “improvements” to society, he means
                    that he will save the elite money. He feels no sympathy for the affected
                    population. Neither does <hi rend="italic">The String of Pearls</hi>’s Sweeney
                    Todd. He invents a labor&#8211;and cost&#8211;saving “mechanical
                        arrangement.”<ptr target="#note60" xml:id="nr60" n="60"/> Namely, he
                    customizes his shop to feature two identical barber’s chairs affixed to a
                    rotating section of the floor that move through a secret trap door, fatally
                    dumping victims into the space below. Their bodies are processed by a few
                    workers at Mrs. Lovett’s “pie manufactory.”<ptr target="#note61" xml:id="nr61"
                        n="61"/> This factory is so productive: <quote>the retail part of Mrs.
                        Lovett’s business which took place principally between the hours of twelve
                        and one, was by no means the most important or profitable portion of a
                        concern which was really of immense magnitude, and which brought in a large
                        yearly income.<ptr target="#note62" xml:id="nr62" n="62"/></quote>This great
                    profit is monopolized by the factory owner (Todd), but his operation harms the
                    employees. When they learn that the flesh they have been rendering is human,
                    they go mad. While Patent’s automata threaten to take away British people’s
                    livelihoods, Todd’s factory morally corrupts them, destroys their will to live,
                    and proximately causes their deaths. Thirty years after Malcolm Rymer first
                    wrote his ambivalence about industrialization into <hi rend="italic">Science and
                        Art</hi>, his son expressed related concerns in a new story, one that has
                    outlasted their century&#8212;just as the debate over the ethics of automation
                    of industry has done. </p>
            </div><div>
                            <head>Editorial Methodology</head>
                <p>Like James Malcolm Rymer, twenty&#8211;first century readers might find <hi
                        rend="italic">Science and Art</hi> worthy of dissemination to a new
                    generation, one that has seen a technological revolution at least as exciting
                    and troubling as that of the Rymers’ Britain. It is my hope that in 2017 the
                    play will reach not only new reading audiences, but living, breathing, human
                    performers. This development is essential to further scholarly exploration of
                        <hi rend="italic">Science and Art</hi> because much that can be learned
                    about any play is more evident in performance than on the page. Consequently,
                    this edition is intended to make the text published in the <hi rend="italic"
                        >Queen’s Magazine</hi> more easily accessible to scholars and theatre
                    practitioners. </p>
                <p>In service of these two audiences, my editorial method combines aspects of
                    documentary and critical editing. I began by creating a faithful transcription
                    of <hi rend="italic">Science and Art </hi>as published in the UNC copy of the
                        <hi rend="italic">Queen’s Magazine.</hi> This transcription preserved the
                    punctuation and formatting idiosyncrasies and the typographical errors of the
                    original. Then, I introduced a few critical features to make the text easily
                    legible, especially to theatre practitioners reading it out loud without
                    rehearsal, in what is known as a cold reading. I have amended those
                    typographical errors that interfere with the meaning or smooth oral delivery of
                    the material. In all cases, these amendations are annotated and the original,
                    erroneous text supplied in note form. Obviously missing words are inserted,
                    marked as such using the “supplied” tag, and distinguished in red font with
                    broken underline. </p>
                <p>I have also standardized the playscript format. In the source text’s stage
                    directions and dialogue headers, character names are abbreviated and “Freeman”
                    used to indicate only “Young Freeman,” but I have silently amended this for
                    clarity’s sake. While the original includes the isolated word “Scene” at the top
                    of each scene, I omit it, replacing it with a numerical act&#8211;scene header.
                    Brief character descriptions are added to the “Dramatis Personae” to enable
                    readers easily to visualize the characters and distinguish them from each other.
                    These new descriptions are presented in square brackets to indicate that they
                    were not part of the source text.</p>
               <p>The more discursive footnotes support the critical work of this introduction by
                    relating the play to its nineteenth&#8211;century cultural contexts. By
                    reconstructing these contexts, I aim to advance a conceptualization of the
                    nineteenth century that foregrounds discourse on technological innovation and
                    automation of industry, that is not artificially disrupted by period boundaries,
                    and that recognizes the literary achievement of the Rymers of London.</p>
                
                
                
            
            </div>
                
        </body>
        <back>
            <div type="notes">
                
                <note xml:id="note1">“The Triumph of Mechanism,” <hi rend="italic">London Morning
                        Post</hi>, July 20, 1820: 1. This article was located by Patrick Feaster,
                        <ref
                        target="http://griffonagedotcom.wordpress.com/2015/02/13/prosopographus-the-automaton-artist"
                        >“Prosopographus, the Automaton Artist,”</ref>
                    <hi rend="italic">Griffonage-Dot-Com: Patrick Feaster’s Explorations in
                        Historical Media</hi> (last modified February 13, 2015).</note>
                
                <note xml:id="note2">“Prosopographus, the Automaton Artist,” <hi rend="italic">The
                        Theatrical Observer and Daily Bills of the Play</hi>, 30 September, 1825: 2.
                    Feaster presents evidence from advertisements showing that the silhouette artist
                    Charles Hervé invented and sometimes manipulated Prosopographus. See also
                    “Prosopographus, the Automaton Artist” <hi rend="italic">The Examiner</hi> 934,
                    no. 87 (1826): 285. H.J. Exeter, “The Camera Lucida,” <hi rend="italic"
                        >Mechanics’ Magazine</hi> 12 (1830): 335&#8211;6 speculates that
                    Prosopographus must have a human operator, who “goes behind” the sitter and
                    “traces the outline of the face [...] which is thrown upon the screen by a gas
                    light.” Prosopographus “can only take profiles” because the operator must keep
                    the sitter facing away from the evidence of his deception.</note>
                
                <note xml:id="note3">Robert Owen, <hi rend="italic">Observations on the Effect of
                        the Manufacturing System, With Hints for the Improvement of Those Parts of
                        it Which are Most Injurious to Health and Morals</hi>, 1815 (London,
                    Edinburgh, and Glasgow, 1817), 15.</note>
                
                <note xml:id="note4">These facts about James Malcolm Rymer’s career were pieced
                    together by Louis James, <hi rend="italic">Fiction for the Working Man, 1830&#8211;1850: a Study of the Literature Produced for the Working Classes in Early Victorian Urban England</hi>
                    (Oxford: Oxford University Press, 1963), 36&#8211;8, Robert Mack, <hi
                        rend="italic">The Wonderful and Surprising History of Sweeney Todd: The Life of Times of an Urban Legend</hi>
                    (Oxford: Oxford University Press, 2007), 146&#8211;7, Helen R. Smith, <hi
                        rend="italic">New Light on Sweeney Todd, James Malcolm Rymer, Thomas Peckett
                        Prest, and Elizabeth Caroline Grey</hi> (London: Jarndyce, 2002), and Dick
                    Collins, ed.,<hi rend="italic">The String of Pearls</hi> (Ware: Wordsworth,
                    2010), vii&#8211;ix. </note>
                
                <note xml:id="note5">“Science and Art,” <hi rend="italic">The Queen’s Magazine
                </hi>1, no. 5 (August, 1820): 190&#8211;207. The volume is continuously
                    paginated. In the source, the title is misspelled “Queens’” on each number’s
                    title page. I have silently amended the error throughout this edition.
                    References to numbers 1 through 5 of this magazine, excepting the no. 1 (April)
                    title page and no. 2 (May), 76 cite the copy in the Rare Book Collection, Wilson
                    Special Collections Library, University of North Carolina (UNC), Chapel Hill,
                    unless otherwise indicated. Other references cite the Cambridge University
                    Library copy. Citations of <hi rend="italic">Science and Art</hi> provide only
                    the page number.</note>
                
                <note xml:id="note6">Charles Laporte, “Post&#8211;Romantic Ideologies: Victorian
                    Poetic Practice, or, the Future of Criticism at the Present Time,” <hi
                        rend="italic">Victorian Poetry</hi> 41, no. 4 (2003): 521.</note>
                    
                <note xml:id="note7"> Gregory Dart, <hi rend="italic">Metropolitan Art and
                    Literature, 1810&#8211;1840: Cockney Adventures</hi> (Cambridge:
                    Cambridge University Press, 2012), 25.</note>
                    
                <note xml:id="note8">The defaced page is no. 2, 76. The sequence of missing pages
                    encompass no. 4, 163&#8211;70.</note>
                
                <note xml:id="note9">These annotations are mentioned in the Jarndyce catalogue entry
                    for the <hi rend="italic">The Queen’s Magazine </hi> volume now at UNC. See
                    Helen R. Smith, <hi rend="italic">Jarndyce Antiquarian Booksellers: Bloods and
                        Penny Dreadfuls: Catalogue no. 219</hi> (London: Jarndyce, 2016), item no.
                    274.</note>
                
                <note xml:id="note10"><hi rend="italic">Science and Art</hi>, 190.</note>
                
                    <note xml:id="note11">Rebecca Nesvet, “<hi rend="italic">The Spaniard</hi> and
                    Sweeney Todd,”<hi rend="italic">Notes and Queries</hi> n.s. 64, no. 1 (2017):
                    112&#8211;116 proposes that Malcolm Rymer composed <hi rend="italic">The
                        Spaniard, or the Pride of Birth, a Tale</hi> (London: G. Robinson, 1806).
                    Many library catalogues attribute this novel to James Malcolm Rymer, who in 1806
                    was not yet born. All discussion of <hi rend="italic">The Spaniard</hi> cites
                    the inscribed presentation copy at the University of California, Los Angeles
                    (UCLA) Libraries, Special Collections. The Malcolm Rymer holograph inscriptions
                    I mention appear on the front pastedown and half title of this copy. </note>
                
                <note xml:id="note12">For the James Malcolm Rymer signature that stylistically
                    recalls the attribution, see London Metropolitan Archives, Saint James,
                    Clerkenwell, <hi rend="italic">Register of Marriages</hi>, P76/JS1, Item no. 043
                    (1839), 240, in <hi rend="italic">The Church of England Parish Registers,
                        1754&#8211;1921,</hi>
                    <hi rend="italic">Ancestry.com Church of England Marriages and Banns,
                        1754&#8211;1921</hi> (accessed January 7, 2017).</note>
                
                <note xml:id="note13">Frédéric Leschot, quoted in Roger Smith, “The Swiss
                    Connection: International Networks in the Eighteenth Century Luxury Trades,” <hi
                        rend="italic">Journal of Design History</hi> 17, no. 2 (2004): 132.</note>
                
                    <note xml:id="note14">Clare Le Corbeiller, “James Cox and his Curious Toys,” <hi
                        rend="italic">Metropolitan Museum of Art Bulletin</hi> n.s. 18, no. 10
                    (1960): 318&#8211;24. While Le Corbeiller recycles the Orientalist stereotype of
                    the “insatiable” Eastern despot, Catherine Pagani, <hi rend="italic">“Eastern
                        Magnifience and European Ingenuity”: Clocks of Late Imperial China</hi> (Ann
                    Arbor: University of Michigan Press, 2001) offers a more nuanced, carefully
                    contextualized picture of the role of gift automata during the reign of the
                    Qianlong (“Ch’ien&#8211;Lung”) Emperor (r. 1735&#8211;96; d. 1799). Pagani, 1
                    introduces the Chinese concept of <hi rend="italic">zimingzhong</hi>, or
                    “self&#8211;sounding bells,” which encompassed clocks, automata, and other
                    apparently self&#8211;acting clockwork devices. As Pagani, 18&#8211;9, 37,
                    62&#8211;3 explains, in the sixteenth through nineteenth centuries, Western
                    visitors presented Chinese emperors with <hi rend="italic">zimingzhong</hi> as
                    diplomatic gifts, and such objects came to be strongly associated with Europe,
                    to the point of being called <hi rend="italic">xiwu</hi> (“western things”) or
                        <hi rend="italic">qiqi</hi> (“strange things,” ). From the early eighteenth
                    century through at least 1879, the Chinese capitol at Peking (Beijing)
                    maintained an Office of Clock Manufacture (<hi rend="italic">Zuozhongchu</hi>),
                    but clocks continued to be imported from Europe. The Qianlong Emperor indeed
                    embraced this tradition, collecting various clocks and mechanical animals and
                    people and writing poems in praise of <hi rend="italic">zimingzhong</hi>.
                    Pagani’s research makes it clear that far from being an infantile
                    toy&#8211;collector, the Qianlong Emperor celebrated his diplomatic relations in
                    the form of their ritual objects.</note>
                
                <note xml:id="note15"><hi rend="italic">Science and Art</hi>, 192.</note>
                
                <note xml:id="note16">Ibid, 197.</note>
                
                <note xml:id="note17">Deirdre Dawson, <hi rend="italic">Britain in the Hanoverian
                    Age, 1714&#8211;1837: An Encyclopedia</hi>, ed. Gerald Newman (New York: Garland, 1997),
                    770&#8211;1.</note>
                
                <note xml:id="note18"><hi rend="italic">The Spaniard</hi>,
                        193. </note>
                
                <note xml:id="note19"><hi rend="italic">Science and Art</hi>, 192.</note>
                
                <note xml:id="note20">Ibid, 192.</note>
                
                <note xml:id="note21">Ibid, 192.</note>
                
                <note xml:id="note22">Ibid, 202.</note>
                
                <note xml:id="note23">Ibid, 207.</note>
                
                <note xml:id="note24">Ibid, 203.</note>
                
                <note xml:id="note25">Ibid, 190.</note>
                
                    <note xml:id="note26">Ibid, 193.</note>
                
                <note xml:id="note27">Ibid, 197.</note>
                
                <note xml:id="note28">Ibid, 201.</note>
                
                <note xml:id="note29">“Symphony, n.” <ref target="http://www.oed.com"><hi
                            rend="italic">Oxford English Dictionary (OED) Online</hi></ref> 
                    (accessed December 22, 2016).</note>
                
                <note xml:id="note30">James P. McClure, <ref
                        target="http://scholarlyediting.org/2015/essays/essay.2015presidentialaddress.html"
                        >“The Second Story: Presidential Address for Documentary Editing Annual
                        Meeting, Louisville, Kentucky, 2014,”</ref>
                    <hi rend="italic">Scholarly Editing</hi> 36 (2015).</note>
                
                <note xml:id="note31">Gavin Rymer, “Peep Show,” “Punch and Judy,” “Guy Fawkes’ Day,”
                    (1834), Guildhall Library and Art Collection. These titles are identical to
                    those of two of the six <hi rend="italic">Scenes in London ... by G. Rymer
                    </hi>(London: Ackermann, 1834), advertised for sale as item no. 649 in the Maggs
                    Brothers’ catalog <hi rend="italic">English Literature of the 19th &amp; 20th
                        Centuries, being a selection of first and early Editions of the works of
                        Esteemed Authors &amp; Book Illustrators</hi> 443, no. 1 (1923): 133. </note>
                
                    <note xml:id="note32">See <hi rend="italic">“</hi>Trial of Thomas Rymer
                    (t18380514&#8211;1173), May 1838,” <ref target="http://www.oldbaileyonline.org"
                            ><hi rend="italic">Old Bailey Proceedings Online</hi></ref>, version 7.2
                    (accessed November 2, 2015). Collins has persuasively identified this convict as
                    James Malcolm Rymer’s brother. See Collins, September 2, 2012, comment on
                    “Thomas Rymer,” <ref
                        target="http://www.convictrecords.com.au/convicts/rymer/thomas/64334"><hi
                            rend="italic">British Convict Transportation Register</hi></ref>, State
                    Library of Queensland, Australia (accessed August 24, 2015). Public records
                    corroborate Collins’s assertion, as James Malcolm Rymer’s brother and the
                    convicted forger share an occupation (engraver), age, and origin, while in the
                    1841 British Census, Malcolm’s son Thomas is absent. Thomas Rymer’s individual
                    post&#8211;transportation convictions for banknote forgery are too numerous to
                    list. An indicative one is “Multum in Parvo,” <hi rend="italic">Sydney Morning
                        Herald</hi>, February 26, 1847, 2.</note>
                  
                <note xml:id="note33">“Forged Notes of the Week,” <hi rend="italic">Bell’s Life
                            in Sydney and Sporting Chronicle</hi>, November 18, 1865, 3.</note>
                
                <note xml:id="note34">Collins, <hi rend="italic">The String of Pearls</hi>, viii;
                    James Malcolm Rymer, <hi rend="italic">Specification of James Malcolm Rymer:
                        Castors for Furniture, &amp;c., A.D. 1840, No. 8485</hi> (London: Eyre and
                    Spottiswoode, 1857).</note>
                
                <note xml:id="note35">As Rymer announced in the “Notices to Correspondents” on the
                    verso of the unnumbered June, 1842 (no. 3) contents page, he intended to complete <hi
                        rend="italic">Jane Shore</hi> “within the twelvemonth, so as to be all in
                    vol. 1.” He did not keep his promise, for the serial was left unfinished when the magazine
                    suddenly folded. <hi rend="italic">Jane Shore</hi> was
                    published in complete form by Edward Lloyd in 1846. It is not known when the
                    later chapters were composed.</note>
                
                <note xml:id="note36"><hi rend="italic">Queen’s Magazine</hi>, no. 1 (1842),
                    7.</note>
                
                <note xml:id="note37"><hi rend="italic">Queen’s Magazine</hi>, no. 1, 31.</note>

                <note xml:id="note38"><hi rend="italic">Northern Star,</hi> March 16, 1839,
                        quoted in Gareth Stedman Jones, <hi rend="italic">Languages of Class:
                            Studies in English Working&#8211;Class History, 1832&#8211;1982
                        </hi>(Cambridge: Cambridge University Press, 1983), 151. Chartism was a
                        national political movement aimed at working&#8211;class enfranchisement,
                        primarily through universal male suffrage. It takes its name from the
                        ‘People’s Charter’ (1838), authored primarily by the London Chartist William
                        Lovett, which set forth six ‘points’ or demands. Repeated attempts to induce
                        Parliament to pass the People’s Charter (in 1839, 1842, and 1848)
                        failed.</note>
                
                <note xml:id="note39">
                    <hi rend="italic">Northern Star</hi>, February 21, 1846, quoted in Lucy Brown,
                    “The Chartists and the Anti&#8211;Corn Law League,“ in <hi rend="italic"
                        >Chartist Studies</hi>, ed. Asa Briggs, 1959 (London: Macmillan, 1977), 343. </note>
                    
                <note xml:id="note40">For the number of petition signatories, see Malcolm Chase,
                        <hi rend="italic">Chartism: A New History</hi> (Manchester: Manchester
                    University Press, 2007), 205. I quote the petition from Chase, 211.</note>
                        
                        <note xml:id="note41">Chase, 211.</note>
                    
                    <note xml:id="note42">G.D.H. Cole and A.W. Filson, <hi rend="italic">British
                        Working Class Movements: Select Documents: 1789&#8211;1875</hi> (London:
                    Palgrave Macmillan, 1965), 396.</note>
                    
                    <note xml:id="note43">Robert Peel to John Wilson Croker, March 8, 1823, in <hi
                        rend="italic">The Croker Papers: The Correspondence and Diaries of the Late
                        Right Honourable John Wilson Croker, LL.D., F.R.S., Secretary to the
                        Admiralty from 1809 to 1830</hi>, ed. Louis J. Jennings (Cambridge:
                    Cambridge University Press, 2012), 262&#8211;3. This letter is discussed in
                    Doron Swade, <hi rend="italic">The Cogwheel Brain: Charles Babbage and the Quest
                        to Build the First Computer</hi> (London: Little, Brown, 1999), 36.    </note>
                    
                    <note xml:id="note44"><hi rend="italic">Science and Art</hi>, 191&#8211;3;
                    Dionysius Lardner, “Babbage’s Calculating Engine,” <hi rend="italic">Edinburgh
                        Review</hi> 120 (1834), quoted in Swade, 85.</note>
                    
                    <note xml:id="note45">Allan G. Bromley, “Charles Babbage’s Analytical Engine,
                    1838” <hi rend="italic">IEEE Annals of the History of Computing</hi> 20, no. 4
                    (1998): 30.</note>
                    
                    <note xml:id="note46">Tamara Ketabgian, <hi rend="italic">The Lives of Machines:
                            The Industrial Imaginary in Victorian Literature and Culture</hi> (Ann
                        Arbor: University of Michigan Press, 2011), 18.</note>
                    
                    <note xml:id="note47"><hi rend="italic">Science and Art</hi>, 192.</note>
                    
                    <note xml:id="note48">Charles Dickens, <hi rend="italic">Little Dorrit</hi>, ed.
                    Peter Sucksmith, 1982 (Oxford: Oxford University Press, 2008),
                    133&#8211;4.</note>
                    
                    <note xml:id="note49">The origin of the phrase “the Hungry Forties” is <hi
                        rend="italic">The Hungry Forties: Life Under the Bread Tax: Descriptive
                        Letters and Other Testimonies from Contemporary Writers</hi>, ed. Jane
                    Cobden (London, 1904), as is explained in Peter J. Gurney, “‘Rejoicing in
                    Potatoes’: The Politics of Consumption in England during the ‘Hungry Forties’”
                        <hi rend="italic">Past and Present</hi> 203, no. 1 (2009):
                    100&#8211;1.</note>
                    
                    <note xml:id="note50">Gurney, 101.</note>
                    
                    <note xml:id="note51">Charlotte Boyce, “Representing the ‘Hungry Forties’ in
                    Image and Verse: The Politics of Hunger in Early&#8211;Victorian Periodicals,”
                        <hi rend="italic">Victorian Literature and Culture</hi> 40 (2012):
                    423.</note>
                    
                    <note xml:id="note52">Anthony Hyman, <hi rend="italic">Charles Babbage: Pioneer
                            of the Computer </hi>(Princeton: Princeton University Press, 1982),
                        191.</note>
                
                    <note xml:id="note53">Peel to Croker, <hi rend="italic">Croker Papers</hi>,
                    263.</note>
                    
                    <note xml:id="note54">Hyman, 85.</note>
                    
                    <note xml:id="note55">Ibid, 115&#8211;6</note>
                    
                    <note xml:id="note56">Ibid, 87.</note>
                    
                        <note xml:id="note57">James, 37.</note>
                    
                    <note xml:id="note58">James Malcolm Rymer, <hi rend="italic">The Lady in Black;
                        or, The Widow and the Wife </hi>(London: Lloyd, 1847), 1.</note>
                    
                    <note xml:id="note59">James Malcolm Rymer, <hi rend="italic">Mazeppa; or, The
                        Wild Horse of the Ukraine</hi> (London: Edward Lloyd, 1850), 85. The very
                    loosely adapted source of the Mazeppa mythos is George Gordon, Lord Byron, <hi
                        rend="italic">Mazeppa, A Poem</hi> (London: John Murray, 1819).</note>
                        
                    <note xml:id="note60">James Malcolm Rymer, <hi rend="italic">The String of
                            Pearls; or, the Barber of Fleet&#8211;Street, A Domestic Romance</hi>
                        (London: Edward Lloyd, 1850), 616.</note>
                    
                    <note xml:id="note61">Ibid, 65.</note>
                    
                    <note xml:id="note62">Ibid, 58.</note>
    
                
            </div>
        </back>
 
 
    </text>
</TEI>
