<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<?xml-model href="http://www.tei-c.org/release/xml/tei/custom/schema/relaxng/tei_all.rng" type="application/xml" schematypens="http://relaxng.org/ns/structure/1.0"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
    <teiHeader xml:lang="eng">
        <fileDesc> 
            <titleStmt>
                <title level="m">Introduction</title>
              
                <author>Rebecca Nesvet</author>
                <respStmt>
                    <resp>Transcription and encoding</resp>
                    <name xml:id="RN">Rebecca Nesvet</name>
                </respStmt>
            </titleStmt>
            <editionStmt>
                <edition>
                    <date>2017</date>
                </edition>
            </editionStmt>
            <publicationStmt>
                <authority>Scholarly Editing: The Annual of the Association for Documentary
                    Editing</authority>
                <address>
                    <addrLine>http://www.scholarlyediting.org</addrLine>
                </address>
                <publisher>Association for Documentary Editing</publisher>
                <publisher>University of Nebraska&#8211;Lincoln</publisher>
                <distributor>
                    <name>Center for Digital Research in the Humanities</name>
                    <address>
                        <addrLine>319 Love Library</addrLine>
                        <addrLine>University of Nebraska&#8211;Lincoln</addrLine>
                        <addrLine>Lincoln, NE 68588-4100</addrLine>
                        <addrLine>http://cdrh.unl.edu</addrLine>
                    </address>
                </distributor>
                <date>2017</date>
                <idno type="file">intro.scienceart</idno>
                <idno type="edition">scienceart</idno>
                <availability>
                    <p>Scholarly Editing: The Annual of the Association for Documentary Editing is
                        freely distributed by the Association for Documentary Editing and the Center for
                        Digital Research in the Humanities at the University of Nebraska-Lincoln and
                        licensed under a Creative Commons Attribution-NonCommercial-ShareAlike 3.0
                        Unported License</p>
                </availability>
            </publicationStmt>
            <seriesStmt>
                <title level="j">Scholarly Editing: The Annual of the Association for Documentary
                    Editing</title>
                <respStmt>
                    <resp>2017 issue editor</resp>
                    <name xml:id="nhg">Nicole Gray</name>
                </respStmt>
                <respStmt>
                    <resp>editor</resp>
                    <name xml:id="ag">Amanda Gailey</name>
                </respStmt>
                <respStmt>
                    <resp>editor</resp>
                    <name xml:id="awj">Andrew Jewell</name>
                </respStmt>
                <idno type="vol">38</idno>
                <idno type="ISSN">2167-1257</idno>
            </seriesStmt>
            <sourceDesc>
                <bibl>
                    <note>Born digital.</note>
                </bibl>
            </sourceDesc>
            
        </fileDesc>
        <revisionDesc status="embargoed">
            <change when="2016-10-19" who="#rn"> made minor encoding corrections suggested by #nhg </change>
            <change when="2016-11-12" who="#rn">major revisions due to discovery of the annotated volume described below.</change> 
            <change when="2016-11-21" who="#rn">minor line edits; added Briggs quote; edited encoding of block quotes.</change>
            <change when="2016-11-29" who="rn">edited Introduction to account for bolding of "supplied" text (in the script file.)</change>
        </revisionDesc>
    </teiHeader>
    <text>
        <front/>        
        <body>
        <div>
                <figure type="enlargeOnClick" n="1">
                    <head>Figure 1</head>
                    <graphic
                        url="Nesvet_190_0012.jpg"/>
                    <figDesc><hi rend="italic">Science and Art</hi> in the <hi rend="italic">Queen’s Magazine</hi>, vol. 1, no. 5 (August, 1842),
                        190. Photograph courtesy of the Louis Round Wilson Library, University of
                        North Carolina, Chapel Hill, © 2016.</figDesc>
                </figure>
                <head>Introduction</head>
            <byline>by Rebecca Nesvet</byline>
                <p>On July 24, 1820, an advertisement in the <hi rend="italic">London Morning
                        Post</hi> announced “The Triumph of Mechanism.” In an exhibition room in the
                    Western Exchange, Bond Street, a man-shaped machine called “PROSOPOGRAPHUS, the
                    AUTOMATON ARTIST” was reportedly drawing perfect silhouettes of astonished
                    visitors and strategically placed portrait busts. European spectators had seen
                    other automata draw pre&#8211;programmed pictures, write the inventor’s name,
                    and play brief pieces of music, but Prosopographus was different. This
                    automaton’s output seemed neither predetermined by its inventor nor limited to a
                    narrow range of options. “[T]he only Automaton in the world that takes
                    Likenesses,” Prosopographus could complete “a Profile Likeness in one
                        minute.”<ptr target="#note1" xml:id="nr1" n="1"/> By 1825, the advertising
                    presented Prosopographus as an existential threat to the human artist. An ad
                    placed in the <hi rend="italic">The Theatrical Observer and Daily Bills of the
                        Play</hi> claimed that the “Automaton Artist [...] draws Likenesses with
                    more certainty,” or accuracy, “than is in the power of the living hand to
                        execute.”<ptr target="#note2" xml:id="nr2" n="2"/></p>
                <p>These ads played upon fears that were common during the Regency. In 1811&#8211;6,
                    the Luddites had protested the imposition of labor&#8211;saving machines upon
                    the weaving industry. In 1815, the Welsh utopian reformer Robert Owen condemned
                    the emerging factory economy and the machines that made it possible. The
                    son&#8211;in&#8211;law of a Scottish manufacturing industrialist, Owen saw
                    firsthand the effects of the “manufacturing system” upon the children who
                    constituted much of his father&#8211;in&#8211;law’s workforce. “Is it to be
                    imagined,” Owen asked, “that the British Government will ever put the chance of
                    a trivial pecuniary gain of a few, in competition with the solid welfare of so
                    many millions of human beings?”<ptr target="#note3" xml:id="nr3" n="3"/> The
                    answer was affirmative. The Luddites were suppressed, and Prosopographus
                    reminded Londoners that even skilled artists could find themselves replaced by
                    self&#8211;acting machines.</p>
                <p>The same warning is issued in an obscure playscript of 1820. Titled <hi
                        rend="italic">Science and Art, A Farce in Two Acts</hi>, this acerbic comedy
                    concerns a young London lawyer, Jack Freeman, who falls in love with Maria, the
                    ward of an inventor of automata, Peter Patent. This industrial&#8211;age
                    Pantalone intends to save his nation’s industrial class a great deal of money by
                    replacing various entire professions with his patent automata. Freeman gains
                    access to Patent’s home to court Maria by masquerading as an automaton, in a
                    performance choreographed by his friend Dick Lobby, another unscrupulous lawyer.
                    When Lobby brings the pseudo&#8211;automaton to Patent’s home, the confusion of
                    machine with human creates comic mayhem, and forces Patent to question his
                    previous dismissal of the human in favor of the machine. Meanwhile, the
                    denouément hints that Freeman is not in fact a self&#8211;acting individual, but
                    a part of a social machine, for he has unwittingly performed according to a
                    program designed by others. </p>
                <p>Written by the critically neglected working&#8211;class London novelist, poet,
                    and engraver Malcolm Rymer, <hi rend="italic">Science and Art</hi> is here
                    reprinted for the first time since the nineteenth century. It deserves scholarly
                    attention not only for its commentary on the Industrial Revolution, but for its
                    “second story”: that of the editor who facilitated its initial publication, the
                    author’s son James Malcolm Rymer (1814-84). In the 1840s&#8211;60s, James
                    Malcolm Rymer achieved literary success by prolifically penning “penny bloods,”
                    or cheap fiction serials targeting working&#8211;class readers. They included
                    the <hi rend="italic">Dracula</hi> precursor <hi rend="italic">Varney, the
                        Vampyre, or the Feast of Blood</hi> and <hi rend="italic">The String of
                        Pearls, or the Barber of Fleet&#8211;street</hi>, the earliest tale of the
                    fictional entrepreneur, machine&#8211;inventor, murderer, and early
                    food&#8211;processing magnate Sweeney Todd.<ptr target="#note4" xml:id="nr4"
                        n="4"/> Before these triumphs, James Malcolm Rymer published his father’s
                    play, without attribution, in the August, 1842 fifth and final number of the <hi
                        rend="italic">Queen’s Magazine</hi>,his earliest known publication. The play
                    can therefore be read as the group output of a nineteenth&#8211;century literary
                    family, whose work spanned the Romantic and Victorian periods. Moreover, as this
                    introduction will show, <hi rend="italic">Science and Art</hi> anticipates key
                    aspects of James Malcolm Rymer’s most successful literary invention, the
                    enduringly horrific, diabolically ingenious Sweeney Todd. Quite possibly, the
                   most transformative gift Malcolm Rymer gave his son was his rage against the machines.</p>
            </div>
            <div>
                <head>“By Mr. M. Rymer&#8212;1820”</head>
                <p>  </p></div>
            <div>
                <p>It has very recently become possible to identify Malcolm Rymer as the author of
                        <hi rend="italic">Science and Art</hi> and the composition date as 1820. The
                    play was unattributed and undated until October 2016, when the Louis Round
                    Wilson Library at the University of North Carolina, Chapel Hill acquired from
                    the London antiquarian book dealer Jarndyce and Company, specialists in penny
                    bloods and dreadfuls, a partial copy of the first volume of the <hi
                        rend="italic">Queen’s Magazine</hi>, edited by James Malcolm Rymer. This volume contains four numbers of
                    the magazine, dated May through August 1842. The April number is missing. According to Jarndyce cataloguer and Rymer
                    scholar Helen R. Smith, this copy of the <hi rend="italic">Queen’s Magazine</hi>
                    had apparently been in James Malcolm Rymer’s possession. Some of its contents
                    bear handwritten corrections. Rymer signed a play review and is also identified
                    as the poet of “Love’s Fables,” which the printed text attributes to “George
                    Hillier Fantome.”<ptr target="#note5" xml:id="nr5" n="5"/> An inscription at the
                    top of the first page of <hi rend="italic">Science and Art </hi> reads “By Mr.
                    M. Rymer&#8212;1820.” (190). I propose that this author is Malcolm Rymer. On the
                    title&#8211;page of his 1806 novel <hi rend="italic">The Spaniard, or the Pride
                        of Birth</hi>, he styled himself “M. Rymer.” As I have shown in a
                    contribution to <hi rend="italic">Notes and Queries</hi> (forthcoming 2017),
                    Malcolm Rymer was the only imaginative writer called “M. Rymer” who was active
                    during the Regency or the early Victorian era. He used the abbreviation “M.
                    Rymer” for the bylines of two poems he published in the <hi rend="italic"
                        >Monthly Magazine</hi> in 1815 and 1818.<ptr target="#note6" xml:id="nr6"
                        n="6"/> These facts make it highly unlikely that an “M. Rymer” published by
                    Malcolm Rymer’s son would be intended to denote anybody else.</p>
                <p>Can we discern if the handwritten attribution to Malcolm Rymer is accurate? I
                    think that we can. I cannot at present identify the handwriting of the <hi
                        rend="italic">Science and Art</hi> annotation, except to say that neither
                    James Malcolm Rymer nor his father are likely possibilities. The hand does not
                    match James Malcolm Rymer’s signature on the theatre review, nor Malcolm Rymer’s
                    handwriting as represented by his 1818 inscription to his sister Helen Rymer in
                    a presentation copy of <hi rend="italic">The Spaniard </hi> that is now in the
                    collections of the University of California, Los Angeles. Nevertheless, it is
                    improbable that the <hi rend="italic">Science and Art</hi> attribution is a
                    fiction. Malcolm Rymer was an extremely obscure author during his Regency
                    heyday. To his son’s Victorian target audience, he was entirely unknown. As he
                    was never famous, there is no reason for anyone to have forged evidence of his
                    authorship, in 1842 or at any subsequent time. It is equally unlikely that
                    anyone outside his family would be sufficiently familiar with his work to
                    erroneously but in good faith attribute a text to him.</p>
                <p>It is also most probable that the play was indeed written in 1820. It references
                    topical events of that particular year. Prosopographus was on display then, and the play also includes a joke about
                    “the dissolution of Parliament” (192). One such dissolution occurred in February
                    1820, subsequent to the death of King George III in the month before. During the
                    1840s, however, Parliament was only dissolved and general elections held in
                    August 1841 (an entire year before the play’s publication) and 1847. Another
                    topical joke, a recurring one, involves Lobby’s claim that Patent, the
                    London&#8211;based inventor of automata, is famous in Asia, and particularly
                    celebrated in China. This would have made sense in the early years of the
                    nineteenth century but not the 1840s because in the late eighteenth and early
                    nineteenth century, London was the global export center for automata, largely on
                    account of the activity of a few automaton&#8211;makers, including James Cox and
                    the Swiss expatriates Henri&#8211;Louis Jaquet&#8211;Droz and his foster brother
                    Frédéric Leschot. Although some Jaquet&#8211;Droz&#8211;Leschot wares were
                    produced in their London workshop and some in Switzerland, Leschot confessed
                    that all were “engraved as though [made] in England, because it is the general
                    opinion that every thing of this kind [automata] made in that country is of
                    better workmanship” (132).<ptr target="#note7" xml:id="nr7" n="7"/> It was also
                    a common belief that the most zealous appreciators of such things were Chinese.
                    In the 1770s&#8211;90s, the Qianlong Emperor (d. 1799) was a frequent client of
                    this community of artisans. He became famous in Europe for his “apparently
                    insatiable” desire for automata and other London&#8211;made mechanical “toys”
                        (318).<ptr target="#note8" xml:id="nr8" n="8"/> By 1842, the deaths of the
                    Qianlong Emperor and all the inventors here named had evaporated this
                    international trade network. </p>
                <p>Additional circumstantial evidence that <hi rend="italic">Science and Art</hi>
                    dates to the early nineteenth century is the fact that the elderly Patent seems
                    to have been a child of the eighteenth century rather than the nineteenth. He
                    wears a wig long enough to appear to get caught on the fake “automaton” (197).
                    The days of elaborate wig&#8211;wearing among men outside the legal profession
                    were much closer to 1820 than 1842. An old man in 1820, as Patent is, could be
                    accustomed to wigs; not so a Victorian. These details suggest that <hi
                        rend="italic">Science and Art</hi> was more likely composed in 1820 than
                    1842. </p>
            </div>
        <div>
            <head>1820: “Those Self&#8211;Moving Machines”</head>
                <p>Malcolm Rymer seems to have been concerned throughout his career about the
                    conflict between man and machine, science and art. <hi rend="italic">The
                        Spaniard </hi>pits an industrious, honest sixteenth&#8211;century Madrid
                    barber, Pedrosa de Leandrez, against the Inquisition. Temperamentally unsuited
                    to the tonsorial trade on account of his aversion to shedding blood or causing
                    pain, Pedrosa (as the novel usually calls him) eventually finds refuge in a more
                    liberal country: either “England or Holland,” Rymer noncomittally concludes.<ptr
                        target="#note9" xml:id="nr9" n="9"/> A closer look at this tale reveals a
                    political agenda. He pits a feeling artisan versus the theory&#8211;driven
                    proverbial machine of the Inquisition, with its literal instruments of torture,
                    suggesting a criticism of the nascent Industrial Revolution.</p>
            <p> In <hi rend="italic">Science and Art</hi>, Malcolm Rymer more clearly represents
                    this contest between mechanical and human ingenuity. “One would imagine that
                    [Patent] thought nothing right in this world, as his invention,” or ingenuity,
                    “is continually on the rack to make it better,” Lobby says. “I don’t know how
                    many machines he has invented,” nor “how many schemes he has proposed for the
                    good of the public” (192). In practice, Patent’s “machines” and “schemes” seem
                    unlikely to improve most people’s lives. Instead, they threaten human labor,
                    dignity, thought, and creativity. The first example of Patent’s ingenuity that
                    the play reveals is a nightmare&#8211;vision of labor disenfranchisement and
                    industrial warfare. In the first scene, Lobby tells Freeman that Patent:
                        <quote>[...] not long ago [...] published proposals for an automaton
                        manufactory, in which he explained the variety of uses those self–moving
                        machines might be put to, and what an immense saving of expense to the
                        nation to employ them. In the first place he contended, that the business of
                        an army, according to the system of modern tactics, might as well be managed
                        by automatons as real soldiers; this would be a wonderful saving, as it
                        would render almost unnecessary almost the whole host of army agents, army
                        contractors, and barrack masters. (193)<ptr target="#note10" xml:id="nr10"
                            n="10"/></quote>Lobby concedes that an automaton army would save lives,
                    as its soldiers would not die and could be “repaired.” However, Patent’s
                    rhetoric is primarily economic. He rejoices in the “saving of expense to the
                    nation,” the “wonderful saving,” and is not concerned for the livelihoods of the
                    “whole host” of men rendered “unnecessary” by his innovation.</p>
                <p>Patent’s subsequent scheme attacks the livelihood of members of the Royal Navy.
                    “When Old Patent went down to the fleet at <placeName>Portsmouth</placeName> to
                    publish his proposals, our brave tars [sailors] would have him thrown overboard
                    for a a rascal who wanted the enemy to get all the fighting to themselves.”
                    Patent then tries to market his automata to the political elite, for a decidedly
                    nefarious purpose. “he offered to manufacture some for a few wealthy noblemen,
                    who told him that if he could conceive to make them say aye and nay, they would
                    probably take a dozen or two, as they might have use for them upon the
                    dissolution of Parliament” (192). In other words, he offers to provide the
                    aristocracy with automated voters, whom they could control more easily than the
                    already small and privileged pre&#8211;Reform electorate. This moment suggests
                    that Patent’s automata cannot improve society, so long as the power to
                    commission, purchase, and operate them remains with those who resist reform. </p>
                <p>Rymer reinforces this idea by making Parent wrest this power away from the elite,
                    although only for a moment. Rymer’s upper&#8211;class lawyer characters are
                    unconcerned about Patent’s disruptive potential until they realize that his
                    inventions could threaten their own livelihoods. When Patent tells his friend,
                    Freeman’s lawyer uncle (“Old Freeman”), that he intends to develop a “scheme” to
                    settle law cases “without delay or expense,” thereby making lawyers unnecessary,
                    Old Freeman erupts in self&#8211;concerned outrage. “What? where would be the
                    traffic, if all mankind were to settle their disputes themselves? I say, where
                    would be the cash?” (202). The elite would need to become Luddites, Malcolm
                    Rymer suggests, were the professions to become the targets of industrial
                    improvement. </p>
                <p>At the play’s comic resolution, Rymer implies that mechanical innovation is not
                    inherently evil and that the boundary between human and machine is quite hazy.
                    Freeman and his uncle each don the automaton costume and, by the art of
                    play&#8211;acting, persuade Patent that they are the wondrous automaton. Here,
                    therefore, artistic ingenuity triumphs over mechanical genius. When the ruse is
                    exposed, Patent happily accepts his ward’s marriage to Freeman, as it is the
                    exact match he had intended for her. This resolution uncomfortably implies that
                    the rebellious young <hi rend="italic">innamorati</hi> in fact behave as their
                    elders had designed, like the cogs of a machine. As the characters commemorate
                    the engagement by dancing, Patent offers to accompany them on his “newly
                    invented hurdy&#8211;gurdy” (207), a traditional Welsh musical instrument that
                    contains a wheel mechanism reminiscent of clockwork. While Patent must learn the
                    pseudo&#8211;automaton’s secret&#8212;that “the most perfect machine the world
                    ever saw” (202) is the human being&#8212;he is able to contribute his mechanical
                    ingenuity to humanity by using it to make music and celebrate love. </p>
                
                </div><div>
                    <figure type="enlargeOnClick" n="2">
                    <head>Figure 2</head>
                 
                    <figDesc>“The Spirit of the Age” in the <hi rend="italic">Queen’s Magazine</hi>, vol. 1, no. 2 (May, 1842), 76.
                        Photograph courtesy of Cambridge University Library, © 2016.</figDesc>
                </figure>
                <head>1842: The “Second Story”</head>
                <p>Having reconstructed some Regency contexts of <hi rend="italic">Science and
                        Art</hi>, we must now turn to the play’s “second story.” “There is always a
                    second story about a published primary text,” observes the historian James P.
                    McClure:</p>
                <p><quote>[I]t always involves at least one textual scholar or documentary editor
                        (whether or not so&#8211;called) [...] As far as the users of the texts are
                        concerned, the second story is often invisible, and its creators [...] are
                        anonymous.<ptr target="#note11" xml:id="nr11" n="11"/></quote></p>
                <p>
                    <hi rend="italic">Science and Art</hi>’s “second story” is that of James Malcolm
                    Rymer’s engagement with it. What aspects of this play of 1820 might have
                    persuaded him to publish this particular work of his father’s? The answer
                    might be in part thematic. From a young age, Rymer <hi rend="italic">fils</hi>
                    found himself torn between vocations in applied “science” and imaginative art,
                    and finally, upon his emergence as an editor and author, tried to integrate them
                    in his published work. </p>
                    <p>As I have noted, his family was a coterie of creative people. His mother, Louisa
                        Rymer (nee Dixon), worked as a milliner: she made hats
                        and accessories (Collins
                        viii). His elder brother Gaven was an artist; three engravings signed
                    by him reside in the collection of the Guildhall Museum.<ptr target="#note12"
                        xml:id="nr12" n="12"/> Another brother, Thomas, James Malcolm’s junior by
                    two years, achieved considerable artistic fame on two continents. An engraver
                    like his father, in 1838 he stood trial for forgery at
                    the Old Bailey, London’s central criminal court. He was accused of engraving a
                    one&#8211;pound banknote to create a fiver&#8212;a considerable sum in those
                    days. He was found guilty and, in 1839, transported to Van Diemen’s Land for
                    life. There and on the Australian mainland, he intermittently practiced
                    engraving and forgery for decades. Repeatedly convicted of using his engraving
                    knowledge to forge banknotes, he essentially dared the authorities to catch and
                    keep him.<ptr target="#note13" xml:id="nr13" n="13"/> In 1865, during his final
                    criminal trial, <hi rend="italic">Bell’s Life in Sydney and Sporting
                        Chronicle</hi> facetiously called him “an artist of great <hi rend="italic"
                        >note</hi>,” but this was not far from the truth, given his oft&#8211;tested
                        ingenuity.<ptr target="#note14" xml:id="nr14" n="14"/> Via criminal
                    creativity, Thomas Rymer identified himself as a scion of the artistic,
                    fiction&#8211;making family he would never again see. </p>
                <p>Like Thomas Rymer and the other Rymer men, James Malcolm Rymer initially learned
                    the art and science of engraving. He also further entrenched himself in the 
                    Rymer clan by marrying a paternal cousin, Caroline Huttly, in 1839. But he was also carving out a new path. He became a civil engineer (Collins viii). In
                    1840, he registered a patent for engraved furniture castors. The engraving, he argued, increased the castors’ friction,
                    making it harder for the furniture to shift about the floor.<ptr
                        target="#note15" xml:id="nr15" n="15"/>  In 1842, he
                    embarked upon a career that combined science, literature, and art by founding the <hi rend="italic"
                        >Queen’s Magazine</hi>. In it, he published an engraving of himself as a
                    distinguished, editor and writer, sitting in a wing chair before a pile of
                    books, including a volume of Shakespeare, and conversing with an ethereal,
                    hovering, female “spirit of the age” (Figure 2). In the Prospectus published with the first number
                    (April 1842), Rymer promised “[t]he Magazine will consist of forty pages of
                    original material, comprising Romance—Poetry—Character—Burlesque […]
                    Music—Art—Science and General Literature.” He made good on this vow. The
                    magazine’s contents eventually included original fiction, such as the earliest
                    instalments of one of Rymer’s first bloods, (<hi rend="italic">Jane Shore,</hi>
                    completed 1846), as well as poetry, drama, engravings of paintings, and a
                    regular column on “Useful and Important Inventions.” The first (and, ultimately,
                    only) instalment of this column showcased a new, controversial method of
                    engraving, “Mr. E. Palmer’s Patent Electrotint,” which Rymer presents as a
                    productive marriage of science and art (31). </p>
                <p/>
                    <figure type="enlargeOnClick" n="2"><figDesc></figDesc></figure>
                    <p><hi rend="italic">Science and Art</hi> reiterates the theme of science’s relation
                        to art, but it also fulfils another of the magazine’s aims: timeliness. Its
                        concern with the displacement of the human worker with machines built to serve
                        the interests of the industrialists remained immediate. On 21 February 1846, an editorialist for the Leeds-based Chartist newspaper <hi rend="italic">The Northern Star</hi> looked back across the 1840s and pronounced that "machinery had pounced upon us with such an unexpected hop, step, and jump that society was compelled to submit to such laws as regulations that its owners thought proper to impose" (342&#8211;3).<ptr target="#note16" xml:id="nr16" n="16"/> Another topical aspect of the 1842 published text of <hi rend="italic">Science and Art</hi> involves Patent's apparently fortuitously resemblance to an inventor who was in the news in 1842: Charles
                        Babbage, whose “calculating engines,” the “Difference Engine” and “Analytical
                        Engine,” were in development then and are now widely considered ancestors of the
                        modern computer. During the summer of 1842, Babbage publicly faced the greatest
                        challenge of his career, as the government considered whether to renew the
                        funding of his calculating engines project, which they had begun to support
                        financially in 1833.<ptr target="#note17" xml:id="nr17" n="17"/> Notably, Babbage’s engines, currently
                    understood as computers, proto&#8211;computers, or calculators, were known as
                    automata. Writing to John Wilson Croker, Peel called the Difference Engine a
                    “scientific automaton” (263).<ptr target="#note18" xml:id="nr18" n="18"/>
                    Therefore, Babbage and Patent invent the same sort of machine. Indeed, while the
                    automaton&#8211;Freeman walks as if “full of wheels” (193), the science
                    popularizer Dionysius Lardner, describing the calculating engines in an <hi
                        rend="italic">Edinburgh Review</hi> article that Babbage helped him to
                    prepare, claimed that the “project of a Calculating Engine” aimed to “substitute
                    an automaton for a compositor” and to “throw the powers of wheel&#8211;work into
                    thought,” which “could not fail to awaken the attention of the world”
                        (50&#8211;1).<ptr target="#note19" xml:id="nr19" n="19"/></p>
                <p>While Patent is described as the man who “invents the wheels and the ax[l]es”
                    (191) , Babbage, too, was seen as an inventor of assemblages of wheels and
                    ax(l)es. In Babbage’s two major Difference Engine models, writes the computer
                    scientist Allan G. Bromley, the originator of the Science Museum’s 1985&#8211;91
                    construction of the first complete, function Difference Engine, “the digits of
                    numbers are represented by the positions of wheels (figure wheels) rotating on
                    vertical axes” (30).<ptr target="#note20" xml:id="nr20" n="20"/> In early
                    twentieth&#8211;century America (ca. 1906) Dwight Goddard’s encyclopedia of <hi
                        rend="italic">Eminent Engineers […] Who Did Most to Further Human
                        Progress</hi>, a publication initially commissioned by the Wyman and Gordon
                    Company&#8212;Cleveland and Worcester, Massachusetts&#8211;based “manufacturers
                    of drop forgings”&#8212;finds Babbage’s engines labyrinths of “wheels within
                    wheels.” Goddard states that Babbage “spoke of 1,000 columns with 50 wheels each
                    in the store alone, and, besides, many thousand wheels mounted on axles in
                    columns for the mill and a vast machinery of cams and cranks for the control”
                    (253).<ptr
                        target="#note21" xml:id="nr21" n="21"/></p>
                   <p>Babbage’s utopian dreaming and overtures to the government also distinguish
                    Patent. His plans to make the army, navy, and legal system more efficient by
                    replacing human labor with automata recalls the critic Tamara Ketabgian’s apt
                    characterization of Babbage as an “technophilia[c]” who “idealizes the machine
                    as an empowering prosthesis for humans,” as in his <hi rend="italic">On the
                        Economy of Machinery and Manufactures</hi>, which problematically “bases its
                       guiding principle on the substitution of machinery for human limbs.”<ptr
                           target="#note22" xml:id="nr22" n="22"/>  We have seen that the sailors
                    stationed at Portsmouth threaten to throw Patent “overboard for a rascal” (192).
                    No doubt some early&#8211;1830s compilers of nautical tables would similarly
                    have eagerly dunked Babbage, and scientifically informed readers of the magazine might have seen Babbage in <hi rend="italic">Science and Art</hi>. </p>
                <p>If we choose to read <hi rend="italic">Science and Art</hi>’s pompous, bumbling Patent as
                    an accidental <hi rend="italic">doppelganger </hi>of Babbage, the play becomes a
                    short&#8211;sighted parody of the man who thought up the computer. It appears in
                    stark contrast to Babbage’s most famous literary doubling, in Charles Dickens’s
                        <hi rend="italic">Little Dorrit</hi> (1857) which shows the genius inventor
                    Daniel Doyce vanquished by the bureaucratic idiocy of the government
                    “Circumlocution Office,” which finds Doyce a “notorious rascal,” “guilty” of
                    being “ingenious” and of “trying to turn his ingenuity to his country’s
                    service,” which “makes him a public offender directly.” <ptr target="#note23"
                        xml:id="nr23" n="23"/> However, Babbage may have deserved the Patent
                    treatment. The entire 1840s has long been known as the ‘Hungry Forties’, and
                    although the term was coined only in the twentieth century, it remains apt.
                    Widespread working&#8211;class and indigent hunger preceded the Irish Potato
                    Famine (1845&#8211;7), and dominated both the nation and the national
                    consciousness throughout the period 1840&#8211;9. We cannot “underestimate the
                    political centrality of the debate on hunger” throughout this decade, writes
                    Peter J. Gurney (101). Charlotte Boyce adds that it was not only the
                    working&#8211;class and radical press that debated hunger in this decade: it was
                    the entire nation (423).<ptr target="#note24" xml:id="nr24" n="24"/>The causes
                    were many: rural to urban migration that obliterated many workers’ and
                    children’s access to home&#8211;grown food; the oppressive Poor Law and Corn
                    Laws, the latter the target of the Peelite Anti&#8211;Corn Law League; a series
                    of crop failures, and of course the three failed potato harvests of the
                    mid&#8211;1840s. </p>
                <p>The food crisis was impossible to ignore—unless, perhaps, one had designed a
                    wondrous machine and was monomaniacally focused on getting it built. That was
                    Babbage’s public image in many quarters, whether or not it was his reality. In
                        <hi rend="italic">Charles Babbage: Pioneer of the Computer</hi> (1982),
                    Babbage’s preeminent modern biographer Anthony Hyman makes a charitable
                    understatement: that “Babbage’s industrial interests and the possibilities of
                    commercial application of his calculating machines were quite unattractive” to
                    Peel (191).<ptr target="#note25" xml:id="nr25" n="25"/> This Prime Minister had
                    never liked the idea of a government-funded calculating engine project, and as
                    early as his 1823 letter to Croker had derided Babbage as an inhabitant of
                    “Laputa,” the levitating island of impractical mathematical enthusiasts in
                    Jonathan Swift’s <hi rend="italic">Gulliver’s Travels</hi> (1726). </p>
                <p>This was a charitable view of Babbage’s political outlook, for he was not a
                    Laputian, but an outspoken political conservative. As Hyman points out,
                    Babbage’s published writings demonstrate that his idea of the “manufacturing
                    class […] included factory workers and factory owners’ collaborating to form a
                    “free market” (85). His <hi rend="italic">Economy of Manufactures</hi> appeared
                    “during the most widespread class struggles in England in the whole of the
                    eighteenth and nineteenth centuries.” During those struggles, Babbage
                    “insist[ed] that working men should realize that their interests and those of
                    their masters were essentially in harmony” (115&#8211;6). </p>
                <p>Unsurprisingly, then, the government only took measures to encourage Babbage’s
                    completion of his engines during relatively conservative periods. While the Duke
                    of Wellington proved his champion, during the Peelite era, Babbage’s political
                    backing vanished (87). It was in the post&#8211;reform 1830s that Babbage
                    received over £17,000 of public money but completed no engine. In 1842, when he
                    requested more public money, it may have seemed that, surrounded by his
                    fragmentary wheel&#8211;work, he could not see humanity beyond. Neither can <hi
                        rend="italic">Science and Art</hi>’s Patent, until he learns that the most
                    “perfect machine” in history is the human.</p>
            </div><div>
                <head>Audience and Exigency</head>
                <p>Who was the audience for <hi rend="italic">Science and Art</hi>? Who was intended
                    to have performed it? To answer these questions, we must again consider the play
                    both in the context of its composition by Malcolm Rymer, circa 1820, and then in
                    the context of its publication by his son. Both Rymers seem to have intended <hi
                        rend="italic">Science and Art</hi> not for professional performance but
                    domestic consumption. It seems never to have been produced in the commercial
                    theatre, as journalism from 1819&#8211;60 records no notices for any public
                    performance. Instead, the play seems intended for reading or domestic
                    performance. Regency Britain had a culture of home theatricals, such as those
                    described in Austen’s novel Mansfield Park (1814). Science and Art appears
                    suited by design to this performance mode. The specified settings are all either
                    vague and featureless or domestic. For instance, the first scene takes place in
                    the high&#8211;living Freeman’s “lodgings at the Temple.” This impressive
                    landmark is represented by merely a “two chairs and [a] table” (190). Likewise,
                    Freeman meets Maria at the Opera at Covent Garden, but we do not see this
                    momentous meeting. Instead, it is described in retrospect in Freeman’s dialogue
                    with his servant Tom. </p>
                <p>The play’s depiction of Patent’s premises also suggests authorial acquiescence to
                    the limitations of domestic theatricals. The home of an eccentric inventor of
                    anthropomorphic automata would seem ripe for scenographic creativity. Many of us
                    have grown up entranced by the uncanny clutter of the rundown home automaton
                    workshops in Fritz Lang’s <hi rend="italic">Metropolis</hi>, Ridley Scott’s <hi
                        rend="italic">Blade Runner</hi>, or Tim Burton’s <hi rend="italic">Edward
                            Scissorhands</hi>. Conversely, <hi rend="italic">Science and Art</hi> calls
                    for only “The House of Mr. Patent” (193). No automata, parts, nor tools are
                    explicitly prescribed, excepting the pseudo&#8211;automaton played by Freeman,
                    and even his automaton costume seems amateur&#8211;proofed. It consists of a
                    “mask and domino,” and the automaton’s mechanical nature appears merely via his
                    stilted walk (197). Any bourgeois household would have been able to realize this
                    stage effect. Such a community would also be able to cope with the musical
                    requirements of the piece. The script calls for Maria’s song to be performed by
                    or as a “symphony” (201), but in the nineteenth century, this word did not imply
                    a full orchestra. Another meaning was “music in parts,” involving multiple
                    performers, or simply “concerted or harmonious music” (<hi rend="italic"
                        >OED</hi>).<ptr target="#note26" xml:id="nr26" n="26"/> A few members of a
                    family and their guests could easily provide this incidental music. Whether any
                    Victorian amateur actors actually staged Science and Art, we cannot at present
                    know, but had they done so, they would have experienced the group creativity
                    that also distinguished kinship coteries such as the Rymers.</p>
                <p>Although James Malcolm Rymer found his niche writing penny bloods for
                    working&#8211;class people like himself, the <hi rend="italic">Queen’s
                        Magazine</hi> aimed to attract a different readership. While his later
                    fiction filled newspapers priced at one penny, an expense affordable to
                    working&#8211;class readers, the <hi rend="italic">Queen’s Magazine</hi> cost a
                    shilling per number, as its title&#8211;page advertises. Its textual contents
                    corroborate that he envisioned it as middle&#8211;class aspirational literature,
                    while also reaching out to the socioeconomic elite and the wider public. The
                    Prospectus identifies it as “A FAMILY MAGAZINE OF THE HIGHEST CLASS,” and
                    suggests that its audience might even include members of the socioeconomic
                    elite. Rymer informs “respectable Advertisers” that “the <hi rend="italic"
                        >Queen’s Magazine</hi> will have a <hi rend="italic">certain</hi> large
                    circulation in a high class of society, quite independent of the popular
                    patronage it is fairly presumed it will receive from a Public, who at no period
                    of English history were so fitted as now to judge of sterling literary
                    pretensions.” In the first number of the <hi rend="italic">Queen’s Magazine</hi>
                    (April, 1842), Rymer exhorts his middle&#8211;class reading to pursue reform,
                    opposing aristocratic tyranny. In the magazine’s major fiction serial, the
                    historical romance <hi rend="italic">Jane Shore, an Historical Romance, by the
                        Editor,</hi> he contends that “with an intelligent and educated people,” the
                    “incessant petty jealousies” and “eternal feuds” of the “nobility [...] would
                    [...] ensure [...] their extinction as a class” (5). This sort of rhetoric
                    renders Rymer’s shilling periodical a tool of general political reform, which
                    would have impressed his future publishers, the Chartists Edward Lloyd and G. W.
                    M. Reynolds, who employed him as a writer of penny bloods and an editor of their
                        periodicals.<ptr target="#note27" xml:id="nr27" n="27"/></p>
                        </div><div>
                <head>Diabolical Ingenuity</head>
            </div>
            <div>
                <p>When James Malcolm Rymer moved onwards from the <hi rend="italic">Queen’s
                        Magazine</hi> to Lloyd’s Salisbury Square publishing house, he did not
                    forget <hi rend="italic">Science and Art.</hi> Aspects of this play reverberate
                    in <hi rend="italic">The String of Pearls, </hi>which Lloyd serialized in his
                        <hi rend="italic">People’s Periodical</hi>in 1846&#8211;7 and then
                    reprinted, in an expanded edition, in 1850. Both <hi rend="italic">Science and
                        Art </hi>and <hi rend="italic">The String of Pearls </hi>take place in the
                    world of London’s lawyers. While <hi rend="italic">Science and Art</hi> opens in
                    “Freeman’s lodgings in the Temple,” and contains many jokes at the expense of
                    profligate, avaricious, or hypocritical barristers, <hi rend="italic">The String
                        of Pearls </hi>is set largely in the same realm. Sweeney Todd keeps his shop
                    in Fleet&#8211;street, in the Temple Bar region. Some of the clients whom he
                    “polishes off” are lawyers. His apprentice, Tobias Ragg, had intended to become
                    a lawyer, but, judged not clever enough, goes to work for Todd instead. “I have
                    gone into another line,” he explains to a friend: “instead of being a lawyer,
                    and helping to shave the clients, I am going to shave the lawyers now.”<ptr
                        target="#note28" xml:id="nr28" n="28"/> He means that he will no longer
                    cheat (“shave”) clients, and accidentally tells the truth about Todd, who cheats
                    the lawyers by murdering them. <hi rend="italic">The String of Pearls</hi> also
                    attacks the “young Templers,” or young lawyers, by representing them as a
                    ravenous mob who consume their fellow human beings. Close to the Temple, in
                    Bell&#8211;yard, Mrs. Lovett’s pie shop caters to crowds of young lawyers. There
                    is “a rush of the legal profession to obtain them.” The lawyers arrive:<quote>mostly from Lincoln's-inn […] bustling and striving, although from the
                    neighbouring legal establishments likewise there came not a few; the Temple
                    contributes its numbers, and from the more distant Gray's-inn there came a
                    goodly lot. (17)</quote> The pies are clandestinely made of the flesh of Todd’s murder victims and
                    advertised as pork or veal pies. The lawyers’ monstrous appetites for their
                    fellow man suggests that their profession is inherently vicious; that it
                    consumes people, giving nothing back. </p>
                <p>A clearer parallel between <hi rend="italic">Science and Art</hi> and<hi
                        rend="italic">The String of Pearls</hi> involves the two texts’ villains,
                    Peter Patent and Sweeney Todd. We have seen that Patent is willing to upend
                    society and destroy many people’s livelihoods in the name of “saving.” When he
                    speaks of technological “improvements” to society, he means that he will save
                    the elite money. He does not think of the human cost of his inventions’
                    implementation, just as he does not think of his ward’s feelings. Sweeney Todd
                    can be read as a hyperbolic version of this flawed inventor. Like Patent, he is
                    an engineer, and his inventions work something like clockwork. He revamps his
                    shop to feature two identical barber’s chairs affixed to a rotating section of
                    the floor to move through a secret trapdoor, dumping victims into the space
                    below to be murdered. This “mechanical arrangement” is an industrial&#8211;age
                    update of the medieval Wheel of Fortune (616). Rymer, inventor of patent
                    engraved castors to move and stabilize furniture, must have seen this
                    contraption as an example of ingeniously evil engineering.</p>
                <p>Like Patent, Todd applies his evil ingenuity to industrial entrepreneurship. His
                    victims are processed by the few, miserable, exploited workers at Mrs. Lovett’s
                    “pie manufactory.” This factory makes Todd a wealthy industrialist only
                    pretending to be an independent artisan, for it is the source of most of his
                    profits. It is so productive: <quote>the retail part of Mrs. Lovett's business which took place principally between
                    the hours of twelve and one, was by no means the most important or profitable
                    portion of a concern which was really of immense magnitude, and which brought in
                    a large yearly income (58).</quote> The workers go mad when they learn that the meat they are processing is human.
                    While Patent’s automata threaten to take away British people’s livelihoods,
                    Todd’s “manufactory” morally corrupts them and destroys their will to live. It
                    is a sobering vision of industrial profiteering when all pretense at ethics is
                    removed. Finally, Todd recalls Patent in his sheer delight at his own
                    inventions. Viewing his machines and their mayhem, he frequently emits a
                    disturbing laugh. In short, while Patent invents automata without regard for
                    industrialism’s human cost, Todd goes a step further, personifying diabolical
                    ingenuity. In creating him, James Malcolm Rymer goes further than his father,
                    using materials from <hi rend="italic">Science and Art</hi> to create a
                    resilient, mythic nightmare of industrial inhumanity.</p>
            </div><div>
                            <head>Editorial Methodology</head>
                <p>This edition aims to reveal the text of <hi rend="italic">Science and Art</hi>
                    published by James Malcolm Rymer in the <hi rend="italic">Queen’s Magazine</hi>,
                    but also to supply a playscript that is accessible and, additionally, actable,
                    because much that can be learned about any play is visible only in performance.
                    To realize these ends, my editorial method combines aspects of documentary and
                    critical editing. I have encoded the text in XML and in accordance with the TEI
                    Guidelines (P5). The documentary aspects of the resulting edition include
                    faithful transcription of <hi rend="italic">Science and Art</hi> (from the UNC
                    copy of the <hi rend="italic">Queen’s Magazine, </hi>checked against the
                    Cambridge University Library copy, with which it is identical.) Most of James
                    Malcolm Rymer’s typographical errors are preserved. Obviously missing words are
                    inserted, marked as such using the “supplied” tag, and distinguished with bold
                    font. However, where a typographical error is more complicated than a single
                    missing word, could be corrected in more than one way, or, if transcribed
                    faithfully, would make the meaning of the line unclear, I have silently amended
                    it in the dialogue, and added a note that supplies the original, erroneous text.  </p>
                <p>In other particulars as well, this edition is a critical one. I have standardized
                    the playscript format, employing the TEI P5 stylesheet for Drama. In the source
                    text’s stage directions and dialogue headers, character names are abbreviated
                    and “Freeman” used to indicate only “Young Freeman.” I have silently amended
                    this for clarity’s sake. Additionally, I have added brief character descriptions
                    to the “Dramatis Personae” to enable readers easily to visualize the characters
                    and distinguish them from each other. These new descriptions are presented in
                    square brackets to indicate that they were not part of the source text. I have
                    also added the phrase  “The End,” as in the source text, the script abruptly
                    terminates with the final line of dialogue.</p>
               <p>The footnotes aim to complete the work of this introduction. They are intended to
                    make the text accessible to readers ranging from scholars of
                    nineteenth&#8211;century literature to undergraduates and theatre professionals
                    who may wish to stage it. They relate the play to its Romantic and Victorian
                    cultural contexts.</p>
                <p>My entire critical apparatus also aims to reveal <hi rend="italic">Science and
                        Art</hi>’s place in the neglected history of the Rymers of London. Scholars
                    of Victorian literature are familiar with prominent literary families, such as
                    the Brontes, Brownings, Rossettis, and Wildes. Notably, these are all
                    upper&#8211; or middle&#8211;class families, and largely active only during the
                    Victorian period. Conversely, the Rymers were working&#8211;class men and women,
                    whose creative activity spanned not only the disciplines of “science and art,”
                    but the Romantic and early Victorian eras, questioning the current fashionable
                    periodization of nineteenth&#8211;century British literature. It is my hope that
                    access to the text and some contexts of <hi rend="italic">Science and Art</hi>
                    will help to facilitate the Rymers’ incorporation into the
                    nineteenth&#8211;century literary canon and curriculum.</p>
                
                
                
            
            </div>
                
        </body>
        <back>
            <div type="notes">
                
                <note xml:id="note1"><hi rend="italic">London Morning Post</hi> July 20, 1820: 1.
                    Located by Patrick Feaster, <ref
                        target="http://griffonagedotcom.wordpress.com/2015/02/13/prosopographus&#8211;the-automaton-artist"
                        >“Prosopographus, the Automaton Artist.”</ref>
                    <hi rend="italic">Griffonage-Dot-Com: Patrick Feaster’s Explorations in
                        Historical Media</hi> February 13, 2015, accessed October 25,
                    2016.</note>
                <note xml:id="note2">“Prosopographus, the Automaton Artist,” <hi rend="italic">The
                    Theatrical Observer and Daily Bills of the Play</hi> no. 1191 (September
                    30, 1825): 2. Feaster presents evidence from advertisements showing that the
                    silhouette artist Charles Hervé invented and sometimes manipulated
                    Prosopographus. See also “Prosopographus, the Automaton Artist” <hi
                        rend="italic">The Examiner</hi> 934, no. 87 (1826): 285. In a letter to
                    the editor of the <hi rend="italic">Mechanics’ Magazine</hi> 12 (1830):
                    335&#8211;6, titled “The Camera Lucida,” H.J. Exeter wrote that
                    Prosopographus must have a human operator, who “goes behind” the sitter and
                    “traces the outline of the face [...] which is thrown upon the screen by a
                    gas light.” Prosopographus “can only take profiles” because the operator
                    must keep the sitter facing away from the evidence of his deception. For
                    Prosopographus’s disappearance from Regency culture, see Feaster.</note>
                <note xml:id="note3">Robert Owen, <hi rend="italic">Observations on
                    the Effect of the Manufacturing System, With Hints for the Improvement
                    of Those Parts of it Which are Most Injurious to Health and Morals</hi>,
                    1815 (London, Edinburgh, and Glasgow, 1817): 15.</note>
                <note xml:id="note4">These facts about James Malcolm Rymer’s career were pieced
                    together by Louis James, <hi rend="italic">Fiction for the Working Man</hi>
                    (Oxford: Oxford University Press, 1963): 36&#8211;8; Robert Mack, <hi
                        rend="italic">Sweeney Todd: The Life of Times of an Urban Legend</hi>
                    (Oxford: Oxford University Press, 2007): 146&#8211;7; Helen R. Smith, <hi
                        rend="italic">New Light on Sweeney Todd, James Malcolm Rymer, Thomas
                        Peckett Prest, and Elizabeth Caroline Grey</hi> (London: Jarndyce,
                    2002), and Dick Collins, ed., intr., <hi rend="italic">The String of
                        Pearls</hi> (Ware: Wordsworth, 2010): vii&#8211;ix. </note>
                <note xml:id="note5">Smith, <hi rend="italic">Jarndyce Antiquarian
                    Booksellers: Catalogue CCXIX: Bloods and Penny Dreadfuls</hi> (London:
                    Jarndyce, 2016): 69, item no. 274. The pseudonym “George Hillier Fantome”
                    combines the name of the bookseller and printer George Hillier
                    (1815&#8211;66) with the French word for “ghost.”</note>
                <note xml:id="note6">Rebecca Nesvet, “The Spaniard and Sweeney Todd,” forthcoming in
                    <hi rend="italic">Notes and Queries</hi> in 2017, lays out the case for
                    Malcolm Rymer’s composition of <hi rend="italic">The Spaniard</hi>, which had until then been unattributed. The piece also 
                    speculates upon the literary coterie he may have assembled and its impact
                    upon his son James Malcolm Rymer’s literary career. </note>
                <note xml:id="note7">Frédéric Leschot, quoted in Roger Smith, “The Swiss
                    Connection: International Networks in the Eighteenth Century Luxury Trades.”
                    <hi rend="italic">Journal of Design History</hi> 17, no. 2 (2004):
                    123&#8211;39.</note>
                <note xml:id="note8">Clare Le Corbeiller. “James Cox and his Curious Toys.” <hi
                    rend="italic">Metropolitan Museum of Art Bulletin</hi> n.s. 18, no. 10
                    (1960): 318&#8211;24. While Le Corbeiller recycles the Orientalist
                    stereotype of the “insatiable” Eastern despot, Catherine Pagani offers a
                    more nuanced, carefully contextualized picture of the role of gift automata
                    during the reign of the Qianlong (“Ch’ien&#8211;Lung”) Emperor (r.
                    1735&#8211;96; d. 1799). Pagani’s <hi rend="italic">“Eastern Magnifience and
                        European Ingenuity”: Clocks of Late Imperial China</hi> (Ann Arbor:
                    University of Michigan Press, 2001), introduces the Chinese concept of <hi
                        rend="italic">zimingzhong</hi>, or “self&#8211;sounding bells,” which
                    encompassed clocks, automata, and other apparently self&#8211;acting
                    clockwork devices (1). In the sixteenth through nineteenth centuries,
                    Western visitors presented Chinese emperors with <hi rend="italic"
                        >zimingzhong</hi> as diplomatic gifts, and such objects came to be
                    strongly associated with Europe, to the point of being called <hi
                        rend="italic">xiwu</hi> (“western things”) or <hi rend="italic"
                            >qiqi</hi> (“strange things,” 18&#8211;9). From the early eighteenth
                    century through at least 1879, the Chinese capitol at Peking (Beijing)
                    maintained an Office of Clock Manufacture (<hi rend="italic"
                        >Zuozhongchu</hi>), but clocks continued to be imported from Europe
                    (37). The Qianlong Emperor indeed embraced this tradition, collecting
                    various clocks and mechanical animals and people and writing poems in praise
                    of <hi rend="italic">zimingzhong</hi> (62&#8211;3). Pagani’s research makes
                    it clear that far from being an infantile toy&#8211;collector, the Qianlong
                    Emperor celebrated his diplomatic relations in the form of their ritual
                    objects.</note>
                <note xml:id="note9">Malcolm Rymer, <hi rend="italic">The Spaniard, or, the Pride of
                    Birth</hi> (London: Robertson, 1806), 193. All discussion of this work
                    references the inscribed presentation copy at the University of California,
                    Los Angeles (UCLA) Libraries’ Special Collections. </note>
                <note xml:id="note10">“Science and Art,” <hi rend="italic">The Queen’s Magazine
                </hi>1, no. 5 (August, 1820): 190&#8211;207. In the source, the title is
                    misspelled  “Queens’” on each number's title page. I have silently amended
                    the error throughout this edition. References to nos. 2 through 5 indicate the copy in the
                    Rare Books Collection of the University of North Carolina (UNC), Chapel Hill’s
                    Louis Round Wilson Library, unless otherwise indicated. References to no. 1 indicate the Cambridge University Library copy.</note>
                <note xml:id="note11">James P. McClure, “The Second Story: Presidential Address for
                    Documentary Editing Annual Meeting, Louisville, Kentucky, 2014” <hi
                        rend="italic">Scholarly Editing</hi> 36 (2015), accessed
                   November 11, 2016.</note>
                <note xml:id="note12">Gavin [sic] Rymer, “Peep Show,” [engraving] (1834); G. Rymer,
                    “London Scenes no. 4: Punch and Judy,” [engraving] (1834); G. Rymer, “Guy
                    Fawkes’ Day,” (1834), Guildhall Library and Art Collection.</note>
                <note xml:id="note13">See Old Bailey Proceedings Online (www.oldbaileyonline.org,
                    version 7.2, 02 November 2015), May 1838, trial of THOMAS RYMER
                    (t18380514&#8211;1173). In 2012, the scholar Dick Collins persuasively
                    identified this convict as James Malcolm Rymer’s brother. On an Australian
                    digital archive page describing Thomas Rymer’s arrival in Van Diemen’s Land,
                    Collins commented that “Mr Rymer was the son of Malcolm Rymer, of Edinburg
                    [sic], and Louisa Dixon of London,” and that “his brother James was an
                    author, and the creator of one of the most popular and enduring villains in
                    English literature,” presumably, Sweeney Todd. “If this were not a pay
                    site,” Collins teases, “I would tell you more.” See Dick Collins, “Comment
                    on “Thomas Rymer” <ref
                        target="http://www.convictrecords.com.au/convicts/rymer/thomas/64334"
                        >British Convict Transportation Register</ref>, State Library of
                    Queensland, Australia, 2 September 2012, accessed 24 August, 2015. Collins
                    has thus far reported this find only on this genealogical research message
                    board. Public records support Collins’ identification, as James Malcolm
                    Rymer’s brother and the convicted forger share an occupation (engraver),
                    age, and origin, while in the 1841 British Census, Malcolm’s son Thomas is
                    absent. Brother and forger are the same man. Thomas Rymer’s individual
                    post&#8211;transportation convictions for banknote forgery are too numerous
                    to list. An indicative one is ”Multum in Parvo," <hi rend="italic">Sydney Morning Herald</hi>,
                      26 February, 1847: 2.</note>
                <note xml:id="note14">“Forged Notes of the Week” <hi rend="italic">Bell’s Life in
                    Sydney and Sporting Chronicle</hi>, 18 November 1865: 3.</note>
                <note xml:id="note15">According to <hi rend="italic">Newton’s London Journal of
                    Arts, Sciences, and Manufactures, and Repertory of Patent
                    Inventions</hi> (London: Office of Patents, 1843), 27, Rymer’s patent
                    for engraved castors was “sealed” (registered) on 23 April, 1840.</note>
                <note xml:id="note16"><hi rend="italic">Northern Star</hi>, 21 February 1846, quoted in Lucy Brown, "The Chartists and the Anti&#8211;Corn Law League," <hi rend="italic">Chartist Studies</hi>, edited by Asa Briggs, 1959 (London: Macmillan, 1977), 342&#8211;71. Chartism was a national political movement
                    aimed at working-class enfranchisement, primarily through universal male
                    suffrage. It takes its name from the ‘People's Charter’ (1838), which set
                    forth six ‘points’ or demands. Repeated attempts to induce Parliament to
                    pass the People's Charter failed. Chartism flourished between 1838 and 1842.
                    In most regions, it ended in the 1850s.</note>
               <note xml:id="note17">Doron Swade, <hi rend="italic">The Cogwheel Brain:
                    Charles Babbage and the quest to build the first computer</hi> (London:
                   Little, Brown, 1999), 135.</note>
                <note xml:id="note18">Robert Peel to John Wilson Croker, 8 March 1824, in <hi
                    rend="italic">The Croker Papers: The Correspondence and Diaries of the
                    Late Right Honourable John Wilson Croker, LL.D., F.R.S., Secretary to
                    the Admiralty from 1809 to 1830</hi>, edited by Louis J. Jennings
                    (Cambridge: Cambridge University Press, 2012), 262&#8211;3. Swade, 36, also
                    discusses this letter.</note>
                <note xml:id="note19">Dionysius Lardner, “Babbage’s Calculating Engine,” <hi
                    rend="italic">Edinburgh Review</hi> 120 (1834), 263&#8211;327, in
                    Anthony Hyman, ed. <hi rend="italic">Science and Reform: Selected Works of
                        Charles Babbage</hi> (Cambridge: Cambridge University Press 1989),
                    51&#8211;109. This anthology is hereafter abbreviated as SWCB.</note>
                <note xml:id="note20">Allan G. Bromley, “Charles Babbage’s Analytical Engine, 1838”
                    <hi rend="italic">IEEE Annals of the History of Computing</hi> 20, no. 4
                    (1998), 29&#8211;45.</note>
                <note xml:id="note21">Dwight Goddard, <hi rend="italic">Eminent Engineers: Brief
                    Biographies of Thirty&#8211;two of the Inventors and Engineers who did most to
                    further mechanical progress, by Dwight Goddard, Member of the American
                    Society of Mechanical Engineers</hi> (N.P., “1905” [1906]), ix and
                    251.</note>
                <note xml:id="note22">Tamara Ketabgian, <hi rend="italic">The Lives of Machines: The
                    Industrial Imaginary in Victorian Literature and Culture</hi> (Ann
                    Arbor: University of Michigan Press, 2011), 18.</note>
                <note xml:id="note23">Charles Dickens, <hi rend="italic">Little Dorrit</hi>, edited
                    by Peter Sucksmith, 1982 (Oxford: Oxford University Press, 2008),
                    133&#8211;4.</note>
                <note xml:id="note24">Peter J. Gurney, “’Rejoicing in Potatoes’: The Politics of
                    Consumption in England during the ‘Hungry Forties’” <hi rend="italic">Past
                        and Present</hi> 203, no. 1 (2009): 99&#8211;136; Charlotte Boyce,
                    “Representing the ‘Hungry Forties’ in Image and Verse: The Politics of
                    Hunger in Early&#8211;Victorian Periodicals,“ <hi rend="italic">Victorian
                        Literature and Culture</hi> 40 (2012): 421&#8211;49.</note>
                <note xml:id="note25"> Anthony Hyman, <hi rend="italic">Charles Babbage: Pioneer of
                    the Computer </hi>(Princeton: Princeton University Press, 1982),
                    191.</note>
                <note xml:id="note26"><hi rend="italic">Oxford English Dictionary (OED)</hi>
                    (Oxford: Oxford University Press, 2004), accessed November 11, 2016, <ref target="www.oed.com">www.oed.com</ref></note>
                <note xml:id="note27">Dorothy Thompson, <hi rend="italic">The Early Chartists</hi>
                    (London: Springer, 1971), 10; James 165. </note>
                <note xml:id="note28"><hi rend="italic">The String of Pearls, or the Barber of
                    Fleet&#8211;Street, A Domestic Romance</hi> (London: Edward Lloyd, 1850),
                    18.</note>
                
            
            </div>
        </back>
 
 
    </text>
</TEI>
