<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<?xml-model href="http://www.tei-c.org/release/xml/tei/custom/schema/relaxng/tei_all.rng" type="application/xml" schematypens="http://relaxng.org/ns/structure/1.0"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
   <teiHeader xml:lang="eng">
      <fileDesc>
         <titleStmt>
            <title level="m" type="main">Science and Art, A Farce, in Two Acts.</title>
            <title level="a" type="main">A Critical Edition.</title>
            <author>Malcolm Rymer</author>
            <editor>James Malcolm Rymer</editor>
            <editor>Rebecca Nesvet</editor>
            <respStmt>
               <resp>Transcription and encoding</resp>
               <name xml:id="rn">Rebecca Nesvet</name>
            </respStmt>
         </titleStmt>
         <editionStmt>
            <edition>
               <date>2017</date>
            </edition>
         </editionStmt>
         <publicationStmt>
            <authority>Scholarly Editing: The Annual of the Association for Documentary
               Editing</authority>
            <address>
                    <addrLine>http://www.scholarlyediting.org</addrLine>
                </address>
            <publisher>Association for Documentary Editing</publisher>
            <publisher>University of Nebraska&#8211;Lincoln</publisher>
            <distributor>
               <name>Center for Digital Research in the Humanities</name>
               <address>
                        <addrLine>319 Love Library</addrLine>
                        <addrLine>University of Nebraska&#8211;Lincoln</addrLine>
                        <addrLine>Lincoln, NE 68588-4100</addrLine>
                        <addrLine>http://cdrh.unl.edu</addrLine>
                    </address>
            </distributor>
            <date>2017</date>
            <idno type="file">script.scienceart.xml</idno>
            <idno type="edition">scienceart</idno>
            <availability>
               <p>Scholarly Editing: The Annual of the Association for Documentary Editing is
                  freely distributed by the Association for Documentary Editing and the Center for
                  Digital Research in the Humanities at the University of Nebraska-Lincoln and
                  licensed under a Creative Commons Attribution-NonCommercial-ShareAlike 3.0
                  Unported License</p>
            </availability>
         </publicationStmt>
         <seriesStmt>
            <title level="j">Scholarly Editing: The Annual of the Association for Documentary
               Editing</title>
            <respStmt>
               <resp>2017 issue editor</resp>
               <name xml:id="nhg">Nicole Gray</name>
            </respStmt>
            <respStmt>
               <resp>editor</resp>
               <name xml:id="ag">Amanda Gailey</name>
            </respStmt>
            <respStmt>
               <resp>editor</resp>
               <name xml:id="awj">Andrew Jewell</name>
            </respStmt>
            <idno type="vol">38</idno>
            <idno type="ISSN">2167-1257</idno>
         </seriesStmt>
         <sourceDesc>
            <bibl>
               <author><persName type="forename">Malcolm</persName>
                  <persName type="surname">Rymer</persName></author>
               <editor><persName type="forename">James Malcolm</persName>
                  <persName type="surname">Rymer</persName></editor>
               <title level="a">Science and Art, A Farce, in Two Acts.</title>
               <date type="composition" when="1820">1820</date>
               <title level="j">The Queen’s Magazine</title>
               <date type="publication" when="1842-08">August 1842</date>
               <biblScope unit="pp">190-207</biblScope>
               <note type="project">
                  <p>Transcribed from the copy of the <hi rend="italic">Queen’s Magazine</hi> in the
                     Rare Books Collection, Louis Round Wilson Library at the University of North
                     Carolina, Chapel Hill (UNC). This magazine ran for one volume, consisting of
                     five numbers, continuously paginated throughout. The UNC copy consists of four
                     of the numbers: volume 1, no. 2 (May, 1842) through volume 1, no. 5 (August,
                     1842); no. 1 (April 1842) is missing. The included numbers contain original
                     wrappers, which were illustrated, like some of the magazine’s contents, by the
                     celebrated cartoonist and engraver Thomas Onwhyn (d. 1886). The UNC copy is
                     further distinguished by his manuscript annotations and amendations, and was
                     not previously known to exist. In this copy, the portrait engraving of Rymer
                     (identified as “the Editor”) conferring with an inspiring “Spirit of the Age”
                     (p. 76) has been cut out. It is not apparent who was responsible for this
                     defacement, nor when it took place. There are no other significant differences
                     between this copy and the British Library and Cambridge copies.</p>
                  <p>On each title page, the title is misspelled  “Queens’”. 
                     I have silently amended the error throughout this edition.</p>
               </note>
            </bibl>
         </sourceDesc>
      </fileDesc>
      <revisionDesc status="embargoed">
         <change when="2016-10-19" who="#rn"> made minor encoding corrections suggested by #nhg </change>
         <change when="2016-11-15" who="#rn"> completed major rewrite subsequent to UNC’s
            acquisition of the copy described above.</change>
         <change when="2016-11-22" who="#rn"> minor encoding corrections and line edits</change>
         <change when="2016-11-24" who="#rn"> proofreading</change>
         <change when="2016-11-28" who="#rn"> added bold font to text tagged as “supplied” due to
            omission.</change>
         <change when="2016-12-07" who="#rn"> various edits in response to draft workup and nhg
            questions; standardized annotations’ description of typographical errors;
            proofreading.</change>
      </revisionDesc>
   </teiHeader>
   <text type="drama">
      <body><pb n="190" facs="Nesvet_190_0012"/>
        <div type="Dramatis_Personae">
           <head type="main"><hi rend="italic">Dramatis Personæ.</hi></head>
            <castList>
               <castGroup>
                  <castItem><role>[Peter] Patent.</role><roleDesc>[An
                     inventor.]</roleDesc></castItem>
                  <castItem><role>Old [Matthew] <seg corresp="#note1">Freeman</seg>.</role><roleDesc>[A country
                     lawyer.]</roleDesc></castItem>
                  <castItem><role>Young [Jack] Freeman.</role><roleDesc>[a city lawyer; Old
                        Freeman’s nephew; in the script, “Freeman.”]</roleDesc></castItem>
                  <castItem><role>Dick <seg corresp="#note1">Lobby</seg>.</role><roleDesc>[Another city lawyer; Freeman’s
                        friend.]</roleDesc></castItem>
                  <castItem><role>Tom [<seg corresp="#note1">Clinker</seg>].</role><roleDesc>[Freeman’s
                     servant.]</roleDesc></castItem>
                  <castItem><role>Maria.</role><roleDesc>[Patent’s ward.]</roleDesc></castItem>
                  <castItem><role>Alice.</role><roleDesc>[Patent’s servant.]</roleDesc><ptr
                     target="#note1" xml:id="nr1" n="1"/></castItem>
                  </castGroup>
            </castList>
         </div>
        <div type="act" n="1"><div type="scene" n="1">
               <head type="main">Act I. Scene I.</head>
               <stage type="setting"><hi rend="italic">Young</hi> FREEMAN<hi rend="italic">’s
                     Lodgings in the <seg corresp="#note2">Temple</seg>.&#8212;Two chairs and
                     table.</hi><ptr target="#note2" xml:id="nr2" n="2"/><lb/>
               </stage>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Freeman.</speaker>
                  <stage type="business"><hi rend="italic">seated, solus (reading).</hi></stage>
                  <p>Bless me! past five o’clock&#8212;Tom not yet returned, and my old uncle will
                     be popping his bald pate into every corner of the Temple in search of me. He
                     expects to see me one day <seg corresp="#note3">Lord Chancellor</seg>. Oh! how
                     irksome is the dry study of the law to an expecting anxious lover!&#8212;but
                     what have I to expect? Surely nothing but disappointment: commanded by my uncle
                     to pay my addresses to a lady with whose person I am unacquainted, whose
                     disposition I am ignorant of, and whose name I have never yet heard, while at
                     the same time I am captivated by the charms of another almost equally
                     unknown&#8212;unknown! No: I beheld every virtue beaming in her bright eyes,
                     every perfection in her celestial form. She has taken entire possession of my
                     heart, and not all the power on earth&#8212;&#8212;&#8212;but here comes
                        Tom.<ptr target="#note3" xml:id="nr3" n="3"/>
                  </p>
               
               <stage type="entrance"><hi rend="italic">Enter </hi>TOM<hi rend="italic">
                     (drunk)</hi></stage>
               
                  <p>Well, my good fellow, Tom, what have you learnt? what news of my unknown,
                     bewitching <seg corresp="#note4">charmer</seg>?<ptr target="#note4"
                        xml:id="nr4" n="4"/></p></sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Tom.</speaker>
                  <p><seg corresp="#note5">Ecod</seg>, I believe she is a witch, with her charms;
                     for I have run after her, and about her, till I can hardly stand.<ptr
                        target="#note5" xml:id="nr5" n="5"/></p>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Freeman.</speaker>
                  <p>You are drunk, you dog.</p>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Tom.</speaker>
                  <p>Drunk: no, no, no, no, no; not absolutely drunk, only in a medium way, that’s
                     all.</p>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Freeman.</speaker>
                  <p>How came you in that condition, you scoundrel?</p>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Tom.</speaker>
                  <p>Why, master, the way that many a man gets drunk, by running after the girls:
                     plague on them!</p>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Freeman.</speaker>
                  <p>What business had you after the girls? Did I not employ you to obtain
                     intelligence of the lady I followed home last night from the <seg
                        corresp="#note6">Opera</seg>?<ptr target="#note6" xml:id="nr6" n="6"/></p>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Tom.</speaker>
                  <p>Well, <seg corresp="#note7">ain’t</seg> she a gig&#8212;gig&#8212;girl?<ptr
                        target="#note7" xml:id="nr7" n="7"/></p>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Freeman.</speaker>
                  <p>True; and a most angelic one: but tell me, how did you proceed?</p>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Tom.</speaker>
                  <p>Why, master, when I set out, you know it was pure warm weather, so being a
                     little thirsty, I called in at the Dog and Duck. </p>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Freeman.</speaker>
                  <p>Damn the Dog and Duck.</p>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Tom.</speaker>
                  <p>Nay, I only drank a little ale there. </p>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Freeman.</speaker>
                  <p>Proceed: tell me what you have learnt concerning her. </p>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Tom.</speaker>
                  <p>Nay, now, have patience, and you shall hear all about it. So thinks I to
                     myself, the best way to get intelligence of this young lady, is to go to the
                     street where she lives, and inquire at the public&#8211;house; so in I popt,
                     and got si&#8212;si&#8212;six&#8211;penny&#8211;worth of
                     brandy&#8211;and&#8211;water; so, says I, “Do you know the young lady that
                     lives in that there house over the way?<supplied reason="omitted-in-original"
                        >”</supplied> “No,” says he: “but if you go down to The World’s&#8211;End,
                     at the bottom of the street, they know all about her.”</p>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Freeman.</speaker>
                  <p>You scoundrel! did you imagine a form of so much celestial beauty, in whose
                     bright eyes shone refinement and intelligence, would be known in every dirty
                     public&#8211;house in the street? I’ll cane you as long as I can stand, you
                     dog!</p>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Tom.</speaker>
                  <p>Stop, stop, master! if you strike, I’ll forget every word I was going to
                     say.</p>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Freeman.</speaker>
                  <p>Go on, then, and make amends for your blundering behaviour.</p>
               </sp>
               <pb n="191"/>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Tom.</speaker>
                  <p>Immediately, sir; let me see where I was at; aye, aye, at the
                     World’s&#8211;End; so in I went, and had just got a pint of ale, when I found I
                     had mistaken the house, and got into the Rainbow.</p>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Freeman.</speaker>
                  <p>Well: go on.</p>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Tom.</speaker>
                  <p>Well, so in I went to the End of the World. “Ho, landlord!” says I, “do you
                     know the person that lives at No. 44?” “No,” says he, “master, being as how
                     they be newly come to the house; but if you’ll inquire at the Brown Bear,
                     they’ll direct you to the widow that keeps the Horse Shoe, who is very well
                     acquainted with the landlord at the Red Lion, who will tell you more about the
                     matter;” so I went, and took a glass with them all; and the one directed me
                     here, and the other directed me there, till at last I found I had been in the
                     wrong street all the time; so I had all to begin over again.</p>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Freeman.</speaker>
                  <p>Was ever man so curst? But what could I expect from a drunken fool? Sirrah! you
                     shall no longer continue in my service!</p>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Tom.</speaker>
                  <p>Very well, master; so this is all my thanks for running about so. I’ll keep my
                     secret to myself. Farewell, master! You don’t want, I find, to hear about
                     Maria, nor about her guardian, nor her twenty thousand pounds she has got, nor
                     her smiles, nor her dimples.</p>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Freeman.</speaker>
                  <p>Oh, my dear fellow! Tom, come and tell me all. Who is her guardian?</p>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Tom.</speaker>
                  <p>Her guardian!&#8212;that is Old Patent, that invents the wheels and the <seg
                        corresp="#note8">axes</seg>, and them there queer kind of things.<ptr
                        target="#note8" xml:id="nr8" n="8"/>
                  </p>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Freeman.</speaker>
                  <p>But tell me&#8212;what did you hear of my angel? How shall I introduce myself
                     to her? Did you learn the private character of her guardian?</p>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Tom.</speaker>
                  <p>Fair and softly, master; you have put me in a pure heat, and I think a glass of
                     wine would not be amiss, while I am telling the story.</p>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Freeman.</speaker>
                  <p>Curse on this beastly drunkard! was ever man so tortured?</p>
              
               <stage type="mixed"><hi rend="italic">(A knocking is heard). </hi>
                  </stage>
              
                  <p> See who knocks. </p>
                  <p>[<hi rend="italic">Exit</hi> TOM.</p>
               </sp>
               <stage type="entrance"><hi rend="italic">Enter</hi> DICK LOBBY.</stage>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Dick.</speaker>
                  <p>Hollo, Jack! how do you do? Called on you, on my way, to take you to the <seg
                        corresp="#note9">Club</seg>.<ptr target="#note9" xml:id="nr9" n="9"/>
                  </p>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Freeman.</speaker>
                  <p>Damn the Club!</p>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Dick.</speaker>
                  <p>How? I say bless the Club. Is this honest Jack Freeman? Where, in the name of
                     wonder, have you picked up that serious, hypocritical <seg corresp="#note10"
                        >phiz</seg>? Has your uncle taken it into his foolish old head to be <seg
                        corresp="#note10">married</seg>? or has&#8212;&#8212;&#8212;<ptr
                        target="#note10" xml:id="nr10" n="10"/></p>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Freeman.</speaker>
                  <p>A truce with your conjectures, my good friend: I am seriously in love.</p>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Dick.</speaker>
                  <p>In love! Ha! ha! ha! ha!</p>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Freeman.</speaker>
                  <p>I am not in a humour to be rallied, Dick; a passion glows in my breast,
                     honourable, pure, and may I add celestial, since it is for an object who, if
                     the excellence of her mind may be guessed at by the sweetness of her form, must
                     be endowed with every virtue, short of absolute perfection. </p>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Dick.</speaker>
                  <p>Mad! mad! mad!</p>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Freeman.</speaker>
                  <p>Did <hi rend="italic">you</hi> never feel the soft enchantment play round your
                     heart, and warm it to soothing tenderness and sweet delight?</p>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Dick.</speaker>
                  <p>No, never.</p>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Freeman.</speaker>
                  <p>Did <hi rend="italic">you</hi> never wish to be united to a sweet, angelic
                     partner, whose charms would strew roses on the rugged paths of life?</p>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Dick.</speaker>
                  <p>No, never, thank Heaven!</p>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Freeman.</speaker>
                  <p>Then to you I need not describe my feelings. The man who&#8212;&#8212;</p>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Dick.</speaker>
                  <p>Stop, stop! in the name of all your mistress’s perfections, do not torture me
                     with sentiment, but tell me who she is.<ptr target="#note11" xml:id="nr11"
                        n="11"/></p>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Freeman.</speaker>
                  <p>She is&#8212;&#8212;an angel!</p>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Dick.</speaker>
                  <p>Pugh! pugh! I knew that before; but what is her earthly name?</p>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Freeman.</speaker>
                  <p>I know not. Last night at the Opera was the first time my wandering eyes beheld
                     her. She was in company with an old gentleman, who, I have since learnt, was
                     her guardian: she dropped her fan; I flew to pick it up; it was then I greedily
                     drank in the sweet accents of her voice. I wished to improve the opportunity
                     thus afforded me, but met with so cold a reception from her antiquated
                     guardian, that all my assurance vanished in a moment, and I remained the victim
                     of despairing love; that <pb n="192"/>despair prompted me to action; the coach
                     they drove off in went at an easy rate; I followed, and discovered the abode of
                     this heavenly creature; but all that I have since learned concerning her is,
                     that she is under the guardianship of one Patent. </p>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Dick.</speaker>
                  <p>What, old Patent, the schemer?</p>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Freeman.</speaker>
                  <p>I believe the same.</p>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Dick.</speaker>
                  <p>I know his character well. If you marry his ward, he’ll make an Egyptian mummy
                     of you, Jack; he’ll take your bones, and turn them into ivory toothpicks. </p>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Freeman.</speaker>
                  <p>I beseech you to let me know particularly his character. </p>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Dick.</speaker>
                  <p>His character! that I can. In the first place, one would imagine that he
                     thought nothing right in this world, as his invention is continually on the
                     rack to make it better. I don’t know how many machines he has invented, and how
                     many schemes he has proposed for the good of the public. </p>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Freeman.</speaker>
                  <p>And have they turned to any account?</p>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Dick.</speaker>
                  <p>You shall hear. It was not long ago that he published proposals for an
                     automaton manufactory, in which he explained the variety of uses these
                     self&#8211;moving machines might be put to, and what an immense saving of
                     expense to the nation to employ them. In the first place he contended, that the
                     business of an army, according to the system of modern tactics, might as well
                     be managed by automatons as real soldiers; this would be a wonderful saving, as
                     it would render <seg corresp="#note 12">unnecessary almost</seg> the whole host of army
                     agents, army contractors, and barrack masters; and besides, those wooden
                     soldiers would go with the greatest coolness into action, never commit the
                     slightest breach of discipline, and, when killed or wounded, might be easily
                     repaired.<ptr target="#note12" xml:id="nr12" n="12"
                     /></p>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Freeman.</speaker>
                  <p>I own, in some countries, this kind of reasoning would not be so absurd; those
                     who march into the field at the arbitrary pleasure of a despot, may be compared
                     to machines, who have no will of their own; but the soldiers of a free country,
                     while they are fighting to secure their own liberty, at the same time command
                     the approbation and applause of mankind, and present the brightest pages of
                     history to admiring posterity. What was the next use he intended <seg
                        corresp="#note 13">for</seg> them?<ptr target="#note13" xml:id="nr13" n="13"
                     /></p>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Dick.</speaker>
                  <p>You shall hear. He contended, that as British seamen, by some blessed knack of
                     their own, uniformly and invariably beat their enemies wherever they found
                     them; so British automatons, made of good hardy British oak, would have the
                     same effect, and thereby save the lives of many an illustrious hero, whose
                     death, though glorious, still drew the tear from every British eye, and stifled
                     the glad sounds of victory.</p>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Freeman.</speaker>
                  <p>This scheme did not succeed.</p>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Dick.</speaker>
                  <p>No: for when Old Patent went down to the fleet at <seg corresp="#note14"
                        >Portsmouth</seg> to publish his proposals, our brave <seg corresp="#note14"
                        >tars</seg> would have him thrown overboard for a rascal who wanted the
                     enemy to get all the fighting to themselves. Baffled in this, he offered to
                     manufacture some for a few wealthy noblemen, who told him that if he could
                     contrive to make them say aye and nay, they would probably take a dozen or two,
                     as they might have use for them upon the <seg corresp="#note14">dissolution of
                        Parliament</seg>.<ptr target="#note14" xml:id="nr14" n="14"/>
                  </p>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Freeman.</speaker>
                  <p>But pray, my good friend, give me your advice.</p>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Dick.</speaker>
                  <p>Advice to a lover! I never saw one who would take anybody’s advice but their
                     own. My advice is, go to the <seg corresp="#note15">club</seg>, drink down old
                     care, and a fig for matrimony.<ptr target="#note15" xml:id="nr15" n="15"/></p>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Freeman.</speaker>
                  <p>Matrimony! the blessing of heaven!</p>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Dick.</speaker>
                  <p>And the curse of all jovial fellows. Happy the bachelor who roams through life
                     free and unrestrained! No scolding wife&#8212;no brawling children&#8212;no
                        horns&#8212;no bills.</p>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Freeman.</speaker>
                  <p>You have beheld the dark side of the picture: let me expose the other to your
                     view, and you will be dazzled with its radiance. Oh! what truer felicity can we
                     enjoy than in the constant society of her we love. The short sweets of life
                     shared with her swell into rapturous enjoyment; and when the clouds of
                     misfortune lour, and we are shunned and despised by the selfish, unpitying
                     world, who speaks peace and comfort to our distracted bosoms? from whose fond
                     heart do we feel sweet consolation and relief? from the lovely and endearing
                     partner of our life. Were the most abandoned sensualist for one short moment to
                     clasp his child to his bosom, to feel its little arms clung around his neck, to
                     feel its lips press his, and to hear it lisp out the endearing name of
                     “father,” he would not forego the delight for all the enjoyment so which
                     trifling vanity and unrestrained folly could afford. </p>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Dick.</speaker>
                  <p>Well, well, Jack, this may be all very good, though I know nothing about it.
                     However, get yourself introduced to your girl, marry her as soon as you can;
                     and if <pb n="193"/>your uncle and her guardian <seg corresp="#note16">turn</seg> you both off,
                     my estate is sufficient for us all. As I never intend to taste the sweets of
                     matrimony myself, I shall at least have the pleasure of contributing to
                     yours.<ptr target="#note16" xml:id="nr16" n="16"/></p>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Freeman.</speaker>
                  <p>You are an honest fellow, Dick; but I forgot to tell you, that I have this
                     morning received a letter from my uncle, which informs me that he will arrive
                     tomorrow, or perhaps this evening, in town, in order to introduce me to a lady
                     he has taken it into his head I ought to marry: his only reasons are, that she
                     is the ward of an old acquaintance, and has a considerable fortune. </p>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Dick.</speaker>
                  <p>So that something must be done in your affair immediately.</p>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Freeman.</speaker>
                  <p>Immediately, my dear friend. How shall I get myself introduced?</p>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Dick.</speaker>
                  <p>Aye, there lies the difficulty; you can’t conveniently, can you, turn yourself
                     into a <seg corresp="#note17">flour mill</seg>, or a <seg corresp="#note17">musical clock</seg>?<ptr target="#note17" xml:id="nr17" n="17"/></p>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Freeman.</speaker>
                  <p>No&#8212;no.</p>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Dick.</speaker>
                  <p>I fear not, however; let me see; oh, aye, I have it: here it is, my boy&#8212;I
                     have it.</p>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Freeman.</speaker>
                  <p>Oh, aye&#8212;let me hear it, my good genius.</p>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Dick.</speaker>
                  <p>You shall be a wonderful piece of machinery. I will introduce you as an
                     automaton. </p>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Freeman.</speaker>
                  <p>An automaton?</p>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Dick.</speaker>
                  <p>Yes; and I shall be the great Doctor Bolasco Rodosco, come from the <seg
                        corresp="#note18">farthest part of Asia</seg>, learned in the sciences of
                     astrology, mythology, <seg
                        corresp="#note18">minerology</seg>, mathematics, optics, and hydraulics, who,
                     after a study of more than one hundred years, has contrived the most excellent
                     and most perfect machine the world ever beheld, which he now presents for the
                     inspection of the <seg corresp="#note18">philosophic</seg> Patent, whose renown
                     has reached his ears from the other side of the globe.<ptr target="#note18"
                        xml:id="nr18" n="18"/></p>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Freeman.</speaker>
                  <p>Ridiculous enough! Do you think he is so credulous?</p>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Dick.</speaker>
                  <p>Credulous! he is the essence of credulity itself: but remember&#8212;none of
                     your sighing and sobbing; you must walk as if your whole body were full of
                     wheels. </p>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Freeman.</speaker>
                  <p>Well, however hard it may be for a lover to perform such a part, I’ll try
                     it&#8212;thus, and thus.</p>
               </sp>
               <stage type="business"><hi rend="italic">(Walks by short starts, as if moved by
                     wheels).</hi></stage>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Dick.</speaker>
                  <p>Bravo! well done! Up, you dog Tom&#8212;a coach instantly.</p>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Freeman.</speaker>
                  <p>I wish such a scheme may succeed.</p>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Dick.</speaker>
                  <p>Do not doubt it. Come on. Bravissimo!</p>
               </sp>
               <stage type="exit"><hi rend="italic">(Exeunt Freeman and Dick Lobby).</hi></stage>
            </div>
   
        <div type="scene" n="2">
               <head type="main">Act I. Scene 2.</head>
               <stage type="setting"><hi rend="italic">The House of Mr.</hi> PATENT.</stage>
               <stage type="entrance"><hi rend="italic">Enter</hi>
                  <hi rend="italic">MARIA</hi> and <hi rend="italic">ALICE.</hi></stage>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Maria.</speaker>
                  <p>Oh, some hither, Alice! come hither! and I’ll tell you all about it.</p>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Alice.</speaker>
                  <p>Well, well; but you do fluster a body so. You have no patience.</p>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Maria.</speaker>
                  <p>How can I have patience? You know we went last night to the Opera, when I saw
                     the sweetest, kindest, loveliest young gentleman I ever beheld in my life.</p>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Alice.</speaker>
                  <p>I do not doubt it.</p>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Maria.</speaker>
                  <p>I am sure I made some impression upon him, for he did every thing in his power
                     to introduce himself to our notice.</p>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Alice.</speaker>
                  <p>That’s the trick of them all; they like to introduce themselves to <hi
                        rend="italic">our </hi>notice.</p>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Maria.</speaker>
                  <p>But my guardian repulsed him with so cold and reserved an air, that I feared he
                     had almost affronted him.</p>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Alice.</speaker>
                  <p>Oh! they are not so easily affronted: I, for my part, always repulse them when
                     they have the audacity to address me.</p>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Maria.</speaker>
                  <p>Surely, Alice, that is the reason you have never got married.</p>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Alice.</speaker>
                  <p>Married! I would have you know, Miss, that I might have been married to <seg
                        corresp="#note19">twenty husbands</seg>, if I had chosen it.<ptr
                        target="#note19" xml:id="nr19" n="19"/></p>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Maria.</speaker>
                  <p>Nay, don’t be angry, Alice; I meant only to say that it was your own
                     cruelty.</p>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Alice.</speaker>
                  <p>Yes, yes, it was all owing to my own cruelty. There was Mr. Freemantle, the
                     clothier, in the city, he never ventured to speak to me, but he was always a
                     standing at his shop door, and looked at me when I passed by. Poor man! he died
                     in about ten years afterwards: I am sure it was I that broke his heart.</p>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Maria.</speaker>
                  <p>Ha! ha! ha! His heart had been very hard to be so long a breaking.</p>
               </sp>
               <pb n="194"/>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Alice.</speaker>
                  <p> And there was Mr. Deputy Dripping, the tallow&#8211;chandler’s son, he used
                     always to sit in the same pew with me at chapel; and there was young Mr. Mite,
                     the cheesemonger’s son, he used to be so delighted when I came to pay his
                     bills; I should most assuredly have gotten him if he had not married
                     another.</p>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Maria.</speaker>
                  <p>Ha! ha! ha!</p>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Alice.</speaker>
                  <p>What do you laugh at, Miss? I’d have you to know that I am not a person to be
                     laughed at.</p>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Maria.</speaker>
                  <p>Indeed, I beg your pardon; but my dear Alice, I can think of nothing but this
                     handsome young gentleman. If you could contrive&#8212;&#8212;</p>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Alice.</speaker>
                  <p>Contrive! I contrive! I’d have you to know, Miss, that I am no contriver. None
                     of your contrivances for me.</p>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Maria.</speaker>
                  <p>I am sorry, my dear Alice, I have offended you; indeed I am.</p>
               </sp>
               <stage type="entrance"><hi rend="italic">Enter </hi>PATENT.</stage>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Patent.</speaker>
                  <p>Maria, my dear Maria, I want to speak with you. Why, you look melancholy.</p>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Maria.</speaker>
                  <p>Indeed, I am so, sir. My head does ache so; I am sure I can’t live much longer
                     in this house.</p>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Patent.</speaker>
                  <p>Why so?</p>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Maria.</speaker>
                  <p>There is the grinding of so many foolish machines, and the clink clank of so
                     many pendulums, that one would think they were all
                     day long in a flour mill.</p>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Patent.</speaker>
                  <p>If you had any genius or taste, Maria, you would be very much amused in
                     examining them.</p>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Maria.</speaker>
                  <p>No, truly, sir, I think there is nothing in the house so diverting as yourself;
                     indeed, sir, I am almost always in spirits when I see you; and when I think of
                     you, I laugh sometimes so, you can’t think.</p>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Patent.</speaker>
                  <p>How, am I so amusing?</p>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Maria.</speaker>
                  <p>I don’t know: you are so queer, so out of the way, not like any other body, as
                     one may say, and have so many strange <seg corresp="#note20">windmill
                        notions</seg> in your head, my dear Guardy&#8212;I dare say every one laughs
                     as much as I do at you.<ptr target="#note20" xml:id="nr20" n="20"/></p>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Patent.</speaker>
                  <p>Every one as ignorant will: but the subject I mean to speak upon is one better
                     fitted to your capacity. Come hither, child, I want to ask you a
                     question&#8212;do you wish to be married?</p>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Maria.</speaker>
                  <p>Do I wish to be married? Oh! now, my dear guardian, you talk sensibly, and like
                     other people: indeed, my dear guardian, I won’t laugh at you now; indeed I
                     won’t!</p>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Patent.</speaker>
                  <p>Well, then, do you wish to be married?</p>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Alice.</speaker>
                  <p>Indeed, sir, she is by far too young for a husband.</p>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Maria.</speaker>
                  <p>Nay, now, hold your tongue, Alice; for I do wish to be married.</p>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Alice.</speaker>
                  <p>Hoity toity! married already! I think she might wait till her betters be
                     served.</p>
               </sp>
               <stage type="exit"><hi rend="italic">(<hi rend="italic">Exit</hi>
                  ALICE).</hi></stage>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Patent.</speaker>
                  <p>I expect my old friend, Mr. Freeman, to introduce his nephew, your lover, here
                     this afternoon.</p>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Maria.</speaker>
                  <p>My lover? Lord, sir! he never <seg corresp="#note21">made love</seg> to me! I
                     never saw him!<ptr target="#note21" xml:id="nr21" n="21"/></p>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Patent.</speaker>
                  <p>No matter, you will soon see him; he’s an excellent young man; my friend
                     informs me that he is always attentive to business; night and morning
                     surrounded by law books; he’ll hardly ever speak a word to you.</p>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Maria.</speaker>
                  <p>Upon my word, a very pretty qualification for a husband. Now, I won’t be
                     married till I have some courting, as we do in the country; if Mr. Freeman’s
                     nephew is to be my lover, he must sigh after me for two or three months
                     together: he must beg to have the pleasure and the honour of my company to all
                     the public places about town; he must be so delighted when I am pleased; and
                     when I don’t find myself in the humour to talk to him, he must look as grave
                     and as melancholy as&#8212;as my worthy, reverend, and honoured guardian.</p>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Patent.</speaker>
                  <p>Well, of all the curiosities of the creation, there is none which more
                     effectually eluded the eye of philosophic inquiry than a woman; she is like a
                     machine that is ever going wrong; vanity is the spring, caprice the pendulum,
                     and folly the pivot upon which she turns.</p>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Maria.</speaker>
                  <p>Hold, hold; I’ll never stop to hear this lecture; but to convince you, my <pb
                        n="195"/> dear guardian, that we can sometimes be constant to one Purpose, I
                     must inform you that I shall never give my hand to any other than the sweet
                     young gentleman who accosted us last night at the Opera, while I have the
                     smallest hope that I have made any impression upon his heart.</p>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Patent.</speaker>
                  <p>Absurd, ridiculous girl! if ever you marry that skipping <seg corresp="#note22"
                        >Bond Street</seg> puppy, I am one of the veriest fools in nature.<ptr
                        target="#note22" xml:id="nr22" n="22"/></p>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Maria.</speaker>
                  <p>And if ever I marry Mr. Freeman’s nephew, then&#8212;then there is no constancy
                     in the resolution of a woman.</p>
               </sp>
               <stage type="exit"><hi rend="italic">(Exit</hi> MARIA).</stage>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Patent.</speaker>
                  <p>What an obstinate creature! Where is Alice? She’ll counsel her to her duty.
                     Alice! Alice! I have set my heart upon the match. <stage type="entrance"><hi
                           rend="italic">Enter</hi> ALICE.</stage>Come hither, I want to speak to
                     you about a very important affair.</p>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Alice.</speaker>
                  <p>A very important affair! good <seg corresp="#note23">luck</seg>! <stage
                        type="delivery"><hi rend="italic">(Aside, adjusting her head
                        dress).</hi></stage>he surely don’t mean to address me. </p>
                  <p>What would your worthy honour please to have?<ptr target="#note23"
                        xml:id="nr23" n="23"/>
                  </p>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Patent.</speaker>
                  <p>Alice, you have always been a dutiful and faithful servant to me. How long is
                     it that you have been in my family?</p>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Alice.</speaker>
                  <p>Oh, dear! sir, I keep no account of years.</p>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Patent.</speaker>
                  <p>I think it is a matter of five&#8211;and&#8211;twenty years, or
                     thereabouts.</p>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Alice.</speaker>
                  <p>Five&#8211;and&#8211;twenty years! no, not so much, neither; to be sure, I was
                     very young then.</p>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Patent.</speaker>
                  <p>During which time I have found you prudent and faithful: and your knowledge of
                     the world, no doubt, increased with age.</p>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Alice.</speaker>
                  <stage type="delivery"><hi rend="italic">(With great agitation).</hi></stage>
                  <p>Aye!</p>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Patent.</speaker>
                  <p>Alice, for some time past I have had in my thoughts a matrimonial project.</p>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Alice.</speaker>
                  <p><stage type="delivery"><hi rend="italic">(Aside, and with a great deal of
                           girlish conceit and leering). </hi></stage>Oh! here it comes! </p>
                  <p>And how is it possible for me, worthy sir, to guess the fortunate female who
                     has interested your heart.</p>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Patent.</speaker>
                  <p>Nay, Alice, you mistake; it is a match for my ward Maria, I mean.</p>
                  <stage type="business"><hi rend="italic">(Alice changes her air to that of gloomy
                        haughtiness, anger, and disappointment). </hi></stage>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <p>Now I wish you to use all your influence to make her marry Mr. Freeman’s
                     nephew.</p>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Alice.</speaker>
                  <p>I have no influence, sir.</p>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Patent.</speaker>
                  <p>Try, however: besides, I wish you to guard well, lest a <seg corresp="#note24"
                        >dangling</seg> young fellow she saw last night at the Opera, should get
                     admittance into the house.<ptr target="#note24" xml:id="nr24" n="24"/></p>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Alice.</speaker>
                  <p>Oh! you may depend upon it, sir; I’ll guard the house against all dangling
                     young fellows. Young fellows! pugh! I hate the very sight of them.</p>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Patent.</speaker>
                  <p>Do so, my dear Alice, and rely upon my gratitude: I’ll bestow upon you a
                     greater reward than you think of. You don’t know what good fortune awaits
                     you.</p>
               </sp>
               <stage type="exit"><hi rend="italic">[Exit</hi> PATENT.</stage>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Alice.</speaker>
                  <p>“My dear Alice!” He’s captivated; as sure as death, he’s smitten; he has it
                     here. “You don’t know what good fortune awaits you.” I was sure to get a
                     promise of marriage to&#8211;day, for I dreamed all last night that somebody
                     put a ring upon my finger. I wonder when it will be.</p>
               </sp>
               <stage type="business"><hi rend="italic">(A knocking at the door).</hi></stage>
               <stage type="entrance"><hi rend="italic">Enter </hi>DICK LOBBY<hi rend="italic">,
                     disguised in a strange outlandish manner, long beard, &amp;c.</hi></stage>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Dick.</speaker>
                  <p>Worthy dame, art thou the mistress of this honoured mansion!</p>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Alice.</speaker>
                  <p>May be I am, sir, and may be not. More wonderfuller things have come to
                     pass.</p>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Dick.</speaker>
                  <p>Is not this the house of the immortal philosopher Patent, the virtues and
                     prudence of whose housekeeper, Miss Alice, <seg corresp="#note25">are</seg> known to all the
                     world.<ptr target="#note25" xml:id="nr25" n="25"/></p>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Alice.</speaker>
                  <p>Oh, la, sir! this, to be sure, is the house of Mr. Patent.</p>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Dick.</speaker>
                  <p>I wish, with your permission, to pass a few moments in his presence.</p>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Alice.</speaker>
                  <p> And pray, sir, who are you? and what do you want?</p>
               </sp>
               <pb n="196"/>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Dick.</speaker>
                  <p>I am the great Doctor Bolasko Rodoska, come from the furthest corner of
                     Asia.</p>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Alice.</speaker>
                  <p>And what is your purpose for coming hither, sir?</p>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Dick.</speaker>
                  <p>To a person of your years and prudence I believe I may safely impart my
                     purpose.</p>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Alice.</speaker>
                  <p>Years!</p>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Dick.</speaker>
                  <p>I come to present the renowned Dr. Patent with a machine which
                     <seg corresp="26">excels</seg> all other machines upon the face of the earth.<ptr target="#note26"
                        xml:id="nr26" n="26"/></p>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Alice.</speaker>
                  <p>Machine! there shall be no machine come here: my master has too many machines
                     already. As for you, Mr. Doctor Snuffy Macrosky, come from the farthest corner
                     of Asia, if you had any good manners, you would have called in at a <seg
                        corresp="#note27">barber’s shop</seg> by the way, and had your beard shaved,
                     before you ventured to appear before the ladies.<ptr target="#note27"
                        xml:id="nr27" n="27"/></p>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Dick.</speaker>
                  <p>Sweet angelic creature! the accents of your voice, even in anger, are
                     delightful; would I could speak with Miss Alice, the worthy housekeeper of Mr.
                     Patent; the sweetness of her disposition would soon yield to my request.</p>
                  <stage type="business"><hi rend="italic">Curtseying affectedly).</hi></stage>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Alice.</speaker>
                  <p>Oh, sir! I&#8212;I am Miss Alice.</p>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Dick.</speaker>
                  <p>Is it possible? Charming as my fond imagination had painted you, you surpass
                     all I had conceived.</p>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Alice.</speaker>
                  <p>Oh, sir! you overpower me.</p>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Dick.</speaker>
                  <p>Oh! what delight to lead so charming a creature to the hymeneal
                     altar.</p>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Alice.</speaker>
                  <p>Oh ,sir! I&#8212;I&#8212;you make me blush.</p>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Dick.</speaker>
                  <p>Deign, fair excellence, to grant my request; let me speak for a moment with Mr.
                     Patent, and again I fly to your arms.</p>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Alice.</speaker>
                  <p>Alas! I can refuse you nothing; but you will be inconstant.</p>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Dick.</speaker>
                  <p>No! no!</p>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Alice.</speaker>
                  <p> You will break my tender heart.</p>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Dick.</speaker>
                  <p>Never, never.</p>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Alice.</speaker>
                  <p>Ah! you’re a bewitching man!</p>
               </sp>
               <stage type="exit">[<hi rend="italic">Exit</hi> Alice<hi rend="italic">, leering and
                     looking tenderly at him.</hi></stage>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Dick.</speaker>
                  <p>Well done, as yet; but ecod, you’re a clever fellow. I hope to serve
                     effectually my friend Freeman; but here comes Old Patent. Now to my aid, all ye
                        <seg corresp="#note28">powers of gravity</seg>!<ptr target="#note28"
                        xml:id="nr28" n="28"/></p>
               </sp>
               <stage type="entrance"><hi rend="italic">Enter PATENT. </hi></stage>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Patent.</speaker>
                  <p> Your pleasure with me, sir.</p>
               </sp>
               <stage type="business">(DICK LOBBY<hi rend="italic"> bows affectedly, with his
                  <seg corresp="#note29">forehead to the ground</seg>, several times, and makes many
                     gesticulations of veneration and respect, while </hi>PATENT<hi rend="italic">
                        gazes at him with astonishment)</hi>. <ptr target="#note29"
                           xml:id="nr29" n="29"/></stage>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Dick.</speaker>
                  <p>Pardon, renowned sir, that I am unable to express the respect and veneration
                     with which the presence of so great a philosopher inspire me.</p>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Patent.</speaker>
                  <p>Few like you, sir, in these degenerate days, estimate the value of men of
                     science and merit; much greater than mine passes unnoticed and unknown. Will
                     you be seated, sir?</p>
                  <stage type="business"><hi rend="italic">(They take their chairs with much
                        ceremony). </hi></stage>
                  <p>Pray, sir, whom have I the honour of beholding? </p>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Dick.</speaker>
                  <p>I am the great Doctor Bolaski Rodoski, the most renowned of the bramins of the east; and I may say, without vanity,
                     the most skilful of the magi.
                  </p>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Patent.</speaker>
                  <p>Most worthy sir, happy am I that my humble dwelling is honoured by such a
                     visit.</p>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Dick.</speaker>
                  <p>The cottage of the philosopher is to me more magnificent than the palace of the
                     Emperor of China; and you, sir, though your country has been tardy in rewarding your merit, your fame has reached the
                     farthest corner of Asia.</p>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Patent.</speaker>
                  <p>Indeed!&#8212;Certainly there are few things in this world I have not
                     endeavoured to improve.</p>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Dick.</speaker>
                  <p>Your extensive knowledge, most worthy sir, has been the theme of our universal
                     admiration: many of your schemes for the benefit of mankind have been there
                     practised, with the happiest effects, and your praise is on every tongue.</p>
               </sp>
               <pb n="197"/>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Patent.</speaker>
                  <p>Oh, sir, you delight me to hear it! And have they yet made use of my new
                     invented sea shoes, for walking on the top of the water.</p>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Dick.</speaker>
                  <p>Oh, certainly, sir! and our learned College of Quimpnaparabo think so highly of
                     that and your other inventions, that they have deputed me, being the head of
                     their venerable body, to wait upon you personally, and present you with their
                     thanks, and to request that you will do them the honour of becoming a member of
                     their learned and venerable society.</p>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Patent.</speaker>
                  <p>I cannot but feel myself delighted in accepting so high an honour.</p>
               </sp>
               <stage type="business"><hi rend="italic">(They bow to each other with great
                     affectation).</hi></stage>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Dick.</speaker>
                  <p>And henceforth you will be pleased, sir, to add to your name, the letters F.
                     double O. L., which in the language of the Bramins mean most learned and
                     extraordinary fellow of the Philosophical Society.</p>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Patent.</speaker>
                  <p>I shall do myself the pleasure of preparing a letter of thanks to the learned
                     body.</p>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Dick.</speaker>
                  <p>And as a further proof of their esteem, they have ordered me to present to you
                     the most wonderful piece of mechanism we believe the world ever saw.</p>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Patent.</speaker>
                  <p>Oh, let me see it. Where is it?</p>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Dick.</speaker>
                  <p>You shall see it presently, sir. It is an automaton; but of so perfect a construction, that the united power of
                     man cannot make such another.</p>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Patent</speaker>
                  <p>My dear sir, I am all impatience to see it.</p>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Dick.</speaker>
                  <p>I respect you too well to refuse you any longer that pleasure. It waits in a
                     coach in the street. I know well how to manage the springs of it: it shall wait
                     upon you in a moment.</p>
               </sp>
               <stage type="exit"><hi rend="italic">[Exit </hi>DICK LOBBY.</stage>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Patent.</speaker>
                  <p> F double O L. This piece of good fortune makes ample amends for the vexation
                     Maria’s obstinacy has occasioned me. Peter Patent, F double O L! Well, men of
                     genius and merit are sure to be rewarded one time or other. I am now known to
                     all the learned in Asia. I shall get myself instructed in Arabic, that I may be able the more easily to correspond with them. I
                     shall write a treatise upon this machine which they have sent me; this will
                     spread my fame th<supplied reason="omitted-in-original">r</supplied>ough all
                     the learned in Europe&#8212;the degree of Doctor will soon be conferred upon
                     me, and&#8212;but stop&#8212;&#8212;&#8212;</p>
               </sp>
               <stage type="mixed"><hi rend="italic">Re&#8211;enter </hi>DICK LOBBY<hi rend="italic"
                     >, leading in </hi>FREEMAN<hi rend="italic">, with a mask and <seg
                        corresp="#note30">domino</seg>: </hi>FREEMAN<hi rend="italic"> steps by
                     starts, as if set a going by wheels. </hi>PATENT<hi rend="italic"> puts on his
                     spectacles to observe him, and while with eager curiosity he stands directly
                     before </hi>FREEMAN<hi rend="italic">, the latter, as if by an involuntary
                     motion, throws him down, and passes.</hi><ptr target="#note30" xml:id="nr30"
                     n="30"/></stage>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Patent.</speaker>
                  <p>Stop it, my dear Doctor&#8212;stop it! it may chance to get into Maria’s room,
                     and frighten her to death.</p>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Dick.</speaker>
                  <p>Worthy sir, be under no uneasiness; I shall stop it in a moment.</p>
               </sp>
               <stage type="business"><hi rend="italic"> (Runs and touches </hi>FREEMAN<hi
                     rend="italic">, who instantly stops. </hi>PATENT<hi rend="italic"> comes
                     forward with very great curiosity to examine him, he by chance touches a part
                     of his robe, </hi>FREEMAN<hi rend="italic"> at this moment, by a seeming
                     involuntary impulse, seizes </hi>PATENT’s<hi rend="italic"> wig, and holds it
                     at arm’s length above his head; </hi>PATENT<hi rend="italic"> retreats
                     fearfully).</hi></stage>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Patent.</speaker>
                  <p>Dear Doctor, be so good as to make it deliver up my wig. What a noble machine
                     it is.</p>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Dick.</speaker>
                  <p>I must instruct you, sir, in the art of commanding it. There are no less than
                     seven hundred wheels, two hundred and fifty pullies, and three hundred
                     pendulums in its belly.</p>
                  <stage type="business">(LOBBY<hi rend="italic"> places </hi>FREEMAN<hi
                        rend="italic"> in an arm chair).</hi></stage>
                  <p>Each of these have two hundred and twenty&#8211;three distinct movements,
                     which, during my short stay in town, I shall endeavour to explain.</p>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Patent.</speaker>
                  <p>You mean, then, soon to return to your own country, sir.</p>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Dick.</speaker>
                  <p>Yes, sir, after I bring about a few changes which I think will be of advantage
                     to this great metropolis.</p>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Patent.</speaker>
                  <p>Aye, aye, what are they?</p>
               </sp>
               <pb n="198"/>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Dick.</speaker>
                  <p>In the first place, sir, I intend to transfer <seg corresp="#note31">Kensington
                        Gardens</seg> to the neighbourhood of <seg corresp="#note31"
                        >Spitalfields</seg>, and place the <seg corresp="#note31">Monument</seg> on
                     the middle of <seg corresp="#note31">Blackfriars Bridge</seg><ptr
                        target="#note31" xml:id="nr31" n="31"/>. </p>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Patent.</speaker>
                  <p>It is not surely possible.</p>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Dick.</speaker>
                  <p>Nothing more easy, sir. The philosophic Mr. Patent cannot doubt that every
                     thing is possible to science.</p>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Patent.</speaker>
                  <p>True, sir. In the mean time I expect to have the pleasure of your company every
                     moment you are disengaged.</p>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Dick.</speaker>
                  <p>Sir, you may command me. I must now take my leave, having important dispatches
                     to forward to the Emperor of <seg corresp="#note32">Mogul Tartary</seg>. Nay,
                     do not stir; I shall not give you the trouble of waiting upon me to the
                        door.<ptr target="#note32" xml:id="nr32" n="32"/></p>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Patent.</speaker>
                  <p>It is an honour, Sir.</p>
               </sp>
               <stage type="mixed"><hi rend="italic">(They bow to each other with great affectation
                     and self&#8211;importance, and exeunt, when the Act Scene drops).</hi></stage>
            </div>
    
   
</div><div type="act" n="2">
<div type="scene" n="1">
               <head type="main">ACT II. Scene 1.</head>
               <stage type="mixed"> FREEMAN<hi rend="italic">’s Lodgings.</hi>&#8212;TOM<hi
                     rend="italic"> discovered sleeping.</hi></stage>
               <stage type="business"> (<hi rend="italic">A loud knocking is heard).</hi></stage>
               <stage type="entrance"><hi rend="italic">Enter </hi>OLD FREEMAN.</stage>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Old Freeman</speaker>
                  <p>What, nobody at home, or all asleep. Hollo! Jack&#8212;Freeman. <stage
                        type="business"><hi rend="italic"> (Raps on the floor with his stick, then
                           perceives </hi>TOM). </stage> Oh! aye! here’s lazy Tom. Up, you lazy
                     drone. </p>
               </sp>
               <stage type="business"><hi rend="italic"> (Tumbles him out of the chair.)
                  </hi></stage>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Tom.</speaker>
                  <p>Mercy on us!</p>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Old Freeman.</speaker>
                  <p>Where’s your master, sirrah?</p>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Tom.</speaker>
                  <stage type="business"><hi rend="italic">(Yawns).</hi></stage>
                  <p>My master, sir&#8212;aye, oh!</p>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Old Freeman.</speaker>
                  <p> Answer me, sirrah, or I’ll knock you down.</p>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Tom.</speaker>
                  <p>Oh, aye!&#8212;beg your pardon, Mr. Freeman&#8212;didn’t see you before.</p>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Old Freeman.</speaker>
                  <p>I suppose, sirrah, you’re drunk, as usual.</p>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Tom.</speaker>
                  <p>Oh, no, no, sir, not I! I am as sober, sir, as a judge&#8212;quite reformed,
                     sir.</p>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Old Freeman.</speaker>
                  <p>I am glad to hear it.</p>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Tom.</speaker>
                  <p>No liquor for me, sir; I hate the very smell of it: indeed, if I had any money
                     now, I should be tempted to drink your honour’s health, I am so glad to see
                     your honour in town.</p>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Old Freeman.</speaker>
                  <p>Well, well, it is better than you have got none&#8212;it might divert you from
                     your good resolution. But where is your master?</p>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Tom.</speaker>
                  <p>My master, sir&#8212;my master, sir, is&#8212;so harassed with business.</p>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Old Freeman.</speaker>
                  <p>Glad to hear it&#8212;glad to hear it&#8212;he’ll make a fortune. </p>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Tom.</speaker>
                  <p>We have been up early, sir, and down late; client after client&#8212;plaintiff
                     and defendant. Mr. Freeman, sir, is at present the ablest counsellor at the
                     bar.</p>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Old Freeman.</speaker>
                  <p>Ecod, he’s a clever fellow&#8212;was always a <seg corresp="#note33">cute</seg>
                     dog&#8212;but where is he? where is he?<ptr target="#note33" xml:id="nr33"
                        n="33"/></p>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Tom.</speaker>
                  <p>Oh, sir, you know where he is.</p>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Old Freeman.</speaker>
                  <p>Not I&#8212;not I. How should I know?</p>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Tom.</speaker>
                  <p>He is retained on a very great <seg corresp="#note34">cause</seg>, <seg
                        corresp="#note34">depending</seg> in <seg corresp="#note34"
                        >Yorkshire</seg>.<ptr target="#note34" xml:id="nr34" n="34"/></p>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Old Freeman.</speaker>
                  <p>What! gone to Yorkshire? How unlucky! when I came expressly to town to get him
                     married to a handsome fortune; but I’m glad he’s so attentive to business.</p>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Tom.</speaker>
                  <p>Oh, sir! were it in my power to give you a specimen of his abilities, it would
                     surprise you.</p>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Old Freeman.</speaker>
                  <p>I do not doubt it; I hope to see him Lord Chancellor some day or other. What
                     particular cause has he been engaged in lately?</p>
               </sp>
               <pb n="199"/>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Tom.</speaker>
                  <p>Oh, what should it be, sir?&#8212;why, a horrid case.</p>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Old Freeman.</speaker>
                  <p>Why, what was it, eh?</p>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Tom.</speaker>
                  <p>A volunteer colonel, sir, was caught drinking tea at <seg corresp="#note35"
                        >Bagnigge Wells</seg> with a tailor’s wife.<ptr target="#note35"
                        xml:id="nr35" n="35"/>
                  </p>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Old Freeman.</speaker>
                  <p>Aye, aye, like enough.</p>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Tom.</speaker>
                  <p>When the tailor heroically resolved to avenge his injured honour, by calling
                     the seducer to account in the&#8212;&#8212;<seg corresp="#note36">Court of
                        Queen’s Bench</seg>.<ptr target="#note36" xml:id="nr36" n="36"/></p>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Old Freeman.</speaker>
                  <p>Aye, aye, like to hear it.</p>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Tom.</speaker>
                  <p>Counsel must be retained on both sides; and the reputation of my master in
                     these cases is so great, that the parties met each other crossing the Temple,
                     on their way to his chambers. The question then was, who should be first; for
                     on that depended my master’s opinion of the cause.</p>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Old Freeman.</speaker>
                  <p>True, true. Well, eh?</p>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Tom.</speaker>
                  <p>The Colonel, by the superior agility of his limbs, outstripped his antagonist
                     by six yards and a half, tabled down the fees, and my master found that the man
                     of war had truth and justice on his side, and that the son of the scissors was
                     not entitled to a farthing of damages.</p>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Old Freeman.</speaker>
                  <p>How did he prove it?&#8212;how did he prove it?</p>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Tom.</speaker>
                  <p>The easiest thing in the world, sir. Let me see&#8212;the law is perfectly
                     clear on this point, which is, that if any man drinks tea with his neighbour’s
                     wife, the injured party is allowed a compensation in damages; but this law was
                     enacted for men; now the Colonel being placed over or above a company of men,
                     he is consequently more than a man; and the tailor being commonly reputed to be
                     less, the law with regard to the parties was in noebus waysibus applicablus,
                     therefore the plaintiff ought to be <seg corresp="#note37">nonsuited</seg>.<ptr
                        target="#note37" xml:id="nr37" n="37"/></p>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Old Freeman.</speaker>
                  <p>Aye, aye, very clear&#8212;very clear. But how did Jack get so soon into
                     notice? how was his merit so soon discovered?</p>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Tom.</speaker>
                  <p>Oh, sir, by his wit!</p>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Old Freeman.</speaker>
                  <p>By his wit!</p>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Tom.</speaker>
                  <p>Yes, sir, <seg corresp="#note38">wit</seg> is the true road to preferment at
                     the bar; and I’ll give you a specimen: let us suppose, sir, that I am a
                     counsellor, and you are a witness. Now answer me as to what I shall interrogate
                     you. Are you not Matthew Freeman, Esq., from <seg corresp="#note38"
                        >Suffolk</seg>?<ptr target="#note38" xml:id="nr38" n="38"/></p>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Old Freeman.</speaker>
                  <p>Yes.</p>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Tom.</speaker>
                  <p>Have not you or your nephew got a servant of the name of Tom Clinker?</p>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Old Freeman.</speaker>
                  <p>Yes.</p>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Tom.</speaker>
                  <p>And have you not been frequently in the habit of giving the said Tom some money
                        <supplied reason="omitted-in-original">to</supplied> drink your health?</p>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Old Freeman.</speaker>
                  <p>I have not given him <seg corresp="#note39">any</seg> for a long time.<ptr target="#note39" xml:id="nr39" n="39"/></p>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Tom.</speaker>
                  <p>Then says I, without the least hesitation, “you have the more need to do it
                     now.” The Court is immediately convulsed with laughter at the smartness of the
                     repartee&#8212;the joke is put into all the fashionable newspapers in the
                     morning&#8212;business pours in on all sides; and, if to a facility of punning,
                     I add a happy knack at teazing and confusing a witness, I become the admiration
                     of the town, and I have nothing to do but to march strait forwards in the road
                     to fortune and honour.</p>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Old Freeman.</speaker>
                  <p>Very good; very good. Ecod, you would make a very good lawyer yourself; and, as
                     a proof how well I am pleased with your behaviour, I shall even give you
                     sixpence; but hark ye, don’t get drunk with it.</p>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Tom.</speaker>
                  <p>Oh no, master! thank you. <stage type="delivery"><hi rend="italic"
                           >(Aside).</hi></stage>Old curmudgeon!</p>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Old Freeman.</speaker>
                  <p>And now I must go and reconcile my old friend to bear with patience my nephew’s
                     absence. I hope he won’t give the girl to another&#8212;he’s so fond of a new
                     project. Good day, Tom! and, do you hear, take care that your master’s chambers
                     be kept clean, and everything in order; and be sure to have an eye that nobody
                     comes to steal, for in London a thief looks so much like a gentleman, one can
                     hardly tell the one from the other. </p>
               </sp>
               <pb n="200"/>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Tom.</speaker>
                  <p>Oh Lord! oh Lord! oh Lord! what shall I do? I am ruined! undone! undone!</p>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Old Freeman.</speaker>
                  <p>What? what? what? what’s the matter?</p>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Tom.</speaker>
                  <p>Lord, sir! if the postman should come, I have not a penny to pay the postage of
                     a letter.</p>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Old Freeman.</speaker>
                  <p>How?</p>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Tom.</speaker>
                  <p>Forgot to ask it. Ruined! undone!</p>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Old Freeman.</speaker>
                  <p>Never mind, never mind, Tom; have no need of them.</p>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Tom.</speaker>
                  <p>Must have my master’s new wig dressed, and all his boots and shoes cleaned,
                     too, sir. Ruined! ruined!</p>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Old Freeman.</speaker>
                  <p>Don’t take on so. Here’s a half&#8211;a&#8211;crown for you; but don’t spend it
                     extravagantly, and be sure to mark everything you lay it out for.</p>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Tom.</speaker>
                  <p>That I will, please you<supplied reason="omitted-in-original">r</supplied>
                     honour. Your honour has quite revived me.</p>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Old Freeman.</speaker>
                  <p>Be diligent, Tom; if your master don’t return in a week or two, I’ll give you
                     more. Be diligent&#8212;be careful.</p>
               </sp>
               <stage type="exit"><hi rend="italic">[Exit</hi> OLD FREEMAN. </stage>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Tom.</speaker>
                  <p>Be diligent&#8212;be careful. There he goes! What an old fool! Well, I’ve heard
                     it said that lies may stick in a man’s throat&#8212;I’m sure they’ve scorched
                     mine. I must go and have beer to moisten it&#8212;that’s for my own health;
                     then I’ll have a glass to drink good luck to my young master; and another glass
                     to wish confusion to my old one.</p>
               </sp>
               <stage type="exit"><hi rend="italic">[Exit</hi> TOM. </stage>
            </div>
        <div type="scene" n="2">
               <head type="main">Act II. Scene 2.</head>
               <stage type="scene"><hi rend="italic">Patent’s House.</hi></stage>
               <stage type="entrance"><hi rend="italic"> Enter </hi>OLD PATENT<hi rend="italic">
                     and</hi> MARIA. </stage>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Patent.</speaker>
                  <p>My dear Maria, is it possible you could ever take a pleasure in contradicting
                     me?</p>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Maria.</speaker>
                  <p>I never did. To me it is always painful.</p>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Patent.</speaker>
                  <p>Then why not consent to a marriage, planned only for your happiness?</p>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Maria.</speaker>
                  <p>And which is sure to make me miserable, seeing my heart is entirely devoted to
                     another.</p>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Patent.</speaker>
                  <p>Madness! Silly, blind, deluded girl!</p>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Maria.</speaker>
                  <p>Nay, there now, you’re in a passion again.</p>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Patent.</speaker>
                  <p> Should Mr. Freeman not arrive to&#8211;day, you shall pack off to the country
                     to&#8211;morrow, far from the pursuit of the silly coxcomb who has entrapped
                     your affections.</p>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Maria.</speaker>
                  <p>My dear sir, be pacified; I can be nowhere more safe from his pursuit than
                     where I am. Love, they say, is strong, and can do many things; but, alas! I am
                     afraid he can’t break down the walls of a house, or jump in at a
                     three&#8211;pair of stairs window.</p>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Patent.</speaker>
                  <p>No! no! I’ll defy him to get admittance here. Some men may be duped; the more
                     fools they: they don’t know the world like me. I believe he’ll find my wisdom
                     rather too much for his cunning. He has got philosophy and science to oppose
                     him, and no wonder that he should be foiled in the contest.</p>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Maria.</speaker>
                  <p>Well, then, my dear guardian, sit down, and be pacified, but think no more of
                     the country; here’s my bag, and while I work I’ll sing you a song.</p>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Patent.</speaker>
                  <p>Do so Maria. I like to hear you sing.</p>
               </sp>
               <stage type="other">SONG&#8212;MARIA.</stage>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Maria.</speaker>
                  <lg>
                     <l>OH! could my sighs my wish impart, </l>
                     <l>And whisper to his ear my love; </l>
                     <l>Oh! could he feel the throbbing heart,</l>
                     <l>Its tenderness and truth to prove! </l>
                  </lg>
                  <lg>
                     <l>Oh! could he view my soul sincere!</l>
                     <l>Though hopeless love disturbs its rest; </l>
                     <l>He’d find his image pictur’d there, </l>
                     <l>For ever lov’d, and still carest.
                     </l>
                  </lg>
                  <pb n="201"/>
                  <lg>
                     <l>At morning<supplied reason="omitted-in-original">,</supplied> dawn<supplied
                           reason="omitted-in-original">,</supplied> or close of day, </l>
                     <l>I’d prize with him the lowest cot;</l>
                     <l>With him would join the <seg corresp="#note40">rural lay</seg><ptr
                           target="#note40" xml:id="nr40" n="40"/></l>
                     <l>All else but love and him forgot. </l>
                  </lg>
                  <lg>
                     <l>And when the term of life drew nigh,</l>
                     <l>I’d wish my pillow were his breast; </l>
                     <l>There breathe the last expiring sigh, </l>
                     <l>And sink within his arms to rest.</l>
                  </lg>
               </sp>
               <stage type="mixed"><hi rend="italic">(During the Song </hi>PATENT<hi rend="italic">
                     falls asleep. </hi>MARIA<hi rend="italic"> repeats the first verse after the
                     symphony has ceased, whilst </hi>YOUNG FREEMAN<hi rend="italic">, who had been
                     searching for her apartment cautiously, enters, attracted by the sound of her
                     voice; he stands enraptured with love and admiration; at the conclusion
                     </hi>MARIA<hi rend="italic"> turns round, and at the appearance of
                     </hi>FREEMAN<hi rend="italic">, screams aloud; </hi>PATENT<hi rend="italic">
                     awakes, and with great terror catches her in his arms. FREEMAN instantly
                     withdraws.</hi>
               </stage>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Patent.</speaker>
                  <p>Bless me! bless me! What’s the matter? what’s the matter?</p>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Maria.</speaker>
                  <p>Oh! oh! oh!</p>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Patent.</speaker>
                  <p>Maria! Maria! what’s the matter?</p>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Maria.</speaker>
                  <p>Nothing&#8212;only!&#8212;oh dear!&#8212;it was nothing!</p>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Patent.</speaker>
                  <p>Nothing? then what made you cry out so?</p>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Maria.</speaker>
                  <p>Oh, nothing! only I fell asleep, and thought I saw a ghost.</p>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Patent.</speaker>
                  <p>Silly, ridiculous girl! you have broken my nap: I must go to finish it in my
                     study.</p>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Maria.</speaker>
                  <p>Oh, no! don’t go, don’t leave me&#8212;&#8212;yes, yes, go away! But I am
                     afraid: stop. </p>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Patent.</speaker>
                  <p>Is the girl mad?</p>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Maria.</speaker>
                  <p>Yes, yes, go away, but&#8212;&#8212;come when I call; be sure to be within
                     hearing&#8212;that is&#8212;if I call very loud&#8212;or send up Alice.</p>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Patent.</speaker>
                  <p>Sit down, Maria, compose yourself; yonder comes Alice. This foolish dream has
                     so affected you.</p>
               </sp>
               <stage type="business">Enter ALICE.</stage>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Alice.</speaker>
                  <p>What’s the matter now?</p>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Patent.</speaker>
                  <p>Here, Alice, take care of her. She fell asleep just now, and had an ugly
                     dream.</p>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Alice.</speaker>
                  <p>Mercy on us! what was it?</p>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Patent.</speaker>
                  <p>Something about a ghost. Take care of her&#8212;take care of her. I’ll look in
                     presently.</p>
               </sp>
               <stage type="business">[<hi rend="italic">Exit</hi> PATENT.</stage>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Maria.</speaker>
                  <p>Oh, Alice! Alice! what think you? I have seen him&#8212;he’s here.</p>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Alice.</speaker>
                  <p>Where? seen whom?</p>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Maria.</speaker>
                  <p>My lover, the sweet young gentleman.</p>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Alice</speaker>
                  <p>Oh! mercy on us! I’m frightened to death. Oh! there he is!</p>
               </sp>
               <stage type="business"><hi rend="italic">(Looks round fearfully, and screams at every
                     turn).</hi></stage>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Maria.</speaker>
                  <p>Do, Alice, be pacified; he don’t mean to speak to you: he’s not in love with
                     you.</p>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Alice.</speaker>
                  <p>Oh, that’s true! but he may make a mistake, you know. Mercy on us! Oh! I won’t
                     stay in the house! <stage type="business"><hi rend="italic">(A loud knocking is
                           heard at the door).</hi>
                     </stage> Oh! there he is again!</p>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Maria.</speaker>
                  <p>Go to the door, Alice. But stop, you must not leave me&#8212;I’ll go to the
                     door with you&#8212;indeed, Alice, you must not leave me.</p>
               </sp>
               <pb n="202"/>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Alice.</speaker>
                  <p>Aye, but I will. What, stop to be&#8212;&#8212;<stage type="business">(A loud
                        knocking).</stage> Oh! mercy on us!</p>
               </sp>
               <stage type="mixed"><hi rend="italic">(Runs out screaming, </hi>MARIA <hi
                     rend="italic">follows).</hi></stage>
               <stage type="business">
                  <hi rend="italic">(A continued knocking).</hi>
               </stage>
               <stage type="entrance"><hi rend="italic">Enter </hi>PATENT.</stage>
               <stage type="business"> </stage>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Patent.</speaker>
                  <p>What’s the matter? where’s Alice? must I open the door myself?</p>
               </sp>
               <stage type="entrance"><hi rend="italic">Enter </hi>OLD FREEMAN.</stage>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Old Freeman.</speaker>
                  <p>Oh! how do you do, old boy? You Londoners, I believe, sleep all day, because
                     you’re awake all night. One may pull the house down before you’ll come to open
                     the door.</p>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Patent.</speaker>
                  <p>I am overjoyed to see my good old friend in London. I have impatiently expected
                     your arrival. Where is your nephew, young Mr. Freeman?</p>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Old Freeman.</speaker>
                  <p>Only about a little business&#8212;down to Yorkshire&#8212;night and day up to
                     the ears in business.</p>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Patent.</speaker>
                  <p>Are there so many law&#8211;suits depending at present?</p>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Old Freeman.</speaker>
                  <p>Thousands!</p>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Patent.</speaker>
                  <p>I have often thought how this might be avoided.</p>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Old Freeman.</speaker>
                  <p>Avoided?</p>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Patent.</speaker>
                  <p>And a scheme set on foot by which these disputes might be settled without
                     either delay or expense.</p>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Old Freeman.</speaker>
                  <p>Mad! mad! What? where would be the traffic, if all mankind were to settle their
                     disputes themselves? I say, where would be the cash? Don’t you know, old boy,
                     that Jack Freeman is making a fortune to settle on your ward’s young ones,
                     eh?</p>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Patent.</speaker>
                  <p>To be sure; I did not think of that; but everything is susceptible of
                     improvement.</p>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Old Freeman.</speaker>
                  <p>No, no; very well as they are.</p>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Patent.</speaker>
                  <p>Had it not been for the discoveries of men of science, and the improvements
                     which they have suggested, mankind would have still been in a state of savage
                     barbarity: dens and caverns would have been his habitation, and his food the
                     rank, spontaneous productions of uncultivated nature.</p>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Old Freeman.</speaker>
                  <p>Nonsence! nonsence! I am for the good old way, the plain downright old way.
                     None of your <seg corresp="#note41">kickshaw</seg> fashions for me. The man
                     that wears his spectacles dangling at his breast instead of placing them right
                     upon his nose, may chance to run his head against a post.<ptr target="#note41"
                        xml:id="nr41" n="41"/></p>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Patent.</speaker>
                  <p>Absurd! ridiculous! Sir, if you are too ignorant to estimate the value of men
                     of genius, others are not. I myself, for the improvements which I have
                     suggested, have attracted the notice of one of the most learned bodies in all
                     Asia, and have now the honour of adding F double O L to my name.</p>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Old Freeman.</speaker>
                  <stage type="delivery"><hi rend="italic">(Aside).</hi></stage>
                  <p>Ha! ha! ha! Fool! by all that’s excellent (but I must make friends with him,
                     else Jack might lose the girl). </p>
                  <p>Come, come, my old friend, don’t let us dispute about either the new way or the
                     old; I don’t understand these things so well as you, and that may be <supplied
                        reason="omitted-in-original">the</supplied> reason we are of contrary
                     opinions.</p>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Patent.</speaker>
                  <p>The very reason; but I shall endeavour to make you comprehend&#8212; &#8212;
                     &#8212; </p>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Old Freeman.</speaker>
                  <p>Any other time, my good friend; but tell me, now, how your ward, Maria is: a
                     nice girl, I dare say.</p>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Patent.</speaker>
                  <p>Charming as an angel, sir.</p>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Old Freeman.</speaker>
                  <p>I hope you take good care to keep her from the young fellows&#8212;keep a sharp
                     look out&#8212;if you don’t, what betwixt cunning and impudence they’ll get the
                     better of you.</p>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Patent.</speaker>
                  <p>Cunning and impudent indeed, would be the man who should entertain the least
                     idea of deceiving me. No, sir; science has made me more than usually
                     circumspect, and appearances which might easily satisfy the minds of other men,
                     are by me regarded with the most scrutinizing eye.</p>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Old Freeman.</speaker>
                  <p>Well, well, I am glad to hear it; only mentioned by way of caution, you know.
                     But come, I must see Maria. Where is she?</p>
               </sp>
               <pb n="203"/>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Patent.</speaker>
                  <p>I shall introduce you immediately.</p>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Old Freeman.</speaker>
                  <p>Come on, then. Nay, after you&#8212;I am not an F double O L, you know.</p>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Patent.</speaker>
                  <p>Oh, sir!</p>
               </sp>
               <stage type="exit"><hi rend="italic">(Exeunt </hi>OLD FREEMAN<hi rend="italic"> and
                  </hi>PATENT). </stage>
            </div>
      <div type="scene" n="3">
               <head type="main">Act II. Scene 3.</head>
               <stage type="scene">PATENT’S <hi rend="italic">Study.</hi>
               </stage>
               <stage type="entrance"><hi rend="italic">Enter </hi>MARIA, <hi rend="italic">followed
                     by</hi> FREEMAN.</stage>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Freeman.</speaker>
                  <p>Nay, but hear me, my lovely Maria.</p>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Maria.</speaker>
                  <p>Under these circumstances, and in this place, sir, I cannot.</p>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Freeman.</speaker>
                  <p> Let love, all powerful love, plead my excuse; it was only under this disguise
                     I could have the pleasure of beholding you; it was this deception alone which
                     could afford me an opportunity of expressing how much I adore you.</p>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Maria.</speaker>
                  <p>And may not that passion which you pretend to, be assumed with your disguise,
                     and thrown off as easily.</p>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Freeman.</speaker>
                  <p>Oh, never! My hand, my heart, my life, will all prove my sincerity.</p>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Maria.</speaker>
                  <p>My heart prompts me to believe you; but, sir, I must insist upon your quitting
                     the house. Under the present circumstances, to listen to you any longer, would
                     betray in me a want of propriety, which would certainly lessen my character,
                     even in your esteem.</p>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Freeman.</speaker>
                  <p> At your commands I fly: but during my painful absence from your presence, do I
                     bear with me the consolation of possessing a portion of your esteem?</p>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Maria.</speaker>
                  <p>You have it.</p>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Freeman.</speaker>
                  <p>And, may I add, your love?</p>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Maria.</speaker>
                  <p>You are not indifferent to me.</p>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Freeman.</speaker>
                  <p>Enraptured sound! How shall I express the overflowings of my soul?</p>
               </sp>
               <stage type="business">(FREEMAN <hi rend="italic">is on one knee, kissing the hand of
                  </hi>MARIA, <hi rend="italic">when</hi> PATENT <hi rend="italic">is heard
                     approaching).</hi>
               </stage>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Patent.</speaker>
                  <stage type="mixed"><hi rend="italic">(without).</hi></stage>
                  <p>Maria!</p>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Freeman.</speaker>
                  <stage type="mixed">(Aside to MARIA, and falls upon his face.</stage>
                  <p>I am the automaton.</p>
               </sp>
               <stage type="delivery">MARIA <hi rend="italic">is greatly agitated). </hi></stage>
               <stage type="entrance"><hi rend="italic">Enter</hi> PATENT.</stage>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Patent.</speaker>
                  <p>Maria, why, what’s the matter? what’s the matter?</p>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Maria.</speaker>
                  <p>Oh, Sir! The automaton&#8212;&#8212;</p>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Patent.</speaker>
                  <p>Aye, aye&#8212;have <supplied reason="omitted-in-original">you</supplied> been
                     meddling with it.</p>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Maria.</speaker>
                  <p>It has fallen, sir.</p>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Patent.</speaker>
                  <p>Heaven grant that it may not be broken! I’ll endeavour to raise it.</p>
                  <stage type="business">
                     <hi rend="italic">(He approaches </hi>FREEMAN,<hi rend="italic"> who the moment
                        he is touched, by a seeming involuntary motion, catches hold of his leg:
                        </hi>PATENT<hi rend="italic"> with difficulty extricates
                     himself).</hi></stage>
                  <p>Mercy on us! I have touched the wrong spring.</p>
               </sp>
               <stage type="entrance"><hi rend="italic">Enter</hi> OLD FREEMAN.</stage>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>OLD FREEMAN.</speaker>
                  <p>What <supplied reason="omitted-in-original">is</supplied> the matter here? All
                     in a bustle.</p>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>PATENT.</speaker>
                  <p>A trifling accident, sir: the automaton has fallen.</p>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>OLD FREEMAN.</speaker>
                  <p>The automaton! What’s that?</p>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>PATENT.</speaker>
                  <p>There it lies, sir, the most perfect machine the world ever saw; sent as a
                     present from one of the most learned bodies and famous universities in
                     Asia.</p>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>OLD FREEMAN.</speaker>
                  <p>It is very like a man.</p>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>PATENT.</speaker>
                  <p>It has exhausted all the powers of human invention. By that, sir, you may see
                     the importance which is attached to my improvements and discoveries, when a
                     present is made to me, for which monarchs might consider me an object of
                     envy.</p>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>OLD FREEMAN.</speaker>
                  <p>Very wonderful! I could have sworn it was a man.</p>
               </sp>
               <stage type="business"><hi rend="italic">(Going forwards).</hi></stage>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Patent.</speaker>
                  <p>Nay, don’t go too near, my friend. It has so many springs in its body, that by
                     touching one of them it may do you a serious injury.</p>
               </sp>
               <pb n="204"/>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Maria.</speaker>
                  <p>For the sake of Heaven, sir, do not approach it.</p>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Patent.</speaker>
                  <p>Maria, you are pale and faint; let me conduct you to your apartment. Come, come
                     along: you’ll soon be better. Will you accompany us, sir?</p>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Old Freeman.</speaker>
                  <p>Aye, aye, I’ll follow.</p>
                  <stage type="mixed"><hi rend="italic">(Exit PATENT,</hi>
                     <hi rend="italic">leading out</hi> MARIA). </stage>
                  <p> </p>
                  <p>Wonderful machine, indeed! I wonder what this world will come to at last. </p>
                  <stage type="business"><hi rend="italic">(Looks with cautious, eager curiosity,
                        and often touches </hi>FREEMAN<hi rend="italic"> with his stick).</hi>
                  </stage>
                  <p>What! do me an injury! I’ll defy it, if it were the devil himself! if it does,
                     I’ll knock it down.<stage type="business"><hi rend="italic">(Approaches and
                           raises the head of his nephew, the stick falls from his hand, both
                           continue for some time on their knees, staring wildly with
                           astonishment).</hi></stage></p>
                  <p>What, Jack!</p>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Freeman.</speaker>
                  <p>My ever honoured uncle!</p>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Old Freeman.</speaker>
                  <p>My dear boy, let me embrace you. How are you here? What, are you turned a
                     machine? After the girl, I dare say. What has come of your great cause in
                     Yorkshire? How are you in this house? Did not think you knew it. <seg
                        corresp="#note42">Odsbuds</seg>! I am glad to see you. What brought you
                        hither?<ptr target="#note42" xml:id="nr42" n="42"/></p>
               </sp>
               <stage type="entrance"><hi rend="italic">Enter </hi>MARIA <hi rend="italic"
                     >behind.</hi></stage>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Freeman.</speaker>
                  <p>Love, sir! all&#8211;powerful love! And let me take advantage, honoured sir, of
                     this present moment, when your heart is overflowing with kindness, to request
                     your forgiveness for my disobedience to your commands. In short, sir, I can
                     never consent to the match which you have proposed to me.</p>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Old Freeman.</speaker>
                  <p>Why not? why not?</p>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Freeman.</speaker>
                  <p>Although ignorant of the merits, and even the name of the lady in question, I
                     solemnly assure you that nothing in this world shall ever induce me to give her
                     my hand, my heart being entirely devoted to another.</p>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Old Freeman.</speaker>
                  <p>Devoted to another!</p>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Freeman.</speaker>
                  <p>Yes, sir; the lovely ward of Mr. Patent concentrates in her mind and person all
                     that I wish of happiness in this world; and no power on earth can lessen the
                     passion with which she has inspired me.</p>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Old Freeman.</speaker>
                  <p>Ha! ha! ha! the very girl! Odsbuds! the very girl! Are you mad, Jack? <seg
                        corresp="#note43">Odsbuds</seg>, she’s the very girl I designed for you.</p>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Freeman.</speaker>
                  <p>Sure, it cannot be. Am I so blessed? Oh, my honoured uncle!</p>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Old Freeman.</speaker>
                  <p>Odsbuds! <seg corresp="#note43">the</seg> very girl! Old Patent and I
                     agreed&#8212;writings drawn up&#8212;licence bought&#8212;odsbuds! the very
                        girl!<ptr target="#note43" xml:id="nr43" n="43"/></p>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Maria.</speaker>
                  <stage type="business"><hi rend="italic">(coming forward).</hi></stage>
                  <p>Mr. Freeman!</p>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Freeman.</speaker>
                  <p>Oh! my Maria! dearest, sweetest partner of my happy days!</p>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Maria.</speaker>
                  <p>You have conquered, sir; I have overheard the manly avowal of your generous,
                     disinterested passion. If this hand, sir, can contribute to your felicity, take
                     it; that you have my heart, time will show.</p>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Freeman.</speaker>
                  <p>Maria! Maria! Existence will be too, too short to show how much I adore
                     you.</p>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Old Freeman.</speaker>
                  <p>My dear sweet girl! I must have a <seg corresp="#note44">buss</seg>; I’m an old
                     fellow, but I’ve a warm heart&#8212;I am so happy&#8212;Heaven bless you both!
                     but tell me, Jack, how came you hither?<ptr target="#note44" xml:id="nr44"
                        n="44"/></p>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Freeman.</speaker>
                  <p>To see and declare my passion to my dear Maria, sir, I contrived to get myself
                     introduced as one of those self&#8211;moving machines, called automatons.</p>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Old Freeman.</speaker>
                  <p>Ha! ha! ha! So you are the most perfect machine the world ever saw, sent as a
                     present from one of the most learned bodies and famous universities in
                     Asia.</p>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Freeman.</speaker>
                  <p>I am afraid I shall find it a hard task to obtain his forgiveness. My dear
                     uncle, shall we call Mr. Patent?</p>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Maria.</speaker>
                  <p>Some one has just now inquired for him.</p>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Old Freeman.</speaker>
                  <p>No, no, don’t call him! I want to rally him a little. I’ll touch him on the
                     sore side. In the mean time here is the licence, and do you two go off and get
                     tacked together by the parson immediately. I’ll stay behind and vex him a
                     little: I owe a grudge in our last dispute. </p>
               </sp>
               <pb n="205"/>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Freeman.</speaker>
                  <p>My dear uncle, let us kneel to thank you.</p>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Old Freeman.</speaker>
                  <p>No, no, no! Go&#8212;run! I’ll see that you’re safely out of doors.</p>
               </sp>
               <stage type="exit"><hi rend="italic">Exeunt</hi> OLD FREEMAN, FREEMAN, <hi
                     rend="italic">and</hi> MARIA). </stage>
            </div>
        <div type="scene" n="4">
               <head type="main">Act II. Scene 4.</head>
               <stage type="scene"><hi rend="italic">Another Apartment in </hi>PATENT’s <hi
                     rend="italic">House</hi>. </stage>
               <stage type="entrance"><hi rend="italic">Enter</hi> PATENT<hi rend="italic">,
                     followed by</hi> TOM <hi rend="italic">(drunk).</hi>
               </stage>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Patent.</speaker>
                  <p>Come along, fellow, whom do you look for here?</p>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Tom.</speaker>
                  <p>I look for my ma&#8212;ma&#8212;master, sir.</p>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Patent.</speaker>
                  <p>You have got no master here, fellow.</p>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Tom.</speaker>
                  <p>Nay, I will see my master, dead or alive; for I know if that old rascal,
                     Patent, catches him, he’ll make a <seg corresp="#note45">gypsy</seg> mummy of
                        him.<ptr target="#note45" xml:id="nr45" n="45"/></p>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Patent.</speaker>
                  <p>What do you mean, fellow?</p>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Tom.</speaker>
                  <p>Hark you, friend!&#8212;were you ever in l l l l love?</p>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Patent.</speaker>
                  <p>In love?</p>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Tom.</speaker>
                  <p>Because my master is. No offence, I hope; but as Old Patent is a bit of a fool,
                     and I and my master are, as one may say, pretty clever, we’ll have the girl in
                     spite of him.</p>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Patent.</speaker>
                  <p>What girl, sir?</p>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Tom.</speaker>
                  <p>Why, his ward, Miss Maria. You don’t know her, I find.</p>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Patent.</speaker>
                  <p>Who are you, sir? what is your master?</p>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Tom.</speaker>
                  <p>My master, sir, is a gentleman, and I am a gentleman.</p>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Patent.</speaker>
                  <p>And why do you seek your master here?</p>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Tom.</speaker>
                  <p>Because he is here. I would not have Old Patent know it, not for a glass of the
                     best liquor ever man tasted.</p>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Patent.</speaker>
                  <p>Certainly not&#8212;certainly not.</p>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Tom.</speaker>
                  <p>Because you see as how he’s a man of no judgement&#8212;a mere fool. You have
                     heard of Old Patent, haven’t you?</p>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Patent.</speaker>
                  <p>But, sirrah, what reason have you to imagine that your master is here? How
                     could he get admittance?</p>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Tom.</speaker>
                  <p>Oh! the rarest trick. I’ll tell you now, just to show you that my master and I
                     are no f&#8212;f&#8212;fools. But don’t mention it to Old Patent.</p>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Patent.</speaker>
                  <p>No! no!</p>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Tom.</speaker>
                  <p>Well, then, my master being, as one might say, devilishly in love with Patent’s
                     gi&#8212;gi&#8212;girl, what does he do but&#8212;&#8212;You know Mr. Lobby,
                     don’t you?</p>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Patent.</speaker>
                  <p>Yes! yes!</p>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Tom.</speaker>
                  <p>Well, what does my master do, but turn himself into a <seg corresp="#note46"
                        >tomtit</seg>.<ptr target="#note46" xml:id="nr46" n="46"/></p>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Patent.</speaker>
                  <p>A tomtit?</p>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Tom.</speaker>
                  <p>Yes, a tomtit. <stage type="business">
                        <hi rend="italic">(Affects the mechanical walk of the
                        automaton).</hi></stage> While Mr. Lobby, my master’s friend, you know,
                     introduces him as the most wonderful machine in all Asia.</p>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Patent.</speaker>
                  <p>Sirrah, what is your master’s name?</p>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Tom.</speaker>
                  <p>I beg your pardon there, sir. Would you have me betray my master’s secrets?</p>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Patent.</speaker>
                  <p>Fire and fury! tell me your master’s name this moment.</p>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Tom.</speaker>
                  <p>Softly, my good friend, softly; would you have me betray my master’s secrets? I
                     am none of your blabbing servants, that tell all they know. I have more
                     prudence.</p>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Patent.</speaker>
                  <p>Get out of the house this instant, rascal! out of the house!</p>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Tom.</speaker>
                  <p>What? what? what?</p>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Patent.</speaker>
                  <p>Out of the house, you scoundrel! <stage type="business"><hi rend="italic"
                           >(Pushes him out of doors).</hi>
                     </stage>Ruined! undone! I shall be ridiculed, despised. I have nothing to do
                     now, when I know the trick which has been practised upon me, but to ascribe the
                     merit of the discovery to my own penetration. Who could have thought of it? but
                        <supplied reason="omitted-in-original">I</supplied> shall be amply revenged
                     on the scoundrel. </p>
               </sp>
               <stage type="business"><hi rend="italic">[Exit</hi> PATENT.</stage>
               <pb n="206"/>
            </div>
        <div type="scene" n="5">
               <head type="main">Act II. Scene 5.</head>
               <stage type="scene">PATENT’s <hi rend="italic">Study.</hi></stage>
               <stage type="business">
                  <hi rend="italic"> Enter </hi>OLD FREEMAN. </stage>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Old Freeman.</speaker>
                  <p>Well, I hope that by this time the young couple have got nearly tacked
                     together. Ha! ha! ha! It was a good trick&#8212;&#8212;but hush, I think I hear
                     Patent on the staircase. I shall be the machine.</p>
               </sp>
               <stage type="business"><hi rend="italic">(Puts on the mask and domino, and stands
                     erect).</hi>
               </stage>
              
                  <stage type="entrance"><hi rend="italic">Enter </hi>OLD PATENT.</stage>
                  
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>Patent.</speaker>
                  <p>Come, come, you scoundrel! It was in vain you thought to impose upon me! <stage
                        type="business"><hi rend="italic">(Tears off the mask and domino, and stares
                           with astonishment when he beholds the face and figure of</hi> OLD
                        FREEMAN).</stage> What! How is this? My friend Freeman! I beg your pardon. I
                     took you for the automaton.</p>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Old Freeman.</speaker>
                  <p>Curse on your mistakes! you have almost blinded me. What though I had been the
                     automaton?</p>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Patent.</speaker>
                  <p>Because it is a rascal.</p>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Old Freeman.</speaker>
                  <p>So I thought; for I saw him run down the street with your ward, Maria, under
                     his arm.</p>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Patent.</speaker>
                  <p>Death and fury!</p>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Old Freeman.</speaker>
                  <p> Nay, ’tis perhaps some of his mechanical tricks; there’s no accounting for
                     what he does, you know; he’s <supplied reason="omitted-in-original"
                        >got</supplied> so many secret springs in his body. </p>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Patent.</speaker>
                  <p>How shall I pursue them? Which way shall I fly?</p>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Old Freeman.</speaker>
                  <p>To be sure ’tis a great loss, as it was one of the most wonderful machines in
                     the world, sent as a present from one of the most learned bodies in Asia.</p>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Patent.</speaker>
                  <p>Where are my <seg corresp="#note47">newly&#8211;invented</seg> pistols!<ptr
                        target="#note47" xml:id="nr47" n="47"/></p>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Old Freeman.</speaker>
                  <p>Nay, you must not stir yet; I want to talk with you a little. That cursed
                     automaton might do you a mischief.</p>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Patent.</speaker>
                  <p>Don’t stop me. I will be revenged.</p>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Old Freeman.</speaker>
                  <p>You are an F double O L, and ought not to be moved at anything.</p>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Patent.</speaker>
                  <p>Sir! sir! Do you mean to affront me? </p>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Old Freeman.</speaker>
                  <p>“Impudent, indeed, would be the man who should entertain such an idea. No, sir,
                     science has made you more than usually circumspect, and appearances are
                     regarded by you with a scrutinizing eye.”</p>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Patent.</speaker>
                  <p>Know, sir, that I have an arm to chastise this insolence.</p>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Old Freeman.</speaker>
                  <p>And to show us the value that is attached to men of science, you yourself have
                     attracted the notice of the most learned bodies in all Asia, and have now the
                     honour adding F double O L to your name.</p>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Old Freeman.</speaker>
                  <p>Insolence! villain!</p>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Old Freeman.</speaker>
                  <p>Nay, do moderate your anger, my good old friend. You know we used to banter one
                     another at school, and I can’t help being a little fond of it yet.</p>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Patent.</speaker>
                  <p>But to use me so&#8212;to rejoice that a <seg corresp="#note48">villain</seg> for a moment
                     deceived me.</p>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Old Freeman.</speaker>
                  <p>The best of us all may be deceived: you know the philosopher, what do you call
                     him, that thought the sun went round instead of the earth, he was deceived.</p>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Patent.</speaker>
                  <p>True, true; Ptolemy; very true.</p>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Old Freeman.</speaker>
                  <p> And I dare say many more, which your extensive reading must have made you
                     acquainted with.</p>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Patent.</speaker>
                  <p>A great many: and all very great men, too.</p>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Old Freeman.</speaker>
                  <p>Besides, you may be perfectly easy about your ward, Maria; for if she marries
                     without your consent, she forfeits all her fortune: now you have given your
                     written consent to nobody but my nephew.</p>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Patent.</speaker>
                  <p>True, true; she’s under age.</p>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Old Freeman.</speaker>
                  <p>Now, my friend, I hope everything will go on well. Forgive my bantering of
                     you.</p>
               </sp>
               <stage type="mixed"><hi rend="italic"> </hi>Enter FREEMAN <hi rend="italic">and</hi>
                     MARIA&#8212;<hi rend="italic"> they kneel. </hi>PATENT<hi rend="italic"> rushes
                     forward to seize</hi> FREEMAN. </stage>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Patent.</speaker>
                  <p>Villain! scoundrel!</p>
               </sp>
               <stage type="business">(OLD FREEMAN <hi rend="italic">throws himself between
                     them).</hi></stage>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Old Freeman.</speaker>
                  <p>Stop! That, sir, is my nephew.</p>
               </sp>
               <pb n="207"/>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Patent.</speaker>
                  <p>Your nephew?</p>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Old Freeman.</speaker>
                  <p>Yes, yes, my nephew. The automaton is no other than Jack Freeman, my
                     nephew.</p>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Patent.</speaker>
                  <p>Can I believe it?</p>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Old Freeman.</speaker>
                  <p>You have been deceived in taking him for an automaton; but he has also deceived
                     himself; for he has taken all this trouble to come at the girl we were
                     persuading him to have. The laugh goes against him, eh, old boy?</p>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Patent.</speaker>
                  <p>I think it does.</p>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Freeman.</speaker>
                  <p>Nothing but my very ardent passion for Maria could have induced me to attempt
                     an imposition on you, sir. I imagined my uncle had destined me for the arms of
                     another, and despair suggested me to means which I own it was in some degree
                     criminal to employ.</p>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Maria.</speaker>
                  <p>Let us solicit your pardon, sir, and blessing.</p>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Patent.</speaker>
                  <p>You have it, you have it. I am so happy. Are you already married?</p>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Young Freeman.</speaker>
                  <p>That sacred rite, sir, is already performed.</p>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Old Freeman.</speaker>
                  <p>Then, my good old boy, we have nothing to do but to feast and be merry. <seg
                        corresp="#note49">Adzooks</seg>! We shall have rare carousing! I have a
                     strong inclination to dance. We must have a dozen or two of fiddlers. Odsbuds!
                     I can hardly keep my legs.<ptr target="#note49" xml:id="nr49" n="49"/></p>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Patent.</speaker>
                  <p> I shall bring my new invented <seg corresp="#note50"
                        >hurdy&#8211;gurdy</seg>.<ptr target="#note50" xml:id="nr50" n="50"/></p>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Old Freeman.</speaker>
                  <p>Do so, man; anything that will make a noise.</p>
               </sp>
               <stage type="entrance"><hi rend="italic">Enter </hi>ALICE.</stage>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Alice.</speaker>
                  <p>Sir, Doctor Snuffy Macrosky desires to speak with you.</p>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Freeman.</speaker>
                  <p>My friend, Mr. Lobby.</p>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Patent.</speaker>
                  <p>Alice, your young mistress is now married. You must provide everything to
                     solemnize the wedding.</p>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Alice.</speaker>
                  <p>Well, sir, I wish my young mistress joy: but I’m mistaken if there won’t be
                     more weddings than one, soon.</p>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Freeman.</speaker>
                  <p>Mrs. Alice, if you please, show the doctor up.</p>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Alice.</speaker>
                  <p>Doctor! My dear Mr. Snuffy Macrosky.</p>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Old Freeman.</speaker>
                  <p>Very kind and familiar.</p>
               </sp>
               <stage type="mixed">(Enter DICK LOBBY in his former disguise. He starts on seeing the
                  company). </stage>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Freeman</speaker>
                  <p>Nay, do not be surprised, Dick: my happiness is complete. Avow yourself my
                     friend. That disguise is no longer necessary.</p>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Dick.</speaker>
                  <stage type="business">(throwing off his beard and cloak). </stage>
                  <p>I can hardly believe it. What, with the consent of your honoured uncle and the
                     learned Mr. Patent.</p>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Old Freeman.</speaker>
                  <p>With our entire approbation, sir.</p>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Dick.</speaker>
                  <p>Jack, give me your hand, and your’s, my lovely creature; for surely if love my
                     be termed a folly, it is in this instance an excusable one. I am a man of few
                     compliments. I shall only say, that if you possess a thousandth part of the
                     felicity I wish you both, you will be the happiest of human beings.</p>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Old Freeman.</speaker>
                  <p>A very good compliment, indeed; give me your hand, my boy. Odsbuds; we’ll have
                     a bottle to&#8211;night.</p>
               </sp>
               <stage type="business">(ALICE <hi rend="italic">begins to cry).</hi></stage>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Patent.</speaker>
                  <p>Alice! Alice! what’s the matter?</p>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Alice.</speaker>
                  <p>Oh, my poor heart! That gentleman won my affections, and I fear will now prove
                     treacherous and inconstant.</p>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Dick.</speaker>
                  <p>Alice, Dr. Rodoska, who made love to you, is no more. Any other reparation
                     which it is in my power to make&#8212;&#8212;&#8212;</p>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Alice.</speaker>
                  <p>Hold your false, deluding tongue, that first won my tender heart. I shall
                     forswear your whole sex forever&#8212;that I will, Oh! my poor heart!</p>
               </sp>
               <stage type="mixed"><hi rend="italic">(Exit, crying)</hi>.</stage>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Patent.</speaker>
                  <p>Poor thing! she has been deceived, too, I think; but as I am soon to lose the
                     company of Maria, a project darts into my mind of taking her myself.</p>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Old Freeman.</speaker>
                  <p>Very humane and very <seg corresp="#note51">philosophic</seg>.<ptr
                        target="#note51" xml:id="nr51" n="51"/></p>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Dick.</speaker>
                  <p>I am sorry for my behaviour to her; but it was necessary for the success of my
                     friend. The first person, however, whose pardon I ought to solicit, is Mr.
                     Patent. May I hope, sir&#8212;&#8212;&#8212;</p>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Patent.</speaker>
                  <p>You have it&#8212;you have it.</p>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Old Freeman.</speaker>
                  <p>Come, now for the merry&#8211;making.</p>
               </sp>
               <stage type="scene">[The End.]</stage>
            </div></div>
        
     </body>
<back>
   <div type="notes">

      <note xml:id="note1"><hi rend="italic">Freeman</hi>: Acording to the <hi rend="italic">Oxford
                  English Dictionary (OED)</hi>, September 2016, Oxford University Press (accessed
               November 11, 2016), a Romantic-era “freeman” was a member of England’s elite class of
               political participation, possessing the right to vote in elections for Minister of
               Parliament. More broadly, a “freeman” is a man who is not enslaved; who is relatively
               autonomous. The first connotation applies to young Jack Freeman, but the play’s
               denouement casts doubt upon the second. <hi rend="italic">Lobby</hi>: This name
               references the character’s propensity to “lobby” his friend Freeman and nemesis
               Patent. <hi rend="italic">Clinker</hi>: perhaps a reference to the clinking of
               glasses, as Tom Clinker is an alcoholic and prefers to drink in public-houses.</note>
      
      
      
      <note xml:id="note2"><hi rend="italic">Temple</hi>: The nerve center of London’s legal
         profession since the mid&#8211;fourteenth century, named for the Knights Templar, whose two
         Temples on the sight became Inns of Court. An article on the Inns of Court appeared
         in the <hi rend="italic">Queen’s Magazine</hi>, attributed, in a manuscript
         annotation in the UNC copy, to one “Charles Wellsley.” This may be a pseudonym, as no
         person of that name exists in the 1841 United Kingdom Census. Notably,<hi
            rend="italic">The String of Pearls</hi> is set in the vicinity of the
         Temple.</note>
      
      
      
      <note xml:id="note3"><hi rend="italic">Lord Chancellor</hi>: Appointed head of the British judiciary and speaker of the House of Lords. These roles were abolished in 2006, though the titular office remains <hi rend="italic">(Britannica)</hi>.</note>
      
      
      <note xml:id="note4"><hi rend="italic">charmer</hi>: beauty <hi rend="italic">(OED)</hi>.</note>
      
      
      <note xml:id="note5"><hi rend="italic">Ecod</hi>: from the expletive “a god,” “o,
         god,” or “egad” <hi rend="italic">(OED)</hi>.</note>
      
      
      <note xml:id="note6"><hi rend="italic">Opera</hi>: The Royal Italian Opera House at Covent
               Garden. Jane Rendell, <hi rend="italic">Pursuit of Pleasure: Gender, Space and
                  Architecture in Regency London</hi> London: Athlone, 2004, observes that the
               Regency Opera was “a place designed to enhance the pleasure of looking (104)” where
               overcrowding at the entrances “provided opportunities for intimate contact between
               strangers of different sexes and classes.” In 1815, the entrance to the boxes was
               widened to give patrons “less of a chance to mingle” (112). A key setting in James
               Malcolm Rymer’s <hi rend="italic">The Dark Woman, or, the Days of the Prince
                  Regent</hi> (London: John Dicks, 1862), in which it is depicted as a place of
               luxurious sexual spectacle for the demonized Prince Regent.</note>
      
      
      
      <note xml:id="note7"><hi rend="italic">ain’t</hi>: in the source text, “’ant” (typographical
               error).</note>
         
      <note xml:id="note8"><hi rend="italic">axes</hi>: According to the <hi rend="italic">OED</hi>,
               this synonym of “axles” is “not found after the Old English period ex[cepting] in
               compounds,” but a cursory search of Romantic-era texts disproves this. One of many
               examples appears in <hi rend="italic">Cyclopaedia, or, University Dictionary of Arts,
                  Sciences, and Literature</hi>, ed. Abraham Rees (39 vols, London: Longman, 1819).
               This encyclopaedia makes several mentions of “wheels and axes” (no page number,
               listed alphabetically under “AXI”). Babbage’s calculating engines’ most prominent
               features were their multitudes of “wheels” and “axes,” as Lardner explains in his
               1834 article. See Introduction.</note>


      <note xml:id="note9"><hi rend="italic">Club</hi>: probably one of the four exclusive
               gentlemen’s clubs in St. James’ Street: Boodle’s, Brooks’s, White’s and Crockford’s.
               These gendered spaces combined exclusively masculine conviviality with
               quasi&#8211;domestic comforts (Rendell, p. 64). Lobby’s paradigmatic opposition of
               the “Club” with the institution of marriage illustrates this point.</note>
      
      
      <note xml:id="note10"><hi rend="italic">phiz</hi>: physiognomy; face (<hi rend="italic"
                  >OED</hi>); <hi rend="italic">uncle [...] married</hi>: if Freeman’s uncle marries
               and has children, Freeman may be disinherited in favor of this uncle’s son.</note>
      
      <note xml:id="note11"><hi rend="italic">mistress’s</hi>: in the source, “mistresses”
               (typographical error).</note>
      
         <note xml:id="note12"><hi rend="italic">unnecessary almost</hi>: in the source, “almost
               unnecessary almost” (typographical error). Were the authorial intention instead
               “render almost unnecessary,” the automata would not make an entire vocation redundant
               in the manner of the other examples.</note>
            
      <note xml:id="note13"><hi rend="italic">intended for</hi>: in the source, “intended to”
               (typographical error).</note>
      
            <note xml:id="note14"><hi rend="italic">Portsmouth</hi>:
         coastal city in Hampshire, southern England; historic home of the
         Royal Fleet and, since 1733, the Naval Academy. (Jack) <hi rend="italic">tars</hi>: sailors,
         implicitly English. The hearty, good&#8211;natured, rough “Jack Tar” was a staple
         of nineteenth&#8211;century melodrama and frequently appears in James Malcolm
         Rymer’s works. An indicative example is <hi rend="italic">Varney, the Vampyre, or
            the Feast of Blood</hi> (1847), which features a tar named Jack Pringle.</note>
      
      
      <note xml:id="note15"><hi rend="italic">club</hi>: Club (typographical error).</note>
      
      <note xml:id="note16"><hi rend="italic">turn</hi>: in the source, “turns” (typographical
               error).</note>
        
      <note xml:id="note17"><hi rend="italic">flour mill [...] musical clock</hi>: The steam-powered
               Albion Flour Mills, which operated in Battersea, London, from 1786-91, exemplified
               for the Romantic generation the mechanization of the bread industry. See, for
               example, John Farey, <hi rend="italic">A Treatise on the Steam Engine: Historical,
                  Practical, and Descriptive</hi> (London: Longman, Rees, Orme, Brown, and Green,
               1827), 443: “The Albion Mills were said to be the means of the sensibly reducing the
               price of flour in the metropolis, whilst they continued at work, for they occasioned
               a greater competition amongst the millers and meal-men than had ever existed before;
               but nevertheless great prejudices were excited against the company amongst the lower
               class of people, to whom it was represented as a monopoly highly injurious to the
               public. These mills were destroyed by fire in 1791 [...] and it has been suspected
               that it was not occasioned by accident; the satisfaction of the populace was
               afterwards expressed by songs in the streets of London.” Late eighteenth-century
               London clockmakers provided China’s Qianlong Emperor (d. 1799) with elaborate
               “musical clocks” and other automata. See Introduction. <note xml:id="note18"><hi
                     rend="italic">minerology</hi>: conventionally spelled “mineralogy.”
                  </note><note xml:id="note19"><hi rend="italic">twenty husbands</hi>: an
                  identically desperate, vicious “old maid,” the Honorable Miss Flint, provides
                  comic relief in James Malcolm Rymer’s penny blood <hi rend="italic">The Sepoys,
                     or, Highland Jessie: A Tale of the Present Indian Revolt</hi>, which was
                  serialized in <hi rend="italic">Reynolds’s Miscellany</hi> in 1858.</note><note
                  xml:id="note20"><hi rend="italic">windmill notions</hi>: enotes both (1) ideas
                  about windmills and (2) fantasies reminiscent of <hi rend="italic">Don
                     Quixote</hi> (1605), in which the eponymous hero on his aimless quest mistakes
                  windmills for giants.</note><note xml:id="note21"><hi rend="italic"> made
                     love</hi>: expressed love <hi rend="italic">(OED)</hi>.</note><note
                  xml:id="note22"><hi rend="italic">Bond Street</hi>: ssociated with luxury;
                  connects Oxford Street, with its famous retail district, with the gentlemen’s
                  playground of Picadilly.</note><note xml:id="note23"><hi rend="italic">luck</hi>:
                  in the source, “lack” (typographical error).</note><note xml:id="note24"><hi
                     rend="italic">dangling</hi>: “To hang after or about any one, especially as a
                  loosely attached follower; to follow in a dallying way, without being a formally
                  recognized attendant” </note><note xml:id="note25"><hi rend="italic">are</hi>: in
                  he source, “is” (typopgraphical error).</note><note xml:id="note26"><hi
                     rend="italic">excels</hi>: exceeds <hi rend="italic">(OED)</hi>.</note><note
                  xml:id="note27"><hi rend="italic">barber’s shop</hi>: In <hi rend="italic">The
                     String of Pearls</hi> (1847) the character Thornhill fatally chooses to visit a
                  barber shop before visiting a lady.</note><note xml:id="note28"><hi rend="italic"
                     >powers of gravity</hi>: Lobby resolves not to laugh, making a pun on the
                  scientific term “gravity.”</note><note xml:id="note30"><hi rend="italic"
                     >domino</hi>: “A kind of loose cloak, app[arently] of Venetian origin, chiefly
                  worn at masquerades, with a small mask covering the upper part of the face” <hi
                     rend="italic">(OED)</hi>.</note><note xml:id="note31"><hi rend="italic"
                     >Kensington [...] Monument</hi>: <hi rend="italic">Kensington Gardens ...
                     Blackfriars</hi>: Moving Kensington Gardens to Spitalfields would be an act of
                  great social justice, as Kensington is a wealthy area, home to Kensington Palace,
                  while Spitalfields is a working&#8211;class neighbourhood, famous for its
                  journeyman silk weavers, who in 1763, broke machinery intended to replace their
                  labor, anticipating the Chartists. The Monument to the Great Fire, completed in
                  1677, offers panoramic views of London, which would be even more scenic from the
                  middle of the River Thames. Blackfriars Bridge connects the Inns of Court and
                  Temple with the South Bank. Its obstruction by the Monument would inconvenience
                  the lawyers of the Temple.</note><note xml:id="note32"><hi rend="italic">Mogul
                     Tartary</hi>: The “warlike and formidable nation” of Chingghis Khan (“Genghis
                  Khan”), occupying northeastern fourteenth&#8211;century China. William
                  Winterbottom, <hi rend="italic">An Historical, Geographical, and Philosophical
                     View of the Chinese Empire.</hi> London: J. Ridgeway, 1795 (118).</note><note
                  xml:id="note33"><hi rend="italic">cute</hi>: in the 1840s, clever; derived from
                  “acute” <hi rend="italic">(OED)</hi>.</note><note xml:id="note34"><hi
                     rend="italic">cause</hi>: case; <hi rend="italic">depending in Yorkshire</hi>:
                  pending in Yorkshire, a county in the North of England. The Great North Road
                  connects Yorkshire’s main city, York, with London.</note><note xml:id="note35"><hi
                     rend="italic">Bagnigge Wells</hi>: <hi rend="italic">Bagnigge Wells</hi>: North
                  London day resort; a garden with tea rooms. According to Geoffrey Dart, <hi
                     rend="italic">Metropolitan Art and Literature, 1810&#8211;1840: Cockney
                     Adventures,</hi> Cambridge: Cambridge University Press, 2012, Bagnigge Wells’s
                  clientele became increasingly working&#8211;class (34&#8211;5). In the nineteenth
                  century. By 1820, the “tea garden” at Bagnigge Wells was “decidedly Cockneyfied,”
                  wrote Warwick Wroth, <hi rend="italic">The London Pleasure&#8211;Gardens of the
                     Eighteenth Century,</hi> (London: Macmillan, 1896), 7, quoted in Gregory Dart,
                     <hi rend="italic">Metropolitan Art and Literature 1810-1840: Cockney
                     Adventures</hi> (Cambridge: Cambridge University Press, 2012), 34.</note><note
                  xml:id="note36"><hi rend="italic">Court of Queen’s Bench</hi>: There was no such
                  court in 1820, as the monarch was a king, but there was in 1842, during Victoria’s
                  reign. Apparently, James Malcolm Rymer edited his father’s manuscript to make it
                  contemporary. This line therefore demonstrates that the script was not printed
                  exactly as originally composed.</note><note xml:id="note37"><hi rend="italic"
                     >nonsuited</hi>: The lawsuit is curtailed and the tailor is “thwarted” or
                  “frustrated.” Both definitions were current <hi rend="italic">(OED)</hi>. This
                  resolution of the case leaves the tailor dehumanized and without justice against
                  his socio&#8211;economic superior.</note><note xml:id="note38"><hi rend="italic"
                     >wit</hi>: in the source, “with” (typographical error); <hi rend="italic"
                     >Suffolk</hi>: A county in East Anglia, to the northeast of London.</note><note
                  xml:id="note39"><hi rend="italic">any</hi>: in the source, “any any”
                  (typographical error).</note><note xml:id="note40"><hi rend="italic">rural
                     lay</hi>: Pastoral song; idyll.</note><note xml:id="note41"><hi rend="italic"
                     >kickshaw</hi>: Fancy, dubious French or other foreign food or fad <hi
                     rend="italic">(OED)</hi>.</note><note xml:id="note42"><hi rend="italic"
                     >odsbuds</hi>: God’s blood <hi rend="italic">(OED)</hi>.</note><note
                  xml:id="note43"><hi rend="italic">the</hi>: originally, “she” (typographical
                  error).</note><note xml:id="note44"><hi rend="italic">buss</hi>: kiss <hi
                     rend="italic">(OED)</hi>.</note><note xml:id="note45"><hi rend="italic"
                     >gypsy</hi>: in this context, ancient Egyptian.</note><note xml:id="note46"><hi
                     rend="italic">tomtit</hi>: “common name of the Blue Titmouse (Parus cæruleus),”
                  or, incorrectly, other “small birds,” used colloquially to (de)mean a “little man
                  or boy” <hi rend="italic">(OED)</hi>.</note><note xml:id="note47"><hi
                     rend="italic">newly-invented</hi>:A popular advertising term indicating a
                  wondrous invention. See, for instance, the reference to a “newly-invented light”
                  in “Substitute for the Sun,” <hi rend="italic">The Champion</hi> 33 (December 23,
                  1838): 6, and <hi rend="italic">Coulson’s Treatise on his Newly-Invented
                     Engineers’ and Mechanics’ Slide Rule</hi> (Stokesley: W. Braithwate,
                  1842).</note><note xml:id="note48"><hi rend="italic">villain</hi>: in the source,
                  “villian” (typographical error).</note><note xml:id="note49"><hi rend="italic"
                     >Adzooks</hi>: “gadzooks,” or God’s hooks: the nails from the Crucifixion <hi
                     rend="italic">(OED)</hi>.</note><note xml:id="note50"><hi rend="italic"
                     >hurdy-gurdy</hi>: “wheel&#8211;fiddle.” A Welsh traditional string instrument.
                  Its major features are a wheel and a crank. It is therefore the instrument that
                  the wheel&#8211;obsessed Patent might be most likely to construct and
                  play.</note><note xml:id="note51"><hi rend="italic">philosophic</hi>: here, not
                  scientific, but Stoic, because marriage to Alice must involve suffering.</note>
            </note>
      </div>
  </back>
  </text>
</TEI>
