<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
    <teiHeader xml:lang="eng">
        <fileDesc>
            <titleStmt>
                <title level="m" type="main">A Digital Edition of Christopher Pearse Cranch's
                    'Journal. 1839.'</title>
                <author>Christopher M. Ohge</author>
                <respStmt>
                    <resp>Creation and encoding</resp>
                    <name xml:id="cmo">Christopher M. Ohge</name>
                </respStmt>
            </titleStmt>
            <editionStmt>
                <edition>
                    <date>2014</date>
                </edition>
            </editionStmt>
            <publicationStmt>
                <idno type="file">intro.cranchjournal</idno>
                <idno type="edition">cranchjournal</idno>
                <authority>Scholarly Editing: The Annual of the Association for Documentary
                    Editing</authority>
                <address>
                    <addrLine>http://www.scholarlyediting.org</addrLine>
                </address>
                <publisher>Association for Documentary Editing</publisher>
                <publisher>University of Nebraska&#8211;Lincoln</publisher>
                <distributor>
                    <name>Center for Digital Research in the Humanities</name>
                    <address>
                        <addrLine>319 Love Library</addrLine>
                        <addrLine>University of Nebraska&#8211;Lincoln</addrLine>
                        <addrLine>Lincoln, NE 68588-4100</addrLine>
                        <addrLine>http://cdrh.unl.edu</addrLine>
                    </address>
                </distributor>
                <date>2014</date>
                <availability>
                    <p>Scholarly Editing: The Annual of the Association for Documentary Editing is
                        freely distributed by the Association for Documentary Editing and the Center
                        for Digital Research in the Humanities at the University of Nebraska-Lincoln
                        and licensed under a Creative Commons Attribution-NonCommercial-ShareAlike
                        3.0 Unported License</p>
                </availability>
            </publicationStmt>
            <seriesStmt>
                <title level="j">Scholarly Editing: The Annual of the Association for Documentary
                    Editing</title>
                <respStmt>
                    <resp>editor</resp>
                    <name xml:id="ag">Amanda Gailey</name>
                </respStmt>
                <respStmt>
                    <resp>editor</resp>
                    <name xml:id="awj">Andrew Jewell</name>
                </respStmt>
                <idno type="vol">35</idno>
                <idno type="ISSN">2167-1257</idno>
            </seriesStmt>
            <sourceDesc>
                <bibl>
                    <note>Born digital.</note>
                </bibl>
            </sourceDesc>
        </fileDesc>
        <revisionDesc>
            <change who="#cmo">Initial creation</change>
        </revisionDesc>
    </teiHeader>
    <text>
        <front>
            <head type="main">"Lest we get too transcendental": Christopher Pearse Cranch's Changes
                of Mind in "Journal. 1839."</head>
            <byline>Christopher M. Ohge</byline>
        </front>
        <body>
            <div>
                <epigraph>
                    <lg type="poem">
                        <l>If death be final, what is life, with all</l>
                        <l>Its lavish promises, its thwarted aims,</l>
                        <l>Its lost ideals, its dishonored claims,</l>
                        <l>Its uncompleted growth? A prison wall,</l>
                        <l>Whose heartless stones but echo back our call;</l>
                        <l>An epitaph recording but our names;</l>
                        <l>A puppet-stage where joys and griefs and shames</l>
                        <l>Furnish a demon jester’s carnival;</l>
                        <l>A plan without a purpose or a form;</l>
                        <l>A roofless temple; an unfinished tale.</l>
                        <l>And men like madrepores through calm and storm</l>
                        <l>Toil, die to build a branch of fossil frail,</l>
                        <l>And add from all their dreams, thoughts, acts, belief,</l>
                        <l>A few more inches to a coral-reef.</l>
                    </lg>
                    <bibl>Christopher Pearse Cranch, "Sonnet XXXL: Life and Death"<note
                            type="editorial" resp="#cmo"><hi rend="italic">Ariel and Caliban, With
                                Other Poems</hi> (Cambridge: Houghton Mifflin, 1887),
                        162.</note></bibl>
                </epigraph>
                <p>A casual reader of this sonnet might suspect Christopher Pearse Cranch
                    (1813&#8211;1892) was a dark romantic, yet he was a transcendentalist with
                    unique versatility, a man seemingly engrossed in second thoughts. He was
                    humorous, playful, and uncommitted, yet earnest and philosophically resourceful;
                    a rugged individualist in the Emersonian spirit, yet (as Coleridge said of
                    Spenser) "a mind constitutionally tender, delicate," exhibiting a "melancholy
                    grace" in much of his writings.<note type="editorial" resp="#cmo">Chapter 2 of
                            <hi rend="italic">Biographia Literaria: The Collected Works of Samuel
                            Taylor Coleridge</hi>, ed. Walter Jackson Bate et al. (Princeton:
                        Princeton University Press, 1985), 7:36.</note> It was in Cranch’s 1839
                    "Journal" that he meticulously recorded his changes of mind in a watershed
                    moment in his life: not yet a transcendentalist, he was about to quit the
                    Unitarian Church, befriend his idol Emerson, and make a life for himself as a
                    visual artist. His "Journal" clearly illustrates his intellectual development
                    alongside the progress of transcendentalism when both were in flux.</p>
                <div>
                    <milestone unit="undeclared" rend="asterisks"/>
                    <p>Cranch is an intriguing figure who warrants further scholarly attention, not
                        merely for his status as an instrumental transcendentalist but also for his
                        commendable artistic failures. As a relative to the storied Adamses,
                        Greenleafs, and Eliots (and a great-uncle to T. S. Eliot), a close friend to
                        Emerson, James Russell Lowell, the Brownings, and Margaret Fuller, one of
                        the very few transcendentalists Edgar Allan Poe praised,<note
                            type="editorial" resp="#cmo">In the 1846 issue of <hi rend="italic"
                                >Godey’s</hi>, Poe called Cranch "the least intolerable of the
                            school of Boston transcendentalists&#8212;and, in fact, I believe that
                            he has at last ‘come out from among them,’ abandoned their doctrines
                            (whatever they are) and given up their company in disgust. [He] seems to
                            me to possess unusual vivacity of fancy and dexterity of expression,
                            while his versification is remarkable for its accuracy, vigor, and even
                            for its originality of effect."</note> and the artist responsible for
                        the famous parody of Emerson’s "transparent eye-ball" passage in <hi
                            rend="italic">Nature</hi>, Cranch has faded into near-obscurity.<note
                            type="editorial" resp="#cmo">Cranch’s obscurity may be the result of
                            articles such as J. C. Levinson’s "Christopher Pearse Cranch: The Case
                            History of a Minor Artist in America," <hi rend="italic">American
                                Literature</hi> 21, no. 4 (January 1950): 415&#8211;26.</note> But
                        the wit and accessibility of his caricatures of New England
                        transcendentalism eventually helped make what was then a fairly
                        self-enclosed regional movement into a nationally identifiable aesthetic.
                        Cranch’s characteristically transcendental expressions on the divinity of
                        nature, juxtaposed with darker musings on the limits of human understanding,
                        distinguishes him among a transcendentalist cohort that continues to be
                        understood largely in terms of its unmitigated optimism.</p>
                    <p>Like Fuller, Cranch was one of the few transcendentalists to leave New
                        England for substantial periods of time. While he saw the Boston area as an
                        intellectual haven&#8212;"that little world, that vortex of life, that spot
                        of all others in the country where life in all its various aspects is so
                        concentrated and distilled"<note type="editorial" resp="#cmo">From an April
                            11, 1842, letter to Miss Julia Myers. Quoted in Lenora Cranch Scott, <hi
                                rend="italic">The Life and Letters of Christopher Pearse
                                Cranch</hi> (Boston: Houghton Mifflin, 1917), 77.</note>&#8212;he
                        often escaped it, traveling to the midwestern United States in the late
                        1830s as well as Europe in 1846–49, 1853–63, and 1880–82. His 1839 "Journal"
                        mostly documents the end of his travels to the new frontiers of Kentucky and
                        Ohio, as he trained to be a Unitarian minister while seeking "Independence
                        of mind and of conduct. To be myself&#8212;and not another&#8212;to be
                        natural and free."<note type="editorial" resp="#cmo">"Journal. 1839," 7. For
                            a biographical introduction to the "Journal," see Francis B. Dedmond,
                            "Christopher Pearse Cranch's ‘Journal. 1839,’" in <hi rend="italic"
                                >Studies in the American Renaissance 1983</hi>, ed. Joel Myerson
                            (Charlottesville: University Press of Virginia, 1983), 129–35.</note> He
                        attended the Semi-Colon discussion groups, frequented the literary salon of
                        George Keats (and was an early appreciator of his brother John), and spent
                        substantial periods of time with James Freeman Clarke and John Sullivan
                        Dwight. At the end of the "Journal" he records his return to the East Coast,
                        trying yet again to find a better sense of purpose and career direction.
                        Never ordained as a minister, Cranch instead traveled widely, was published
                        in early issues of the <hi rend="italic">Dial</hi>, continued to write in
                        commonplace and sketch books, and spent the rest of his life painting in the
                        manner of the Hudson River school and occasionally writing poetry and
                        children’s literature. Throughout his life he endeavored to capture the
                        material facts from which Emerson’s philosophy sprang, sometimes
                        demonstrating Emerson’s thought more clearly in one drawing or painting than
                        Emerson himself did in paragraphs. Yet he also defied exclusive association
                        with any identifiable profession or artistic convention: he was, in the
                        estimation of Van Wyck Brooks, "a man who had taken Emerson at his word and
                        planted himself on his instincts, wherever they led him."<note
                            type="editorial" resp="#cmo">See Hazen C. Carpenter, "Emerson and
                            Christopher Pearse Cranch," <hi rend="italic">New England Quarterly</hi>
                            37 (March 1964): 18–42; Van Wyck Brooks, <hi rend="italic">The Flowering
                                of New England, 1815&#8211;1865</hi> (New York: Modern Library, 1941),
                            258.</note> Cranch settled in Cambridge, Massachusetts, in 1873, and
                        died in 1892 a minor transcendentalist in an era of realism. Herman
                        Melville, who died only a year before Cranch, had written a poem toward the
                        end of his life implying the plight of creating unappreciated art&#8212; <lg
                            type="poem">
                            <l>Craftsmen, in dateless quarries dim,</l>
                            <l>Stones formless into form did trim,</l>
                            <l>Usurped on Nature’s self with Art,</l>
                            <l>And bade this dumb I AM to start,</l>
                            <l>Imposing Him.<note type="editorial" resp="cmo">"The Great Pyramid,"
                                        <hi rend="italic">Published Poems: The Writings of Herman
                                        Melville</hi>, ed. Robert C. Ryan et al (Chicago and
                                    Evanston: The Newberry Library and Northwestern University
                                    Press, 2002), 11:316. I am also reminded of Cranch when reading
                                    Melville’s ironic opening lines to "The Fiddler": "So my poem is
                                    damned, and immortal fame is not for me! I am nobody forever and
                                    ever. Intolerable fate!" In various aspects Cranch also
                                    resembles Jones Very (1813&#8211;1880): they were both
                                    spiritually attuned poets, good friends with leading
                                    Transcendentalists (including Emerson), devoted to the
                                    cultivation of the intellect and the spirit, and experienced
                                    brief moments of fame in their lifetime only to retire to very
                                    quiet, unassuming lives.</note></l>
                        </lg> Melville’s pun on "I AM" with <hi rend="italic">iamb</hi> suggests the
                        uneasy relationship between the crafting of poetry and identity, which
                        imposes itself, one foot after another, on Nature in order to make sense of
                        its place in a chaotic world. Although Cranch, like Melville, enjoyed only a brief period of notoriety in his lifetime, both of them saw art as the
                        raison d’être of their everyday lives. Melville eventually got his
                        recrudescence, yet Cranch still remains an oddity, an obscure American
                        metaphysical artist. In 1917, Cranch’s daughter, Lenora Cranch Scott,
                        published what remains the only comprehensive biography of him.<note
                            type="editorial" resp="#cmo">In his book <hi rend="italic">Andrew
                                Jackson Downing and the Architecture of Popular Antebellum
                                Literature, 1835&#8211;1855</hi> (Hanover, NH: University Press of
                            New England, 1996), 200, Adam Sweeting points out the need for a modern
                            biography on Cranch. See also David Robinson’s essay "Christopher Pearse
                            Cranch," in <hi rend="italic">The Transcendentalists: A Review of
                                Research and Criticism,</hi> Ed. Joel Myerson (New York: Modern
                            Language Association, 1984), 123&#8211;30.</note> Despite the wealth of
                        unedited materials available on this enigmatic figure, and some recent
                        interest in Cranch’s children’s literature, a scholarly industry on him is
                        still lacking.<note type="editorial" resp="#cmo">See <hi rend="italic">Three
                                Children’s Novels by Christopher Pearse Cranch</hi>, edited, with an
                            introduction, by Greta D. Little and Joel Myerson (Athens: University of
                            Georgia Press, 1993; reprint edition, 2010).</note></p>
                    <p>Until now, the most significant scholarly work on the "Journal" was Francis
                        B. Dedmond’s transcription of it, which was published in 1983.<note
                            type="editorial" resp="#cmo">Dedmond, "Cranch’s ‘Journal. 1839,’"
                            136–49. The most effective critical work on the significance of the
                            journal is Julie M. Norko’s "Christopher Pearse Cranch’s Struggles with
                            the Muses," <hi rend="italic">Studies in the American Renaissance
                                1992</hi>, ed. Joel Myerson (Charlottesville: University Press of
                            Virginia, 1992), 209–27.</note> My purpose is to improve upon Dedmond’s
                        work with updated technology and information, and to reopen a critical
                        conversation that Dedmond likely had in mind with his publication. Dedmond
                        lacked the advantages of TEI encoding, high-resolution images, and open
                        access journals, and his transcription does not record manuscript changes,
                        explain his editorial principles, or record all textual features (such as
                        line and paragraph breaks). His transcription is also supported by only
                        three low-quality black-and-white facsimiles.<note type="editorial"
                            resp="#cmo">Dedmond’s transcription has quite a few minor
                            errors&#8212;and a few substantive ones&#8212;which are recorded in the
                            xml document under <hi rend="bold">sic</hi> tags (within <hi rend="bold"
                                >choice</hi>).</note> Here presented is the entire "Journal 1839,"
                        digitized for the first time and encoded in TEI with an updated apparatus
                        and a corrected reading text available for download.</p>
                </div>
                <div>
                    <head type="main">Significance of the "Journal": Diffidence, Allusion, and the
                        Fate of Transcendentalism</head>
                    <p>Cranch’s 1839 "Journal" presents an immediate, humane, and compelling account
                        of his quest for personal advancement as a young man. It is the only
                        surviving handwritten document from a crucial moment in Cranch’s life when
                        he turned away from the Unitarian ministry and toward transcendentalism and
                        the uncertain path of a multigenre artist. The "Journal" also demonstrates
                        Cranch’s budding aesthetic process: working through his philosophical
                        forefathers and using devices borrowed from Carlyle, Emerson, and the German
                        romantics to convey a sense of self that is in frustrating progress, he
                        echoes Horace’s plea to Maecenas to be patient and seek action, "To make the
                        world serve me, not me the world" (Epistle I).<note type="editorial"
                            resp="#cmo">As translated by David Ferry in his <hi rend="italic"
                                >Epistles of Horace: A Bilingual Edition</hi> (New York: Farrar,
                            Straus &amp; Giroux, 2001), 5.</note></p>
                    <p>In his "Journal" Cranch displays an allusiveness masked in a modesty topos
                        that prefigures a similar tactic in T. S. Eliot’s prose, in addition to
                        channeling a curious tradition of diffidence in English poetry.<note
                            type="editorial" resp="#cmo">I borrow the "modesty topos" idea from
                            Christopher Ricks, <hi rend="italic">Decisions and Revisions in T. S.
                                Eliot</hi> (London: British Library, 2003). </note> The dominant
                        view of Cranch is that he was a <hi rend="italic">diffident</hi> man. The
                        word "diffidence" (or "diffident") appears nine times in Scott’s biography;
                        Julie M. Norko’s article has it four times, as to his "struggles with the
                        muse"; and Dedmond twice, in relation to the "Journal." Cranch admitted to
                        Clarke in an August 1837 letter that he is <quote>"reserved, secretive,
                            proud, indolent, but above all diffident. This besetting diffidence lies
                            at the root of all my reserve, and keeps me again and again silent and
                            seemingly cold, when no one could tell how deep and strong the stream
                            which ran hidden within."</quote><note type="editorial" resp="#cmo"
                            >Quoted in Scott, <hi rend="italic">Life and Letters</hi>, 35. See also
                            note 36 to the "Journal" edition.</note> Perhaps Cranch knew of
                        Emerson’s warning in his 1838 "Literary Ethics" oration that "the diffidence
                        of mankind in the soul has crept over the American mind."<note
                            type="editorial" resp="#cmo">"Literary Ethics: An Oration Delivered
                            before the Literary Societies of Dartmouth College, July 24, 1838," in <hi
                                rend="italic">Nature, Addresses, and Lectures: Collected Works of
                                Ralph Waldo Emerson</hi>, ed. Alfred R. Ferguson et al. (Cambridge:
                            Harvard University Press, 1971), 1:100. Cited hereafter as <hi
                                rend="italic">CW</hi>.</note> Diffidence, in the currently rare
                        sense, is a "Want of confidence or faith; mistrust, distrust, misgiving,
                        doubt," and in the common usage, a "Distrust of oneself; want of confidence
                        in one’s own ability, worth, or fitness; modesty, shyness of disposition"
                            (<hi rend="italic">Oxford English Dictionary</hi>). "Sickness," Pope
                        once said in a letter to Richard Steele, "teaches us a diffidence in our
                        earthly state."<note type="editorial" resp="#cmo">June 15, 1712, letter to
                            Sir Richard Steele, in <bibl><hi rend="italic">Mr. Pope’s Literary
                                    Correspondence for Thirty Years; from 1704 to 1734: Being a
                                    Collection of Letters Which Passed between Him and Several
                                    Eminent Persons</hi> (London, 1735), 1:166.</bibl></note> Given
                        the many untimely deaths Cranch witnessed in childhood, Pope’s words may
                        shed some light on Cranch’s demeanor. Furthermore, Cranch's psychic
                        "sickness" (otherwise referred to as his "problem" in his letters and
                        reminiscences) usually follows a conceit about cosmic injustice, his lack of
                        talent, or his longing for beauty. He may have known Countess Teresa
                        Guiccioli's assessment of Byron's modesty, in which she quoted "a great
                        moralist of the present day" who said that "no real modesty" exists "without
                        the diffidence of self, inspired by a deep sense of the beautiful and by the
                        fear of not being able to reach the perfection we conceive."<note
                            type="editorial" resp="#cmo"><bibl>Countess Guiccioli, <hi rend="italic"
                                    >My Recollections of Lord Byron</hi> (London: Richard Bentley,
                                1869), 278.</bibl></note> (Later in this essay I quote Cranch's
                        thoughts on the "Byronic" nature of early transcendentalism.) The first
                        sense of <hi rend="italic">diffidence</hi> suggests that the person in
                        question is plainly distrustful, but the meaning has shifted to apperception
                        (a "distrust of oneself")&#8212;which is odd in Cranch's case, because his
                        friends and acquaintances all found him immensely trustworthy and talented.
                        Yet in <hi rend="italic">An Essay on Criticism</hi> Pope takes the common
                        sense of diffidence further: "Be <hi rend="italic">silent</hi> always when
                        you <hi rend="italic">doubt</hi> your Sense; / And <hi rend="italic"
                            >speak</hi>, tho’ <hi rend="italic">sure</hi>, with <hi rend="italic"
                            >seeming Diffidence</hi>" (lines 566&#8211;7)<note type="editorial"
                            resp="#cmo"><bibl><hi rend="italic">The Poems of Alexander Pope, Volume
                                    I: Pastoral Poetry and An Essay on Criticism</hi>, ed. E. Audra
                                and Aubrey Williams (London: Methuen &amp; Co. Ltd., 1961),
                                305.</bibl></note>. Diffidence can be part of a performance, a <hi
                            rend="italic">seeming</hi> shyness or modesty resulting from a
                        calculated effort not to play the prattler. When Cranch first arrived in
                        Cincinnati, he himself suggested that "I feel that I must be another man
                        before I can enter into [the ministry] as I ought. At times I feel zealous,
                        resolute &amp; full of faith&#8212;but I am usually, while looking at it, in
                        prospect, a perfect coward&#8212;the slave of self, the sport of habits,
                        temperament, and a wavering faith and purpose."<note type="editorial"
                            resp="#cmo">Letter to Edward P. Cranch, January 1, 1839, quoted in
                            Dedmond, "Cranch's 'Journal. 1839,'" 134.</note> Want of faith and trust
                        in oneself, despite a zealous feeling&#8212;these are Cranch’s "problems" on
                        first glance, yet they ought not to be confused with, for instance, a
                        "spiritual depression."<note type="editorial" resp="#cmo">Dedmond explains
                            Cranch’s lack of boldness as "recurring seasons of doubt and spiritual
                            depression" ("Cranch's 'Journal. 1839,'" 131).</note> Noticing Elizabeth
                        Barrett Browning’s "diffidence" when he met her and Robert Browning in
                        Florence in 1849, Cranch may have associated the term with an artistic
                            temperament.<note type="editorial" resp="#cmo">See also Norko, "Cranch's
                            Struggles with the Muses," 216.</note> He sometimes uses the term not
                        only to provoke action but also to weigh his words, again, in seeming
                        diffidence. The modesty topos is to speak surely to himself, but with
                        restraint, as a careful poet should. His self-deprecations lead to second
                        thoughts, revisions of himself, avoiding the danger of self-satisfaction. He
                        professes to be more of a searcher than an oracular bard or rigid
                        philosopher.</p>
                    <p>Cranch’s diffidence conveys a subtle modesty, juxtaposed with his
                        indebtedness to thinkers in the romantic tradition, including the principle
                        that revelation comes after crisis (that joy and suffering go hand in hand).
                        Cranch employs several romantic tropes&#8212;announcing himself ("I begin
                        this day a Journal"; "I am <hi rend="double-underline">Here</hi>"),
                        espousing his individualism ("I must be a more independent <hi
                            rend="underline">thinker</hi>"), lambasting himself throughout for
                        slothfulness, and exercising religious doubt ("I need to be <hi
                            rend="underline">based</hi> more firmly upon eternal truths. I want a
                        sound philosophy to prop up my too wavering faith"). The void still haunts
                        him at the end of the "Journal"; he does not capitalize "eternal truths,"
                        and still seeks a "sound philosophy" for an unmoored faith. His modesty in
                        the "Journal" is analogous to Wordsworth’s tension between the
                        transcendental ecstasy of the natural world and the works of great poets in
                            <hi rend="italic">The Prelude</hi>: "this only let me add / From
                        heart-experience, and in humblest sense / Of modesty" (Book V, lines
                            584&#8211;86).<note type="editorial" resp="#cmo">For more on
                            Wordsworth’s (and, by extension, the Romantics’), use of "sense," see
                            William Empson's "Sense in the <hi rend="italic">Prelude</hi>," in <hi
                                rend="italic">The Structure of Complex Words</hi> (London: Hogarth
                            Press, 1985), 289&#8211;305. The word changes throughout Wordsworth’s
                            career, going from the "wavering and untrammeled natural growth" in the
                            early work to the "unrelaxing Will" (a la Milton) in the later work
                            (294). In <hi rend="italic">The Prelude</hi>, sense "means both the
                            process of sensing and the supreme act of imagination, and unites them
                            by a jump; the same kind of jump as that in the sentence about crossing
                            the Alps, which identifies the horror caused by the immediate sensations
                            with the exultation that developed from them" (304). Cranch uses "sense"
                            in a similar way, not only relating to perception but also to that mix
                            of imagination and indeterminacy in his writings and drawings.</note>
                        Triumph paradoxically breeds the deepest sadness; diffidence (or modesty)
                        comes from this sadness, leaving one perplexed, and leading to rethinking.
                        In the words of T. H. Green (on Wordsworth): "The natural man is the passive
                        man." Cranch’s sense of "natural and free"&#8212;coupled with his
                        diffidence&#8212;is a voice of his own nature as well as the humility of
                        "perplexed persistence."<note type="editorial" resp="#cmo">The "perplexed
                            persistence"&#8212;itself a borrowing of the "sad perplexity" from
                            "Tintern Abbey"&#8212;comes from A. C. Bradley’s discussion of
                            Wordsworth’s "Resolution and Independence" in <hi rend="italic">Oxford
                                Lectures On Poetry</hi>, 2nd ed. (1909; reprint, London: St.
                            Martin's Press, 1965), 131; T. H. Green, <hi rend="italic">Works of
                                Thomas Hill Green</hi>, ed. R. L. Nettleship (London: Longmans,
                            Green, 1888), 3:119.</note> Cranch’s modesty sets the tenor for his
                        earnest devotion to art and spiritual well-being, his contemplation of
                        nature and the writers who attempted to channel it.<note type="editorial"
                            resp="#cmo">While he was in Louisville, on October 14, Cranch wrote his
                            sister Margaret as he was putting together the November number of the
                                <hi rend="italic">Western Messenger</hi>: "I have contributed
                            several articles. . . . I would stuff it with more poetry but I am
                            ashamed that so many pieces should go forth with ‘C.P.C.’ dangling at
                            the end" (Scott, <hi rend="italic">Life and Letters</hi>, 37&#8211;38).
                            He continued to contribute for two more years.</note> Therefore his
                        diffidence is more complicated than merely a "conflict between religion and
                        aestheticism" or a spiritual depression&#8212;it imitates Pope and
                            Wordsworth.<note type="editorial" resp="#cmo">See Norko, "Cranch's
                            Struggles with the Muses," 212.</note> It is a product of his devouring
                        various ethical and aesthetic ideas, weighing them against himself,
                        attempting, as Emerson says in <hi rend="italic">Nature</hi>, to achieve the
                        poet’s vision&#8212;"a property in the horizon which no man but he whose eye
                        can integrate all the parts"&#8212;and then getting the whiff of mortality
                        even if he believes he succeeds.<note type="editorial" resp="#cmo">From the
                            first chapter of <hi rend="italic">Nature</hi>, in <hi rend="italic"
                                >CW</hi>, 1:9.</note></p>
                    <div>
                        <milestone unit="undeclared" rend="asterisks"/>
                        <p>Cranch’s allusiveness constitutes another kind of rethinking, the
                            necessary move to turn away from the dogma of Unitarianism and toward
                            the spiritual, transcendental ideals of Carlyle, Emerson, and the German
                            romantics who preceded him.<note type="editorial" resp="#cmo">This came
                                just before the Andrews Norton–George Ripley controversy following
                                Emerson’s "Divinity School Address" that would settle the chasm
                                between the Unitarians and Transcendentalists. See F. DeWolfe
                                Miller, <hi rend="italic">Christopher Pearse Cranch and His
                                    Caricatures of New England Transcendentalism</hi> (Cambridge:
                                Harvard University Press, 1951), 51&#8211;54, for a more detailed
                                account of Cranch’s involvement in this controversy after he
                                returned to Boston in July 1839. Cranch’s caricaturing played a part
                                in the controversy; he sent Clarke a sketch, which is supposed to be
                                a fairly accurate representation of Norton, satirizing Norton’s
                                claim that the Transcendentalists are not Christians because they
                                deny miracles and the personality of God. See the image at <ref
                                    type="url"
                                    target="http://nrs.harvard.edu/urn-3:FHCL.Hough:2317956"
                                    >http://nrs.harvard.edu/urn-3:FHCL.Hough:2317956</ref>.</note>
                            Leon Jackson has argued that Cranch's reading of Carlyle’s <hi
                                rend="italic">Sartor Resartus</hi> focused on "three very specific
                            chapters of the book dealing with the protagonist’s spiritual journey
                            out of context, but in an intensive fashion, using them as a guide to,
                            or catalyst for, conversion."<note type="editorial" resp="#cmo">Leon
                                Jackson, "The Reader Retailored: Thomas Carlyle, His American
                                Audiences, and the Politics of Evidence," <hi rend="italic">Book
                                    History</hi> 2 (1999): 151, 158&#8211;59.</note> Taking the book
                            in parts, Cranch certainly made his "Journal" Sartorish, but a thorough
                            reading of the "Journal" shows little evidence that Cranch read the book
                            out of context or engaged in "selective appropriations." The following
                            discussion and the footnotes in the edition of the "Journal" show that
                            he understood Carlyle quite well. Carlyle does serve as a template for
                            Emerson, and for Cranch’s ideal self, who aspires to key conversion
                            experiences from <hi rend="italic">Sartor</hi>.</p>
                        <p>Carlyle’s looming presence in the "Journal" suggests the pervasive value
                            of "work" and the quest toward the Everlasting Yea. Whereas Emerson
                            relied on Carlyle and European romanticism for its questions (and many
                            of its answers), Cranch commiserates with his British and European
                            counterparts, swinging on a pendulum of No and Yea throughout his
                            "Journal" without settling the dispute.<note type="editorial"
                                resp="#cmo">See David Greenham’s <hi rend="italic">Emerson’s
                                    Transatlantic Romanticism</hi> (New York: Palgrave Macmillan,
                                2012), which discusses Emerson's reliance on European romanticism,
                                yet he does not discuss Cranch, or how Emerson’s transatlanticism
                                was interpreted by his followers. Cranch came under the spell of
                                German literature&#8212;due to Harvard Divinity School, under the
                                direction of Dr. Charles Follen&#8212;before he was entirely exposed
                                to Emerson’s "transatlanticism."</note> That Cranch says on page 8
                            that Clarke "swallows all formulas" suggests that he read Carlyle
                            closely, for he refers to the Duke of Mirabeau’s <hi rend="italic"
                                >Memoirs</hi>, which was translated by Carlyle and quoted in his <hi
                                rend="italic">French Revolution</hi>.<note type="editorial"
                                resp="#cmo">See also note 22 of the edition.</note> Cranch’s
                            idiosyncratic comparison is even more instructive if one considers the
                            thrust of Carlyle’s passage, that human action cannot be quantified,
                            contra the British sensibility of the hedonic calculus, so a formula for
                                <hi rend="italic">Seele</hi> (soul) or <hi rend="italic">Geist</hi>
                            (spirit) is a presumptuous endeavor. Cranch followed suit in the
                            tradition of German idealism, though he would later deny that
                            affiliation to his father;<note type="editorial" resp="#cmo">On July 11,
                                1840, Cranch wrote his father to allay his concerns that he is
                                "inclined to the Transcendental sentiments of the German
                                theologist’s"; Cranch’s response offered a subtle distinction
                                between him and the transcendentalists: "The Philosophy of Kant,
                                Fichte, Hegel, Schelling, etc., which is what I suppose to be the
                                Transcendental philosophy, has always, from the very slight idea I
                                have of it, struck me as a cold, barren system of Idealism, not
                                calculated to strengthen the soul’s faith in the external realities
                                of the spiritual world, or enable it as a perfect philosophy should,
                                to give a reason for the hope that is in us; although to some minds
                                it may have this effect" (quoted in Scott, <hi rend="italic">Life
                                    and Letters</hi>, 50).</note> and in 1839 he distinguished
                            himself from utilitarian thinking. Ultimately Cranch’s journal is a
                            spiritual autobiography in the mold of <hi rend="italic">Sartor
                                Resartus</hi>: passing through the "grim desert" of infidelity, he
                            experiences the skepticism of hopeless despair, and with each and every
                            turn, the world responds to his questions with negations.<note
                                type="editorial" resp="#cmo"><hi rend="italic">Sartor Resartus: The
                                    Life and Opinions of Herr Teufelsdröckh</hi>, ed. Rodger L. Tarr
                                et al. (Berkeley: University of California Press, 2000), 122.</note>
                            What then is the intellectual significance of Cranch’s appropriating
                            Carlyle’s mythology if he keeps returning to doubt?</p>
                        <p>Cranch’s journal-writing may be examined in relation to the dialectical
                            method that he likely intuited from Emerson’s <hi rend="italic"
                                >Nature</hi> (which Emerson borrowed from Coleridge)&#8212;namely,
                            that the more one seeks to "realize," the "vaster the horizon
                            assimilated by the Soul," and thus, the greater the freedom of being
                            both in the world and above the throng of everyday perception. As in
                            Coleridge’s <hi rend="italic">The Friend</hi>, in which the "living
                            soul" of "universal knowledge" is "sending sovereign glances to the
                            circumference of things," Emerson responds with the idea that "The
                            health of the eye seems to demand a horizon. We are never tired, so long
                            as we can see far enough."<note type="editorial" resp="#cmo"><hi
                                    rend="italic">CW</hi>, 1:13. See also Barry Wood, "The Growth of
                                the Soul: Coleridge's Dialectical Method and the Strategy of
                                Emerson's <hi rend="italic">Nature</hi>," <hi rend="italic"
                                    >PMLA</hi> 91, no. 3 (May 1976): 387.</note> Emerson calls for a
                            poetical kind of seeing, which Cranch attempts to realize in the
                            "Journal." In "Self-Reliance" Emerson would call the work of genius
                            "alienated majesty"; that is, genius recognizes its own "rejected
                            thoughts" as much as we do. The idea of "alienated majesty" was itself a
                            second thought, originating in his recognition of "Otherism" in <hi
                                rend="italic">Nature</hi>, which Geoffrey Hill writes has the double
                            sense of <hi rend="italic">Entfremdung</hi> (estrangement) and <hi
                                rend="italic">Verfremdung</hi> (artistic distancing).<note
                                type="editorial" resp="#cmo">Emerson’s "Otherism" is recorded in a
                                November 24, 1836 journal entry; see Geoffrey Hill, "Alienated
                                Majesty: Ralph Waldo Emerson," in <hi rend="italic">Collected
                                    Critical Writings</hi>, ed. Kenneth Haynes (Oxford: Oxford
                                University Press, 2008), 494.</note> Cranch’s sense of estrangement,
                            distancing (especially in his eschewing the ministry to the poor), the
                            need for a certain kind of seeing&#8212;all these are at play in the
                            "Journal," two years before Emerson published "Self-Reliance."</p>
                        <p>The other crucial metaphors in Emerson’s dialectic are growth and
                            compensation. In addition to his use of Coleridge’s distinction between
                            Reason and Understanding, Emerson appropriated from <hi rend="italic"
                                >The Friend</hi> and <hi rend="italic">Aids to Reflection</hi> the
                            concept of "polarity," which he links with spiritual development.<note
                                type="editorial" resp="#cmo">Wood, "The Growth of the Soul,"
                                389.</note> In the "Language" chapter of <hi rend="italic"
                                >Nature</hi>, Emerson establishes a connection between logical
                            thought and poetical language, saying that "man is an analogist, and
                            studies relations in all objects. He is placed in the centre of beings,
                            and a ray of relation passes from every other being to him." This
                            unification of <hi rend="italic">mythos</hi> and <hi rend="italic"
                                >logos</hi> leads to "proper creation," the "blending of experience
                            with the present action of the mind."<note type="editorial" resp="#cmo"
                                    ><hi rend="italic">CW</hi>, 1:19, 20&#8211;21.</note> Like
                            vision, growth involves the progress toward self-reliance: one moves
                            farther away from the world in order to fully understand it.</p>
                        <p>Compensation is not merely the fruits of good acts (in the sense of <hi
                                rend="italic">karma</hi> and <hi rend="italic">phala</hi>); it is a
                            balanced wholeness. Following this line of thought, Cranch uses the word
                            "compensation" on page 9 of the "Journal" while musing on traveling and
                            respecting the land&#8212;which is intriguing, given the fact that
                            Emerson’s poem-essay "Compensation" would not appear until 1841 in his
                                <hi rend="italic">Essays: First Series</hi>. Furthermore, Cranch’s
                            nod to Wordsworth’s "Tintern Abbey" (to "see into the life of
                                things")<note type="editorial" resp="#cmo">Coleridge’s concise
                                analysis of "Tintern Abbey" is also analogous to Cranch’s absorption
                                of intuition: in a February&#8211;March 1801 journal entry,
                                Coleridge indicated that to "see into life of things" means, "By
                                deep feeling we make our Ideas dim&#8212;&amp; this is what we mean
                                by our Life&#8212;ourselves [. . .] Now (let me) think of <hi
                                    rend="italic">myself</hi>&#8212;of the thinking Being&#8212;the
                                Idea becomes dim whatever it be&#8212;so dim that I know not what it
                                is&#8212;but the Feeling is deep &amp; steady&#8212;and this I call
                                    <hi rend="italic">I</hi>" (Bollingen Series of <hi rend="italic"
                                    >The Notebooks of Samuel Taylor Coleridge</hi>, ed. Kathleen
                                Coburn [New York: Pantheon Books, 1957], entry 921). Entry 923 also
                                features the follow-up thought, "of <hi rend="italic">Thinking</hi>
                                as distinguished from <hi rend="italic">Thoughts</hi>."</note> also
                            points to the <hi rend="italic">intueri</hi> (literally, seeing into) of
                            Milton’s archangel Raphael, who instructs Adam: <quote>
                                <lg type="poem">
                                    <l>So from the root</l>
                                    <l>Springs lighter the green stalk, from thence the leaves</l>
                                    <l>More aerie, last the bright consummate floure</l>
                                    <l>Spirits odorous breathes: flours and thir fruit</l>
                                    <l>Mans nourishment, by gradual scale sublim’d</l>
                                    <l>To vital Spirits aspire, to animal,</l>
                                    <l>To intellectual, give both life and sense,</l>
                                    <l>Fansie and understanding, whence the Soule</l>
                                    <l>Reason receives, and reason is her being,</l>
                                    <l>Discursive, or Intuitive (Book V, lines 479&#8211;87)<note
                                            type="editorial" resp="#cmo">Milton, <hi rend="italic"
                                                >Paradise Lost</hi>, The Riverside Milton, ed. Roy
                                            Flannagan (Boston: Houghton Mifflin, 1998),
                                        491.</note></l>
                                </lg>
                            </quote> Milton’s metaphor of organic life&#8212;"one first matter all,"
                            which originates from the same divine source, and the "root" giving
                            "flours and thir fruit"&#8212;allows for a different kind of reasoning.
                            Milton's call for a well-nourished mind morphed into Coleridge's Reason
                            and Understanding distinction, and Emerson’s intuition and growth. As
                            Keane suggests, the ideas of Milton, "once ‘filtered’ through the
                            transatlantic pipeline, Coleridge, and conveyed (by himself and through
                            Wordsworth) to New England, came out as American
                                Transcendentalism."<note type="editorial" resp="#cmo">Patrick J.
                                Keane, <hi rend="italic">Emerson, Romanticism, and Intuitive Reason:
                                    The Transatlantic "Light of All Our Day"</hi> (Columbia:
                                University of Missouri Press, 2005), 3.</note> But Cranch himself
                            said several times in 1839 that he was not yet a transcendentalist; he
                            was merely absorbing the flow of ideas, and still wavering, to use
                            Norko’s words, "between service to the Unitarian God and service to the
                                Muses."<note type="editorial" resp="#cmo">Norko, "Cranch's Struggles
                                with the Muses," 219.</note> That Cranch quoted Wordsworth’s
                            "Resolution and Independence" illustrates his struggle to <hi
                                rend="italic">reflect</hi> beauty, just as Wordsworth portrayed the
                            leech-gatherer, one vagrant muse to another.<note type="editorial"
                                resp="#cmo">I owe the "vagrant muse" to Gary Lee Harrison’s <hi
                                    rend="italic">Wordsworth’s Vagrant Muse: Poetry, Poverty, and
                                    Power</hi> (Detroit: Wayne State Press, 1994), 135, where he
                                discusses how the leech gatherer’s "indeterminacy" disturbs the
                                poet.</note> Wordsworth uses the "mind’s eye" to elevate the
                            suffering of the wanderer. Geoffrey Hartman’s comments about
                            Wordsworth’s poem (channeling Bradley)&#8212;"We feel the poet’s
                            distraught perplexity, as if this could not be, or could not
                            last"&#8212;suggests too that Cranch may sympathize with Wordsworth’s
                            performance of a living mind open to the terror of indeterminacy.<note
                                type="editorial" resp="#cmo">Geoffrey Hartman, <hi rend="italic"
                                    >Wordsworth’s Poetry: 1787&#8211;1814</hi> (New Haven: Yale
                                University Press, 1971), 268.</note> Yet a spirit of striving abates
                            the terror; on page 6 of the "Journal" Cranch says, "I must begin to <hi
                                rend="underline">Live</hi>. Then I shall begin to <hi
                                rend="underline">Realize</hi> &#8212;then to think, feel, act,
                            grow." In this way Cranch illustrates what Coleridge said about
                            Wordsworth that "his genius was not a spirit that descended to him
                            through the air; it sprang out of the ground like a flower"&#8212;or,
                            say, like <hi rend="italic">flours and thir fruit</hi>, the <hi
                                rend="italic">outgrowth</hi> of the earth and the air, nature and
                            imagination, in loving opposition.<note type="editorial" resp="#cmo"
                                >Wood connects the outgrowth idea in Coleridge’s dialectical method
                                to Emerson’s interest in compensation: "The growth of a plant
                                involves a seed in position (thesis), a nourishing environment in
                                op-position (antithesis), an equilibrium of the two (mesothesis),
                                and the composition (synthesis) of a plant out of this dialectic.
                                The importance of this illustration for Emerson can hardly be over-stated, for it not only reinforced his earlier notion about the
                                growth of the soul by assimilation, but also forced upon him the
                                crucial connection between the growth of the soul and the logical
                                method of thought. At one stroke the importance of the organic
                                metaphor became clear: organic growth was a dialectical process;
                                logical thought was dialectical thought [. . .]" ("The Growth of the
                                Soul," 390). The concerns of philosophical essayist and poet
                                coincide.</note></p>
                        <p>The point of Coleridge’s dialectic is that the opposition meets at some
                            point to support the overall being, like the arch. Cranch used this
                            metaphor about himself in an 1837 letter: "I must not feel myself
                            detached from society, but as forming a stone in the arch, helping to
                            support the building."<note type="editorial" resp="#cmo">October 1837
                                letter to his sister (quoted in Scott, <hi rend="italic">Life and
                                    Letters</hi>, 39).</note> His talents may well have contributed
                            to this detachment, and he likely remembered Emerson’s warning in the
                            "The American Scholar" that American literary culture suffers from "men
                            of talent, that is, who start wrong, who set out from accepted dogmas,
                            not from their own sight of principles."<note type="editorial"
                                resp="#cmo"><hi rend="italic">CW</hi>, 1:56.</note> His life, in all
                            its parts, aspired to a work of art, which explains his assorted
                            engagements with art and literature in the "Journal," as well as his
                            self-criticisms for slothfulness, but he struggled with the "sight" of
                            his principles, and his responsibility to the public (what it meant to
                            see himself in relation to the whole). And his self-absorption in the
                            "Journal" does not exactly suggest a serious engagement with the natural
                            world but a set of ethical concerns about how to live well (and make a
                            living). He knew from Emerson that "Genius creates"; and so, in the
                            "Journal" he attempts creation with what he calls "practical
                            illustration," anticipates the doomed intimations of failure, and then
                            fails to fail better. He nevertheless understood that action and growth
                            lead to the "pure efflux" of the divine. It should be no surprise, then,
                            that Cranch’s embrace of the Carlyle–Wordsworth–Coleridge phalanx led to
                            two drawings of Emerson that depict vision and growth. While Emerson is
                            Cranch’s foremost philosophical guide (only slightly more important than
                            Carlyle), Cranch still engaged in an education of a well-balanced
                            aesthetic livelihood, as well as the unencumbered musical mysticism of
                            the German romantics.</p>
                    </div>
                    <div>
                        <milestone unit="undeclared" rend="asterisks"/>
                        <p>Besides Carlyle and Coleridge, Clarke and Dwight provided Cranch the most
                            immediate conduit of German thought, which lends a new perspective to
                            the "Journal."<note type="editorial" resp="#cmo">Greenham, 21–22, points
                                out that Emerson changed his mind about the literal authority of the
                                Bible under the influence of Dr. Edward Everett, who also taught
                                Cranch and studied with the early philologist Johann Gottfried
                                Eichhorn on the German Higher Criticism that called the accuracy of
                                the Bible into question. Theodore Parker is another friend of
                                Cranch’s who taught him about German literature. The <hi
                                    rend="italic">New Philosophy</hi> scrapbook has a drawing of
                                Parker going after an entire shelf of books at a German library.
                                More evidence suggests that at this time Cranch was more affected by
                                Dwight and Clarke. Dwight was a more effective communicator of
                                German ideas, since he (like Cranch) was more of a poet-musician,
                                whereas Parker had a more scholarly temperament. </note> Two years
                            before his "Journal" Cranch told his sister Margaret that he "spent most
                            of the evening with [Clarke], talking and looking over Retzsch’s
                            illustrations of the Second Part of ‘Faust.’"<note type="editorial"
                                resp="#cmo">Quoted in Scott, <hi rend="italic">Life and
                                Letters</hi>, 39.</note> In 1839 Clarke published translations of
                            Goethe’s "For Life," "Forever," "In Memory of Schiller," and "Orphic
                            Sayings," and Schiller’s "Thekla: A Spirit’s Voice," so Goethe and
                            Schiller must have been topics of conversation in Louisville.</p>
                        <p>Cranch also absorbed German music and musical criticism from Dwight.<note
                                type="editorial" resp="#cmo">Norko, "Cranch's Struggles with the
                                Muses," 219, briefly mentions Cranch’s use of musical metaphor in
                                his prose pieces, but she does not connect it to the source of
                                German aesthetics vis-à-vis Dwight.</note> In the words of J. Wesley
                            Thomas, Dwight became "the greatest influence in the assimilation of
                            this Romanticism into American culture" (as well as being the great
                            arbiter of American music).<note type="editorial" resp="#cmo">J. Wesley
                                Thomas, "John Sullivan Dwight: A Translator of German Romanticism,"
                                    <hi rend="italic">American Literature</hi> 21, no. 4 (January
                                1950): 427.</note> When he entered Harvard Divinity School in 1832,
                            with his new friends and classmates Cranch and Theodore Parker, Dwight
                            actively studied German culture, even though the Unitarian Church
                            largely frowned upon German philosophers and artists.<note
                                type="editorial" resp="#cmo">See Thomas, "John Sullivan Dwight,"
                                428</note> The condemnation of New England divines did not concern
                            Dwight and Cranch, who did not wholly adopt the strict philosophical
                            systems of Kant, Fichte, and Schelling. Both were censured by fellow
                            friends in Unitarianism and transcendentalism alike for their aloofness,
                            or "deficiency" in embracing the cult of self development.<note
                                type="editorial" resp="#cmo">As to Dwight’s "deficiency," I quote
                                from Thomas, "John Sullivan Dwight," 428&#8211;29. Cranch’s
                                "deficiency" has received due attention most clearly from Norko,
                                "Cranch's Struggles with the Muses."</note> Dwight and Cranch
                            remained unpretentious, practical intellectuals, religiously open-minded
                            mystics, and keenly attuned appreciators of music and lyric poetry.</p>
                        <p>Cranch probably knew Dwight’s translation of Schiller’s "Lied an die
                            Freude," which was published in the May 1835 issue of <hi rend="italic"
                                >New England Magazine</hi>. German romanticism provided the
                            foundation for Dwight’s aesthetic sensibility in poetry and music; it
                            also inspired Cranch in his "Journal" to capture the intuitive, sublime,
                            indefinite, <hi rend="italic">wogende Aussummen</hi> that characterizes
                            the German aesthetic, uplifting <hi rend="italic">Dichtkunst</hi> into
                                <hi rend="italic">Saiten und Töne</hi>. Some passages in the
                            "Journal" illustrate a nebulous impressionism, where feeling aspires to
                            the bliss of music, such as when he praises Clarke’s "poetic imagination
                            with the tenderest feeling" (8). Cranch may have appropriated this sense
                            from Dwight, whose commencement address at the Harvard Divinity School
                            in 1836 struck the same chords: <floatingText>
                                <body>
                                    <p>The rare Lyric,&#8212;the choicest flower on poetic soil,
                                        which is not <hi rend="italic">made</hi> but <hi
                                            rend="italic">flows</hi>, which cannot be imitated, for
                                        it is the work of nature, which springs from feeling, shapes
                                        itself under the most delicate touch of the purest sense of
                                        the beautiful,&#8212;every drop in whose composition is from
                                        the soul’s depth, every tint and hue elaborated from
                                        wondrous machinery within, whose shadowy shapes suggested
                                        the eye but dimly sees, for it sees through tears, whose
                                        sound never comes to a determinate close upon the ear, for
                                        it touches the creative sympathies of every heart and lives
                                        on there forever.<note type="editorial" resp="#cmo">"On the
                                            Proper Character of Poetry and Music for Public
                                            Worship," <hi rend="italic">Christian Examiner</hi> 21,
                                            no. 262 (November 1836); quoted in Thomas, "John
                                            Sullivan Dwight," 431.</note></p>
                                </body>
                            </floatingText> As the "natural expression of certain feelings," music
                            ties to Cranch’s search in his "Journal" for being "natural and
                            free"&#8212;another idea perhaps borrowed from Dwight, who once wrote in
                            a letter to Carlyle that in his translations he "pondered and digested
                            the substance, and in this way has the literal imitation become natural
                            and free."<note type="editorial" resp="#cmo">George Willis Cooke, <hi
                                    rend="italic">John Sullivan Dwight</hi> (Boston, 1898),
                                23.</note> In the year of his "Journal" Cranch also saw the
                            publication of his translation of Schiller’s "The Division of the Earth"
                            in Dwight’s collection of the <hi rend="italic">Select Minor Poems
                                Translated from the German of Goethe and Schiller</hi> (which is
                            dedicated to Carlyle).<note type="editorial" resp="#cmo">The poem
                                appears on pp. 290–91 of <hi rend="italic">Select Minor Poems
                                    Translated from the German of Goethe and Schiller</hi>, ed. John
                                Sullivan Dwight (Boston: Hilliard, Gray, 1839).</note> This poem
                            captures the same kinds of anxieties about his profession reflected in
                            his "Journal": Jove tells his "elves," "HERE, Take the world!" and
                            divide the wealth of the land among themselves. The farmers take to the
                            land, merchants the "warehouse loads," and so on. Then, <quote>
                                <lg type="poem">
                                    <l>Quite late, long after all had been divided,</l>
                                    <l rend="left_2em">The Poet came, from distant wandering </l>
                                    <l>Alas! the thing was every where decided,&#8212;</l>
                                    <l rend="left_2em">Proprietors for every thing! (lines
                                        13–16)</l>
                                </lg>
                            </quote> The poet-wanderer is not concerned with material things,
                            choosing instead to be close to the divine; and, appropriate to Cranch’s
                            own experience, the poem comes with a conceit: <quote><lg type="poem">
                                    <l rend="left_2em">"Ah, woe is me! shall I alone of all</l>
                                    <l rend="left_2em">Forgotten be &#8212;I, thy most faithful
                                        son?"</l>
                                    <l>In loud lament he thus began to bawl,</l>
                                    <l rend="left_2em">And threw himself before Jove’s throne.
                                        (lines 14–17)</l>
                                </lg>
                            </quote> Jove reveals that the poet's "home" is with the divine spirit,
                            and the poet suggests that poetry and music intermingle: "Mine eyes hung
                            on thy countenance so bright, / Mine ear drank in thy Heaven’s harmony"
                            (lines 22&#8211;23). He echoes this sentiment in his "Journal" when he
                            recalls a musical evening: "My passion for music is such that I
                            sometimes wonder tis not all-absorbing. No enjoyment of my existence is
                            greater. When I sit down at twilight to the piano forte, and roam over
                            the soul like chords of that glorious instrument, I can feel what <hi
                                rend="underline">perfect beauty</hi> is. What <hi rend="underline"
                                >God</hi> is. I can feel what the language of the angels must be.
                            That language <hi rend="underline">must</hi> be music." Not just music
                            but the <hi rend="italic">language</hi> of the divine, just as he
                            conveys in his rendering of the Schiller poem. Also in the "Journal,"
                            when Cranch quotes from "Tintern Abbey," he must also have in mind the
                            way in which "harmony, and the deep power of joy" allows one to "see
                            into the life of things." Schiller’s sentiment about "professions," his
                            aestheticism as a poet, and the aspirations of his work to the power of
                            harmony in music&#8212;all of these appealed to Cranch. Harmony and
                            language find common ground in music, creating not only a congruity of
                            feeling and sentiment but also tuneful sound. Poe shrewdly recognized
                            Cranch’s capacity for "harmonious combinations of thought," but he
                            compares those conceits to the metaphysical poets Donne and Cowley,
                            suggesting, according to Poe, "uncommon pains to make a fool of
                            himself." Nevertheless, Cranch’s "Journal" anticipates the harmony in
                            his "Lines on Hearing Triumphant Music," where <quote>
                                <lg type="poem">
                                    <l>a light Shines in to-night</l>
                                    <l>Round the good angels trooping to their posts,</l>
                                    <l>And the black cloud is rent in twain</l>
                                    <l>Before the ascending strain.</l>
                                </lg>
                            </quote> Even as Emerson attempted a harmonious combination of thought
                            in the "The American Scholar," Cranch caricatured "This is my music;
                            this is myself" with a chimera whose nose is a clarinet.<note
                                type="editorial" resp="#cmo"><hi rend="italic">CW</hi>, 1:63. For
                                the drawing, see <ref type="url"
                                    target="http://nrs.harvard.edu/urn-3:FHCL.Hough:2317945"
                                    >http://nrs.harvard.edu/urn-3:FHCL.Hough:2317945</ref></note></p>
                        <p>Dwight suggests in his Goethe and Schiller edition that the
                            Schiller&#8211;Beethoven collaboration in the "Ode to Joy" conclusion to
                            the Ninth Symphony is the highest artistic achievement: "The boundless
                            yearning, which is the foundation of our being, and which is nothing
                            less than a yearning to embrace the whole, has found its natural
                            language in music."<note type="editorial" resp="#cmo">Dwight, <hi
                                    rend="italic">Select Minor Poems of Goethe and Schiller</hi>,
                                436.</note> Cranch’s perpetual yearning in his "Journal" not only
                            appropriates German romantic aesthetics from Dwight, it also subtly
                            merges the project of self-development, literature, and music into the
                            same language. Music, poetry, and ethics spring from the same fount. The
                            "Journal" unpretentiously records the impressionistic <hi rend="italic"
                                >Sturm und Drang</hi>, and the quasi-mystical zeal, of the German
                            idols of his time&#8212;Goethe, E. T. A. Hoffmann, Jean Paul, Beethoven,
                            Schumann. Introductory comparisons between Cranch and Dwight must
                            emphasize that they both sought a path toward the Unitarian ministry
                            only to quit it for the agency of art. Both amalgamated the pursuit of
                            philosophy and poetry into music, believing that the <hi rend="italic"
                                >Dichtkunst</hi> could improve peoples’ spiritual lives. Not only
                            was Cranch in the midst of his defining moment as a transcendentalist,
                            not only was he using caricatures to humorously work through Emerson’s
                            new philosophy&#8212;he was also attempting to achieve that musical
                            sense that he learned from German romanticism.<note type="editorial"
                                resp="#cmo">For more on Cranch’s writings on German music, see Ora
                                Frishberg Saloman’s "American Writers on Beethoven, 1838&#8211;1849:
                                Dwight, Fuller, Cranch, Story," <hi rend="italic">American Music,
                                    Music of the Nineteenth Century</hi> 8, no. 1, (Spring 1990):
                                12&#8211;28.</note> When Cranch lambasts himself in the "Journal"
                            for not reading enough, and then speaks of his pure love for music, he
                            may be recalling Goethe’s "Lina" (as translated by Dwight): "Wildly set
                            the chords to ringing, / And then o’er the book incline; &#8212; / But
                            not reading &#8212;only singing: / So shall every leaf be thine." Rather
                            than being the bookworm, Cranch aspired to the higher forms of musical
                            bliss, as evident in his later poem "The Three Muses": <quote><lg
                                    type="poem">
                                    <l>all the subtler shades of feeling live</l>
                                    <l>Perfected life, when wed to chord and tone.</l>
                                    <l>And thou shalt know how tone embodies love,</l>
                                    <l>As speech embodies thought, and haply reach</l>
                                    <l>The large, creative power of those who move</l>
                                    <l>The heart by music.</l>
                                </lg></quote> Cranch’s new philosophy was to be an amalgamation of
                            Carlyle’s <hi rend="italic">Sartor Resartus</hi>, Emerson's aphoristic
                            artistry, and German romantic music, all of which, as he suggests in
                            "Enosis," "Shall be all absorbed again, / Melting, flowing into one."
                            Transcendentalism, Swedenborgianism, German idealism&#8212;these were
                            unhelpful labels, "the glancing of a dream." He also surpassed
                            Unitarianism, for Cranch seemed to only value social awareness and
                            unique style of preaching, practiced best by William Henry Channing, as
                            lasting Unitarian values.<note type="editorial" resp="#cmo">See David
                                Robinson’s "William Henry Channing’s Political Oddysey," <hi
                                    rend="italic">American Quarterly</hi> 34, no. 2 (Summer 1982):
                                165&#8211;84.</note> His process of echoing others’ writings
                            involves a peculiar form of anxiety; his acts of allusion and
                            self-criticism couched in the modesty topos constitute "an imaginative
                            form of second thought, itself revising or revisionary" that made the
                            confidence of "Correspondences" and "Enosis" possible.<note
                                type="editorial" resp="#cmo">Ricks, <hi rend="italic">Decisions and
                                    Revisions in T. S. Eliot</hi>, 3.</note> Nevertheless, Cranch’s
                            journal might also be self-staging, just another performance of the
                            dilettante on the other side of the mountains. Yet for this earnest
                            truth-seeker, modesty and majesty (not ministry) rendezvous in the heart
                            and mind.</p>
                        <p>Cranch’s growth narrative, coupled with his modesty topos, has him going
                            forth into experience, wavering from the bale-fire Unitarianism of his
                            1838 poem "The True Christian"&#8212;where "The stars shine bright in
                            eternal light, / Nor storm, nor rain, can ever blight / One ray of their
                                purity"<note type="editorial" resp="#cmo">Published in the May 1838
                                edition of the <hi rend="italic">Western Messenger</hi>,
                                5:182.</note>&#8212;to a "dreadful <hi rend="underline"
                                >indifference</hi>" and "night-mare life in death" (borrowed from
                            Coleridge) in his 1839 "Journal." Whether coincidental or not, it is
                            fitting that Cranch ends his "Journal" (at least in its present state)
                            with the word "gesture."</p>
                        <p>The "Journal" attempts a conversion narrative using <hi rend="italic"
                                >Sartor Resartus</hi> as a spiritual template; and, making use of
                            the "noble doubt" in <hi rend="italic">Nature</hi> that "perpetually
                            suggests itself," he moves toward faith in himself, and then the world
                            responds by producing doubt.<note type="editorial" resp="#cmo"><hi
                                    rend="italic">CW</hi>, 1:29. I owe the "conversion narrative"
                                idea to Jackson’s "The Reader Retailored," 159&#8211;64.</note>
                            Carlyle’s No and Yea and the Coleridge-Emerson dialectic coalesce into a
                            new ethical system of self-reliance. Cranch’s diffidence resembles
                            Emersonian doubt, synthesizing faith and skepticism about nature into
                            spirit. Like Emerson and Coleridge before him, he saw the "steps of
                            thought" as an organic process, "as the life of the tree puts forth new
                            branches and leaves through the pores of the old."<note type="editorial"
                                resp="#cmo"><hi rend="italic">CW</hi>, 1:38.</note> Yet Cranch
                            undergoes no epiphany in the "Journal": still going far and wide, he had
                            more traveling to do on his "life’s pilgrimage."</p>
                    </div>
                    <div>
                        <milestone unit="undeclared" rend="asterisks"/>
                        <p>Many years after writing his "Journal" Cranch reflected on this crucial
                            time with his "Sermon on Transcendentalism and Emerson," which not only
                            challenges the idea that he left the West as a full-fledged
                            transcendentalist (as some have suggested)<note type="editorial"
                                resp="#cmo">Miller makes this point in <hi rend="italic">Cranch and
                                    His Caricatures</hi>, 12&#8211;13, which was then re-affirmed by
                                Norko, "Cranch's Struggles with the Muses," 214. Furthermore, the
                                poem in Appendix 2 of this edition at least shows his uneasiness
                                with being called a transcendentalist in late 1839.</note>&#8212;it
                            also reveals his unique observations on transcendentalism's growing
                            pains.</p>
                        <p>In his sermon Cranch indicates that Emerson’s <hi rend="italic"
                                >Nature</hi> "was like the sunrise" and "seemed to open new and
                            undiscovered vistas in a world of ideas, along which breathed all the
                            perfume and hope of a morning in June."<note type="editorial"
                                resp="#cmo">From here I quote from an unpublished typescript in Box
                                2 of the Cranch Papers at the Massachusetts Historical Society, an
                                omitted section from Scott’s <hi rend="italic">Life and
                                Letters</hi>. </note> After <hi rend="italic">Nature</hi> came the
                            "Divinity School Address," which Cranch said "was like a chapter from
                            the Prophets," exceeding <hi rend="italic">Nature</hi>, and illustrating
                            "a dangerous error and delusion which the professors demanded from the
                            pulpit": <floatingText>
                                <body>
                                    <p>It was this discourse that drew the dividing line between
                                        orthodox and heterodox Unitarianism, between schools of
                                        thought which daily seemed to see a chasm widening between
                                        them. I well remember at the time I made preaching my
                                        profession, and was in the West, talking with a young
                                        minister a little younger than myself, about this famous
                                        "Divinity School Address." To me it was profound and
                                        refreshing truth: to him it was delusion and heresy. And I
                                        saw at once there was a split in the Unitarian Church, a
                                        chasm destined never to be closed or bridged over, when the
                                        young were so divided as to the grounds and essence of
                                        authority in matters of faith.</p>
                                    <p>When after two years I came East again, your pastor<note
                                            type="editorial" resp="#cmo">The "pastor" is probably
                                            Theodore Parker.</note> was in the mélée of the fight.
                                        He had thrown down the gauntlet, and the lists were ringing
                                        with the shock of arms.</p>
                                    <p>In my own imperfect way I spoke the truth as I conceived it,
                                        and found many who believed as I did. Gradually the pulpits
                                        were being closed to the Transcendentalists.</p>
                                </body>
                            </floatingText> How slyly he speaks the truth in his "own imperfect
                            way," while clearly staking his claim as one of the happy warriors.
                            Cranch went on to clarify that the Unitarians succeeded with "the more
                            peaceful and liberal attitude of that church which was then so
                            belligerent and exclusive to the wide extension of liberal thought of
                            today, to a revival of common sense in theological matters, to the
                            gradual secularization of the Church and co-extensive sanctification of
                            the platform, to the reforms of Temperance, of Anti-slavery societies,
                            to the philanthropic institutions, to schools and colleges, [. . .] though
                            with many signal failures, to a healthier tone in political
                            organization." Nevertheless, the eventual triumph of transcendentalism
                            came from its insistence on "first truths and first principles, without
                            any meditation on the part of old authorities": <floatingText>
                                <body>
                                    <p>Transcendentalism is but one of the streams by which our time
                                        is blessed, blended with other familiar tendencies, and all
                                        flowing from this Divine Providence working with the human
                                        tendencies of the time, which we call the spirit of the
                                        age.</p>
                                    <p>No doubt in the first stages of New England Transcendentalism
                                        there was a good deal that was mere restlessness under worn
                                        out conventions, or partly somewhat exaggerated
                                        individualism, if not egotism, forgetful that the individual
                                        is, after all, one member of a great societal body.
                                        Transcendentalism was sometimes very sentimental and
                                        Byronic. These were the infant mumps and measles. It outgrew
                                        them long before the war of our rebellion. That certainly
                                        did drive out all lingering vestiges of the complaint.</p>
                                </body>
                            </floatingText> In hindsight, Cranch saw his early years when he was
                            transitioning from Unitarian to transcendentalist as full of
                            sentimentality and fervor, with the brashness of a new revolution. </p>
                        <p>From German romanticism to the Transcendentalist Club to the present age,
                            they advocated, as Dwight said, "the insignificance of creeds compared
                            with life and practice," providing the basis for pragmatism.<note
                                type="editorial" resp="#cmo">Quoted in Thomas, "John Sullivan
                                Dwight," 434.</note> In 1883 William James responded to Cranch's
                            avowed appreciation of his writings, saying "I naturally find myself
                            pleased and flattered enough," and adding that his philosophy seeks to
                            reinstate common sense "against more pretentious ways of formulating
                                things."<note type="editorial" resp="#cmo">Quoted in Scott, <hi
                                    rend="italic">Life and Letters</hi>, 342.</note> The word cloud
                            of the "Journal" shows the dominance of <hi rend="italic">shall</hi>,
                            not only inspired by Carlyle and Emerson ("To think is to act"), but
                            also a main tenet in pragmatism&#8212;the implicitness of an ideal in
                            action. <figure>
                                <head>Word cloud of the 1839 "Journal"</head>
                                <p>Screenshot of a Cirrus word cloud produced with Voyant Tools <ref
                                        target="http://voyant-tools.org/" type="url"
                                        >http://voyant-tools.org/</ref></p>
                                <graphic url="Cranch_1839_Journal_word_cloud.png"/>
                                <figDesc>Screenshot of a Cirrus word cloud produced with Voyant
                                    Tools: <ref target="http://voyant-tools.org/"/></figDesc>
                            </figure> Implicitness entails that the full consequences of our values
                            are not entirely in our consciousness when we embrace them (the act of
                            embracing is the crucial thing). James delineates the personal aspect of
                            implicitness in his <hi rend="italic">Principles of
                            Psychology</hi>&#8212;namely, "the emotion that beckons me on is
                            indubitably the pursuit of an ideal social self, of a self that is at
                            least <hi rend="italic">worthy</hi> of approving recognition by the
                            highest <hi rend="italic">possible</hi> judging companion, if such
                            companion there be."<note type="editorial" resp="#cmo">William James,
                                    <hi rend="italic">Principles of Psychology</hi> (New York:
                                Cosimo, 2007), 1:315. Toward the end of Cranch’s life, he knew and
                                appreciated James, who initially inspired him to write a poem
                                "suggested by a very remarkable article ["A Word to Philosophers"]
                                which I have been re-reading for the fourth or fifth time, written
                                by a friend of ours, Dr. William James, son of Henry James, senior,
                                and published in the January number, 1878, of the St. Louis ‘Journal
                                of Speculative Philosophy.’ I wish you would look it up and read it.
                                It is a sharp and very able criticism of Herbert Spencer’s
                                ‘Definition of Mind.’ Dr. James is also Professor James, Professor
                                of Philosophy in Harvard,&#8212;and promises, I think, to make a
                                great mark as a philosophical writer" (quoted in Scott, <hi
                                    rend="italic">Life and Letters</hi>, 303). James was then a
                                frequent guest in Cranch’s study, and they continued to exchange
                                letters. For more on the Emerson–Nietzsche–Pragmatism connections,
                                see the "Emerson and Pragmatism, Emerson and Nietzsche" section of
                                Lawrence Buell’s <hi rend="italic">Emerson</hi> (Cambridge: Harvard
                                University Press, 2003), 218&#8211;38.</note> Nietzsche, like James,
                            was fond of Emerson for his "benevolent and intelligent serenity which
                            discourages all severity"<note type="editorial" resp="#cmo">From
                                aphorism 13 of <hi rend="italic">Twilight of the Idols</hi>, as
                                translated by Hermann Hummel in his article "Emerson and Nietzsche,"
                                    <hi rend="italic">New England Quarterly</hi> 19, no. 1 (March
                                1946): 64.</note>&#8212;the positive willing in the spirit of
                            Goethe. Despite all the emphases on Cranch’s diffidence, he was
                            implicitly working toward transcendentalist ideals in a practical
                            fashion, even in spite of his occasional ennui. Cranch was also an
                            iconoclast, yet an inoffensive one. His open-mindedness in his 1839
                            "Journal" anticipates pragmatism&#8212;but what makes him unique in
                            these recorded moments is the modesty topos in the face of serious
                            artistic endeavor, and the grace and severity with which he strove for
                            the ideals that the pragmatists eventually articulated.</p>
                        <p>Soon after his "Journal," Cranch found himself in the middle of Emerson’s
                            "recruiting efforts." David Dowling has claimed that "Emerson was
                            arguably the least successful promoter of aspiring writers of the entire
                            American nineteenth century. Despite his lack of success in this area,
                            Emerson's keen interest ‘in modifications to the various callings of
                            men, and the customs of business,’ along with his own successful career
                            shift from Unitarian minister to full-time writer and lecturer, made him
                            particularly susceptible to the temptation of discovering and growing
                            young authorial talent."<note type="editorial" resp="#cmo">David
                                Dowling, <hi rend="italic">Literary Partnerships and the
                                    Marketplace</hi> (Baton Rouge: Louisiana State University Press,
                                2012), 117.</note> Dowling lists Cranch, along with Jones Very and
                            William Ellery Channing, as Emerson’s "failed projects" during the years
                                1838&#8211;42.<note type="editorial" resp="#cmo">Dowling, <hi
                                    rend="italic">Literary Partnerships and the Marketplace</hi>,
                                209&#8211;10. For more on this story, see William Moss, "‘So Many
                                Promising Youths’: Emerson’s Disappointing Discoveries of New
                                England Poet-Seers," <hi rend="italic">New England Quarterly</hi>
                                49, no. 1 (1976): 47. </note> The "Journal" situates him in the
                            beginning of that endeavor: by 1840 Cranch is meeting and corresponding
                            with Emerson,<note type="editorial" resp="#cmo">Scott’s fourth chapter
                                of <hi rend="italic">Life and Letters</hi> is devoted to the
                                Cranch–Emerson correspondence.</note> and only two years later
                            Cranch once again finds himself at a loss, and decides to be a
                            painter.</p>
                        <p>Was Cranch was a "wasted talent" or a "minor artist"? Even Emerson told
                            Cranch in 1874 that all the muses conspired against him, that he was
                            "the victim of your own various gifts."<note type="editorial"
                                resp="#cmo">Scott, <hi rend="italic">Life and Letters</hi>,
                                281.</note> To use Samuel Johnson’s remark about Cowley, perhaps
                            Cranch was "beloved by every muse he courted"&#8212;and he courted many
                            muses, making him "equally qualified for sprightly sallies, and for
                            lofty flights." Norko argues that the standard views of Cranch&#8212;his
                            humor, multifaceted talents, and failures as an artist&#8212;are too
                                simplistic.<note type="editorial" resp="#cmo">Norko, "Cranch's
                                Struggles with the Muses," 209.</note> Not just simplistic but
                            vague; for the intelligence and grace in some of his poems rival the
                            forcefulness of Jones Very, his diffidence anticipates the loafing
                            spirit of Whitman, and the ideas-in-progress in the "Journal" should at
                            least allow us to rethink Cranch’s "failures" as part of a protracted
                            intellectual development. His intelligence is flush with second
                            thoughts, his revisions of himself and his philosophy, and his talent
                            was often masked in seeming diffidence, which became a self-fulfilling
                            prophecy (in that he was accused of lacking the courage of his
                            convictions).</p>
                        <p>A record of ministerial Unitarian life in the frontier lands, Cranch’s
                            1839 "Journal" is one of his few surviving journals, showing the
                            original drafts of two of his best-known caricatures of Emerson and the
                            crucibles of thought preceding his best-known poems, "Correspondences"
                            and "Enosis." Critical speculation aside, the journal does exist in
                            scraps, just as the caricatures exist in many scraps, which is a fine
                            complement to <hi rend="italic">Sartor Resartus</hi>; so we, like the
                            editor of Herr Teufelsdröckh’s papers, must continue to patch the scraps
                            together to make sense of his narrative, after the eccentric Mr. Cranch
                            has long disappeared.</p>
                    </div>
                    <div>
                        <head type="main">Versions of the Caricatures</head>
                        <p>Of particular interest in Cranch’s "Journal" are the two consecutive
                            rough drafts of Emerson caricatures appearing on pages 10 and 11. Since
                            F. DeWolfe Miller’s small book on Cranch's caricatures, and Dedmond’s
                            transcription of the "Journal," very little attention has been paid to
                            these caricatures, despite their widespread use in American literature
                            courses. Most scholarship on these two caricatures cites not the
                            original drawings in the "Journal" but published clips of the drawings
                            from Clarke’s <hi rend="italic">New Philosophy</hi> scrapbook at
                            Harvard’s Houghton Library. A thorough study of Cranch’s drawings has
                            yet to be published since Miller’s work.</p>
                        <p>The drawings reveal Cranch’s serious purpose&#8212;one of self-reliance
                            and self-improvement&#8212;as well as a sense of humor that is not
                            regularly associated with transcendentalists. As Cranch says on page 8,
                            having just caricatured Wordsworth, he intends to produce "Illustrations
                            which have a sense&#8212;Carlylean graphic-ness&#8212;and truth. There
                            can be a touch of comicality in them too &#8212;to give them a relish."
                            This "graphic-ness" began at a young age, and surviving evidence
                            suggests that he considered his poetry and visual art to be equally
                            important enterprises. For example, a draft of an illustrated poem
                            called "Childe Christopher," which he wrote into a journal-book in 1836,
                            is a playful send-up of Byron’s "Childe Harold," with annotations in the
                            manner of Coleridge’s "Rime of the Ancient Mariner."</p>
                        <p>What did Cranch mean by "Illustrations which have a sense"? The
                            "Transparent Eyeball" sketch reflects Cranch’s willingness to entertain
                            multiple perspectives on the intellectual movement with which he was
                            eventually identified. While Miller only devotes a few paragraphs to the
                            "Transparent Eyeball" and "Corn and Melons" sketches, he nevertheless
                            shows how they follow an interesting thread: in the paragraph in <hi
                                rend="italic">Nature</hi> where the "transparent eye-ball" appears (in <hi
                                    rend="italic">CW</hi>, 1:10),
                            Emerson distinguishes himself from Wordsworth, suggesting that "Nature
                            always wears the colors of the spirit," which poetically renders the
                            individual’s engagement with nature.<note type="editorial" resp="#cmo"
                                >Cranch suggests a similar interpretation of this passage in one of
                                his best sketches, where Emerson joyfully tosses his hat in the air
                                amidst a bleak surrounding (Miller, <hi rend="italic">Cranch and His
                                    Caricatures</hi>, 40&#8211;41): <figure>
                                    <head>Cranch's caricature of Emerson tossing his hat</head>
                                    <p>This is a drawing from the <hi rend="italic">New Philosophy
                                            Scrapbook</hi> depicting Emerson in ecstasy (printed as
                                        Figure 2 in Miller, <hi rend="italic">Cranch and His
                                            Caricatures</hi>)</p>
                                    <graphic url="Cranch_Emerson_Ecstasy_drawing.png"/>
                                    <figDesc>This is a drawing from the <hi rend="italic">New
                                            Philosophy Scrapbook</hi> depicting Emerson in ecstasy
                                        (printed as Figure 2 in Miller, <hi rend="italic">Cranch and
                                            His Caricatures</hi>)</figDesc>
                                </figure></note> Nature is a mood intensifier for whatever the
                            individual feels at the moment, so "the same scene which yesterday
                            breathed perfume and glittered as for the frolic of the nymphs, is
                            overspread with melancholy today."<note type="editorial" resp="#cmo"><hi
                                    rend="italic">CW</hi>, 1:10.</note> Cranch’s sketch of Emerson’s
                            bliss quotes the passage from the first edition of <hi rend="italic"
                                >Nature</hi> that Emerson revised in the second edition: "Almost I
                            fear to think how glad I am," when in the midst of the common, or the
                            "bare ground."<note type="editorial" resp="#cmo"><hi rend="italic"
                                    >CW</hi>, 1:10.</note> Nature becomes almost Gothicized, and
                            uncanny, yet further in the paragraph Emerson takes the mystical turn,
                            where "all
                            mean egotism vanishes," and the individual morphs into the "transparent eye-ball." The annihilation of ego follows the Hindu <hi
                                rend="italic">anatman</hi> doctrine, that the self in pure austerity
                            becomes the no-self. Bliss is ego annihilation. Now Cranch likely saw
                            this passage not in terms of its Hindu precursor, but in terms of pure
                            ecstasy, the sheer optimism that "nothing can befall me in life." The
                            drawing illuminates Cranch’s process of ethical growth, and the
                            attainment of a less restrained self. He arrives at Emerson’s "new
                            philosophy" of unmitigated delight and poetic exhilaration after
                            starting with Wordsworth’s line to "see into the life of things" and
                            Carlyle’s <hi rend="italic">work and action</hi>. He approached
                            Emerson’s passage with some irony: in a thought about losing oneself in
                            the presence of the natural world, and attempting a direct relation with
                            the Divine Presence (or the Over-Soul, as he would later call it),
                            Cranch headed the drawing with the full name of the figure portrayed
                            below, "Ralph Waldo Emerson." Miller rightly points out that Cranch
                            caricatured "in the days of Thomas Nast when the practice of caricature
                            was frequently vicious and underhanded and always caustic," so Cranch
                            took pains to assure others that he meant no ridicule by the
                                drawings.<note type="editorial" resp="#cmo">Miller, <hi
                                    rend="italic">Cranch and His Caricatures</hi>, 51.</note> Here
                            again modesty plays a role, for Cranch probably obliterated the Emerson
                            inscription so as not to seem too disrespectful to his forerunner.
                            Comparing two versions of this drawing reveals some intriguing details:
                                <figure type="enlargeOnClick">
                                <head>Two versions of the "Transparent Eyeball" caricature: 1839
                                    "Journal" (left), <hi rend="italic">New Philosophy
                                        scrapbook</hi> (right).</head>
                                <p>Christopher P. Cranch journal, 1839. Page 10. Original Manuscript
                                    from the Christopher P. Cranch Papers. Massachusetts Historical
                                    Society; Christopher Pearse Cranch, 1813&#8211;1892. Illustrations of
                                    the New Philosophy: drawings, [ca. 1837&#8211;1839] (MS Am 1506).
                                    Houghton Library, Harvard University, Cambridge, Massachusetts.
                                    See the drawing (Image 4) at <ref type="url"
                                        target="http://nrs.harvard.edu/urn-3:FHCL.Hough:2317939"
                                        >http://nrs.harvard.edu/urn-3:FHCL.Hough:2317939</ref></p>
                                <graphic url="transparent_eyeball_comparison.jpg"/>
                                <figDesc>Christopher P. Cranch journal, 1839. Page 10. Original
                                    Manuscript from the Christopher P. Cranch Papers. Massachusetts
                                    Historical Society; Cranch, Christopher Pearse, 1813&#8211;1892.
                                    Illustrations of the New Philosophy: drawings,
                                    [ca. 1837&#8211;1839] (MS Am 1506). Houghton Library, Harvard
                                    University, Cambridge, Massachusetts. See the drawing (Image 4)
                                    at <ref type="url"
                                        target="http://nrs.harvard.edu/urn-3:FHCL.Hough:2317939"
                                    />http://nrs.harvard.edu/urn-3:FHCL.Hough:2317939</figDesc>
                            </figure> The original draft lacks the tails on the coat, the details of
                            the town in the valley, and perhaps a pair of trousers.<note
                                type="editorial" resp="#cmo">Another version of the "Transparent
                                Eyeball" sketch is housed in the Joel Myerson Collection of American
                                Literature at the University of South Carolina. It resembles the
                                original draft more than the Houghton copy, suggesting that the
                                Myerson sketch is the middle phase of Cranch’s revisions to the
                                drawing. The Concord Library has featured an image of the sketch in
                                the Myerson collection: <ref type="url"
                                    target="http://www.concordlibrary.org/scollect/CT/70.html"
                                    >http://www.concordlibrary.org/scollect/CT/70.html</ref>
                            </note> It also features a decidedly different gaze: whereas Clarke’s
                            copy has a clear upward gaze, perhaps indicating the idealism intended
                            in the passage, the original has the eyeball staring straight ahead, and
                            the right foot appears to be lifting itself, about to walk. The
                            unfinished business of Cranch’s travels out West suggests an uneasy
                            perpetual motion, and Cranch’s own struggles seem to shine through much
                            better in the original draft. Here again Cranch shows his sensitivity to
                            his forbearers: the vacant gaze of the walking eyeball recalls Milton’s
                            thoughts on blankness in <hi rend="italic">Paradise Lost</hi>:
                                    <quote><lg type="poem">
                                    <l>But cloud in stead, and ever-during dark</l>
                                    <l>Surrounds me, from the chearful wayes of men</l>
                                    <l>Cut off, and for the Book of knowledg fair</l>
                                    <l>Presented with a Universal blanc</l>
                                    <l>Of Natures works to mee expung’d and ras’d,</l>
                                    <l>And wisdome at one entrance quite shut out. (Book III, lines
                                        45&#8211;50)<note type="editorial" resp="#cmo">Milton, <hi rend="italic"
                                        >Paradise Lost</hi>, 417</note></l>
                                </lg></quote> Coleridge's
                            interpretation of the "Universal blanc" shows in his "Dejection"
                            ode&#8212;"And still I gaze&#8212;and with how blank an eye! / And those
                            thin clouds above, in flakes and bars, / That give away their motion to
                            the stars" (which is more attuned to Virgil’s <hi rend="italic">lacrimae
                                rerum</hi>)&#8212;and Wordsworth’s "Immortality Ode" shows how the
                            "Blank misgivings" lead to the sight of the immortal sea. Emerson’s
                            understanding of Wordsworth's and Coleridge's readings of blankness in
                                <hi rend="italic">Nature</hi> culminates in the phrase that "The
                            ruin or the blank, that we see when we look at nature, is in our own
                                eye."<note type="editorial" resp="#cmo"><hi rend="italic">CW</hi>,
                                1:43.</note> This shows how the "gentle shock of mild surprise"
                            allows us to see into the life of things.<note type="editorial"
                                resp="#cmo">See also Keane, <hi rend="italic">Emerson, Romanticism,
                                    and Intuitive Reason</hi>, 208.</note> The final, most
                            frequently cited Cranch drawing of the eyeball in Clarke’s scrapbook is
                            a more mature rendering of the spirit of Emerson’s idea: the eyeball is
                            about to lose himself in the clouds. Cranch’s original draft, however,
                            with the blank eye staring straight ahead, implies that he is still on
                            his way. Toward the end of the "Journal" (page 21), Cranch, having left
                            the comforts of home life, curiously says that he is "once more <hi
                                rend="underline">be mistered</hi>," which suggests his attentiveness
                            to blurred vision, the <hi rend="italic">bemisting</hi> of his
                            spirit.<note type="editorial"
                                resp="#cmo">See the <hi rend="italic">Oxford English
                                    Dictionary</hi>, entry for "bemist": 1. "To overtake with, or
                                involve in mist; fig. to confuse the senses of, bepuzzle, bewilder,"
                                as well as the sense of "becloud" in 2.</note></p>
                        <p>The "Corn and Melons" draft alongside Clarke’s copy in the <hi
                                rend="italic">New Philosophy scrapbook</hi> indicates the same
                            optimism in the former sketch: "I have no hostility to nature, but a
                            child’s love to it. I expand and live in the warm day like corn and
                            melons."<note type="editorial" resp="#cmo"><hi rend="italic">CW</hi>,
                                1:35.</note> While the "Corn and Melons" drawings do not exhibit
                            the striking differences between the "Transparent Eyeball," they still
                            show different gazes: in the first draft the eyes are once again turned
                            downward, looking content; the later iteration has a more stern face
                            looking slightly upward. <figure type="enlargeOnClick">
                                <head>Two versions of the "Corn and Melons" caricature: "Journal.
                                    1839." (left), <hi rend="italic">New Philosophy scrapbook</hi>
                                    (right).</head>
                                <p>Christopher P. Cranch journal, 1839. Page 11. Original Manuscript
                                    from the Christopher P. Cranch Papers. Massachusetts Historical
                                    Society; Christopher Pearse Cranch, 1813-1892. Illustrations of
                                    the New Philosophy: drawings, [ca.1837&#8211;1839] (MS Am 1506).
                                    Houghton Library, Harvard University, Cambridge, Massachusetts.
                                    See the drawing at <ref type="url"
                                        target="http://nrs.harvard.edu/urn-3:FHCL.Hough:2317938"
                                    >http://nrs.harvard.edu/urn-3:FHCL.Hough:2317938</ref></p>
                                <graphic url="corn_and_melons_comparison.jpg"/>
                                <figDesc>Christopher P. Cranch journal, 1839. Page 11. Original
                                    Manuscript from the Christopher P. Cranch Papers. Massachusetts
                                    Historical Society; Cranch, Christopher Pearse, 1813-1892.
                                    Illustrations of the New Philosophy: drawings,
                                    [ca.1837&#8211;1839] (MS Am 1506). Houghton Library, Harvard
                                    University, Cambridge, Massachusetts. See the drawing at <ref
                                        type="url"
                                        target="http://nrs.harvard.edu/urn-3:FHCL.Hough:2317939"
                                        >http://nrs.harvard.edu/urn-3:FHCL.Hough:2317939</ref></figDesc>
                            </figure> Miller suggests that the figure’s round head makes it unlikely
                            to be a representation of Emerson (unlike the "Transparent Eyeball" and
                            "Almost I fear to think how glad I am!" drawings)&#8212;so it is at once
                            a more respectful rendering of Emerson as well as a clue that Cranch
                            understood the thrust of the passage: man and vegetable, vegetable and
                            man, are part of the same underlying unity.<note type="editorial"
                                resp="#cmo">Miller, <hi rend="italic">Cranch and His
                                    Caricatures</hi>, 43.</note> The companion piece to the "Corn
                            and Melons" drawing is a vegetable with the face of a man, so Cranch
                            incorporates both the idealism and the commonsense materialism of
                            Emerson’s passage in the closing paragraph in <hi rend="italic"
                                >Nature</hi>.<note type="editorial" resp="#cmo">The companion
                                drawing on the frontispiece of the <hi rend="italic">New
                                    Philosophy</hi> scrapbook can be accessed at <ref type="url"
                                    target="http://nrs.harvard.edu/urn-3:FHCL.Hough:2317937"
                                    >http://nrs.harvard.edu/urn-3:FHCL.Hough:2317937</ref></note>
                            With the full context of Emerson’s passages and Cranch’s "Journal"
                            considered, these two drawings suggest his sympathy with Emerson's
                            thought and a humorous tolerance of escapism. While both drawings depict
                            vision and growth, vision clearly underlies the changes made from draft
                            to revised scraps: seeing into the life of things meant to embrace the
                            "doctrine that man is one," not to take himself too seriously, and not
                            to blindly follow any dogma, whether religious or philosophical.</p>
                        <p>Soon afterward Cranch abandoned doing caricatures. On February 12, 1841,
                            he wrote Dwight from Bangor, Maine, that "I use the pencil not for
                            comical subjects or devils&#8212;I am out of that vein&#8212;but in
                            landscape sketching."<note type="editorial" resp="#cmo">Quoted in Scott,
                                    <hi rend="italic">Life and Letters</hi>, 69.</note> Even if he
                            did not caricature for long, his drawings took fresh eyes to Emerson.
                            Cranch’s playfulness makes him a unique, more subtle thinker amidst a
                            philosophical school that might be criticized for being too abstract,
                            mystical, anti-intellectual, and optimistic. These caricatures expand
                            the historical account of transcendentalism into a multifarious
                                aesthetic.<note type="editorial" resp="#cmo">This is not to neglect
                                the extensive exhibit on Cranch's transcendentalist landscapes,
                                titled "At Home and Abroad," which was held at the Lyman Allyn Art
                                Museum in New London, Connecticut (2007–8). The exhibition
                                catalogue, to which scholars such as David Robinson, Nancy Stula,
                                Barbara Novak, and Joel Myerson made contributions, is a good
                                starting point for studying Cranch's visual sense.</note> A volume
                            dedicated to his neglected paintings would add to his small literary
                            reputation, showing how he transformed a transcendentalist poetic
                            sensibility into the Hudson River school of painting.</p>
                    </div>
                    <div>
                        <head type="main">Editorial Principles</head>
                        <p>Cranch fashioned the journal book, initially consisting of sixteen sheets
                            (21 1/2 x 28 cm), into quarto segments and expanded it to thirty leaves.
                            The resulting sixty-page soft cover notebook was bound with a gray cover
                            of heavy stock paper and stitched at the fold with string. The journal
                            survives in fifteen manuscript leaves, with handwritten text in pen on
                            thirty pages (and six of those pages cut away) housed at the
                            Massachusetts Historical Society.</p>
                        <p>My primary purpose is to provide a diplomatic transcription of each
                            manuscript page that preserves most of the stylistic characteristics of
                            this important piece of documentary evidence. Dedmond's transcription is
                            not entirely faithful to the manuscript, leaving out aspects such as
                            cancellations, insertions, line breaks, and false starts, among other
                            things. His transcription also does not distinguish single- and
                            double-underlined words (and his decision to italicize both kinds of
                            underlining disregards Cranch's varying emphases). Against Tanselle's
                            principles, Dedmond's work "is altering the nature of the document and
                            is obscuring evidence of potential significance for interpreting the
                            author's state of mind and motivation."<note type="editorial"
                                resp="#cmo">G. Thomas Tanselle, "Textual Scholarship," in <hi
                                    rend="italic">Introduction to Scholarship in Modern Languages
                                    and Literatures</hi>, ed. Joseph Gibaldi (New York: Modern
                                Language Association, 1981), 34.</note> For this transcription I use
                            the "plain text" rationale of the Mark Twain Project's letters edition,
                            that "the editor essentially defines what is possible by deciding what
                            can be transcribed legibly," and creates a critical text by making
                            decisions about how the newly created text will differ from the
                                document.<note type="editorial" resp="#cmo">See Tanselle, "Textual
                                Scholarship," 32 and 47; and the Mark Twain Project's "Guide to
                                Editorial Practice," <ref type="url"
                                    target="http://www.marktwainproject.org/xtf/view?docId=letters/MTDP00005.xml;brand=mtp;style=letter"
                                >http://www.marktwainproject.org/xtf/view?docId=letters/MTDP00005.xml;brand=mtp;style=letter</ref></note>
                            While the diplomatic transcription has retained as many textual
                            features&#8212;line breaks, hyphenation, punctuation, variant spellings,
                            and abbreviations&#8212;as possible in the source text, it was not
                            possible to record all nuances. I did not render the ornamentation on
                            the cover of the "Journal," because a high-resolution facsimile of the
                            original is available, which does more work than an attempt at
                            replicating the border in the transcription. See also, for example, the
                            horizontal rule on page 19 of the edition that appears to morph into
                            leaves, which reflects Cranch's interest in visual art and the natural
                            world. The transcription follows Tanselle's principles of documentary
                            editing&#8212;namely, to transcribe the document as faithfully as
                            possible&#8212;while also adopting the plain text approach to critical
                            editing, which gives the editor the impetus to decide what ought to be
                            transcribed. This edition omits the notes in pencil (in the form of "X"
                            marks and "use" notes), because they were probably written by Scott as
                            she compiled notes for her biography.<note type="editorial" resp="#cmo"
                                >See in particular Jerome McGann's "extrapolation" of Tanselle's
                                plea for more accurate documentary editing in "The Socialization of
                                Texts" in <bibl><hi rend="italic">The Textual Condition</hi>
                                    (Princeton: Princeton University Press, 1991),
                                    69&#8211;87</bibl>. While I agree with McGann and McKenzie on
                                the importance of visual and non-linguistic components of texts,
                                Cranch's "Journal" stands outside of "the full range of social
                                realities" that "directs us to consider the human motives and
                                interactions which texts involve at every stage of their production,
                                transmission, and consumption," because the "Journal" consists of
                                the author's private papers, which were not originally meant to be
                                transmitted and consumed, so my purpose is primarily documentary (D.
                                F. McKenzie, <title>Bibliography and the Sociology of Texts</title>
                                [Cambridge: Cambridge University Press, 1999], 15). See also
                                Tanselle's <bibl>"Textual Criticism and Literary Sociology,"
                                        <title>Studies in Bibliography</title> 44 (1991): 129n70,
                                    142–43.</bibl></note> As these marks do not aid in the
                            legibility of the transcription, they are excluded as corruptions of the
                            manuscript.</p>
                        <p>The document presented some transcription issues. The first involves
                            Cranch's use of dashes. Because this is a journal not intended for
                            publication, Cranch did not seem to engage in systematic dash-writing;
                            instead, he used them frequently as arbitrary pauses (and sometimes full
                            stops). This is not unusual for a nineteenth-century writer, but it
                            bears explaining here that every dash was treated in the transcription
                            as an em-dash (as that was probably Cranch's intended effect), and that
                            sometimes it is unclear whether some horizontal markings were meant to
                            be dashes or full stops.</p>
                        <p>I also did not choose to modernize and normalize the text.<note
                                type="editorial">Dedmond silently modernized his text&#8212;e.g.,
                                his changing of Cranch's "shew" into "show."</note> For example, I
                            retained capitalized nouns: as a nineteenth-century writer, Cranch
                            frequently capitalized nouns, and I see no reason to change, for
                            example, "Spirit" to lower case, especially as it is not consistently
                            capitalized in the journal. I also retained minor oddities in Cranch's
                            word usage, mostly concerning his compounds ("vestry room" versus
                            "vestryroom" on pages 12 and 14, and "newyear" on page 2). In some
                            cases, it appears that two words may be blended together (such as "of
                            mind" on page 3), but Cranch sometimes made a continuous stroke of the
                            pen after ending a word with an "f," and it seems unlikely that he meant
                            those words to be compounded. Cranch also inconsistently dotted (and in
                            one or two cases encircled) page numbers; it is not clear if those pages
                            were meant to be more important than the unmarked ones, but these
                            features were retained in the diplomatic transcription.</p>
                        <p>As for the few abbreviations Cranch used (e.g., "wh" for "which" and
                            "shd" for "should"), I have left the words as seen on the page and coded
                            them with <hi rend="bold">abbr</hi> tags. Since Cranch did not engage in
                            widespread or eccentric abbreviating, I saw little justification to
                            include accompanying <hi rend="bold">expan</hi> tags. The reading text,
                            however, does expand some of the abbreviations that may be
                            confusing.</p>
                        <p>Some words are unclear or scribbled hastily and difficult to identify
                            with full confidence; a search of the accompanying XML file will show
                            which words are unclear and which have high or low certainty values. In
                            the edition unclear words are colored gray. </p>
                        <p>From the diplomatic transcription I have also established a new reading
                            text for the purposes of making this the standard text for American
                            literature researchers and students.</p>
                        <p>My principle regarding endnotes is to focus on contextual and
                            intertextual instances that provide clarification of Cranch’s journey
                            and intellectual development (i.e., context for understanding a major
                            person or clarifying the subject of a given passage). As Cranch was
                            steeped in the thoughts of Carlyle, Emerson, and the German romantics,
                            among others, I considered it important to gloss instances in the
                            "Journal" where he echoes or quotes from those writers. In most cases, I
                            did not choose to put biographical information in endnotes; instead,
                            that information is encoded within <hi rend="bold">persName</hi> tags in
                            the XML document (with the more prominent names and relevant information
                            included within the TEI header under <hi rend="bold">listPerson</hi>
                            tags) and featured in the edition as optional hyperlinked notes separate
                            from the endnotes. Some persons mentioned in the edition did not recieve notes,
                            either because they were not essential to understanding the edition
                            (e.g., Bertha Wood's sister Kate) or because they simply could not be
                            identified (e.g., Mr. Lynch). Because I envisage a readership here that
                            would know such literary luminaries as Wordsworth and Carlyle, it was
                            also not necessary to provide elaborate notes on them (but I still find
                            that birth and death dates are helpful).</p>
                        <p>As I indicate in the edition, the manuscript was altered: starting with
                            the April 18 entry, three pages are cut in half or cut in thirds, and a
                            total of fifteen leaves are entirely cut out. For each instance of excision I
                            explain how much of the page was taken out, and whether or not the
                            excised page or leaf contained writing in Cranch's hand, but I did not
                            choose to transcribe the letters (and portions of letters) in the
                            gutters of the excised pages because it would not aid in the
                            intelligibility of the transcription. I hope that providing the
                            manuscript images will satisfy the curiosity of those who wish to
                            investigate the missing pages. The group of excised leaves nevertheless
                            remains one of the most enigmatic aspects of the manuscript. We can
                            never know who altered the journal, though it seems unlikely that Cranch
                            did it himself: out of the five boxes of manuscript material, this journal
                            is the only one that is altered in like fashion. </p>
                    </div>
                    <div>
                        <head type="main">Acknowledgments</head>
                        <p>My thanks go to the Office of the Dean of the College of Liberal Arts and
                            Sciences at the University of Maine, which provided financial support
                            for the digitization of Cranch’s "Journal"; Amanda Gailey and Andrew
                            Jewell, editors of <hi rend="italic">Scholarly Editing</hi>, as well as
                            my peer reviewers, for their helpful comments; Dr. Marcia Karp and
                            Professor Christopher Ricks, both of whom commented on an
                            early version of this project; Professor Steven Olsen-Smith, who helped
                            me with my proposal and with moral and intellectual support; Rob
                            Velella, of the Longfellow
                            House in Cambridge, who commented on a draft of the edition, and
                            led me to Cranch’s grave at Mount Auburn Cemetery (which does not list
                            Cranch's grave as one of its prominent attractions); Professor Robert Brinkley, my colleague when I was at the
                            University of Maine, who commented on the introduction and
                            provided essential expertise to the Wordsworth and Coleridge
                            connections; and finally, pride of last place to Jillian Saucier, who
                            commented on this introduction and engaged in many conversations
                            about Cranch.</p>
                    </div>
                </div>
            </div>
        </body>
    </text>
</TEI>
