<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<?oxygen RNGSchema="http://www.scholarlyediting.org/scholarlyediting.rng" type="xml"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
    <teiHeader>
        <fileDesc>
            <titleStmt>
                <title type="main">About <hi rend="italic">Scholarly Editing</hi></title>
                <title type="sub">electronic edition</title>
                <principal xml:id="awj">Jewell, Andrew, 1975-</principal>
                <principal xml:id="ag">Gailey, Amanda, 1976-</principal>
            </titleStmt>
            <editionStmt>
                <edition>
                    <date when="2014">2014</date>
                </edition>
            </editionStmt><publicationStmt>
                <idno type="file">se.about</idno>
                <authority>Scholarly Editing: The Annual of the Association for Documentary
                    Editing</authority>
                <address>
                    <addrLine>http://www.scholarlyediting.org</addrLine>
                </address>
                <publisher>Association for Documentary Editing</publisher>
                <publisher>University of Nebraska&#8211;Lincoln</publisher>
                <distributor>
                    <name>Center for Digital Research in the Humanities</name>
                    <address>
                        <addrLine>319 Love Library</addrLine>
                        <addrLine>University of Nebraska&#8211;Lincoln</addrLine>
                        <addrLine>Lincoln, NE 68588-4100</addrLine>
                        <addrLine>http://cdrh.unl.edu</addrLine>
                    </address></distributor>
                <date>2011</date>
                <availability>
                    <p>Scholarly Editing: The Annual of the Association for Documentary Editing is
                        freely distributed by the Association for Documentary Editing and the Center
                        for Digital Research in the Humanities at the University of Nebraska-Lincoln
                        and licensed under a Creative Commons Attribution-NonCommercial-ShareAlike
                        3.0 Unported License</p>
                </availability>
            </publicationStmt><sourceDesc>
                <bibl>
                    <note>Born digital.</note>
                </bibl>
            </sourceDesc></fileDesc>
        <encodingDesc>
            <projectDesc>
                <p>Text created for online distribution in Scholarly Editing: The Annual of the
                    Association for Documentary Editing (http://www.scholarlyediting.org).</p>
            </projectDesc>
        </encodingDesc>
        <revisionDesc>
            <change when="2014-07-22" who="#awj">Added language about rights</change>
            <change when="2014-03-31" who="#awj">Altered due dates to reflect current CFP</change>
            <change when="2011-04-15" who="#awj">Initial Creation</change>
        </revisionDesc>
    </teiHeader>
    <text>
        <body>
            <div><head type="main">Editorial Staff</head>
                <list type="bulleted"><item>Editors: <ref type="email" target="gailey@unl.edu">Amanda Gailey</ref> and <ref type="email" target="ajewell2@unl.edu">Andrew Jewell</ref></item>
                    <item>Reviews Editor: W. Bland Whitley</item>
                    <item>Editorial Assistant: Gabi Kirilloff</item>
                    <item>Editorial Contributors: Karin Dalziel, Keith Nickum, and Laura Weakly, <ref type="url" target="http://cdrh.unl.edu">Center for Digital Research in the Humanities, University of Nebraska-Lincoln</ref></item>
                    <item>Copyeditor (starting with 2013 issue): Lona Dearmont</item></list>
            </div>
            <div>
                <head type="main">Background</head>
                <p>Since 1979, <hi rend="italic">Documentary Editing</hi> has been a premier journal
                    in the field of documentary and textual editing. Beginning with the 2012 issue,
                        <hi rend="italic">Documentary Editing</hi> has been renamed <hi
                        rend="italic">Scholarly Editing: The Annual of the Association for
                        Documentary Editing</hi> and has become an open-access, digital publication.
                    While retaining the familiar content of the print journal, including
                    peer-reviewed essays about editorial theory and practice, the 2012 issue of <hi
                        rend="italic">Scholarly Editing </hi>is the first to publish peer-reviewed
                    editions.</p>
            </div>
            <div><head type="main">An Open-Access Journal</head>
                <p><hi rend="italic">Scholarly Editing</hi> is committed to being an open-access journal. We publish all content under a 
                    <ref type="url" target="http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by-nc-sa/3.0/">Creative Commons
                            Attribution-NonCommercial-ShareAlike 3.0 Unported License</ref>, and contributors retain all rights to their original content. For each of our editions, we provide access not only to the user interface developed for web publication, but also to the XML file which contains the core metadata for the edition.</p>
                    </div>
            <div>
                <head type="main">A Note on Peer Review</head>
                <p>All editions and articles published in <hi rend="italic">Scholarly Editing: The
                        Annual of the Association for Documentary Editing</hi> are rigorously
                    reviewed by at least two experts in their respective fields. Articles follow a
                    standard blind review process, but editions must pass through a somewhat more
                    involved process. The journal editors select promising editions from submitted
                    proposals and work with each project's editor(s) to put the edition online at an
                    unpublished URL. The edition is then sent for review to two experts in its field
                    who review its content and editorial soundness. The reviewers anonymously
                    recommend that the edition be accepted as-is, accepted with revisions, revised
                    and resubmitted, or rejected. Those that are accepted as-is or require only
                    specific revisions are then finalized and published in <hi rend="italic"
                        >Scholarly Editing: The Annual of the Association for Documentary
                        Editing</hi>.</p>
            </div>
            <div>
                <head type="main">Call for Editions</head>
                <p>We believe that many scholars have discovered fascinating texts that deserve to
                    be carefully edited and published, and we offer a venue to turn these
                    discoveries into sustainable, peer-reviewed publications that will enrich the
                    digital record of our cultural heritage.</p>
                <p>If you are interested in editing a small-scale digital edition of a single
                    document or a collection of documents, we want to hear from you.</p>
            </div>
            <div>
                <head type="main">Proposals</head>
                <p>We invite proposals for rigorously edited digital small-scale editions. Proposals
                    should be approximately 1000 words long and should include the following
                    information:</p>
                <list>
                    <item><hi rend="bold">A description of content, scope, and approach.</hi> Please
                        describe the materials you will edit and how you will approach editing and
                        commenting on them. A well-researched apparatus (an introduction,
                        annotations, etc.) will be key to most successful proposals.</item>
                    <item><hi rend="bold">A statement of significance.</hi> Please briefly explain
                        how this edition will contribute to your field.</item>
                    <item>
                        <hi rend="bold">Approximate length.</hi>
                    </item>
                    <item><hi rend="bold">Indication of technical proficiency.</hi> With only rare
                        exceptions, any edition published by <hi rend="italic">Scholarly
                            Editing</hi> must be in XML (Extensible Markup Language) that complies
                        with TEI (Text Encoding Initiative) Guidelines, which have been widely
                        accepted as the de facto standard for digital textual editing. Please
                        indicate your facility with TEI or explain why another technical approach
                        makes better sense for your work.</item>
                    <item><hi rend="bold">A brief description of how you imagine the materials
                            should be visually represented.</hi>
                        <hi rend="italic">Scholarly Editing</hi> will provide support to display
                        images and text in an attractive house style. If you wish to create a highly
                        customized display, please describe it and indicate what technologies you
                        plan to use to build it.</item>
                </list>
            </div>
            <div>
                <p>All contributors to <hi rend="italic">Scholarly Editing: The Annual of the
                        Association for Documentary Editing</hi> are strongly encouraged to be
                    members of the Association for Documentary Editing, an organization dedicated to
                    the theory and practice of documentary and textual editing. To become a member,
                    go to <ref type="url" target="http://www.documentaryediting.org"
                        >www.documentaryediting.org</ref>.</p>
                <p>Please send proposals as Rich Text Format (RTF), MS Word, or PDF to the editors
                    via email (<ref type="email" target="gailey@unl.edu">gailey@unl.edu</ref>, <ref type="email" target="ajewell2@unl.edu">ajewell2@unl.edu</ref>). Proposals for editions for the 2016 issue are due by May 15, 2015.</p>
            </div>
            <div>
                <head type="main">Call for Articles</head>
                <p><hi rend="italic">Scholarly Editing</hi> welcomes submissions of articles
                    discussing any aspect of the theory or practice of editing, print or digital.
                    Please send submissions via email to the editors and
                    include the following information in the body of your email:</p>
                <list>
                    <item>Names, contact information, and institutional affiliations of all
                        authors</item>
                    <item>Title of the article</item>
                    <item>Filename of article</item>
                </list>
                <p>Please omit all identifying information from the article itself. Send proposals
                    as Rich Text Format (RTF), MS Word, or PDF; if you wish to include image files
                    or other addenda, please send all as a single zip archive. For questions of
                    style and citation format, please consult the current edition of <hi
                        rend="italic">The Chicago Manual of Style</hi>.</p>
                <p>If you wish your submission to be considered for the "Reflections on the Editor's Craft" feature, please indicate that in your email.</p> <p>Submissions for the 2015 issue are due by September 14, 2015. Please, no simultaneous submissions.</p>
                <p>Thank you,</p>
                <closer>
                    <address>
                        <addrLine>Amanda Gailey</addrLine>
                        <addrLine>Department of English </addrLine>
                        <addrLine>Center for Digital Research in the Humanities</addrLine>
                        <addrLine>University of Nebraska-Lincoln </addrLine>
                        <addrLine>
                            <ref type="email" target="gailey@unl.edu">gailey@unl.edu</ref>
                        </addrLine>
                    </address>
                    <address>
                        <addrLine>Andrew Jewell</addrLine>
                        <addrLine>University Libraries</addrLine>
                        <addrLine>Center for Digital Research in the Humanities</addrLine>
                        <addrLine>University of Nebraska-Lincoln</addrLine>
                        <addrLine>
                            <ref type="email" target="ajewell2@unl.edu">ajewell2@unl.edu</ref>
                        </addrLine>
                    </address>
                </closer>
            </div>
        </body>
    </text>
</TEI>
