<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
  <teiHeader xml:lang="eng"><!-- this XML contains the translation into English of the non-English text in the transcription; the alignment is contained in the document BinyonDestree.original.translation.xml; this document uses the identical TEI header as BinyonDestree.original.xml -->
    <fileDesc>
      <titleStmt>
        <title level="m" type="main">The correspondence between Laurence Binyon and Olivier-Georges Destrée as a case of transnational literary networks around 1900</title>
        <author>Laurence Binyon</author>
        <author>Olivier-Georges Destrée</author>
        <editor>Eloise Forestier</editor>
        <editor>Gero Guttzeit</editor>
        <editor>Marysa Demoor</editor>
        <respStmt>
          <resp>Transcription, edition, annotation, translation and encoding</resp>
          <name xml:id="ef">Eloise Forestier</name>
          <name xml:id="gg">Gero Guttzeit</name>
          <name xml:id="md">Marysa Demoor</name>
        </respStmt>
      </titleStmt>
      <editionStmt>
        <edition>
          <date>2016</date>
        </edition>
      </editionStmt>
      <publicationStmt>
        <idno type="file"><!-- Name of XML file --></idno>
        <!-- You will only need to use the following idno if you are creating an edition -->
        <idno type="edition"><!-- Edition name --></idno>
        <authority>Scholarly Editing: The Annual of the Association for Documentary
          Editing</authority>
        <address>
          <addrLine>http://www.scholarlyediting.org</addrLine>
        </address>
        <publisher>Association for Documentary Editing</publisher>
        <publisher>University of Nebraska&#8211;Lincoln</publisher>
        <distributor>
          <name>Center for Digital Research in the Humanities</name>
          <address>
            <addrLine>319 Love Library</addrLine>
            <addrLine>University of Nebraska&#8211;Lincoln</addrLine>
            <addrLine>Lincoln, NE 68588-4100</addrLine>
            <addrLine>http://cdrh.unl.edu</addrLine>
          </address>
        </distributor>
        <date><!-- Year --></date>
        <availability>
          <p>Scholarly Editing: The Annual of the Association for Documentary Editing is
            freely distributed by the Association for Documentary Editing and the Center for
            Digital Research in the Humanities at the University of Nebraska-Lincoln and
            licensed under a Creative Commons Attribution-NonCommercial-ShareAlike 3.0
            Unported License</p>
        </availability>
      </publicationStmt>
      <seriesStmt>
        <title level="j">Scholarly Editing: The Annual of the Association for Documentary
          Editing</title>
        <respStmt>
          <resp>editor</resp>
          <name xml:id="ag">Amanda Gailey</name>
        </respStmt>
        <respStmt>
          <resp>editor</resp>
          <name xml:id="awj">Andrew Jewell</name>
        </respStmt>
        <idno type="vol"><!-- The Journal's volume number --></idno>
        <idno type="ISSN">2167-1257</idno>
      </seriesStmt>
      <sourceDesc>
        <bibl>
          <author>Laurence Binyon</author>
          <author>Olivier-Georges Destrée</author>
          <title>Archive of Laurence Binyon</title>
          <idno type="callno">Loan MS 103/1-77</idno>
          <orgName>
            British Library
          </orgName>
          <title>Letters from Binyon to Destrée</title>
          <idno type="callno">no call no</idno>
          <orgName>
            Library of the Benedictine Abbey of Mont-César at Louvain
          </orgName>
          <note type="project">Transcribed from the original manuscript, then annotated and encoded in XML.
          </note>            
        </bibl>
      </sourceDesc>
    </fileDesc>
  </teiHeader>
  <text>
    <front><!-- front matter of copy text, if any, goes here --></front>
  <body>
    <p>
    <s xml:id="s1">Dearest friend.</s>
    <s xml:id="s2">Your letter gave me much pleasure because your arrival here seems almost a certainty.</s>
    <s xml:id="s3">And to make quite sure of it I hasten my answer to your letter with precise details.</s>
    <s xml:id="s4">You have quite enough with 20 pounds and even more than enough as you will see.</s>
    <s xml:id="s5">The return journey with an excursion in Pisa or even more excursions if you take a circular ticket costs I believe about 10 pounds – no more.</s>
    <s xml:id="s6">You will then have 10 pounds left.</s>
    <s xml:id="s7">That is 250 frcs.</s>
    <s xml:id="s8">You will find here on the Piazza del Duomo in front of the Giotto Campanile – the nardini pension where I have often stayed and whose price is 5 fcs a day service included – so 2 weeks adds up to 70 frcs - a generous reckoning, with coffees and museum entrance fees, may amount to let us say 100 frcs for your two weeks here – you still have 150 frcs left for excursions – 
Now if at Nardini you only pay for lodgings and breakfast as I used to do and if you dine in the best restaurant in Florence at Mellini, which is more entertaining and which I was doing only a few weeks ago – I reckon that it will be a little bit more expensive with 150 instead of 100 frcs.</s>
    <s xml:id="s9">But even in that case you still have 100 frcs left over – which you may devote to going on excursions, with me I hope.</s>
    <s xml:id="s10">So you are coming – dear Laurence – and the dream we had made up of being reunited over here will then become true.</s>
    <s xml:id="s11">The only thing I will ask if it is possible for you would be to move up your journey;</s>
    <s xml:id="s12">if you can it would be better for me;</s>
    <s xml:id="s13">but if it is not possible for you it doesn’t matter.</s>
    <s xml:id="s14">I am happy to know you are at work on a big poem and I hope the final result will be as beautiful as the 4 verses that you sent me and that are so clear and evocative.</s>
    <s xml:id="s15">As to me I have been working for the last week on my poem of the Three Wise Men which I told you about in England I believe.</s>
    <s xml:id="s16">I left the centre of Florence for a more peaceful place and have moved into this quiet and charming little apartment 77 via niccolo Machiavelli (Florence) – at the foot of the hills of San Domenico and Fiegoli.</s>
    <s xml:id="s17">When you will come all the flowers will be in bloom and it will be the best time to see this wonderful city.</s>
    <s xml:id="s18">My poem, which swells in my mind to the size of an entire volume, will be I hope at least half the size, and I will be delighted to read you here some chapters from it and hear your opinion.</s>
    <s xml:id="s19">Now I must get back to work because half the morning has already gone by and I work the most regularly from 10 to 5.</s>
    <s xml:id="s20">So dear Laurence see you soon, that is here, we will converse at our ease and resume our strolls and excursions together.</s>
    <s xml:id="s21">My best wishes to you and Image.</s>
    <s xml:id="s22">O. Georges Destree</s>
    <s xml:id="s23">About Image and since we spoke business or money at the beginning of this letter – when you see him ask him please if one of the volumes I suggested to him would suit Elkin Matthews.</s>
    <s xml:id="s24">Image will explain to you what it is about.</s>
    <s xml:id="s25">You will then be able to see for yourself if such a volume could please Matthews and if you do so, I will ask you to suggest it to him yourself and tell me when you write back what Matthews will have answered.</s>
    <s xml:id="s26">Thank you very much O. GD</s>
    <s xml:id="s27">PS Horne is well, working a lot and his volume on Botticelli will be I think a model of its kind.</s>
    </p>

  
  </body>
</text>
    
</TEI>
