<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<?oxygen RNGSchema="http://www.scholarlyediting.org/scholarlyediting.rng" type="xml"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xml:lang="eng">
    <teiHeader>
        <fileDesc>
            <titleStmt>
                <title level="a" type="main">This Editing Life: The Joys and Imperatives of
                    Documentary Editing</title>
                <title level="a" type="sub">Presidential Address Association for Documentary Editing
                    Annual Meeting Ann Arbor, Michigan, 2013 </title>
                <author key="Chase, Phil">Phil Chase</author>
            </titleStmt>
            <editionStmt>
                <edition>
                    <date>2014</date>
                </edition>
            </editionStmt>
            <publicationStmt>
                <idno type="file">essay.2014presidentialaddress</idno>
                <authority>Scholary Editing: The Annual of the Association for Documentary
                    Editing</authority>
                <address>
 <addrLine>http://www.scholarlyediting.org</addrLine>
</address>
                <publisher>Association for Documentary Editing</publisher>
                <publisher>University of Nebraska&#8211;Lincoln</publisher>
                <distributor>
                    <name>Center for Digital Research in the Humanities</name>
                    <address>
<addrLine>319 Love Library</addrLine>
<addrLine>University of Nebraska&#8211;Lincoln</addrLine>
<addrLine>Lincoln, NE 68588-4100</addrLine>
<addrLine>http://cdrh.unl.edu</addrLine>
 </address>
                </distributor>
                <date>2014</date>
                <availability>
                    <p>Scholary Editing: The Annual of the Association for Documentary Editing is
                        freely distributed by the Association for Documentary Editing and the Center
                        for Digital Research in the Humanities at the University of Nebraska-Lincoln
                        and licensed under a Creative Commons Attribution-NonCommercial-ShareAlike
                        3.0 Unported License</p>
                </availability>
            </publicationStmt>
            <seriesStmt>
                <title level="j">Scholarly Editing: The Annual of the Association for Documentary
                    Editing</title>
                <respStmt>
                    <resp>editor</resp>
                    <name xml:id="ag" key="Gailey, Amanda A.">Amanda Gailey</name>
                </respStmt>
                <respStmt>
                    <resp>editor</resp>
                    <name xml:id="awj" key="Jewell, Andrew W.">Andrew Jewell</name>
                </respStmt>
                <idno type="vol">35</idno>
                <idno type="ISSN">2167-1257</idno>
            </seriesStmt>
            <sourceDesc>
                <bibl>
                    <note>Born digital.</note>
                </bibl>
            </sourceDesc>
        </fileDesc>
        <revisionDesc>
            <change when="2014-01-27"><name xml:id="gk" key="Kirilloff, Gabrielle">Gabrielle
                    Kirilloff</name> markup in TEI XML</change>
        </revisionDesc>
    </teiHeader>
    <text>
        <front>
            <head type="main">This Editing Life: The Joys and Imperatives of Documentary
                Editing</head>
            <head type="sub">Presidential Address</head>
            <head type="sub">Association for Documentary Editing Annual Meeting</head>
            <head type="sub">Ann Arbor, Michigan, 2013</head>

            <byline>Phil Chase</byline>
        </front>
        <body>
            <p>No young child, when asked what he or she wants to grow up to be, is likely to say "a
                documentary editor," unless, of course, the child has been brainwashed by a
                documentary editor parent or grandparent. Truth be told, few if any of us could have
                imagined becoming such a person when we received our undergraduate college degrees,
                even if we had known exactly what a documentary editor was. It’s a graduate school
                thing, and even there documentary editing often appears as an alternative career
                path, to which our attention is first drawn by the force of economic necessity in
                the face of a discouragingly soft academic job market. So it was with me.</p>

            <p>I first encountered modern documentary editing in graduate school at Duke University.
                I had gone there to work under John Richard Alden, because I was deeply interested
                in the writing of history, and I had been told by my undergraduate advisors that I
                could find no better mentor for my purpose. I was well advised. Alden was not only a
                superbly gifted prose writer in his own right, but also that rare sort of teacher
                who could make a good writer a much better one. He was also a renowned Revolutionary
                War scholar, a fact that had unintended but important consequences for me. If Alden
                had been in Chinese history, I might have become a sinologist. Instead I found
                myself happily studying early American history and by necessity immersed in those
                first gems of modern documentary editing: the papers of Thomas Jefferson, Benjamin
                Franklin, Alexander Hamilton, James Madison, and the Adamses. The volumes of those
                great editions were much newer and fewer in the mid-1960s, and, of course, they were
                available only in hot-lead print. The digital revolution lay far in the future.
                Those volumes were revolutionary nonetheless. The contrast between the new editions
                and the many older ones on which we still had to rely was especially vivid in those
                early days, and it had a big impact on me and many of my contemporaries. We became
                big fans of the new editions, and it was with considerable respect and a bit of awe
                that we wrote the names Boyd, Labaree, Syrett, Hutchinson, Rachal, and Butterfield
                in our bibliographies. But I had only the faintest inklings of how documentary
                editors did their work and none at all that I would ever become one.</p>

            <p>All of that was to come later, after the bottom had fallen out the academic job
                market and while I was persisting, nevertheless, in finishing my dissertation. It
                was a mountain that I was climbing because it was there. During the latter stages of
                my dissertation work, I not only used the Jefferson Papers extensively but also had
                an opportunity to consult the editor in person. One of my undergraduate professors
                had grown up with Julian Boyd, and through him it was arranged for me to talk with
                Boyd about my dissertation subject, the Prussian drillmaster Baron von Steuben.
                Steuben had locked horns more than a few times with Governor Thomas Jefferson during
                the Virginia campaign of 1781. Understandably Professor Boyd’s views of the baron,
                like Jefferson’s, were not warm and fuzzy, but his discussion of the documents that
                I was using gave me a better understanding of them. It was the next best thing to
                being able to interview Jefferson himself! Near the end of our conversation,
                Professor Boyd mentioned to me the one-year editing fellowships then being sponsored
                by the National Historical Publications Commission ("Records" had not yet been added
                to the commission’s name), and he suggested that I might think about applying for
                one. Unexpectedly, a golden opportunity had landed in my lap, but as such things
                usually go, it was some time before I realized it. The fellowship application
                deadline was several months in the future, and meantime I had a dissertation to
                finish.</p>

            <p>The application, when I at last got around to it, required among other things a
                one-page typed (yes, typed!) statement of why the applicant thought that he or she
                would benefit from the fellowship (obviously other than from the stipend). Having
                drafted and typed such a statement, I was proofreading it when it suddenly occurred
                to me: "This is very convincing! It even convinces me that this is what I should be
                doing!" Fortunately, those whose opinions really mattered—Don Jackson, editor of the
                Papers of George Washington, and Dorothy Twohig, the project’s associate editor,
                were also convinced enough to bring me to Charlottesville for a year that turned
                into thirty-five years of editing.</p>

            <p>Don and Dorothy’s training method was a simple but effective one: immediate total
                immersion in the work of the project. Work had just begun on Washington’s diaries,
                and I was assigned a year to edit: that wonderful, exciting year of 1771! But I was
                far from being on my own. In the crowded Washington Papers offices, I quickly
                learned that of the many things that characterize a successful documentary editing
                enterprise, one of the most important is collaboration. I learned much on a daily
                basis, not only from the editors but also from the transcribers and research
                assistants. Just as important, as I gained some experience, I was not only allowed
                but expected to contribute my two cents’ worth. We didn’t simply cooperate. We
                collaborated to the point where, after a passage of time, we often had trouble
                distinguishing who wrote what note. We consciously tried to develop what we thought
                of as the Washington Papers’ "voice."</p>

            <p> Of course, in those early years of the project, we all were learning how to edit the
                Washington Papers. In that regard, starting with the diaries was highly educational
                in many ways. Much of what historians refer to as Washington’s "diaries" are not
                diaries at all, but pretty barebones stuff that Washington himself called "Where
                &amp; How my Time is Spent." His entry for June 16, 1775, the day that he accepted
                command of the Continental Army, reads simply: "Dined at Doctr. Cadwaladers. Spent
                the Evening at my lodgings."<ptr target="#note1" xml:id="nr1" n="1"/> Washington was justly famous for his silences. Such
                material tested our editorial skills every day (both diary days and our days). We
                had to figure out what was happening behind those cryptic entries and the
                connections among them, and then help the reader understand those things without
                overwhelming the text. We did not always hit exactly the right balance, but we
                learned and improved as we went along. </p>

            <p>Editing the diaries first was also useful because we were forced to go through much
                of Washington’s life—coming to terms with people, places, and sources—before
                starting to work on the voluminous correspondence series. More to the point, it
                forced us to deal with the less famous parts of his life. Except for the Yorktown
                campaign, there are no diaries for the Revolutionary War, and those for the
                presidential years are very sparse. What we have in the diaries for the most part is
                Washington the farmer and agricultural experimenter, the country squire, the family
                man, and the traveler. The mythical Washington is almost nowhere to be seen. Instead
                we got to know Washington as a rather normal person with ordinary pleasures—fox
                hunting, cards, and barbeques—and ordinary concerns—droughts and floods, a broken
                milldam, a sick child, and muddy roads. We also had to deal with the large cast of
                characters who came and went in Washington’s life: old John Smith the smallpox
                inoculator, Washington’s old French-and-Indian-War comrade Dr. Craik, the French
                sculptor Houdon who arrived at Mount Vernon late at night after everyone had gone to
                bed, and many others. They all became real parts of our lives also, and we excitedly
                exchanged the latest tidbits of information that we learned about them.</p>

            <p>That is another thing I learned that was characteristic of editors. The intimate
                acquaintance that editors develop with the documents in their editions yields them
                an equally intimate acquaintance with the people who wrote those documents and the
                people to whom and about whom they wrote. For documentary editors, as William
                Faulkner wrote, "The past is never dead. It’s not even past."<ptr target="#note2" xml:id="nr2" n="2"/> Less grandly—adapting
                a bit of online humor to my purpose—you might be a documentary editor if <list
                    type="bulleted">
                    <item>Many of your favorite people are dead or fictional.</item>
                    <item>You use quotes from famous people or literary characters in casual
                        conversation.</item>
                    <item>When you point out a historical or literary place, your spouse says, "It’s
                        just a house" or "It’s just a field."</item>
                </list>
            </p>
            <p>Yes, the battle smoke has long since drifted away; the daffodils are not blooming at
                this time of the year; and Walden is just a pond. But documents and text bring them
                alive.</p>
            <p>Such knowledge and insights, however, are hard won. Scholarly diligence is imperative
                in all its forms: focus, concentration, painstaking care, thoroughness, persistence,
                and perseverance. One must, as Don Jackson often said, "wrestle with the documents."
                One useful way of understanding editors and their demanding work is to think of them
                as explorers of the vast, strange world of the past or the intricate worlds of
                literary or intellectual creation. We are not the only ones who venture into those
                realms, but we spend much more time there than almost anyone else because that’s our
                job. Many researchers and writers make relatively quick forays into the documentary
                records with specific, narrow purposes in mind, consciously or unconsciously looking
                for textual excerpts to bolster preconceived ideas and/or amusing anecdotes with
                which to amaze and entertain their readers. Editors are more like Lewis and Clark,
                plodding mile after mile for months on end, ever attentive to everything around
                them: typography, geology, flora and fauna, human inhabitants, and human creations.
                Our aim is not so much to tell others about our journey, but to enable them to make
                a similar journey and see for themselves. Editors lay the documents out in an
                orderly, easy-to-follow route, but even more importantly, they post signs along the
                way indicating alternate routes that readers may wish or need to follow. The first
                generation of Washington Papers editors often said that our "see" and "see also"
                references were some of our most useful notes, pointing out, as they do, important
                connections between documents that are not otherwise readily apparent.</p>

            <p>Unlike others, editors cannot sidestep documents because they have to be dug out of
                remote repositories or private collections or because they are difficult to read or
                comprehend. Every surviving relevant document or bit of text demands to be found and
                to be transcribed, understood, and accounted for in our edition—not necessarily
                published, but, ideally, at least listed or referred to in a note. During my first
                year at the Washington Papers, another editor and I were searching the Virginia
                State Library (now the Library of Virginia) when we came across a catalog card under
                "Washington, George" that simply read "110 inconsequential items." Of course, we
                asked to see them all! They could not possibly be inconsequential to us! Editors
                know that "routine" documents are not always routine. The discovery of an addressed
                cover can reveal to whom a letter was actually written, and the identification of an
                enclosure can drastically change our understanding of the covering letter. "Oh,
                that’s what she is referring to." "Oh, that’s why he wrote that." Nor can an editor
                cavalierly ignore dockets, marginal notations, insertions and deletions, or even
                flecks of ink—they might be punctuation! In all my years of editing the Washington
                Papers, I don’t think I ever had a volume that turned out to say exactly what I had
                so confidently expected it to say when I started working on it. In parts, it wasn’t
                even close.</p>

            <p>One of the greatest strengths of documentary editing for me has always been its power
                to counteract the effects of the heroic, superlative-laden history that generally
                dominates our culture—what one historian has called "whitewashing of warts and
                hanging halos."<ptr target="#note3" xml:id="nr3" n="3"/> Not that there is anything wrong in saying good, even laudatory
                things about the people of the past, but too much of it distorts our understanding
                of history and how it operates in our lives. Even in the papers of the Founding
                Fathers—in fact, most especially in the papers of the Founders—one finds that the
                star actors were surrounded by a huge supporting cast, and all of them were very
                human with foibles both large and small. The ever-colorful Major General Israel
                Putnam, known to his contemporaries as "Old Put" (he was sixty years old), wrote
                Washington in January 1779, requesting a month’s leave to go home to Connecticut "to
                lay an Anchor to windward for a Wife, again [at] the expirations of the War."<ptr target="#note4" xml:id="nr4" n="4"/> His
                wife had died fifteen months earlier. "Old Put" received his leave, but he returned
                to the army unmarried. A paralytic stroke in December 1779 ended both his military
                career and his marriage prospects. He died in 1790.</p>

            <p>British historian Max Hastings says in his book <hi rend="italic">Retribution: The
                    Battle for Japan, 1944–45</hi> that <q rend="block">The phrase "the greatest
                    generation" is sometimes used in the U.S. to describe those who lived through
                    those times. This seems inapt. The people of World War II may have adopted
                    different fashions and danced to different music from us, but human behavior,
                    aspirations and fears do not alter much. It is more appropriate to call them,
                    without jealousy, "the generation to which the greatest things happened."<ptr target="#note5" xml:id="nr5" n="5"/></q>
            </p>
            <p>The same thing can be said of the Revolutionary War generation. Writing from his
                Valley Forge headquarters in April 1778, Washington told Virginia congressman John
                    Banister:<q rend="block">Men may speculate as they will—they may talk of
                    patriotism—they may draw a few examples from ancient story of great
                    atchievements performed by it's influence; but, whoever builds upon it, as a
                    sufficient basis, for conducting a long and bloody War, will find themselves
                    deceived in the end. We must take the passions of Men, as nature has given them,
                    and those principles as a guide, which are generally the rule of action. I do
                    not mean to exclude altogether the idea of patriotism. I know it exists, and I
                    know it has done much in the present contest. But I will venture to assert, that
                    a great and lasting War can never be supported on this principle alone—It must
                    be aided by a prospect of interest or some reward. For a time it may, of itself,
                    push men to action—to bear much—to encounter difficulties; but it will not
                    endure unassisted by interest.<ptr target="#note6" xml:id="nr6" n="6"/></q></p>

            <p>The same applies to documentary editors. No one, of course, can live on scholarly
                commitment alone. Like Washington’s officers and soldiers, editorial staff members
                need and deserve professionally competitive pay and working conditions. That
                inevitably entails fundraising and much paperwork—those necessary but time- and
                energy-consuming activities that few, if any, project directors relish. Editors have
                to be hard-nosed pragmatists. And yet—to turn Washington’s argument around—we know
                that to truly succeed in their work, editors must also be passionate about it. There
                are easier ways to earn a living if that is all you want to do in life. Editors have
                to be clear-eyed visionaries as well as hard-nosed pragmatists. That’s certainly a
                tough job description. These are, however, more than just "a few examples from
                ancient story" of editors who fit it. In 2006, when I was working on the ADE Report
                on Institutional Relationships and Support of Documentary Editing Projects, I
                surveyed thirty project directors, most of whom were remarkably candid in their
                responses. Having been in documentary editing for many years, I was not surprised by
                the severity of the financial and administrative challenges they faced, but I was
                impressed by the intelligence and resourcefulness with which they confronted those
                challenges. Above all, I came to see that the greatest assets that most projects
                possess are their editors—not just the editors’ scholarly knowledge and editing
                skills, but also their unshakable determination to protect and preserve their
                projects and see them through to successful completion even at the cost in some
                cases of sacrificing other personal goals and financial advancement.</p>
            <p>Far more interesting and fun are the many public outreach activities in which editors
                engage. Although few projects are officially set up to be reference and research
                centers for their subject areas, many become such and often important ones.
                Inquiries come in from an amazing variety of people, ranging from elementary
                students to members of Congress. Don Jackson liked to tell about the fifth-grader
                from California who wrote him: "Dear Sir: Please send me everything that you have on
                George Washington." That was not practicable in the 1970s, but Don would be
                delighted to know that now, thanks to the Internet, California fifth-graders and a
                lot of other people around the world can, if they wish, get almost everything that
                the project has on George Washington.</p>
            <p>My first media interview, which Dorothy Twohig hastily referred to me, concerned the
                change of Washington’s birthdate from the eleventh to the twenty-second of February
                due to the belated British switch from the Julian to the Gregorian calendar in 1752
                when George was twenty years old. Only at the end of the interview did I remember to
                ask the reporter what newspaper she represented. I gulped when she said, "<hi
                    rend="italic">The National Enquirer</hi>." I imagined the worst. I got the best.
                Although the article appeared on a page full of outlandish stories, it was factual
                and quoted me accurately.<ptr target="#note7" xml:id="nr7" n="7"/> I guess the <hi rend="italic">National Enquirer</hi>’s
                editors found truth to be actually stranger than fiction in this case. It was an
                object lesson not to worry too much about such things. Reporters more often than not
                get their stories right, and if they don’t, they don’t. It’s only the media. In any
                case, I have not only been quoted in the <hi rend="italic">National Enquirer</hi>, I
                have the rarer distinction of being quoted accurately in the <hi rend="italic"
                    >National Enquirer</hi>!</p>
            <p>There is, however, one thing about which I think you should worry. Fight to keep from
                being overly distracted from your editing. There are many interesting and necessary
                things to do outside the world of your documents and text, but the imperative is to
                edit and edit well. Don’t let anyone tell you that documentary editors can never
                gain respect in the academic world unless they give priority to nonediting
                activities. Don’t be like a politician who thinks that she no longer has to go out and
                press the flesh with voters in the precincts or like a musician or athlete who
                thinks that he doesn’t have to practice regularly in order to continue to perform at
                a high level. Your truest knowledge and best insights come from your editing. It’s
                fine to be a part-time editor; just don’t be a no-time or a slow-time editor. Time
                spent editing is time added to your life, because you are living simultaneously in
                two different worlds whenever you edit.</p>
            <p>In 1971 Julian Boyd took time to write to an obscure graduate student who knew
                nothing about documentary editing as a profession, trying to give him "as balanced a
                picture as possible" of "editorial scholarship on this scale and at this particular
                time." "On the material level," Boyd wrote, "salaries can be equated with those of
                normal academic positions. The rewards and satisfactions, of course, are those that
                come from clearing out new paths through the jungle—as well as abandoning those that
                have led in the wrong directions."<ptr target="#note8" xml:id="nr8" n="8"/></p>
            <p>I knew much more about documentary editing in 1985, when Don Jackson, who by then had
                retired to his beloved Colorado mountain cabin, wrote me a letter on his equally
                beloved first-generation PC, reminiscing about the early days of the Washington
                Papers: "It seems so long since those first big rolls of Copyflo reproductions
                started arriving [from the Library of Congress], fifteen or so years ago, and we
                were floundering with computer language and never dreaming how electronic we would
                eventually become. But the essence of editing is still, you will agree, a scholar
                sitting at a desk surrounded by books and papers, with a yellow pad before him,
                piecing everything together like a quiltmaker. Trying to identify a man named
                Cuthbert Gleep."<ptr target="#note9" xml:id="nr9" n="9"/></p>
            <p>Today we are much more likely to have an iPad in front of us instead of a yellow
                legal pad, and I am not so sure about those salaries. But yes, Julian, the rewards
                and satisfactions of clearing out new paths continue to motivate documentary
                editors, and yes, Don, although we have become immensely more electronic, editors
                are still piecing things together and trying to identify people like Cuthbert Gleep.
                Nothing could be better.</p>
        </body>

        <back>
            <div type="notes">
                <note xml:id="note1">Donald Jackson, ed., <hi rend="italic">The Papers of George Washington: Diaries</hi> (Charlottesville: University of Virginia Press, 1978), 3:336.</note>

                <note xml:id="note2">William Faulkner, <hi rend="italic">Requiem for a Nun</hi>, Act 1, sc. 3.</note>

                <note xml:id="note3">Philander D. Chase and William M. Ferraro, eds., <hi rend="italic">The Papers of George Washington, Revolutionary War Series</hi> (Charlottesville: University of Virginia Press, 2009), 19:72.</note>

                <note xml:id="note4">Thomas A. Bailey, "The Mythmakers of American History," <hi rend="italic">Journal of American History</hi> 55 (1968): 14.</note>

                <note xml:id="note5">Max Hastings, <hi rend="italic">Retribution: The Battle for Japan</hi>, 1944–45 (New York: Knopf, 2007), Kindle edition.</note>

                <note xml:id="note6">David R. Hoth, ed., <hi rend="italic">The Papers of George Washington, Revolutionary War Series</hi> (Charlottesville: University of Virginia Press, 2004), 14:574.</note>

                <note xml:id="note7"><hi rend="italic">National Enquirer</hi>, February 19, 1980.</note>

                <note xml:id="note8">Julian P. Boyd to Philander Chase, November 19, 1971, in author’s files.</note>

                <note xml:id="note9">Donald Jackson to Phil Chase, July 13, 1985, in author’s files.</note>



            </div>

        </back>
    </text>
</TEI>
