<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<?oxygen RNGSchema="http://www.scholarlyediting.org/scholarlyediting.rng" type="xml"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xml:lang="eng">
    <teiHeader>
        <fileDesc>
            <titleStmt>
                <title level="a" type="main">Digital Documentary Editions and the Others</title>
                <author key="Pierazzo, Elena">Elena Pierazzo</author>
            </titleStmt>
            <editionStmt>
                <edition>
                    <date>2014</date>
                </edition>
            </editionStmt>
            <publicationStmt>
                <idno type="file">essay.pierazzo</idno>
                <authority>Scholary Editing: The Annual of the Association for Documentary
                    Editing</authority>
                <address>
 <addrLine>http://www.scholarlyediting.org</addrLine>
</address>
                <publisher>Association for Documentary Editing</publisher>
                <publisher>University of Nebraska&#8211;Lincoln</publisher>
                <distributor>
                    <name>Center for Digital Research in the Humanities</name>
                    <address>
<addrLine>319 Love Library</addrLine>
<addrLine>University of Nebraska&#8211;Lincoln</addrLine>
<addrLine>Lincoln, NE 68588-4100</addrLine>
<addrLine>http://cdrh.unl.edu</addrLine>
 </address>
                </distributor>
                <date>2014</date>
                <availability>
                    <p>Scholary Editing: The Annual of the Association for Documentary Editing is
                        freely distributed by the Association for Documentary Editing and the Center
                        for Digital Research in the Humanities at the University of Nebraska-Lincoln
                        and licensed under a Creative Commons Attribution-NonCommercial-ShareAlike
                        3.0 Unported License</p>
                </availability>
            </publicationStmt>
            <seriesStmt>
                <title level="j">Scholarly Editing: The Annual of the Association for Documentary
                    Editing</title>
                <respStmt>
                    <resp>editor</resp>
                    <name xml:id="ag" key="Gailey, Amanda A.">Amanda Gailey</name>
                </respStmt>
                <respStmt>
                    <resp>editor</resp>
                    <name xml:id="awj" key="Jewell, Andrew W.">Andrew Jewell</name>
                </respStmt>
                <idno type="vol">35</idno>
                <idno type="ISSN">2167-1257</idno>
            </seriesStmt>
            <sourceDesc>
                <bibl>
                    <note>Born digital.</note>
                </bibl>
            </sourceDesc>
        </fileDesc>
        <revisionDesc>
            <change when="2014-01-28"><name xml:id="gk" key="Weakly, Laura K.">Gabrielle
                    Kirilloff</name> markup in TEI XML</change>
        </revisionDesc>
    </teiHeader>
    <text>
        <front>
            <head type="main">Digital Documentary Editions and the Others</head>

            <byline>Elena Pierazzo</byline>
        </front>
        <body>
            <p>It is a truth universally acknowledged that documentary editions have found a very
                welcoming home in cyberspace. Documentary editing has often been considered a lower
                form of scholarship, as suggested by its being commonly called "noncritical
                editing," a name that barely hides the conviction of its being a non- or
                prescholarly endeavor.<ptr target="#note1" xml:id="nr1" n="1"/> However, this
                allegedly humble form of editing has now taken a leading role in the digital arena,
                boosted, it seems, by the availability of digital facsimiles. This rise in scholarly
                esteem has led to a worried call by Peter Robinson for editors to go back to
                preparing multiwitness critical editions. While conceding that "one can welcome this
                attention to documents as a long overdue correction to the millennia-long
                concentration of scholarly editors on the work rather than on the document," he sees
                "dangers" because "if we make only digital documentary editions, we will distance
                ourselves and our editions from the readers"; furthermore, "such editions [i.e.,
                digital documentary editions], with their narrow focus on editor and document, fall
                far short of achieving the potential of editions in the digital world."<ptr
                    target="#note2" xml:id="nr2" n="2"/> Franz Fischer has presented a not
                dissimilar line: if not detrimental, the provision of proper critical editions is
                much more worth pursuing than diplomatic editions of the sources. As he declares, if
                "all texts are equal, critical texts are more equal than others."<ptr
                    target="#note3" xml:id="nr3" n="3"/> However, one must ask if this is really
                true. Does the provision of documentary editions represent a threat to the work of
                the editor and to the entire digital textual scholarship?</p>
            <p>The fact that these scholars have felt the need to defend the benefit of critical
                editions based on multiple witnesses, associated with the fear that "[i]f we make
                only digital documentary editions, we will distance ourselves and our editions from
                    readers,"<ptr target="#note4" xml:id="nr4" n="4"/> clearly demonstrates the
                central role that documentary editing has assumed in the digital environment. This
                is, in fact, the format chosen by many high-profile digital editions, for instance
                    <hi rend="italic">Jane Austen’s Fiction Manuscripts</hi>, the edition of the <hi
                    rend="italic">Manuscrits de Madame Bovary</hi>, the <hi rend="italic">Walt
                    Whitman Archive</hi>, the <hi rend="italic">William Blake Archive</hi>, and many
                    others.<ptr target="#note5" xml:id="nr5" n="5"/> It is remarkable to note that
                as recently as 2007 Gabler felt the need to advocate for new attention to
                documentary editions, which, in his opinion, were still underestimated in the
                editorial scene, and he claimed that the digital environment is the most suitable
                for this type of edition.<ptr target="#note6" xml:id="nr6" n="6"/> Apparently he was
                right; his position has been so successful that it has now, only a few years later,
                generated the opposite reaction among the scholarly community, namely a call for a
                renewed attention to critical editions based on multiple witnesses. Such editions
                may be produced according to different editorial methodologies, such as, for
                instance, copy-text, where different versions of the same work are considered as a
                single artistic endeavor with different level of authorial engagements; stemmatics,
                where the lost original or archetype is reconstructed from several witnesses,
                organized according to genealogical principles; or phylogenetic, where the variation
                of witnesses is organized following the models developed to map and predict genetic
                    mutation.<ptr target="#note7" xml:id="nr7" n="7"/> But before discussing whether
                the new centrality of digital documentary editions represents a real threat to
                digital textual scholarship, it is perhaps necessary to investigate the reasons why
                the digital medium has so much favored this type of edition over the critical
                edition based on multiple witnesses. We must first define the objects of such
                investigation.</p>
            <p>For the purposes of this discussion, I define a documentary edition as an edition of
                a text based on a single document, which attempts to reproduce a certain degree of
                the peculiarities of the document itself, even if this may cause disruption to the
                normal flow of the text presented by the document. It can assume different formats,
                by presenting the textual content of the document as semi-diplomatic, diplomatic,
                    ultra-diplomatic,<ptr target="#note8" xml:id="nr8" n="8"/> or even facsimile
                editions, which differentiate themselves by the level of editorial intervention,
                ranging from the largest to the smallest concession to the reading habits of the
                public of choice. The documentary edition differs from transcription in the sense
                that a documentary edition is meant to be publicly distributed, while a
                transcription represents the private first stage of the editorial work; a
                transcription can become a documentary edition in the moment its creator (the
                editor) decides it is accurate enough and follows accepted scholarly conventions
                well enough to be distributed publicly.<ptr target="#note9" xml:id="nr9" n="9"/> As
                with all definitions, it is hard to convey the different aspects and shades of a
                multiform scholarly practice (and it might be noted that Kline and Perdue, in order
                to respond to the question "What Is Documentary Editing?" have preferred to give
                historical accounts of how it has established itself, rather than giving a
                definition as such).<ptr target="#note10" xml:id="nr10" n="10"/> However, this
                definition could be considered as a useful starting point for the discussion that
                follows. Digital documentary editions (henceforth DDEs) have been defined as "the
                recording of as many features of the original document as are considered meaningful
                by the editors, displayed in all the ways the editors consider useful for the
                readers, including all the tools necessary to achieve such a purpose."<ptr
                    target="#note11" xml:id="nr11" n="11"/> This definition includes not only the
                textual content but also the digital infrastructure (visible to the final user or
                not) necessary for the publication and exploitation of such content. DDEs can assume
                the form of diplomatic, ultra-diplomatic, semi-diplomatic, or reading editions on
                demand, thanks to digital (usually online) delivery of an appropriately encoded
                text, transformed in many ways by customized scripts and tools.</p>
            <p>The availability of digital facsimiles and their ease of publication on the web have
                already been cited as one of the main reasons for the success of DDEs: enthusiasm
                for the opportunity given by digital photography made Kevin Kiernan propose the
                image-based scholarly edition and declare that this type of edition "subsumes the
                purpose of a diplomatic edition."<ptr target="#note12" xml:id="nr12" n="12"/> This
                claim has been already refuted elsewhere,<ptr target="#note13" xml:id="nr13" n="13"
                /> but it is recalled here to highlight one crucial feature of diplomatic editions,
                namely that historically they were conceived and used as a substitute for facsimile
                editions when the latter were impractical or too expensive. Kiernan’s declaration
                implies an assumption that, once digital images are made easily available, the need
                for diplomatic editions would fade. Time has demonstrated that this assumption is
                wrong. In fact, the availability and the improved publishing opportunities offered
                by the different digital formats (CD-ROMs, DVDs, and the Web) and the subsequent
                publication online of millions of digital facsimiles, has by no means made
                diplomatic and more generally non-image-based documentary editions redundant: quite
                the contrary. The fact that DDEs have proven to be one of the most successful
                digital editorial formats demonstrates that their alleged function as surrogate
                facsimiles is only one of their possible purposes, and possibly the least important
                one at that. Far from being subsumed by image-based editions, DDEs have <hi
                    rend="italic">de facto</hi> incorporated them, because the most common format
                for digital documentary editions is the side-by-side layout, in which the diplomatic
                (or ultra-diplomatic) edition is juxtaposed with its digital facsimile. In this
                format the editor engages in a sort of competition with the facsimile where, as
                noted by Kathryn Sutherland, "the editor is continually on trial, open to account
                and correction."<ptr target="#note14" xml:id="nr14" n="14"/> The dialectic
                relationship between the diplomatic edition and the facsimile representation, while
                demanding extreme editorial rigor, engages the users in close inspection of the
                    transcriptions/translations<ptr target="#note15" xml:id="nr15" n="15"/> enacted
                by the editor in a sort of imaginary competition. The diplomatic edition alongside
                the facsimile provides the reader with a simplified, mediated, interpreted version
                of "what’s on the page"; therefore, the diplomatic edition, instead of being made
                redundant by the presence of the image, represents a sort of map and key for the
                understanding and navigation of that image. Just as a map of any given area of the
                Earth provides the user with a way to navigate an unfamiliar place, the diplomatic
                edition provides the reader with the tools to decipher the linguistic and
                bibliographic codes that inform the document.<ptr target="#note16" xml:id="nr16"
                    n="16"/> Therefore, while the provision of high-quality digital facsimiles has
                effectively made redundant the provision of diplomatic editions as a substitute for
                facsimile editions—since facsimile editions can now be provided easily—they have
                also revealed that diplomatic editions (and especially DDEs) are scholarly tools and
                not surrogates, the provision of which is worthwhile because they are indispensible
                interpretative tools. Consequently, the more we offer digital facsimiles of primary
                sources, the greater the need for DDEs will become.</p>
            <p>The (implicit) recognition of this type of functionality has considerably helped the
                establishment of DDEs among scholarly practices, but this alone is perhaps not
                enough to explain their sudden success. The provision of digital documentary
                editions based on text encoding, which enables the possibility of presenting the
                users with many outputs from the same source-encoded files, has made DDEs a very
                powerful and versatile tool. Perhaps these types of editions could be called <hi
                    rend="italic">paradigmatic editions</hi>, as they embed many alternative options
                for the same string of text in a nonlinear way, as opposed to editions that can only
                display the text in one format (such as printed editions, among others), which could
                instead be called <hi rend="italic">syntagmatic editions</hi>. Text encoding has in
                fact enabled editors to have their cake and eat it: features that were once
                normalized without mercy to produce reading, critical (or syntagmatic) editions can
                now be retained and simply switched on and off at leisure to please different
                audiences, thereby opening the way to new scholarship and readership. In fact, one
                can store as much information or alternative points of view as one wishes for each
                string of text, following the paradigmatic axis, in a nonlinear way, and processed
                differently according to the editorial vision. These functions have attracted the
                attention of scholars for whom documents and documentary evidences have a central
                role, namely those engaged with New (or Material) Philology and Genetic Criticism:
                scholars that recognize themselves as belonging to these editorial orientations were
                in fact among the first to embrace the digital medium.<ptr target="#note17"
                    xml:id="nr17" n="17"/> As paradigmatic editions are able to store an indefinite
                amount of information, it is therefore possible to remain faithful to the document
                (retaining for instance, old and odd spellings, abbreviations, scribal errors,
                etc.), as well as to make concessions to the reader who is then given the
                opportunity to choose which version to read. This is the case, for instance, in the
                LangScape project, where the passages describing land bounds contained within the
                corpus of Anglo-Saxon charters are presented as semi-diplomatic, edited, or
                linguistically glossed texts.<ptr target="#note18" xml:id="nr18" n="18"/></p>
            <p>Yet this is not all: as it happens, digital critical editions based on multiple
                witnesses gave a decisive boost to the fortunes of digital documentary editions.
                This is due to the fact that collation—the essential, time-consuming activity that
                consists in the comparison of text proposed by many documents (the witnesses)—can be
                done automatically only if all the witnesses are individually transcribed.
                Experiments in digital collation were one of the first activities attempted by
                practitioners of the embryonic digital humanities: comparing strings is an activity
                for which computers are much more gifted than human beings, and so automatic or
                computer-assisted collation seemed almost inevitable.<ptr target="#note19"
                    xml:id="nr19" n="19"/> This task proved to be much more complicated than
                expected, yet the necessity of producing transcriptions of all witnesses in order to
                be collated has <hi rend="italic">de facto</hi> generated many documentary editions
                once these transcription are made publicly available, one for each witness, for any
                critical edition. This is the case in the editions published under the umbrella of
                the <hi rend="italic">Canterbury Tales Project</hi>, for instance.<ptr
                    target="#note20" xml:id="nr20" n="20"/> Access to the sources has always been
                one of the biggest limitations offered by traditional critical editions, where only
                the categories of variants considered relevant by the editor were collected and
                organized in the <hi rend="italic">apparatus criticus</hi>. Again, it seemed
                natural, then, that together with a critical edition, the diplomatic edition of the
                sources would be offered for readers’ inspection in digital form, where the space
                constraints that have determined the format and the selectiveness of the printed
                apparatus no longer apply.</p>
            <p>Perhaps the main reason behind the success of DDEs is that we can unashamedly “do”
                them: the fact that there are already quite a few of them out there and that they
                have become so versatile and powerful have made them more attractive than ever.
                Editors have always had to face the question of what to edit, texts or documents (or
                texts of works vs. texts of documents);<ptr target="#note21" xml:id="nr21" n="21"/>
                they have resolved this mostly by choosing texts (i.e., texts of works) over (texts
                of) documents, given the cost of and the traditionally smaller readership for
                diplomatic editions. This choice has been almost inevitable for works for which many
                witnesses survive: who indeed, apart from the editor and possibly a couple of other
                scholars, would be interested in buying and/or consulting seven hundred versions of
                Dante’s <hi rend="italic">Commedia</hi>, one for each of the surviving witnesses?
                Historically, in cases like these, the only sensible solution has been to
                reconstruct the version that corresponded most with the theoretical orientation of
                the editor,<ptr target="#note22" xml:id="nr22" n="22"/> and to serialize the
                rejected variant readings in the apparatus. The result is the provision of a clean,
                reading edition, where the variants are conveniently marginalized at the bottom of
                the page or at the end of the volume, in the name of ease of reading. However, such
                a format has generated a fair amount of criticism because it gives texts a false
                impression of stability and purity, and makes it almost impossible to really
                appreciate the editorial work and the complexity of the tradition.<ptr
                    target="#note23" xml:id="nr23" n="23"/> But, while this was (and in many
                respects still is) the most pragmatic solution for texts with a large tradition, it
                is not necessarily the best solution in other cases, such as when only one witness
                survives. However, a sort of critical edition has traditionally still been provided
                even for texts preserved in a single witness, with the provision of a clear reading
                text, with internal variations and apparent errors appropriately set aside, in order
                to avoid disturbing the reading experience. This is the case, for instance, with
                editions of Jane Austen’s <hi rend="italic">Juvenilia</hi> and other unfinished
                works unpublished in her lifetime. These were first published by R. W. Chapman from
                the 1920s; the text Chapman printed is a clean, “final” version, with all the
                authorial workflow that can be reconstructed through a deep investigation of the
                original source material relegated to notes at the end of the book. This has been
                the only way readers have known these particular works, at least until the online
                publication of <hi rend="italic">Jane Austen’s Fiction Manuscripts Digital
                    Editions</hi> in 2010. In cases like this, it can be argued that the edition of
                the manuscripts as critical text is the only sensible way to edit the material.
                Certainly the provision of a critical text is of fundamental importance to the
                general readership; however, the edition of the manuscript as document can also be
                justified on scholarly grounds. This is demonstrated by the fact that the
                publication of the digital edition has generated a considerable debate around Jane
                Austen’s authorial habits, with readers and scholars alike expressing their
                disbelief in discovering that she was not the polished, organized writer that was
                presented through the edited pages.<ptr target="#note24" xml:id="nr24" n="24"/> The
                reception of Hans Walter Gabler’s edition of <hi rend="italic">Ulysses</hi> shows
                the same situation: by presenting the documentary evidence of the autograph
                manuscripts in a synoptic manner, dense with symbolism, he shocked his audience,
                which was not used to being exposed to the messiness of the authorial work.<ptr
                    target="#note25" xml:id="nr25" n="25"/> Indeed, the same story holds for many
                literary works: even when the survival of only one or a handful of witnesses could
                have made a documentary edition viable, this has rarely been done. When it has been
                done, it has been often attacked as “dangerous”: Paul Eggert beautifully recounts
                the polemic led by Fredson Bowers, champion of the authorial intention and critical
                editing, against editors of variorum editions and documentary editions, a battle
                continued by Thomas Tanselle at the expense of historical documentary editors.<ptr
                    target="#note26" xml:id="nr26" n="26"/></p>
            <p>The battle for critical editing versus documentary editing<ptr target="#note27"
                    xml:id="nr27" n="27"/> has been fought on many fronts: disciplinary,
                theoretical, methodological, and economic. The point here is that the attitude
                toward one or the other editorial framework (documentary or critical) has always
                been colored by strong theoretical positions. The question has very rarely been
                which editorial framework was best for the type of document under consideration,<ptr
                    target="#note28" xml:id="nr28" n="28"/> but rather which was the theoretical
                orientation of the editor.<ptr target="#note29" xml:id="nr29" n="29"/> Of a
                different opinion is Peter Shillingsburg, who argues that a certain level of
                influence among theories (“orientations”) is always present, determined by
                “particular circumstances surrounding a textual problem,” but then his reference to
                “fierce editorial debates between partisans of these basic positions” shows how the
                influence among these orientations is more a “matter of fact” accident rather than a
                conscious theoretical decision, namely that editors tend to adopt converging
                methodologies in spite of their theoretical positions more or less when the
                materials they are editing force them to do so.<ptr target="#note30" xml:id="nr30"
                    n="30"/> Historically, this conflict has tended to pit historians against
                literary scholars,<ptr target="#note31" xml:id="nr31" n="31"/> with the former
                traditionally associated with the documentary edition at least in the Anglo-American
                editorial tradition. From a theoretical point of view, advocates of documentary
                editions accused critical editors of hybridizing their texts from many sources,
                building texts that never existed and hence altering the evidence from the past.<ptr
                    target="#note32" xml:id="nr32" n="32"/> This latter attitude also characterizes
                the theoretical positions of New Philology, the arguments of which are based in turn
                on fundamental critiques advanced by Joseph Bédier regarding the Lachamannian
                    method.<ptr target="#note33" xml:id="nr33" n="33"/></p>
            <p>Another episode of this debate has focused on methodological issues, and in
                particular the rigor and accountability of criteria for transcription, with literary
                scholars (mainly Tanselle) accusing historians of having a cavalier attitude toward
                their transcription criteria. This episode served as a “wake-up call” for
                documentary editors, initiating a period of reexamination of their methodological
                approaches and procedures.<ptr target="#note34" xml:id="nr34" n="34"/></p>
            <p>And again, the discussion has been over what readers want: a nice reading edition
                without any hint about a potentially complex tradition, or a critical edition with a
                critical apparatus and extensive commentary, or a documentary edition (or editions),
                possibly accompanied by many facsimiles to allow inspection of the original
                documents by themselves?<ptr target="#note35" xml:id="nr35" n="35"/> In this latter
                case the documentary editions have generally been considered unsuitable for the
                wider public, unreadable, or both. Genetic editing and genetic editions could also
                be included here: indeed, genetic editions resemble documentary editions a great
                deal, with the former also trying to embed information about the different phases of
                writing and rewriting of the manuscript. The most prestigious theoretical framework
                for the understanding and editing of draft manuscripts has been provided by the
                French school of <hi rend="italic">Critique Génétique</hi>, which is concentrated
                around the activities promoted by the ITEM (<hi rend="italic">Institut des Textes et
                    Manuscrits Modernes</hi>).<ptr target="#note36" xml:id="nr36" n="36"/> Yet while
                the scholarly methodologies of the French school have generally been judged
                positively, printed genetic editions have been criticized as unreadable, unusable,
                time-consuming, and, in general, deceptive.<ptr target="#note37" xml:id="nr37"
                    n="37"/> The obscure, intricate symbolism that necessarily characterizes such
                editions in print is perhaps the principal reason for their cold reception by the
                academic community.<ptr target="#note38" xml:id="nr38" n="38"/> Economic factors
                have also been considered: the cost of producing a documentary edition has often
                been seen as not justified by the small number of prospective readers except in the
                case of very important, unique documentary sources.<ptr target="#note39"
                    xml:id="nr39" n="39"/> In the United States, however, documentary and diplomatic
                editions have been used to a great extent for the publication of historical
                documents of the Founding Fathers (Jefferson’s and Washington’s, for instance), but
                this fact, instead of encouraging the diffusion of such an editorial formula, has
                increased the theoretical and disciplinary divide, with literary scholars
                consistently producing critical editions based on the editorial framework of the
                copy-text and historians championing documentary editions. A documentary edition for
                works of literature in the Anglo-American world seems to be rarer than, say, in
                France, Germany, or Italy,<ptr target="#note40" xml:id="nr40" n="40"/> and this
                applies also to authors for whom we only have works transmitted by one witness, such
                as, for instance, the <hi rend="italic">Juvenilia</hi> or the unfinished novels of
                Jane Austen, as discussed above. French-style genetic editions or German-style <hi
                    rend="italic">Historisch-Kritische Ausgaben</hi> are even more rare in the
                English-speaking world.<ptr target="#note41" xml:id="nr41" n="41"/> One can see, for
                instance, the relative misfortune of the edition of Austen’s <hi rend="italic">Sir
                    Charles Grandison</hi> edited by Brian Southam, whose editorial choice has been
                rejected by Michael Hunter: “For, painstaking as it is, it fails to replicate all
                features of the original—not only different handwritings and letterforms, but also
                ink blots, different methods of striking through words, or exact details of the
                layout, for which only a pictorial facsimile suffices.”<ptr target="#note42"
                    xml:id="nr42" n="42"/></p>
            <p>In Eggert’s view the cultural hegemony exerted by the copy-text theory (the so-called
                Greg-Bowers-Tanselle line) can be held responsible for the perceived lack of
                interest in documentary editions by (mainly Anglophone) literary scholars. However,
                this methodological hegemony has been tolerated with increasing irritation by the
                scholarly community. The most famous reaction to this editorial approach is
                represented by Jerome McGann’s theory of the social text and by the rise in favor of
                New (or “material”) Philology. Both these theories focus on the importance of the
                material support: the “bibliographical codes” of McGann can be paired, in a way,
                with the <hi rend="italic">codex</hi> of Cerquiglini.<ptr target="#note43"
                    xml:id="nr43" n="43"/> Both these contributions were elaborated around 1990,
                more or less in the same period when digital editions began to be produced, thus it
                might not be a coincidence that practitioners of innovative textual theories have
                looked into an innovative publishing medium to convey their editorial products.
                Richard J. Finneran notes that the advent of new technologies “coincided with a
                fundamental shift in textual theory, away from the notion of a single-text
                ‘definitive edition,’” remarking that while “a traditional print edition is able to
                accommodate this new thinking in textual theory either awkwardly or not at all,
                digital technology is its necessary and inevitable realization.”<ptr
                    target="#note44" xml:id="nr44" n="44"/></p>
            <p>As we have seen, documentary editions have been at the center of a long-lasting
                theoretical debate, as they have been identified as the ideal editorial framework of
                those scholars who reject the creation of critical editions based on multiple
                witnesses. However, <hi rend="italic">per se</hi>, they are simply an editorial
                methodology that has no particular theoretical implication in itself. This is
                demonstrated by the fact that documentary editions have been serving different
                theoretical positions, that is, the “best-text” method,<ptr target="#note45"
                    xml:id="nr45" n="45"/> the social edition, historical edition, genetic edition,
                and material philology, to name a few, without demanding one.<ptr target="#note46"
                    xml:id="nr46" n="46"/> So documentary editions do not constitute or do not aim
                at constituting a theory of digital editions.<ptr target="#note47" xml:id="nr47"
                    n="47"/> Rather, they happen to have been chosen as an editorial format by
                scholars who had a theoretical position, but not necessarily the same one. They are
                “tools,” not theories. It is not surprising, then, that the elaboration of the new
                model of the Text Encoding Initiative (TEI) for the encoding of documents represents
                the result of the collaboration of scholars coming from many of the above-mentioned
                theoretical positions, as well as from different disciplinary areas.<ptr
                    target="#note48" xml:id="nr48" n="48"/> A Venetian proverb says that “an
                umbrella can be useful for more than one rainfall”; here we can perhaps say that
                (digital) documentary editions can be useful for more than one theory. The reasons
                for their digital diffusion are therefore varied and diverse, but ultimately, in my
                opinion, once they have been attempted in digital form, scholars have discovered
                documentary editions to offer far more scholarly value than was suggested by the
                “noncritical” label and their supposed surrogate function. Furthermore, DDEs seem
                able to answer old and new scholarly questions that have never found a proper answer
                before, particularly not in print-based editions. Documents are information-rich
                sites, and “putting the text back into context” is bound to reveal much more about
                the text than if we considered documents as simple supports.<ptr target="#note49"
                    xml:id="nr49" n="49"/> For instance, are quantitative data about spellings and
                use of punctuation able to provide evidences over the diffusion of literacy or the
                influence of certain type of publications? Is there any difference in the spelling
                habits or punctuation of men and women? How much does the type of writing tools
                influence the tendency for revision? When and why do drafts become so messy, and is
                there any influence in the way the text is authored and in the type of work that is
                produced? The adoption of documentary editions is then likely to be connected with
                the desire to fill a gap in textual scholarship, now that the technology supports it
                and makes it a worthwhile pursuit.</p>
            <p>While the provision of digital documentary editions <hi rend="italic">per se</hi>
                does not represent an editorial theory, it is likely that new theories will be
                developed by experimenting with the increased representational capabilities offered
                by computers. Let us consider, for instance, the possibilities that are offered to
                editors who are interested in the process that has produced the manuscripts rather
                than in the end result, that is to say, the representation of the manuscript as
                process rather than as a static “normalized” photograph like that provided by a
                diplomatic edition. This approach recognizes that manuscripts embed an implicit
                dynamicity: writing is always a process that develops in time. This is even more
                true for authoring (as opposed to copying), which includes not simply linear writing
                but also rewriting, adding, deleting, transposing, and so on.<ptr target="#note50"
                    xml:id="nr50" n="50"/> Draft manuscripts are complex, data-rich objects that
                require the long, patient work of scholars to unpack them and make them “consumable”
                by people other than the specialists. Because of the complexity offered by these
                materials, they have rarely taken a central role in scholarship beyond that of their
                editors. The problem is that draft manuscripts present texts before they become
                readable, before they become texts. The nonlinear, fragmented, paradigmatic
                textuality of most drafts proves to be opaque, tiring, and only rewarding if one
                commits a substantial amount of time to the task; they are often overlooked as a
                result, in spite of representing a mine of information on the work of authors.<ptr
                    target="#note51" xml:id="nr51" n="51"/> The printed-book model has proved to be
                unsuitable for the task of presenting such material in an accessible way to scholars
                other than editors, let alone for members of the general public. The digital
                environment, however, has shown great potential in dealing with the complexities of
                draft manuscripts, or pre-texts (the French <hi rend="italic"
                    >avant-textes</hi>).<ptr target="#note52" xml:id="nr52" n="52"/></p>
            <p>The interactivities we now expect in any web page can easily be used to the advantage
                of digital editions, making them much more accessible and, it is hoped, giving them
                a much more prominent role in the scholarly discourse. These principles are at the
                base of a small prototype of a few pages of a notebook of Proust’s, which has been
                developed with the collaboration of Julie André and Raffaele Viglianti.<ptr
                    target="#note53" xml:id="nr53" n="53"/> In this website the user is initially
                presented with the “clean” image of one opening of Cahier 46 (folios 46v–47r); then,
                by clicking on the image, the zones containing the transcribed text appear in the
                order in which they are presumed to have been written. Different colors have been
                used as background for the zones according to the different level of certainty and
                confidence that the editor had in ordering the sequences: the darker the color, the
                greater the uncertainty. In this way, a visual semiotic codification conveys the
                doubts and decisions of scholars in an intuitive way. A timeline bar marks the
                passing of time for the writing sequences, allowing the user to go back in time, so
                to speak, and reenact the process of authoring as many times as is wished. The zones
                of transcription can also be moved around at will to reveal the underlying
                facsimile, or they can be minimized and then restored following an order that
                differs from the one provided by the editor, enabling users and scholars to test new
                hypotheses. This prototype has been “powered by TEI,”<ptr target="#note54"
                    xml:id="nr54" n="54"/> and in particular by the new documentary encoding
                proposed by the TEI as a sort of proof of concept in order to test its viability in
                a real project. Although the experiment has been quite successful and has inspired
                further research and theoretical reflection, it has proved to be quite
                labor-intensive and requires considerable technical skills: without a strong
                financial investment in the development of editorial tools it seems unlikely that
                this type of encoding will substitute the more “traditional” text-based TEI
                encoding. This consideration could also be made for digital critical editions based
                on multiple witnesses: without large investment in developing tools that can support
                the editorial work, it seems unlikely that this type of edition will take off on the
                web anytime soon.</p>
            <p>However, tool development is held back by more than lack of investment. According to
                Tara Andrews, there is resistance within the editorial community that prevents the
                agreement necessary to enable the development of effective tools. She writes, almost
                bitterly, that “flexibility and customizability is currently much more important to
                textual scholars than the sort of standardization that would allow for true progress
                toward digital critical editions.”<ptr target="#note56" xml:id="nr56" n="56"/> DDEs,
                on the other hand, require less investment. If one is able to find an editor who is
                brave enough to accept the challenge offered by XML-TEI encoding, and is able to
                develop a style sheet or can find a small grant to support web development, then DDEs&#8212;including dynamic documentary editions on the model of the Proust
                prototyp&#8212;become a viable option much more easily than other types of editions.
                Critical editions require considerable effort on many fronts, starting from the
                development of tools to support the many operations that are part of producing such
                an edition, such as transcription, collation, stemma generation, and web publishing,
                among others. Before this, however, and most importantly, is the development of
                scholarly agreement over standard manipulations and management operations like the
                ones just mentioned (transcription, collation, and so on). Is this agreement
                achievable? At the moment there are a few positive signals in this direction, but
                perhaps too few.<ptr target="#note57" xml:id="nr57" n="57"/> Andrews seems doubtful
                about the feasibility of such an agreement.<ptr target="#note58" xml:id="nr58"
                    n="58"/> I have expressed a similar opinion;<ptr target="#note59" xml:id="nr59"
                    n="59"/> faced with the options either of not having computing support or of
                compromising on scholarly traditions (not quality), scholars will choose to remain
                faithful to the habits and approaches of their disciplinary and national areas. One
                of the reasons for the TEI’s establishment as the <hi rend="italic">de facto</hi>
                standard data-model for the preparation of digital scholarly editions is precisely
                in the very “flexibility and customizability” which is dreaded by developers.
                Blaming scholars does not help here, though. One of the reasons for choosing
                flexibility over standardization may lie in the need to validate digital outputs and
                to convince the more “traditional” scholarly community. The recognizability of the
                editorial methods and interfaces, idiosyncrasies included, may be necessary to
                demonstrate that digital editions are “as good as” printed ones.<ptr
                    target="#note60" xml:id="nr60" n="60"/></p>
            <p>On the other hand, documentary editions come with much lighter baggage. They require
                less computational efforts, and having been neglected as poorer relatives of
                critical editions, they have resulted in a greater flexibility and adaptability to
                new conditions. Furthermore, as discussed above, the digital environment has proved
                to be a much more suitable environment for them. </p>
            <p>Here I have listed many possible explanations why documentary editions are thriving
                in the digital environment while other editorial forms seem to find more difficulty
                in establishing themselves within the new medium. The convergence of scholarly,
                disciplinary, and technological reasons is, then, at the base of this unexpected
                    development.<ptr target="#note61" xml:id="nr61" n="61"/> But is the success of
                digital documentary editions a danger for textual scholarship and the digital
                humanities in general? According to Peter Robinson, the answer is yes, and this
                danger consists in “fall[ing] short of achieving the potential of editions in the
                digital world,” with the “flood of facsimile editions in digital form” failing to
                address questions such as “how the received text changed over time, how was it
                received, how was it altered, transformed, passed into different currencies.”<ptr
                    target="#note62" xml:id="nr62" n="62"/> The discussion above shows how many
                different and complex conditions have favored the establishment of documentary
                editions in digital form, but perhaps, more simply, documentary editions may just be
                the best editorial scenario for some types of documents, like those listed in an
                article I co-authored with Peter Stokes in 2010.<ptr target="#note63" xml:id="nr63"
                    n="63"/> A documentary edition is not only the best editorial solution but also,
                most often, the only scholarly justifiable choice in the following cases:<list
                    type="ordered">
                    <item>The process of making the document is at least as important as the text,
                        meaning that the history of the making, as deduced from the document,
                        represents perhaps the most important research object rather than the final
                        product. This applies to some very stratified documents that contain many
                        layers of writing, such as draft manuscripts, but also to historical
                        “living” documents, like the medieval <hi rend="italic">libri vitae</hi>,
                        for instance, within which one can distinguish hundreds of hands that have
                        added names and annotations for hundreds of years. In this case, an edition
                        that does not investigate the evidence of the documents and does not put
                        this at the center will seriously misrepresent its content and historical
                        value. A more modern example is Puccini’s <hi rend="italic">Tosca</hi>, the
                        draft manuscripts of which result from the coauthoring process by four
                        people over the course of two years. The final version of <hi rend="italic"
                            >Tosca</hi> is rather uncontroversial, and it is quite different from
                        that suggested by the evidence of the drafts, the importance of which
                        resides, then, in witnessing the way Puccini and his librettists worked
                        collaboratively. For these types of documents, the “text” simply cannot be
                        considered out of context.</item>
                    <item>The text is determined by the documents, that is, some features of the
                        supporting document have determined in a fundamental way the text’s content
                        or its reception. Letters limited by space and by the convention of the
                        genre can be mentioned here, but also fundamental works such as <hi
                            rend="italic">Beowulf</hi>, the only surviving manuscript of which has
                        been through many events, such as a fire, and at least one reordering of the
                        quires, all of which have seriously undermined our understanding of the work
                        itself.</item>
                    <item>The text is graphically presented, as in the case of graphic poetry such
                        as <hi rend="italic">calligrames</hi>, a type of poetry practiced in
                        particular by French poets of the past century (Guillaume Apollinaire is
                        perhaps the most famous of them), or the medieval <hi rend="italic">carmina
                            figurata</hi>. In both cases, an edition that does not respect the
                        precise layout of the original document will lose almost every aspect of the
                        original work.</item>
                    <item>There is no text. Draft manuscripts, for example, have been defined as <hi
                            rend="italic">avant-textes</hi>, “pre-texts,” or “recipes to make texts”
                        rather than finished texts.<ptr target="#note64" xml:id="nr64" n="64"/>
                        Therefore, their evidence must be presented “as is” in the documents. In
                        many cases drafts propose alternative, paradigmatic readings, with or
                        without a clear indication from the author about which would be the final or
                        preferred version. In theses cases, too, the provision of “a text” seems
                        unsuitable for the type of evidence. </item>
                </list></p>
            <p>Documentary editions, thanks to the digital medium, are establishing themselves in
                the editorial arena as equals to critical editions. This is done on scholarly bases:
                there are cases for which they are simply the best editorial framework. Seeing this
                as a menace means ignoring the scholarly reasons why they have been chosen to convey
                the editorial vision and understanding of the particular text. Franz Fischer
                maintains that critical texts are “more equal than others,” that they are more
                important than other types of texts such as diplomatic and documentary editions, but
                this assertion of his is like declaring literature to be more important than
                history, which, of course, is nonsense. History and literature both have their
                fundamental function and position at the heart of textual scholarship. Different
                editorial frameworks may be suitable to different types of text or to different
                types of research questions. There might be some editions that are therefore more
                equal than others, but this attribution needs to be contextualized considering the
                type of document, the type of text, the research question, and so on. Attributing
                the supremacy of one editorial framework over another <hi rend="italic">a
                    priori</hi> would be an error. The diffusion of DDEs is offering the opportunity
                of opening new paths to scholarship, exploring and unpacking the bibliographic and
                “codicological codes” of our texts,<ptr target="#note65" xml:id="nr65" n="65"/> with
                consequences to textual studies that have yet to be quantified but are hard to
                overestimate.</p>
            <p>While it is true that DDEs have found a comfortable home on the web, to blame them
                for the slow establishment of critical editions based on many witnesses also means
                ignoring the real reasons why critical editions seem to find more difficulties in
                the digital medium. Having been invented and informed by print technology, and
                having been the arena for the confrontation of many theoretical, disciplinary, and
                national debates, they seem to resist the switch to the new medium. This resistance
                can perhaps only be overcome by a deep rethinking of their functions, requirements,
                and publics.<ptr target="#note66" xml:id="nr66" n="66"/> Underlying this, however,
                is the need for a strong intellectual investment in standardization, which in turn
                requires interdisciplinary and international collaborations. It is this that is
                called for here, and perhaps then, once this is in place, critical editions with
                multiple witnesses may finally have their day in digital form.</p>
        </body>
        <back>
            <div type="notes">
                <note xml:id="note1">See Mary-Jo Kline and Susan Holbrook Perdue, <hi rend="italic"
                        >A Guide to Documentary Editing</hi> (Charlottesville: University of
                    Virginia Press, 2008), 3, who feel obliged to insist on the amount of critical
                    work necessary to produce a documentary edition: “The documentary editor’s goal
                    is not to supply the words or phrases of a vanished archetype but rather to
                    preserve the nuances of a source that has survived the ravages of time.
                    Documentary editing, although noncritical in terms of classical textual
                    scholarship, is hardly an <hi rend="italic">un</hi>critical endeavor. It demands
                    as much intelligence, insight, and hard work as its critical counterpart,
                    combined with a passionate determination to preserve for modern readers the
                    nuances of evidence” (italics in the source). Paul Eggert defines the <hi
                        rend="italic">Guide to Documentary Editing</hi> as “a manifesto of
                    intellectual independence from the Greg-Bowers school and a claim of
                    methodological and theoretical coherence” (<hi rend="italic">Securing the Past:
                        Conservation in Art, Architecture and Literature</hi> [Cambridge: Cambridge
                    University Press, 2009], 184).</note>
                <note xml:id="note2">Peter Robinson, “Towards a Theory of Digital Editions,” <hi
                        rend="italic">Variants</hi> 10 (2013): 105–32, p. 127.</note>
                <note xml:id="note3">Franz Fischer, “All texts are equal, but . . . Textual
                    Plurality and the Critical Text in Digital Scholarly Editions,” <hi
                        rend="italic">Variants</hi> 10 (2013): 77–92, p. 90.</note>
                <note xml:id="note4">Robinson, “Towards a Theory of Digital Editions,” 127.</note>
                <note xml:id="note5">Respectively: <hi rend="italic">Jane Austen’s Fiction
                        Manuscripts: A Digital Edition</hi>, edited by Kathryn Sutherland (2010),
                        <ref type="url" target="http://www.janeausten.ac.uk"
                        >http://www.janeausten.ac.uk</ref>; <hi rend="italic">Le manuscripts de
                        Madame Bovary</hi>, Bibliothèque de Rouen, Centre Flaubert de l'Université
                    de Rouen, <ref type="url" target="http://www.bovary.fr"
                        >http://www.bovary.fr/</ref>; <hi rend="italic">The Walt Whitman
                        Archive</hi>, edited by Ed Folsom and Kenneth M. Price, Center for Digital
                    Research in the Humanities at the University of Nebraska–Lincoln, <ref
                        type="url" target="http://whitmanarchive.org/"
                        >http://whitmanarchive.org/</ref>; <hi rend="italic">The William Blake
                        Archive</hi>, edited by Morris Eaves, Robert N. Essick and Joseph Viscomi,
                        <ref type="url" target="http://www.blakearchive.org/blake/"
                        >http://www.blakearchive.org/blake/</ref>.</note>
                <note xml:id="note6">Hans Walter Gabler, “The Primacy of the Document in Editing,”
                        <hi rend="italic">Ecdotica</hi> 4 (2007): 197–207.</note>
                <note xml:id="note7">For a more detailed overview, see D. C. Greetham, <hi
                        rend="italic">Textual Scholarship: An Introduction</hi> (New York: Garland,
                    1994).</note>
                <note xml:id="note8">An ultra-diplomatic edition aims to preserve the layout of the
                    document as well as its textual content.</note>
                <note xml:id="note9">For a historical overview of different types of edition, see
                    Greetham, <hi rend="italic">Textual Scholarship</hi>, 347–72.</note>
                <note xml:id="note10">Kline and Perdue, <hi rend="italic">A Guide to Documentary
                        Editing</hi>, 1–34.</note>
                <note xml:id="note11">Elena Pierazzo, “A Rationale of Digital Documentary Editions,”
                        <hi rend="italic">Literary and Linguistic Computing</hi> 26, no. 4 (2011)
                    463–77, p. 475.</note>
                <note xml:id="note12">Kevin Kiernan, “Digital Facsimile in Editing,” in <hi
                        rend="italic">Electronic Textual Editing</hi>, ed. John Unsworth, Lou
                    Burnard, and Katherine O’Brien O’Keefe (New York: Modern Language Association of
                    America, 2006), 262–68, p. 266.</note>
                <note xml:id="note13">Pierazzo, “A Rationale of Digital Documentary Editions,”
                    472–73.</note>
                <note xml:id="note14">Kathryn Sutherland and Elena Pierazzo, “The Author’s Hand:
                    From Page to Screen,” in <hi rend="italic">Collaborative Research in the Digital
                        Humanities</hi>, ed. Marilyn Deegan and Willard McCarty (Aldershot: Ashgate,
                    2011), 191–212.</note>
                <note xml:id="note15">On the concept of transcription as a form a translation, see
                    Peter Robinson and Elizabeth Solopova, “Guidelines for Transcription of the
                    Manuscripts of the Wife of Bath’s Prologue,” in <hi rend="italic">The Canterbury
                        Tales Project: Occasional Papers</hi>, ed. N. F. Blake and P. M. W. Robinson
                    (Oxford: Oxford University Computing Services, Office for Humanities
                    Communication, 1993), 1:19–52: “transcription of a primary textual source cannot
                    be regarded as an act of substitution, but as a series of acts of translation
                    from one semiotic system (that of the primary source) to another semiotic system
                    (that of the computer). Like all acts of translation, it must be seen as
                    fundamentally incomplete and fundamentally interpretative” (p. 21).</note>
                <note xml:id="note16">"Bibliographical codes” is an expression crafted by Jerome
                    McGann in The <hi rend="italic">Textual Condition</hi> (Princeton: Princeton
                    University Press, 1991). As McGann mainly refers to printed books, I have
                    proposed in a forthcoming article the expression “codicological codes” as a
                    similar concept applied to manuscripts (Elena Pierazzo, “Of Time and Space: A
                    New Framework for Digital Editions of Draft Manuscripts,” <hi rend="italic"
                        >Variants</hi> 2014 [forthcoming]).</note>
                <note xml:id="note17">See M. J. Driscoll, “The Words on the Page: Thoughts on
                    Philology, Old and New,” in <hi rend="italic">Creating the Medieval Saga:
                        Versions, Variability, and Editorial Interpretations of Old Norse Saga
                        Literature</hi>, ed. Judy Quinn and Emily Lethbridge (Odense: Syddansk
                    Universitetsforlag, 2010), 85–102; and Jean-Louis Lebrave, “De l’édition
                    informatisée à l’édition électronique,” in <hi rend="italic">L’Édition du
                        Manuscrit: De l’Archive de Création au Scriptorium Électronique, Au Coeur
                        des Textes</hi>, ed. Aurèle Crasson (Louvain-La-Neuve: Academia Bruylant,
                    2008), 169–88.</note>
                <note xml:id="note18">See the project website (<ref type="url"
                        target="http://www.langscape.org/">http://www.langscape.org/</ref>) and
                    Peter Stokes and Elena Pierazzo, “Encoding the Language of Landscape: XML and
                    Databases at the Service of Anglo-Saxon Lexicography,” in <hi rend="italic"
                        >Perspectives on Lexicography in Italy and Europe</hi>, ed. Silvia Bruti,
                    Roberta Cella, and Marina Foschi Albert (Newcastle: Cambridge Scholars
                    Publishing, 2009), 203–38.</note>
                <note xml:id="note19">See, for instance, TuStep, a software suite developed since
                    the sixties at the University of Tübingen under the direction of Wilhelm Ott,
                    assisting scholars in the creation of scholarly editions—including collation.
                    See Ott, “Strategies and Tools for Textual Scholarship: The Tübingen System for
                    Text Processing Program (TUSTEP),” <hi rend="italic">Literary and Linguistic
                        Computing</hi> 15, no. 1 (2000): 93–108. But see also P. Gilbert, “Automatic
                    Collation: A Technique for Medieval Texts,” <hi rend="italic">Computers and the
                        Humanities</hi> 7, no. 3 (1973): 139–47.</note>
                <note xml:id="note20"><hi rend="italic">The Canterbury Tales Project</hi> is
                    directed by Peter Robinson, <ref type="url"
                        target="http://www.canterburytalesproject.org/index.html"
                        >http://www.canterburytalesproject.org/index.html</ref>. See a sample of <hi
                        rend="italic">The Nun’s Priest’s Tale</hi>, edited by Paul Thomas, at the
                    publisher’s website: <ref type="url"
                        target="http://www.sd-editions.com/AnaAdditional/NPEx/index.html"
                        >http://www.sd-editions.com/AnaAdditional/NPEx/index.html</ref>. Here, by
                    clicking on “Compare,” one can compare different diplomatic editions of the
                    various witnesses that compose the tradition of that tale.</note>
                <note xml:id="note21">G. Thomas Tanselle, <hi rend="italic">A Rationale of Textual
                        Criticism</hi> (Philadelphia: University of Pennsylvania Press, 1989). The
                    terminology has been adopted by Robinson, “Towards a Theory of Digital
                    Editions.”</note>
                <note xml:id="note22">The oldest preserved, the best survived, the closest to the
                    authorial intentions, the latest editions, and so on. Peter Shillingsburg does a
                    very good job in putting different theoretical editorial position into an
                    historical perspective: “Each generation seems to hope for the best answer and
                    finds the effort of the older generations to be inadequate. Soon it will be our
                    turn to have failed.” Shillingsburg, <hi rend="italic">From Gutenberg to
                        Google</hi> (Cambridge: Cambridge University Press, 2006), p. 153. </note>
                <note xml:id="note23">“The smoothness of the clear reading text, a hall mark of
                    critical editing, in effect denies us an immediate awareness of the actual
                    roughness of the textual record, and textuality itself.” John Bryant, <hi
                        rend="italic">The Fluid Text: A Theory of Revision and Editing for Book and
                        Screen</hi> (Ann Arbor: University of Michigan Press, 2002), 27. Peter
                    Shillingsburg complains about the format and content of the apparatus which
                    leave readers “between wanting [. . .] to know the variant versions of the work [. . .]
                    and, on the other hand to forget the whole thing as more trouble than the effort
                    of deciphering and sifting an apparatus was worth.” Shillingsburg, <hi
                        rend="italic">Scholarly Editing in the Computer Age: Theory and
                        Practice</hi> (Ann Arbor: University of Michigan Press, 1996), 118. See also
                    J. Lavagnino, “Access,” <hi rend="italic">Literary and Linguistic Computing</hi>
                    24, no. 1 (2009): 63–76.</note>
                <note xml:id="note24">See <ref type="url"
                        target="http://www.bbc.co.uk/news/entertainment-arts-11610489"
                        >http://www.bbc.co.uk/news/entertainment-arts-11610489</ref>.</note>
                <note xml:id="note25">See the story beautifully told by Eggert, <hi rend="italic"
                        >Securing the Past</hi>, 164–78.</note>
                <note xml:id="note26">Eggert, <hi rend="italic">Securing the Past</hi>, 180–84. See
                    also Kline and Perdue, <hi rend="italic">A Guide to Documentary Editing</hi>,
                    1–34.</note>
                <note xml:id="note27">Or the battle of the intentionalists against the materialists,
                    to use Bryant’s terminology (<hi rend="italic">The Fluid Text</hi>).</note>
                <note xml:id="note28">By “best” it is here meant which editorial framework is better
                    able to respond to the editors’ research questions. Fredson Bowers, in spite of
                    being a strong champion of critical eclectic editing, seems to hint toward this
                    direction in his essay of 1991, where he declares that it might be advisable in
                    some cases to provide different editions for different types of readers, with
                    documentary editions offered to scholars and critical editions for the general
                    public (“Authorial Intention and the Editorial Problems,” <hi rend="italic"
                        >Text</hi> 5 [1991]: 55, 61).</note>
                <note xml:id="note29">In the Italian tradition of textual scholarship (in which I
                    was trained), the contrary is true: editors approach works to be edited
                    differently, according to the type of tradition that transmits the texts,
                    “contaminating” methodologies in the search of the “most economic working
                    hypothesis accounting for the data we possess” (“l’ipotesi di lavoro più
                    economica che tenga conto dei dati”) (Gianfranco Contini, <hi rend="italic"
                        >Breviario di Ecdotica</hi> [Torino: Einaudi, 1989]). Alfredo Stussi has
                    elaborated an approach he calls <hi rend="italic">filologia d’autore</hi>
                    (“philology of the author”), which suggests, in particular for modern authors,
                    that editors apply the method that is better able to account for the surviving
                    evidence (Stussi, <hi rend="italic">Introduzione agli Studi di Filologia
                        Italiana</hi> [Bologna: Il Mulino, 2006]).</note>
                <note xml:id="note30">Shillingsburg, <hi rend="italic">Scholarly Editing in the
                        Computer Age</hi>, 26.</note>
                <note xml:id="note31">“For the sake of convenience, they [i.e. documentary and
                    critical editing] came to be known as historical and literary editing, a
                    division many regarded as unrealistic and unfortunate” (Kline and Perdue, <hi
                        rend="italic">A Guide to Documentary Editing</hi>, 11).</note>
                <note xml:id="note32">See this position accounted for in Shillingsburg, <hi
                        rend="italic">Scholarly Editing in the Computer Age</hi>, 17. The criticism
                    of the critical editor is mostly implicit in Kline and Perdue, <hi rend="italic"
                        >A Guide to Documentary Editing</hi> (cf., for instance, the mention of the
                    “vanished archetype” at p. 3); however, it is mostly the principal argument of
                    German editorial theories against Anglo-American copy-text orientation (cf.
                    Shillingsburg, <hi rend="italic">From Gutenberg to Google</hi>, 173–88, for an
                    account of the debate).</note>
                <note xml:id="note33">See Greetham, <hi rend="italic">Textual Scholarship</hi>, and
                    Bernard Cerquiglini, <hi rend="italic">Éloge de la variante: Histoire critique
                        de la philologie</hi> (Paris: Seuil, 1989), English translation by Betsy
                    Wing, <hi rend="italic">In Praise of the Variant: A Critical History of
                        Philology</hi> (Baltimore: Johns Hopkins University Press, 1999).</note>
                <note xml:id="note34">This criticism lies at the heart of the polemic between
                    Tanselle and the ADI: see G. Thomas Tanselle, “The Editing of Historical
                    Documents,” <hi rend="italic">Studies in Bibliography</hi>, 31 (1978): 1–56, and
                    Kline and Perdue, <hi rend="italic">A Guide to Documentary Editing</hi>,
                    19–22.</note>
                <note xml:id="note35">Edward Vanhoutte, “Every Reader His Own Bibliographer—An
                    Absurdity?” in <hi rend="italic">Text Editing, Print and the Digital World</hi>,
                    ed. Marilyn Deegan and Kathryn Sutherland (Aldershot: Ashgate, 2009),
                    99–110.</note>
                <note xml:id="note36">More information about ITEM can be found at the Institute website at <ref type="url" target="http://www.item.ens.fr/"
                        >http://www.item.ens.fr/</ref>.</note>
                <note xml:id="note37">Almuth Grésillon, <hi rend="italic">Eléments de critique
                        génétique: Lire les manuscrits modernes</hi> (Paris: Presses universitaires
                    de France, 1994), 195–202.</note>
                <note xml:id="note38">A particularly good (or bad) example of this is represented by the genetic edition of Gustave Flaubert’s <hi rend="italic">Hérodias</hi>, edited by Giovanni Bonaccorso et al. (Paris: Nizet, 1991); this edition encompasses nine different types of arrows to mark the location of interlinear and marginal insertions belonging to four different revision campaigns. But see also Michael Hunter, <hi
                        rend="italic">Editing Early Modern Texts: An Introduction to Principles and
                        Practice</hi> (New York: Palgrave Macmillan, 2007), 118–20, for complaints
                    about similar issues in documentary editions of early modern texts.</note>
                <note xml:id="note39">See, for instance, the diplomatic edition of the Domesday Book
                    by Abraham Farley and Herry Ellis in 1783.</note>
                <note xml:id="note40">An exception is some of the editions sponsored by the Early
                    English Text Society (EETS), whose focus is on Old and Middle English texts,
                    covering works that have literary, linguistic, and historical interest.</note>
                <note xml:id="note41">One of the rare exceptions is represented, for instance, by
                    Hans Walter Gabler’s edition of <hi rend="italic">Ulysses</hi>, which has been
                    mentioned before. It is not, strictly speaking, a <hi rend="italic"
                        >Historisch-Kritische Ausgaben</hi> nor a genetic edition but an
                    adaptation of their methodologies to specific case. It is not a surprise,
                    then, that such an edition was conceived in a country with a more favorable
                    attitude toward this type of edition (James Joyce, <hi rend="italic">Ulysses: A
                        Critical and Synoptic Edition</hi>, ed. Hans Walter Gabler [New York:
                    Garland, 1984]). </note>
                <note xml:id="note42">Hunter, <hi rend="italic">Editing Early Modern Texts</hi>,
                    75.</note>
                <note xml:id="note43">Cerquiglini, <hi rend="italic">In Praise of the Variant</hi>;
                    McGann, <hi rend="italic">The Textual Condition</hi>. Cf. Driscoll, “The Words
                    on the Page.”</note>
                <note xml:id="note44">Richard J. Finneran, ed., <hi rend="italic">The Literary Text
                        in the Digital Age</hi> (Ann Arbor: University of Michigan Press, 1996),
                    x.</note>
                <note xml:id="note45">Supported by Joseph Bédier, “La tradition manuscrite du Lai de
                    l’Ombre: Réflexions sur l’art d’éditer les anciens textes,” <hi rend="italic"
                        >Romania</hi> 54 (1928): 61–96, 321–56.</note>
                <note xml:id="note46">Cf. Shillingsburg, <hi rend="italic">Scholarly Editing in the
                        Computer Age</hi>, 16–27. </note>
                <note xml:id="note47">This is what Peter Robinson seems to fear the most: “The
                    dominance of the document model of textual editing in the digital realm suggests
                    that a theory of digital editions is emerging, based on page-by-page
                    transcription of individual documents, which asserts that a digital edition
                    should concentrate on documents alone” (“Towards a Theory of Digital Editions,”
                    126).</note>
                <note xml:id="note48">The people that contributed to the elaboration of the new
                    model are: Anne Bohnenkamp (Goethe Universität), John Bryant (Hofstra
                    University), Aurèle Crasson (ITEM), Jean-Daniel Fekete (INRIA), Daniel Ferrer
                    (ITEM), Hans Walter Gabler (Ludwig-Maximilians Universität München), Axel
                    Gellhaus (Institut für Germanistische und Allgemeine Literaturwissenschaft der
                    RWTH Aachen), Almuth Grésillon (ITEM), Claus Huitfeldt (University of Bergen),
                    Dirk van Hulle (Universitte of Antwerp), Jean-Louis Lebrave (ITEM), Wolfgang
                    Lukas, Kenneth M. Price (University of Nebraska–Lincoln), Kathryn Sutherland
                    (St. Anne’s College, Oxford University). Members of the working group were
                    Fotis Iannidis (University of Würzburg), Gregor Middell, Moritz Wissenbach
                    (University of Würzburg), Malte Rehbein (University of Passau), Lou Burnard
                    (University of Oxford), Paolo D’Iorio (ITEM), and Elena Pierazzo (King’s College
                    London).</note>
                <note xml:id="note49">See Elena Pierazzo and Peter A. Stokes, “Putting the Text Back
                    into Context: A Codicological Approach to Manuscript Transcription,” in <hi
                        rend="italic">Kodikologie und Paläographie im Digitalen Zeitalter
                        2—Codicology and Palaeography in the Digital Age 2</hi>, ed. Franz Fischer,
                    Christiane Fritze, and Georg Vogeler, Schriften des Instituts für Dokumentologie
                    und Editorik 3 (Norderstedt, 2010), 397–430, urn:nbn:de:hbz:38-43605.</note>
                <note xml:id="note50">Elena Pierazzo, “Digital Genetic Editions: The Encoding of
                    Time in Manuscript Transcription,” in <hi rend="italic">Text Editing, Print and
                        the Digital World</hi>, ed. Marilyn Deegan and Kathryn Sutherland, 169–86
                    (Aldershot: Ashgate, 2009), p. 169.</note>
                <note xml:id="note51">See, for instance, some of the work done by Dirk Van Hulle
                    over Samuel Beckett’s draft manuscripts, and in particular D. Van Hulle, <hi
                        rend="italic">The Making of Samuel Beckett's “Stirrings Still / Soubresauts”
                        and “Comment dire /what is the word”</hi> (Brussels: Academic Scientific
                    Publishers, 2011). The book represents the theoretical counterpart of the <hi
                        rend="italic">Samuel Beckett Digital Manuscript Project</hi>, direction by
                    Dirk Van Hulle and Mark Nixon and technical realization by Vincent Neyt, <ref
                        type="url" target="http://www.beckettarchive.org/"
                        >http://www.beckettarchive.org/</ref>.</note>
                <note xml:id="note52">Again, the works of Samuel Beckett included in the Beckett’s
                    archive, edited by Dirk Van Hulle, demonstrates how flexible and suitable the
                    web is in accommodating the complexities of the draft manuscripts.</note>
                <note xml:id="note53">See J. André and E. Pierazzo, “Le codage en TEI des brouillons
                    de Proust: vers une édition numérique,” <hi rend="italic">Genesis</hi> 36
                    (2013): 155–61, and Pierazzo, “Of Time and Space.”</note>
                <note xml:id="note54">Citing one of the badges proposed by the TEI: <ref type="url"
                        target="http://www.tei-c.org/About/Badges/"
                        >http://www.tei-c.org/About/Badges/</ref>.</note>
                <note xml:id="note55">See the experience of the Faust Edition Project in using the
                    documentary encoding on a full-scale project: Gerrit Brüning, Katrin Henzel, and
                    Dietmar Pravida, “Multiple Encoding in Genetic Editions: The Case of ‘Faust,’”
                        <hi rend="italic">Journal of the Text Encoding Initiative</hi> 4 (2013),
                        <ref type="url"
                        target="http://jtei.revues.org/697;
                        DOI:10.4000/jtei.697"
                        >http://jtei.revues.org/697; DOI:10.4000/jtei.697</ref>.</note>
                <note xml:id="note56">Tara Andrews, “The Third Way: Philology and Critical Edition
                    in the Digital Age,” <hi rend="italic">Variants</hi> 10 (2013): 63.</note>
                <note xml:id="note57">See the excellent work and reflections developed within the
                    Interedition project (<ref type="url" target="http://www.interedition.eu/"
                        >http://www.interedition.eu/</ref>); the seminars and meetings organized by
                    the NeDiMAH network (<ref type="url" target="http://www.nedimah.eu/"
                        >http://www.nedimah.eu/</ref>); the recent workshop “Easy Tools for
                    Difficult Texts” organized by the Huygens Institute for the History of the
                    Netherlands in The Hague (<ref type="url"
                        target="http://easytools.huygens.knaw.nl/"
                        >http://easytools.huygens.knaw.nl/</ref>); and many other initiatives along
                    these lines. </note>
                <note xml:id="note58">Andrews, “The Third Way,” 73.</note>
                <note xml:id="note59">See Elena Pierazzo, “The Role of Technology in Scholarly
                    Editing” (paper presented at the TEI Members’ Meeting at the University of
                    Würzburg, 2011), abstract available at <ref type="url"
                        target="http://www.tei-c.org/Vault/MembersMeetings/2011/tei_mm_2011/abstracts/abstracts_papers/index.html"
                        >http://www.tei-c.org/Vault/MembersMeetings/2011/tei_mm_2011/abstracts/abstracts_papers/index.html</ref>.</note>
                <note xml:id="note60">But see also Tim McLoughlin’s illuminating contribution over
                    the intellectual difficulties that editors have to face once confronted with the
                    standardization required by the use of digital methodologies: McLoughlin,
                    “Bridging the Gap,” in <hi rend="italic">Jahrbruch für Computerphilologie</hi>,
                    ed. Malte Rehbein and Sean Ryder, 10 (2010): 37–54, <ref type="url"
                        target="http://computerphilologie.tu-darmstadt.de/jg08/mclough.pdf"
                        >http://computerphilologie.tu-darmstadt.de/jg08/mclough.pdf</ref>.</note>
                <note xml:id="note61">Unexpected by its own supporters: as mentioned above, in 2007
                    only Gabler was advocating for a renewed scholarly interest in documentary
                    editions (Gabler, “The Primacy of the Document”). </note>
                <note xml:id="note62">Robinson, “Towards a Theory of Digital Editions,” 127.</note>
                <note xml:id="note63">Pierazzo and Stokes, “Putting the Text Back into
                    Context.”</note>
                <note xml:id="note64">Daniel Ferrer, “The Open Space of the Draft Page: James Joyce
                    and Modern Manuscripts,” in T<hi rend="italic">he Iconic Page in Manuscript,
                        Print and Digital Culture</hi>, ed. George Bornstein and Theresa Tinkle,
                    249–67 (Ann Arbor: University of Michigan Press, 1998).</note>
                <note xml:id="note65">Pierazzo, “Of Time and Space.”</note>
                <note xml:id="note66">See, for instance, the very promising research undertaken by
                    Edward Vanhoutte in several of his contributions such as “Every
                    Reader His Own Bibliographer” and “Defining Electronic Editions: A Historical
                    and Functional Perspective” in <hi rend="italic">Text and Genre in Reconstruction: Effects of
                    Digitalization on Ideas, Behaviours, Products and Institutions</hi>, ed. Willard
                    McCarty, 119–44 (Cambridge: Open Book Publisher, 2010).</note>

            </div>
        </back>
    </text>
</TEI>
