<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
    <teiHeader xml:lang="eng">
        <fileDesc>
            <titleStmt>
                <title level="a" type="main">Recent Editions</title>
                <title level="a" type="sub">2012</title>
                <author>W. Bland Whitley</author>
            </titleStmt>
            <editionStmt>
                <edition>
                    <date>2012</date>
                </edition>
            </editionStmt>
            <publicationStmt>
                <idno type="file">review.recenteditions2012</idno>
                <authority>Scholary Editing: The Annual of the Association for Documentary
                    Editing</authority>
                <address>
          <addrLine>http://www.scholarlyediting.org</addrLine>
        </address>
                <publisher>Association for Documentary Editing</publisher>
                <publisher>University of Nebraska&#8211;Lincoln</publisher>
                <distributor>
                    <name>Center for Digital Research in the Humanities</name>
                    <address>
            <addrLine>319 Love Library</addrLine>
            <addrLine>University of Nebraska&#8211;Lincoln</addrLine>
            <addrLine>Lincoln, NE 68588-4100</addrLine>
            <addrLine>http://cdrh.unl.edu</addrLine>
          </address>
                </distributor>
                <date>2012</date>
                <availability>
                    <p>Scholary Editing: The Annual of the Association for Documentary Editing is
                        freely distributed by the Association for Documentary Editing and the Center
                        for Digital Research in the Humanities at the University of Nebraska-Lincoln
                        and licensed under a Creative Commons Attribution-NonCommercial-ShareAlike
                        3.0 Unported License</p>
                </availability>
            </publicationStmt>
            <seriesStmt>
                <title level="j"
                    >Scholarly Editing: The Annual of the Association for Documentary
                    Editing</title>
                <respStmt>
                    <resp>editor</resp>
                    <name xml:id="ag">Amanda Gailey</name>
                </respStmt>
                <respStmt>
                    <resp>editor</resp>
                    <name xml:id="awj">Andrew Jewell</name>
                </respStmt>
                <idno type="vol">33</idno>
                <idno type="ISSN">2167-1257</idno>
            </seriesStmt>
            <sourceDesc>
                <bibl>
                    <note>Born digital.</note>
                </bibl>
            </sourceDesc>
        </fileDesc>
        <revisionDesc>
            <change when="2012-01-25" who="#awj">markup in TEI XML</change>
        </revisionDesc>
    </teiHeader>
    <text>
        
<front><head type="main">Recent Editions</head>
<byline>Compiled by W. Bland Whitley</byline></front><body>
            <p>This annual bibliography of documentary editions recently
                published in the fields of American and British history, literature, and
                culture is generally restricted to scholarly first editions of English-language
                works. In addition to the bibliographical references, Internet addresses are
                provided for the editorial project or the publisher.</p>
            <list type="simple">
                <item><p>ADAIR, LYLE G. <hi rend="italic"
                            >"They
                Have Left Us Here to Die": The Civil War Prison Diary of Sgt. Lyle G.
                Adair, 111th U.S. Colored Infantry</hi>. Edited by Glenn Robins. Kent
                State University Press. 2011. 72 pp. $19.95. ISBN: 9781606351017. Adair was
                captured by Confederate cavalry and spent the last seven months of the war in
                five different Confederate prison camps. This edited and annotated version of
                the diary Adair kept reflects his strong allegiance to the Union cause and
                provides insights into the breakdown of the prisoner exchange system between
                the Union and Confederacy. A white soldier serving in an African American
                regiment, Adair also provided revealing observations about the influence of
                race on the experience of captivity.</p>
                    <p><ref type="url" target="http://www.kentstateuniversitypress.com"
                            >http://www.kentstateuniversitypress.com</ref></p>
                </item>
                <item>
                    <p>ADAMS FAMILY. <hi rend="italic"
                            >Adams
                    Family Correspondence, Volume 10: January 1794&#8211;June 1795</hi>. Edited by
                    Margaret A. Hogan, C. James Taylor, Sara Martin, Hobson Woodward, Sara B.
                    Sikes, Gregg L. Lint, and Sara Georgini. Belknap Press of Harvard University
                    Press. 2011. 608 pp. $105. ISBN: 978067405845. In this volume's over 300
                    letters, the Adams family offers important observations and commentary on a
                    contentious period of American history, as tensions with Great Britain and
                    France sparked political factionalism. Other highlights of the volume include
                    the birth of Abigail and John Adams's first granddaughter and John Quincy's
                    appointment as resident minister at the Hague, where he and his brother Thomas
                    Boylston witnessed the French invasion of the Netherlands and the impact of the
                    French Revolution on the broader European society.</p>
                    <p><ref type="url" target="http://www.adamspapers.org"
                            >http://www.adamspapers.org</ref></p>
                </item>
                <item>
                    <p>AMERICAN REVOLUTION. <hi rend="italic"
                            >Captured
                    at Kings Mountain: The Journal of Uzal Johnson, a Loyalist Surgeon</hi>. Edited
                    by Wade S. Kolb III and Robert M. Weir. University of South Carolina Press.
                    2011. 248 pp. $39.95. ISBN: 9781570039614. A New Jersey native, Johnson
                    traveled with the American Volunteers, a Loyalist unit, to South Carolina. His
                    journal recounted his experiences and observations during a critical year that
                    culminated in the American victory at Kings Mountain. The journal advances our
                    understanding of the social, medical, and military history of the Revolution in
                    the southern theater.</p>
                    <p><ref type="url" target="http://www.uscpress.com"
                            >http://www.uscpress.com</ref></p>
                </item>
                <item>
                    <p>AMERICAN SOUTH. <hi rend="italic"
                        >See</hi>
BROWN, WILLIAM WELLS; HEYWARD FAMILY.</p></item>
                <item>
                    <p>ANGLICANISM. <hi rend="italic"
                            >The
Letters of George Davenport, 1651-1677</hi>. Edited by Brenda M. Pask. Boydell
&amp; Brewer. 2011. 312 pp. $90. ISBN: 9780854440702. Consisting largely of
letters from Davenport to fellow Anglican William Sancroft, this collection sheds
considerable light on efforts of committed Anglicans to sustain their faith
during the Commonwealth period and also on the Restoration settlement in and around
Durham. Also included is a list of manuscripts that Davenport contributed to
the famous library of John Cosin, bishop of Durham.</p>
                    <p><ref type="url" target="http://www.boydellandbrewer.com"
                            >http://www.boydellandbrewer.com</ref></p></item>
                <item>
                    <p>AUDEN, W. H. <hi rend="italic"
                        >The Age
of Anxiety: A Baroque Eclogue</hi>. Edited by Alan Jacobs. Princeton University
Press. 2011. 200 pp. $22.95. ISBN: 9780691138152. First published in 1947,
Auden's book-length poem struck an immediate chord, winning the Pulitzer Prize
and inspiring a symphony and ballet, but later fell out of critical favor. This
critical edition introduces the poem to a new generation of readers and
provides thorough annotations that will encourage appreciation of Auden's
accomplishment.</p>
                    <p><ref type="url" target="http://press.princeton.edu"
                            >http://press.princeton.edu</ref></p></item>
                <item>
                    <p>BACHMAN, JOHN. <hi rend="italic"
                            >Selected
Writings on Science, Race, and Religion</hi>. Edited by Gene Waddell. University
of Georgia Press. 2011. 400 pp. $39.95. ISBN: 9780820338187. Bachman was a
Lutheran minister in Charleston and the world's leading authority on North
American mammals. In arguing that humans constituted a single species, he
challenged the polygenetic views of Louis Agassiz. This is the first collection
of his writings and includes selections from his three major books, letters,
and his articles on a wide range of subjects.</p>
                    <p><ref type="url" target="http://www.ugapress.org"
                            >http://www.ugapress.org</ref>
                    </p></item>
<item>                    <p>BARTRAM, WILLIAM. <hi rend="italic"
                            >William
Bartram: The Search for Nature's Design: Selected Art, Letters, and Unpublished
Writings</hi>. Edited by Thomas Hallock and Nancy E. Hoffmann. University of
Georgia Press. 2010. 608 pp. $50. ISBN: 9780820328775. This work assembles a
selection of letters, presented chronologically, various manuscripts, and other
material by the famous naturalist and travel writer. Over 100 illustrations by
Bartram bring to life his correspondence and the manuscripts, which include
horticultural texts, poetry, and philosophical and ethnographic reflections.</p>
                    <p><ref type="url" target="http://www.ugapress.org"
                            >http://www.ugapress.org</ref></p></item>
                <item>
                    <p>BALL, AUGUSTUS V. <hi rend="italic"
                            >Love
and War: The Civil War Letters and Medicinal Book of Augustus V. Ball</hi>.
Edited by Donald S. Frazier and Andrew Hillhouse. Compiled by Anne Ball Ryals.
Texas A&amp;M University Press. 2011. 528 pp. $59.95. ISBN: 9781933337425. The
letters between Ball, his wife, and other friends and acquaintances depict his
growing disillusionment as a Confederate doctor in the trans-Mississippi
theater. His medicinal recipe book, the first of its kind to appear in print
completely annotated, will introduce readers to the medical and herbal lore of
the Civil War era.</p>
                    <p><ref type="url" target="http://www.tamupress.com"
                            >http://www.tamupress.com</ref></p></item>
                <item>
                    <p>BECKETT, SAMUEL. <hi rend="italic"
                            >The
Letters of Samuel Beckett, Volume 2: 1941-1956</hi>. Edited by George Craig,
Martha Dow Fehsenfeld, Dan Gunn, and Lois More Overbeck. Cambridge University
Press. 2011. 886 pp. $50. ISBN: 9780521867948. Opening with the War years, when
Beckett could conduct little correspondence, this volume includes a surge of
letters beginning in 1945, which illuminate his transformation from a
little-known author to an international literary figure. Contextual information
includes discussions of Beckett's move into the French language, translations,
profiles of correspondents, and chronologies.</p>
                    <p><ref type="url" target="http://www.cambridge.org"
                            >http://www.cambridge.org</ref></p></item>
                <item>
                    <p>BENTHAM, JEREMY. <hi rend="italic"
                            >Church
of Englandism and Its Catechism Explained</hi>. Edited by James E. Crimmins,
Catherine Fuller, and Philip Schofield. Oxford University Press. 2011. 668 pp.
$160. ISBN: 9780199590254. Published in 1818, this work was part of Bentham's
sustained attack on English political, legal, and ecclesiastical
establishments. Bentham argued that the purpose of the Anglican
educational system was to instill habits of insincerity and protect abuses that
were useful to the church and the ruling classes in general. Published here for
the first time is an appendix based on original manuscripts.</p>
                    <p><ref type="url" target="http://www.oup.com/us"
                        >http://www.oup.com/us</ref></p></item>
                <item>
                    <p>BRADBURY, RAY. <hi rend="italic"
                            >The
Collected Stories of Ray Bradbury: A Critical Edition. Volume 1, 1938-1943</hi>.
Edited by William F. Touponce and Jonathan R. Eller. Kent State University
Press. 2011. 544 pp. $65. ISBN: 9781606350713. Using texts that reflect
Bradbury's earliest settled intention for each tale, this edition presents for
the first time the author's stories in chronological order. The first volume
includes 13 stories and examines Bradbury's relationships with his agent,
editor, and publisher, thereby documenting the transformations of the stories
from their original forms to the versions known today.</p>
                    <p><ref type="url" target="http://www.kentstateuniversitypress.com"
                            >http://www.kentstateuniversitypress.com</ref></p></item>
                <item>
                    <p>BROWN, WILLIAM WELLS. <hi rend="italic"
                            >My
Southern Home: The South and Its People</hi>. Edited by John Ernest. University
of North Carolina Press. 2011. 288 pp. $69.95. ISBN: 9780807835111. The
culmination of Brown's long writing career, <hi
                            rend="italic"
                        >My
Southern Home</hi> recounted his efforts to find a home in the chaotic and
racist social landscape of the American South after the Civil War. Presenting
the text in its original form, this edition illuminates the work's complexity
and documents the many instances in which Brown borrows from his previous
writings and the writings of others to form an underlying dialogue.</p>
                    <p><ref type="url" target="http://www.uncpress.unc.edu"
                            >http://www.uncpress.unc.edu</ref></p></item>
                <item>
                    <p>CAMBRIDGE UNIVERSITY. <hi rend="italic"
                            >The
Palfrey Notebook: Records of Study in Seventeenth-Century Cambridge</hi>. Edited
by C. J. Cook. Boydell &amp; Brewer. 2011. 818 pp. $99. ISBN: 9781843836667.
Compiled by George Palfrey of Sidney Sussex College, Cambridge, about 1623,
this study notebook is a unique survival of the period. The fully annotated
transcription covers many of the widely used texts of the period, filtered
through the moderate Calvinism of Palfrey's principal instructor. It also
includes a survey of the literature on magic, records of orations, personal
notes, and an anti-papal diatribe.</p>
                    <p><ref type="url" target="http://www.boydellandbrewer.com"
                            >http://www.boydellandbrewer.com</ref></p></item>
                <item>
                    <p>CATHOLICISM. <hi rend="italic"
                            >Testamentary
Records of the English and Welsh Episcopate, 1200-1413: Wills, Executors'
Accounts &amp; Inventories, &amp; the Probate Process</hi>. Edited by C. M.
Woolgar. Boydell &amp; Brewer. 2011. 418 pp. $45. ISBN: 9780907239741. Consisting
of the probate material of almost 300 English or Welsh individuals overseen by
the late medieval episcopate, this fully annotated collection illustrates
common patterns of living, customary and devotional practices, and the efforts
to keep ecclesiastical property out of the hands of the Crown.</p>
                    <p><ref type="url" target="http://www.boydellandbrewer.com"
                            >http://www.boydellandbrewer.com</ref></p></item>
                <item>
                    <p>CIVIL WAR. <hi rend="italic"
                            >Tejanos in
Gray: Civil War Letters of Captains Joseph Rafael de la Garza and Manuel Yturri</hi>.
Edited by Jerry Thompson. Translations by Jos Roberto Jurez. Texas A&amp;M
University Press. 2011. 160 pp. $29.95. ISBN: 9781603442435. Gathered for the
first time, these letters between two members of San Antonio's <hi
                            rend="italic"
                        >Tejano</hi> elite reveal the intricate and
intertwined relationships that characterized the Mexican Texas community in the
years leading up to and including the Civil War. The letters complicate readers'
understanding of Confederate allegiance and loyalty.</p>
                    <p><ref type="url" target="http://www.tamupress.com"
                            >http://www.tamupress.com</ref></p></item>
                <item>
                    <p>CIVIL WAR. <hi rend="italic"
                        >See also</hi>
ADAIR, LYLE G.; BALL, AUGUSTUS V.; CYPERT, THOMAS JEFFERSON; HAYWARD, AMBROSE
HENRY; HEYWARD FAMILY; REYNOLDS, DANIEL HARRIS.</p></item>
                   <item> <p>CODY, WILLIAM F. <hi rend="italic"
                            >The
Life of Hon. William F. Cody, Known as Buffalo Bill</hi>. Edited by Frank
Christianson. University of Nebraska Press. 2011. 456 pp. $27.95.
9780803232914. Based on Cody's original edition of 1879, when Cody was 33, this
volume offers the frontiersman and showman's mythical take on his career as a
trapper, buffalo hunter, Army scout, and Indian fighter. Christianson's
annotations reveal both Cody's personal history and the Buffalo Bill of
American myth, as well as the aspects of his life that lived up to both myth
and the harsher realities of the American West.</p>
                       <p><hi rend="italic">www.nebraskapress.unl.edu</hi></p></item>
                <item>
                    <p>CONGRESS. <hi rend="italic"
                            >Documentary
History of the First Federal Congress of the United States of America, March 4,
1789-March 3, 1791. Correspondence: Second Session</hi>. Edited by Charlene
Bangs Bickford, Kenneth R. Bowling, William Charles diGiacomantonio, and Helen
E. Veit. The Johns Hopkins University Press. 2011. Volume 18: 952 pp. $125.
ISBN: 9780801894459. Volume 19: 1136 pp. $125. ISBN: 9780801894466. Volume 20:
992 pp. $125. ISBN: 9780801894473. Three new volumes present letters written by
and to members of the First Federal Congress during its second session, as well
as communications from other informed individuals at the seat of government in
New York City. Bringing to life the legislation and debates of this most
important and productive Congress, the volumes provide a rich source of
information about the members of Congress. Many of the documents will be
incorporated into <hi
                            rend="italic">The Early Republic</hi>,
an online reference.</p>
                    <p><ref type="url" target="http://www.press.jhu.edu"
                            >http://www.press.jhu.edu</ref></p></item>
                <item>
                    <p>CONSTITUTION. <hi rend="italic"
                            >The
Documentary History of the Ratification of the Constitution, Volume 24,
Ratification by the States: Rhode Island, No. 1</hi>. Edited by John P.
Kaminski, Gaspare J. Saladino, Jonathan M. Reid, Charles H. Schoenleber,
Richard Leffler, Margaret R. Flamingo. Wisconsin Historical Society Press.
2011. 424 pp. $95. ISBN: 9780870204685. The first of three volumes documenting
Rhode Island's private and public debates about the Constitution, it brings
together the convention <hi
                            rend="italic">Journal</hi>  and <hi rend="italic"
                        >Debates</hi>, the correspondence and notes of
delegates, the notes of the secretary of the convention, and contemporary
newspaper accounts.</p>
                    <p><ref type="url" target="http://www.wisconsinhistory.org"
                            >http://www.wisconsinhistory.org</ref></p></item>
                <item>
                    <p>COREY, ELIZABETH. <hi rend="italic"
                            >An
Iowa Schoolma'am: Letters of Elizabeth "Bess" Corey, 1904-1908</hi>.
Edited by Philip L. Gerber and Charlotte Wright. University of Iowa Press.
2011. 216 pp. $25. ISBN: 9781587299605. As a teenager, Elizabeth Corey received
a certificate to teach, which she did during the first decade of the twentieth
century in a series of rural schools in Shelby and Cass Counties, Iowa. Her
letters of this period reveal her lighthearted attitude and provide insights
into the teaching profession as it was practiced in the rural Midwest.</p>
                    <p><ref type="url" target="http://www.uiowapress.org"
                            >http://www.uiowapress.org</ref></p></item>
                <item>
                    <p>CROCKER, HANNAH MATHER. <hi rend="italic"
                            >Reminiscences
and Traditions of Boston by Hannah Mather Crocker</hi>. Edited by Eileen Hunt
Botting and Sarah L. Houser. New England Historic Genealogical Society. 2011.
539 pp. $39.95. ISBN: 9780880822534. Crocker descended from some of Boston's
most important families and was a writer and women's rights advocate. Her early
nineteenth-century reminiscences, published here for the first time, present a
unique history of the Boston area from the 1620s to the 1820s and chronicle
such subjects as Puritan law, church history, and women's work and culture.</p>
                    <p><ref type="url" target="http://www.americanancestors.org"
                            >http://www.americanancestors.org</ref></p></item>
                <item>
                    <p>CROMMELIN, CLAUDE AUGUST. <hi rend="italic"
                            >A Young Dutchman Views Post-Civil War America: Diary of Claude August
Crommelin</hi>. Translated by Augustus J. Veenendaal, Jr. Edited by Augustus J.
Veenendaal, Jr., and H. Roger Grant. Indiana University Press. 2011. 208 pp.
$29.95. ISBN: 9780253356093. A wealthy young Dutchman, Crommelin used family
connections to meet important people in his travels through New England, the
Middle Atlantic states, the South, and the upper Mississippi Valley. Published
in English for the first time, his journal reveals an astute observer of
industry and politics, as well as an engaging writing style.</p>
                    <p><ref type="url" target="http://www.iupress.indiana.edu"
                            >http://www.iupress.indiana.edu</ref></p></item>
                <item>
                    <p>CYPERT, THOMAS JEFFERSON. <hi rend="italic"
                            >Tried Men and True, or Union Life in Dixie</hi>. Edited by Margaret M.
Storey. University of Alabama Press. 2011. 184 pp. $26. ISBN: 9780817317508. A
staunch Unionist of Wayne County, Tennessee, Cypert helped organize a regiment
of loyalist white Southerners enlisted to combat Confederate cavalry in west
Tennessee and northern Alabama. He later served two terms in the Tennessee
state senate. Never before published, Cypert's memoir reflected his Unionist
beliefs and advanced loyalists' claims for post-war power.</p>
                    <p><ref type="url" target="http://www.uapress.ua.edu"
                            >http://www.uapress.ua.edu</ref></p></item>
                <item>
                    <p>DUNCAN, ROBERT. <hi rend="italic"
                            >The
H.D. Book: The Collected Writings of Robert Duncan</hi>. Edited by Michael
Boughn and Victor Coleman. University of California Press. 2011. 704 pp.
$49.95. ISBN: 9780520260757. A major figure in the San Francisco literary
community, Duncan, through an examination of the modernist poet H.D. and other
modernist figures, sought to develop a unique poetics. Formerly existing only
as chapters in out-of-print magazines, Duncan's meditation on modernism is now
published in its entirety, as its author originally intended.</p>
                    <p><ref type="url" target="http://www.ucpress.edu"
                        >http://www.ucpress.edu</ref></p></item>
                <item>
                    <p>EDISON, THOMAS A. <hi rend="italic"
                            >The
Papers of Thomas A. Edison, Volume 7: Losses and Loyalties, April 1883-December
1884</hi>. Edited by Paul B. Israel, Louis Carlat, Theresa M. Collins, and David
Hochfelder. The Johns Hopkins University Press. 2011. 864 pp. $95. ISBN:
9781421400907. This volume captures Edison's efforts to replicate the success
of his New York electric central system, which required him to forego the lab
in favor of expanding his business interests. The volume also includes the
unexpected death of Edison's wife and concludes with his return to the lab to
develop new communications technology.</p>
                    <p><ref type="url" target="http://www.press.jhu.edu"
                            >http://www.press.jhu.edu</ref></p></item>
                <item>
                    <p>ELIOT, T. S. <hi rend="italic"
                            >The
Letters of T. S. Eliot</hi>. Edited by Valerie Eliot and Hugh Haughton. Yale
University Press. 2011. <hi
                            rend="italic"
                            >Volume 1:
    1898-1922, Revised Edition</hi>. 912 pp. $45. ISBN: 9780300176452. <hi
                            rend="italic"
                            >Volume 2: 1923-1925</hi>. 912 pp. $45. ISBN:
9780300176865. Volume 1, first published in 1988, covers the years of Eliot's
childhood through his relocation to England, marriage, and the publication of <hi
                            rend="italic"
                        >The Waste Land</hi>. It now includes 200
newly discovered documents. Volume 2 includes about 1,400 letters, which shed
light on Eliot's developing thought about poetry, his embrace of Anglicanism,
and his transition from banking to publishing.</p>
                    <p><ref type="url" target="http://yalepress.yale.edu"
                            >http://yalepress.yale.edu</ref></p></item>
                <item>
                    <p>EMERSON, RALPH WALDO. <hi rend="italic"
                            >The Collected Works of Ralph Waldo
Emerson, Volume 9: Poems</hi>. Edited
by Albert J. von Frank and Thomas Wortham.Belknap Press of Harvard University Press. 2011. 864 pp. $95.
ISBN: 9780674049154. This edition of all the poems Emerson published during his
lifetime allows readers to situate Emerson's poetry alongside his celebrated
essays and to consider their interrelationship. Although his reputation as an
essayist has long since eclipsed his reputation as a poet, Emerson
self-identified as a writer of verse and worked out his transcendental
philosophy in this genre. Also included in the annotated edition are
chronological lists of variants and texts constituting the historical collation,
and public and private writings that reveal Emerson's own estimation of his
poetry.</p>
                    <p><ref type="url" target="http://www.hup.harvard.edu"
                            >http://www.hup.harvard.edu</ref></p></item>
                <item>
                    <p>FRANKLIN, BENJAMIN. <hi rend="italic"
                            >The
Papers of Benjamin Franklin, Volume 40: May 16 through September 15, 1783</hi>.
                        <!-- Ellen R. Cohn, Editor; Jonathan R. Dull, Senior Associate Editor; Karen Duval and Kate M. Ohno, Associate Editors; Alicia K. Anderson, Adrina M. Garbooshian, Michael Sletcher, and Philipp Ziesche, Assistant Editors; Alysia M. Cain, Editorial Assistant -->Edited by Ellen R. Cohn, Jonathan R. Dull, Kate M. Ohno, Karen Duval, Alicia K. Anderson, Adrina M. Garbooshian, Michael Sletcher, and Philipp Ziesche. Yale University
Press. 2011. 784 pp. $100. ISBN: 9780300165463. This volume covers the final
phase of the negotiations that culminated in the peace treaty between the
United States and Great Britain. In addition to correspondence with Franklin's
fellow peace commissioners, the volume includes documents related to his many
scientific and literary interests, as well as a discussion of the slave trade
with a British abolitionist.</p>
                    <p><ref type="url" target="http://www.yalepress.yale.edu"
                            >http://www.yalepress.yale.edu</ref></p></item>
                <item>
                    <p>GARDENING. <hi rend="italic"
                            >Becoming
Elizabeth Lawrence: Discovered Letters of a Southern Gardener</hi>. Edited by
Emily Herring Wilson. John F. Blair, Publisher. 2010. 315 pp. $19.95. ISBN:
9780895873750. The first woman to receive a degree in landscape architecture
from what is now North Carolina State University, Lawrence wrote extensively on
gardening in horticultural journals and for the <hi
                            rend="italic"
                        >Charlotte Observer</hi>. She also published several books, some that
remain in print. This volume consists of letters Lawrence wrote to a close
friend that extend from 1934 to 1966 and reveal much about Lawrence's
development as a gardener and writer, as well as the mores of a woman of her
class and Episcopal faith.</p>
                    <p><ref type="url" target="http://www.blairpub.com"
                            >http://www.blairpub.com</ref></p></item>
                <item>
                    <p>GARVEY, MARCUS. <hi rend="italic"
                            >The
Marcus Garvey and Universal Negro Improvement Association Papers, Volume 11:
The Caribbean Diaspora, 1910-1920</hi>. Edited by Robert A. Hill, John Dixon,
Mariela Haro Rodriguez, and Anthony Yuen. Duke University Press. 2011. 1128 pp.
$120. ISBN: 9780822346906. This volume reveals the connections between the
major African-American mass movement of the interwar era and the struggles of
Caribbean people for independence. It includes letters, speeches, and writings
of Caribbean Garveyites and their opponents, as well as documents and speeches
by Garvey. Highlights include a 1920 strike by Panama Canal workers sponsored
by the UNIA.</p>
                    <p><ref type="url" target="http://www.dukeupress.edu"
                            >http://www.dukeupress.edu</ref></p></item>
                <item>
                    <p>GORDON, MARGARET E. P. <hi rend="italic"
                            >Pansy's
History: The Autobiography of Margaret E. P. Gordon, 1866-1966</hi>. Transcribed
and Edited by Claudia L. Bushman. Utah State University Press. 2011. 344 pp.
$34.95. ISBN: 9780874217841. Margaret "Pansy" Gordon's career took
her from England to an Anglican mission among the Tsimshian Indians in British
Columbia to Salt Lake City to an Ojibway village on Georgian Bay, and finally
to Los Angeles, where she was a Mormon missionary. Gordon's well-written,
engaging memoir of her many travels and adventures reveals the economic challenges
and religious service that defined her long life.</p>
                    <p><ref type="url" target="http://www.usu.edu/usupress"
                            >http://www.usu.edu/usupress</ref></p></item>
                <item>
                    <p>HAYWARD, AMBROSE HENRY. <hi rend="italic"
                            >Last
to Leave the Field: The Life and Letters of First Sergeant Ambrose Henry
Hayward, 28th Pennsylvania Volunteers</hi>. Edited by Timothy J. Orr.
University of Tennessee Press. 2011. 320 pp. $52. ISBN: 978157233729x. A native
of Massachusetts, Hayward saw action in five states, including the Battles of
Antietam, Gettysburg, and Atlanta, before his death at the Battle of Pine Knob
in Georgia. His correspondence highlights many of the war's most significant
developments and reveal his continued devotion to the Union cause, despite the
brutality of the war.</p>
                    <p><ref type="url" target="http://utpress.org"
                    >http://utpress.org</ref></p></item>
                <item>
                    <p>HEMINGWAY, ERNEST. <hi rend="italic"
                            >The
Letters of Ernest Hemingway, Volume 1: 1907-1922</hi>. Edited by Sandra Spanier
and Robert W. Trogdon. Cambridge University Press. 2011. 516 pp. $40. ISBN:
9780521897334. This volume encompasses Hemingway's youth, experience in World
War I, and his arrival in Paris, and reveals a more complex individual than the
hyper-masculine persona Hemingway presented publicly. The letters afford
insight into his creative process and reveal his opinions of his own work and
that of his contemporaries.</p>
                    <p><ref type="url" target="http://www.cambridge.org"
                            >http://www.cambridge.org</ref></p></item>
                <item>
                    <p>HEYWARD FAMILY. <hi rend="italic"
                            >Twilight
on the South Carolina Rice Fields: Letters of the Heyward Family, 1862-1871</hi>.
Edited by Margaret Belser Hollis and Allen H. Stokes. University of South
Carolina Press. 2010. 427 pp. $39.95. ISBN: 9781570038945. This edited
collection of letters of one of South Carolina's wealthiest families traces the
decline in their fortunes resulting from the Civil War, and their efforts to
preserve their standing in an altered political and economic environment. Most
of the letters included were from Barnwell Heyward to his wife Catherine and reflect
his experiences as an engineer during the war and his efforts to rebuild the
family's plantations after the war in the face of devastation and an
African-American work force claiming new rights.</p>
                    <p><ref type="url" target="http://www.uscpress.com"
                            >http://www.uscpress.com</ref></p></item>
                <item>
                    <p>JACKSON, ANDREW. <hi rend="italic"
                            >The
Papers of Andrew Jackson, Volume 8, 1830</hi>. Edited by Daniel Feller, Thomas
Coens, and Laura Eve Moss. University of Tennessee Press. 2010. 853 pp. $80.
ISBN: 987157233715x. This volume presents more than 500 documents, many never
published, in a tumultuous year in his presidency. In 1830, Jackson pursued his
Indian removal policy, concluding treaties to force the Choctaws and Chickasaws
to resettle west of the Mississippi, nurtured his opposition to the Second Bank
of the United States, and pronounced his ban on nullification. Meanwhile the
scandal surrounding Peggy Eaton continued to divide his cabinet and hinder his
administration.</p>
                    <p><ref type="url" target="http://utpress.org"
                    >http://utpress.org</ref></p></item>
                <item>
                    <p>JAMES, HENRY. <hi rend="italic"
                            >The
Complete Letters of Henry James, 1872-1876</hi>. Volume 3. Edited by Pierre A.
Walker and Greg W. Zacharias. University of Nebraska Press. 2011. 296 pp. $95.
ISBN: 9780803234574. The letters in this volume find James settling in Paris,
where he befriended the Russian novelist Ivan Turgenev and mixed with other
writers, such as Zola, Flaubert, and Alphonse Daudet. During this time he
published travel essays, critical notices, and the novels <hi
                            rend="italic">Roderick Hudson</hi> and <hi rend="italic"
                            >The
American</hi>.</p>
                    <p><ref type="url" target="http://www.nebraskapress.unl.edu"
                            >http://www.nebraskapress.unl.edu</ref></p></item>
                <item>
                    <p>JAMES, HENRY. <hi rend="italic"
                            >A Small
Boy and Others: A Critical Edition</hi>. Edited by Peter Collister. University
of Virginia Press. 2011. 400 pp. $55. ISBN: 9780813930817. James's memoir of
his boyhood in Albany and New York City, as well as his first travels in
Europe, illuminated his initiation into the world of art. This critical edition
guides readers through James's allusive prose and offers insights into his
formative years.</p>
                    <p><ref type="url" target="http://upress.virginia.edu"
                            >http://upress.virginia.edu</ref></p></item>
                <item>
                    <p>JAMES, HENRY. <hi rend="italic"
                            >Notes of
a Son and Brother and The Middle Years: A Critical Edition</hi>. Edited by Peter
Collister. University of Virginia Press. 2011. 600 pp. $75. ISBN: 9780813930831.
The first fully researched, critical edition of James's memoirs of his youth
and development as a writer in New England, and his middle years, when he was
residing in London, illuminates the context in which James developed a
characteristic voice. Annotations provide rich biographical details on James
and his literary circle.</p>
                    <p><ref type="url" target="http://upress.virginia.edu"
                            >http://upress.virginia.edu</ref></p></item>
                <item>
                    <p>JEFFERS, ROBINSON. <hi rend="italic"
                            >The
Collected Letters of Robinson Jeffers, with Selected Letters of Una Jeffers.
Volume 2, 1931-1939</hi>. Edited by James Karman. Stanford University Press.
2011. 1128 pp. $95. ISBN: 9780804777032. The second volume of Jeffers's
annotated correspondence documents his struggles and rising fame as a poet, the
growth and maturation of his twin sons, and his network of friends and acquaintances.
The volume also provides an intimate portrait of his relationship with his wife
Una Jeffers, including the 1938 controversy that nearly destroyed their
marriage.</p>
                    <p><ref type="url" target="http://www.sup.org"
                    >http://www.sup.org</ref></p></item>
                <item>
                    <p>JEFFERSON, THOMAS. <hi rend="italic"
                            >The
Papers of Thomas Jefferson, Volume 37: 4 March 1802 to 30 June 1802.</hi> Edited
by Barbara B. Oberg, James P. McClure, Elaine Weber Pascu, Martha J. King, Tom
Downey, and W. Bland Whitley. Princeton University Press. 2010. 844 pp. $99.50.
ISBN: 9780691150017. Opening on the one year anniversary of Jefferson's first
inauguration as president, this volume includes a conference with the Seneca
Indians, a treaty with the Choctaw nation to allow a wagon road across their
land, and worries about French control of New Orleans, worries strong enough to
force Jefferson to contemplate an alliance with the British. Among other
documents are a list of books purchased for the new Library of Congress and
several letters related to the ongoing renovations at Monticello. </p>
                    <p><ref type="url" target="http://press.princeton.edu"
                            >http://press.princeton.edu</ref></p></item>
                <item>
                    <p>JEFFERSON, THOMAS. <hi rend="italic"
                            >The
Papers of Thomas Jefferson: Retirement Series, Volume 7: 28 November 1813 to 30
September 1814</hi>. Edited by J. Jefferson Looney, Susan Holbrook Perdue, Robert
F. Haggard, Julie L. Lautenschlager, Ellen C. Hickman, and Christine Sternberg
Patrick. Princeton University Press. 2010. 832 pp. $99.50. ISBN: 9780691149752.
The 526 documents of this volume include Jefferson's review of the extant
sources on the 1765 Stamp Act Crisis, his largely favorable appraisal of George
Washington, and an updated reading list he drew up for law students. During
this time, he became a trustee of Albemarle Academy, a forerunner of the
University of Virginia, replied to queries on religion and abolition, and
offered to sell his massive book collection to Congress to replace the library
destroyed by the British.</p>
                    <p><ref type="url" target="http://press.princeton.edu"
                            >http://press.princeton.edu</ref></p></item>
                <item>
                    <p>JOHNSON, SAMUEL. <hi rend="italic"
                            >The
Works of Samuel Johnson, Volumes 21-23: The Lives of the Poets</hi>. Edited by
John H. Middendorf. Yale University Press. 1,696 pp. $350. ISBN: 9780300123142.
Initially planned as a series of short prefaces introducing separate volumes on
English poets, Johnson's project evolved into a comprehensive biographical and
critical survey of English poetry. This definitive edition reflects Johnson's final
wishes for its wording and includes explanatory annotations.</p>
                    <p><ref type="url" target="http://www.yalepress.yale.edu"
                            >http://www.yalepress.yale.edu</ref></p></item>
                <item>
                    <p>KAZIN, ALFRED. <hi rend="italic"
                        >Alfred
Kazin's Journals</hi>. Selected and Edited by Richard M. Cook. Yale University
Press. 2011. 512 pp. $45. ISBN: 9780300142037. Kazin contributed almost daily
to his journals, which trace his journey from Brooklyn's Brownsville
neighborhood to his position as a leading figure in American letters. In
addition to insights into Kazin's searching intellect and reflections on
literature, history, and politics, readers will encounter an array of
interesting and notable individuals.</p>
                    <p><ref type="url" target="http://www.yalepress.yale.edu"
                            >http://www.yalepress.yale.edu</ref></p></item>
                <item>
                    <p>MADISON, JAMES. <hi rend="italic"
                            >The
Papers of James Madison, Secretary of State Series, Volume 9: 1 February-30
June 1805</hi>. Edited by Mary A. Hackett, J. C. A. Stagg, Anne Mandeville
Colony, Mary Parke Johnson, and Katherine E. Harbury. University of Virginia
Press. 2011. 616 pp. $85. ISBN: 9780813930985. During the months covered in
this volume, Madison attended Jefferson's second inauguration, continued
staffing the governments of the Orleans and Louisiana Territories, and observed
growing factionalism within his Republican Party. The expansion of the
Napoleonic Wars following the declaration of war between Spain and Great
Britain hindered Madison's efforts to obtain settlements with both countries and
ultimately to the failure to gain a favorable interpretation of Louisiana's
boundaries. The correspondence also reveals the toll that the war had on
American shipping.</p>
                    <p><ref type="url" target="http://www.upress.virginia.edu"
                            >http://www.upress.virginia.edu</ref></p></item>
                <item>
                    <p>MANUMISSION. <hi rend="italic"
                            >The
Having of Negroes Is Become a Burden: The Quaker Struggle to Free Slaves in
Revolutionary North Carolina</hi>. Edited by Michael J. Crawford. University
Press of Florida. 2010. 248 pp. $69.95. ISBN: 9780813034706. Embedding primary
documents within his own analysis, Crawford presents the story of North
Carolina Quakers' efforts to free their slaves in the midst of rampant fears of
slave insurrection. Diaries, petitions, and other materials reveal the personal
motivations of individual Quakers and the ways that their activism impacted
local, state, and even national developments.</p>
                    <p><ref type="url" target="http://www.upf.com"
                    >http://www.upf.com</ref></p></item>
                <item>
                    <p>MILITARY HISTORY. <hi rend="italic"
                            >Reminiscences
of Conrad S. Babcock: The Old U.S. Army and the New, 1898-1919</hi>. Edited by
Robert H. Ferrell. University of Missouri Press. 2011. 176 pp. $30. ISBN:
9780826219817. A shortened, edited version of Babcock's original manuscript,
until now only available in the archives of the Hoover Institute, this memoir
by a second generation army officer offers invaluable insights into the
transition the U. S. army underwent during the first decades of the twentieth
century. Babcock graduated from West Point in 1898 and saw action in the
Philippines during the Spanish American War and subsequent Filipino
anti-colonial insurrection and in World War I. In addition, he led a troop of
cavalry into San Francisco after the devastating earthquake and fires of 1906
and served along the border in Arizona. Filled with astute observations,
Babcock's memoir tracks a military forced to adapt to new technology and weaponry
in the cauldron of warfare.</p>
                    <p><ref type="url" target="http://press.umsystem.edu"
                            >http://press.umsystem.edu</ref></p></item>
                <item>
                    <p>MILITARY HISTORY. <hi rend="italic"
                            >Roi
Ottley's World War II: The Lost Diary of an African American Journalist</hi>.
Edited by Mark A. Huddle. University of Kansas Press. 2011. 200 pp. $29.95.
ISBN: 9780700617692. Journalist Vincent "Roi" Ottley covered the
experiences of African American soldiers that neither white reporters nor the
American military were willing to report. His personal diary, now published for
the first time, reveals a war effort even more hampered by racism than that
portrayed in Ottley's reportage. Mess hall brawls between white southern and
black soldiers, the casual indifference of Britons toward their own black
soldiers, and other personal accounts make Ottley's diary a fine resource for
scholars of World War II and of the long struggle for racial justice.</p>
                    <p><ref type="url" target="http://www.kansaspress.ku.edu"
                            >http://www.kansaspress.ku.edu</ref></p></item>
                <item>
                    <p>MILITARY HISTORY. <hi rend="italic"
                            >Letters
from a War Bird: The World War I Correspondence of Elliot White Springs</hi>.
Edited by David K. Vaughan. University of South Carolina Press. 2011. 392 pp.
$39.95. ISBN: 9781611170405. Ranked among America's best flying aces during
World War I, Springs went on to become executive of a textile company in his
native South Carolina and a writer. Enlisting out of Princeton University,
Springs served in both British and American flying corps. His wartime letters
reveal his deep attraction to the wartime culture of England and France, while
annotations explore his complex relationships with his family and connect his
firsthand experiences with his later writings.</p>
                    <p><ref type="url" target="http://www.uscpress.com"
                            >http://www.uscpress.com</ref></p></item>
                <item>
                    <p>MORMONS. <hi rend="italic"
                            >In the
Whirlpool: The Pre-Manifesto Letters of President Wilford Woodruff to the
William Atkin Family, 1885-1890</hi>. Edited by Reid L. Neilson. The Arthur H.
Clarke Company. 2011. 240 pp. $29.95. ISBN: 9780870623905. As Utah's statehood
grew imminent, pressure against Mormons who practiced plural marriage
intensified. Woodruff, who became church president in 1887, went into hiding in
1879 to avoid prosecution. The letters in this volume between Woodruff and the
family that had provided him sanctuary, never before published, highlight the
spiritual and political conflicts that led ultimately to Woodruff's 1890
manifesto, which officially disallowed polygamy.</p>
                    <p><ref type="url" target="http://www.ahclarke.com"
                            >http://www.ahclarke.com</ref></p></item>
                <item>
                    <p>MORRIS, GOUVERNEUR. <hi rend="italic"
                            >The
Diaries of Gouverneur Morris: European Travels, 1794-1798</hi>. Edited by
Melanie R. Miller. University of Virginia Press. 2011. 784 pp. $99.50. ISBN:
9780813929491. As American minister to France, Morris witnessed the unraveling
of the French Revolution into terror and war. After the French government
forced his removal as minister in 1794, Morris spent the next four years
traveling through Europe. This newly transcribed and annotated edition of the
diaries Morris kept during his journey brings to life his surprisingly modern
voice and humor and is filled with vivid descriptions of the people and places
he encountered.</p>
                    <p><ref type="url" target="http://upress.virginia.edu"
                            >http://upress.virginia.edu</ref></p></item>
                <item>
                    <p>MURDOCH, IRIS. <hi rend="italic"
                            >Iris
Murdoch, a Writer at War: Letters and Diaries, 1939-1945</hi>. Edited by Peter
J. Conradi. Oxford University Press. 2011. 304 pp. $35. ISBN: 9780199756032. 
These never before published writings include a journal Murdoch kept as a
touring actor in 1939 and wartime correspondence with two early intimates,
Frank Thompson, a poet and brother of the historian E. P. Thompson, and David
Hicks, with whom Murdoch was engaged during a short, passionate affair.</p>
                    <p><ref type="url" target="http://www.oup.com"
                    >http://www.oup.com</ref></p></item>
                <item>
                    <p>NATURAL HISTORY. <hi rend="italic"
                            >The
Codex Canadensis and the Writings of Louis Nicolas: The Natural History of the
New World, Histoire Naturelle des Indes Occidentales</hi>. Edited by
Franois-Marc Gagnon, Nancy Senior, and Ral Quellet. McGill-Queen's University
Press. 2011. 676 pp. $65. ISBN: 9780773538764. The Codex Canadensis was a
seventeenth-century illustrated work on the flora and fauna of Canada, while <hi
                            rend="italic"
                        >The Natural History of the World</hi> was a
literary natural history. Gagnon argues that both were produced by Louis
Nicolas, a Jesuit priest who traveled throughout Canada between 1664 and 1675,
and has had them translated from the classical French in which they were
written into modern French, and also into English. The work presents a
pre-Linnaean botany and pre-Darwinian account of living things and illuminates
how early-modern Europeans perceived the natural world they encountered in
America.</p>
                    <p><ref type="url" target="http://mqup.mcgill.ca"
                        >http://mqup.mcgill.ca</ref></p></item>
                <item>
                    <p>NEHRU, JAWAHARLAL. <hi rend="italic"
                            >Selected
Works of Jawaharlal Nehru (1 January-31 March 1958)</hi>. Second Series, Volume
41. Edited by Aditya Mukherjee and Mindula Mukherjee. Oxford University Press.
2011. 968 pp. $75. ISBN: 9780198070665. This volume includes lectures,
writings, letters, speeches, and other works from three months of Nehru's prime
ministership. His writings reveal his wide range of interests in national and
international affairs. A highlight of the volume involves the infamous LIC
scandal, or "Mundhra Affair," which prompted the resignation of the
Indian government's finance minister.</p>
                    <p><ref type="url" target="http://www.oup.com"
                    >http://www.oup.com</ref></p></item>
                <item>
                    <p>REYNOLDS, DANIEL HARRIS. <hi rend="italic"
                            >Worthy
of the Cause for Which They Fought: The Civil War Diary of Brigadier General
Daniel Harris Reynolds, 1861-1865</hi>. Edited by Robert Patrick Bender.
University of Arkansas Press. 2011. 343 pp. $34.95. ISBN: 9781557289711. A
lawyer in Chicot County, Arkansas, Reynolds enlisted as a captain in 1861, and
served throughout the war in the western theater. His articulate journal
described the harsh realities of battle and the personal and political
difficulties that sometimes divided his soldiers. It offers a view of the
nature of command at the company and brigade levels.</p>
                    <p><ref type="url" target="http://www.uapress.com"
                        >http://www.uapress.com</ref></p></item>
                <item>
                    <p>RIX, ALFRED AND CHASTINA W. <hi rend="italic"
                            >New England to Gold Rush California: The Journal of Alfred and Chastina
W. Rix, 1849-1854</hi>. Edited by Lynn A. Bonfield. The Arthur H. Clarke
Company. 2011. 356 pp. $45. ISBN: 9780870623929. After marrying in a town in
northern Vermont, schoolteachers Alfred and Chastina Rix began keeping a joint
journal. After Alfred's departure for gold rush era California, Chastina
maintained the journal, summarizing her husband's frequent letters home.
Chastina and their young son joined Alfred in California after recording the
journey by ship via Panama, and the couple resumed their life together, as well
as alternating journal entries. Bonfield's edition is enlivened with
photographs and insightful historical annotations.</p>
                    <p><ref type="url" target="http://www.ahclark.com"
                        >http://www.ahclark.com</ref></p></item>
                <item>
                    <p>ROOSEVELT, ELEANOR. <hi rend="italic"
                            >The
Eleanor Roosevelt Papers, Volume 1: The Human Rights Years, 1945-1948</hi>.
Edited by Allida Black. University of Virginia Press. 2010. 1200 pp. $99.50.
ISBN: 9780813929248. The 410 documents in this volume chronicle Roosevelt's
impact on American politics and the United Nations, for which she served as
chair of the commission drafting the Universal Declaration of Human Rights.
Letters, speeches, columns, committee transcripts, and other material
illuminate the actions Roosevelt took to define, implement, and promote the
twentieth-century conception of human rights.</p>
                    <p><ref type="url" target="http://www.upress.virginia.edu"
                            >http://www.upress.virginia.edu</ref></p></item>
                <item>
                    <p>SANTAYANA, GEORGE. <hi rend="italic"
                            >The
Works of George Santayana, Volume 7: The Life of Reason or the Phases of Human
Progress. Introduction and Reason in Common Sense</hi>. Edited by Martin A.
    Coleman. The MIT Press. 2011. 408 pp. $75. ISBN: 9780262016742. Santayana's <hi
                            rend="italic">Life of Reason</hi> was inspired by Aristotle's
<hi
                            rend="italic"
                            >De Anima</hi>, Darwin's evolutionary
theory, and William James's <hi
                            rend="italic"
                        >Principles of
Psychology</hi>, and traced the development of the human capacity for
appreciating and cultivating the ideal. This critical edition of the first of
the five books includes a chronology, notes, textual commentary, and other
tools useful to scholars.</p>
                    <p><ref type="url" target="http://mitpress.mit.edu"
                            >http://mitpress.mit.edu</ref></p></item>
                <item>
                    <p>SANTAYANA, GEORGE. <hi rend="italic"
                            >George
Santayana's Marginalia, A Critical Selection: Book One, Abell-Lucretius, Volume
6</hi>. Edited by John McCormick. The MIT Press. 2011. 524 pp. $65. ISBN:
978026201629x. <hi
                            rend="italic"
                        >Book Two, McCord-Zeller</hi>.
518 pp. $65. ISBN: 9780262016308. Santayana was an inveterate maker of notes in
the margins of his books. Transcribed from books in Santayana's library, the
notes in these volumes present Santayana's comments, which illuminate, contest,
or expand the authors' thoughts.</p>
                    <p><ref type="url" target="http://mitpress.mit.edu"
                            >http://mitpress.mit.edu</ref></p></item>
                <item>
                    <p>SMITH, JOSEPH. <hi rend="italic"
                            >Journals,
Volume 2: December 1841-April 1843</hi>. Edited by Andrew H. Hedges, Alex D.
Smith, and Richard Lloyd Anderson. Church Historian's Press. 2011. 558 pp.
$54.95. ISBN: 9781609087371. This volume features Smith's first Nauvoo,
Illinois, journal and part of the second. It chronicles such developments as
the organization of the Female Relief Society of Nauvoo, proxy baptisms,
publication of the Book of Abraham, construction of the Nauvoo temple, the
dissent of John C. Bennett, the attempt by Missouri and Illinois authorities to
extradite Smith, and the maturing of Smith as a religious and political leader.</p>
                    <p><ref type="url" target="http://josephsmithpapers.org"
                            >http://josephsmithpapers.org</ref></p></item>
                <item>
                    <p>SMITH, JOSEPH. <hi rend="italic"
                            >Revelations
and Translations, Volume 2: Published Revelations</hi>. Edited by Dean C. Jessee
and Ronald K. Esplin. Church Historian's Press. 2011. 726 pp. $69.95. ISBN:
9781606419090. This volume presents Smith's revelations in the form that most
early Latter-day Saints read and experienced them. Included are photographic
reproductions of the Book of Commandments (1833), the Doctrine and Covenants
(1835), transcripts of 26 revelation texts published in the church newspaper,
and a proposed reconstruction of what would have likely been added to the final
32 pages of the Book of Commandments.</p>
                    <p><ref type="url" target="http://josephsmithpapers.org"
                            >http://josephsmithpapers.org</ref></p></item>
                <item>
                    <p>TAFT, WILLIAM HOWARD. <hi rend="italic"
                            >My
Dearest Nellie: The Letters of William Howard Taft to Helen Herron Taft,
1909-1912</hi>. Edited by Lewis L. Gould. University Press of Kansas. 2011. 320
pp. $39.95. ISBN: 9780700618002. This collection of letters, written during
Taft's one term as president and most previously unpublished, reveal the close
personal and political relationship that the Tafts enjoyed. The letters, at
once gossipy and incisive, open a window into the Progressive Era and indicate
a Taft who was far more thoughtful a chief executive than scholars have
previously portrayed.</p>
                    <p><ref type="url" target="http://www.kansaspress.ku.edu"
                            >http://www.kansaspress.ku.edu</ref></p></item>
                <item>
                    <p>THURMAN, HOWARD WASHINGTON. <hi rend="italic"
                            >The Papers of Howard Washington Thurman, Volume 2: Christian, Who Calls
Me Christian?, April 1936-August 1943</hi>. Edited by Walter Earl Fluker, Kai
Jackson Issa, Quinton H. Dixie, Peter Eisenstadt, and Catherine Tumber.
University of South Carolina Press. 2011. 496 pp. $59.95. ISBN: 9781611170436.
This volume documents Thurman's return from South Asia, where he had met with
Gandhi, and his final years as professor of philosophy and religion at Howard
University. The documents reflect the maturation of Thurman's theological and
social vision and his embrace of radical non-violence.</p>
                    <p><ref type="url" target="http://www.uscpress.com"
                            >http://www.uscpress.com</ref></p></item>
                <item>
                    <p>TRANSLATED WORKS. <hi rend="italic"
                        >See</hi>
CROMMELIN, CLAUDE AUGUST; NATURAL HISTORY.</p>
                </item>
                <item><p>TRAVEL NARRATIVES. <hi rend="italic"
                        >See</hi>
CROMMELIN, CLAUDE AUGUST; MORRIS, GOUVERNEUR</p>
                </item>
                <item>
                    <p>WARREN, ROBERT PENN. <hi rend="italic"
                            >Selected
Letters of Robert Penn Warren, Volume 5: Backward Glances and New Visions,
1969-1979</hi>. Edited by James A. Perkins and Randy Hendricks. Louisiana State
University Press. 2011. 584 pp. $90. ISBN: 9780807138274. In these turbulent
years, Warren produced <hi
                            rend="italic">Audubon: A Vision</hi>,
<hi rend="italic"
                            >Or Else&#8212;Poem/Poems</hi>, the
Pulitzer Prize-winning <hi
                            rend="italic">Now and Then</hi>,
and the revised version of <hi
                            rend="italic"
                        >Brother to
Dragons</hi>, securing his place in the canon of American literature.</p>
                    <p><ref type="url" target="http://lsupress.org"
                    >http://lsupress.org</ref></p></item>
                <item>
                    <p>WASHINGTON, GEORGE. <hi rend="italic"
                            >The
Papers of George Washington, Presidential Series, Volume 16: 1 May&#8211;30
September 1794.</hi> Edited by David R. Hoth and Carol S. Eber. University of
Virginia Press. 2011. 848 pp. $85. ISBN: 9780813930992. During the months
covered by this volume, Washington faced concerns that arose from the ongoing
war in Europe. Embargo evasions, privateers, and the formation of a league of
armed neutrality by Denmark and Sweden all required responses. Problems with
restive citizens on the southern frontier and with Native Americans were
dwarfed in early August by the open rebellion against the excise tax on whiskey
in western Pennsylvania. Washington called up the militia after negotiations
failed and left Philadelphia on 30 September to join the troops, the same day
that news of General Anthony Wayne's victory at the Battle of Fallen Timbers
reached the city.</p>
                    <p><ref type="url" target="http://www.upress.virginia.edu"
                            >http://www.upress.virginia.edu</ref></p></item>
                <item>
                    <p>WASHINGTON, GEORGE. <hi rend="italic"
                            >The
Papers of George Washington, Revolutionary War Series, Volume 20: 8 April&#8211;31
May 1779</hi>. Edited by Edward G. Lengel. University of Virginia Press. 2010.
846 pp. $85. ISBN: 9780813930244. As this volume opens, Washington is gathering
intelligence for an expedition against the Iroquois Confederacy, which enables
him to develop a campaign plan. He views with concern the worsening situation
in the southern theater, where the British had captured Savannah and were
pressing on Charleston. He is forced to respond instead, however, to a British
raid on Portsmouth, Virginia. Intelligence gathered in New York allows
Washington to block a British attack up the Hudson River.</p>
                    <p><ref type="url" target="http://www.upress.virginia.edu"
                            >http://www.upress.virginia.edu</ref></p></item>
                <item>
                    <p>WILLIAMS, RALPH VAUGHAN. <hi rend="italic"
                            >Letters
of Ralph Vaughan Williams, 1895-1958</hi>. Edited by Hugh Cobbe. Oxford
University Press. 2010. 668 pp. $55. ISBN: 9780199587643. A selection of about
750 letters from an extant corpus of about 3,300, this
chronological volume provides a picture of the famous composer in his own
words. The letters reflect Williams's major preoccupations: musical, personal,
and political. Although Williams was reluctant to discuss his creative process,
the letters include many discussions of his music.</p>
                    <p><ref type="url" target="http://www.oup.com"
                    >http://www.oup.com</ref></p></item>
                <item>
                    <p>WOMEN'S HISTORY. <hi rend="italic"
                        >See</hi>
COREY, ELIZABETH; CROCKER, HANNAH MATHER; GORDON, MARGARET E. P.; RIX, ALFRED
AND CHASTINA W.</p></item>
                <item>
                    <p>WORCESTERSHIRE. <hi rend="italic"
                        >Little
Malvern Letters I: 1482-1737</hi>. Edited by Aileen M. Hodgson and Michael
Hodgetts. Boydell &amp; Brewer. 2011. 296 pp. $80. ISBN: 9780902832268. A
selection of family letters and other documents in the Worcestershire Record
Office, this volume relates to the family that has occupied the dissolved
priory of Little Malvern since 1538 and illustrates the impact of the
Reformation and English Civil War on this area of England.</p>
                    <p><ref type="url" target="http://www.boydellandbrewer.com"
                            >http://www.boydellandbrewer.com</ref></p></item>
            </list>
        </body>
    </text>
</TEI>
