<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<?oxygen RNGSchema="http://www.scholarlyediting.org/scholarlyediting.rng" type="xml"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
    <teiHeader xml:lang="eng">
        <fileDesc>
            <titleStmt>
                <title level="a" type="main">Review: <hi rend="italic">The
                    Having of Negroes Is Become a Burden: The Quaker Struggle to Free Slaves in
                    Revolutionary North Carolina</hi>. By Michael J. Crawford. </title>
                
                <author>Beverly Wilson Palmer</author>
            </titleStmt>
            <editionStmt>
                <edition>
                    <date>2012</date>
                </edition>
            </editionStmt>
            <publicationStmt>
                <idno type="file">review.quaker</idno>
                <authority>Scholary Editing: The Annual of the Association for Documentary
                    Editing</authority>
                <address>
          <addrLine>http://www.scholarlyediting.org</addrLine>
        </address>
                <publisher>Association for Documentary Editing</publisher>
                <publisher>University of Nebraska&#8211;Lincoln</publisher>
                <distributor>
                    <name>Center for Digital Research in the Humanities</name>
                    <address>
            <addrLine>319 Love Library</addrLine>
            <addrLine>University of Nebraska&#8211;Lincoln</addrLine>
            <addrLine>Lincoln, NE 68588-4100</addrLine>
            <addrLine>http://cdrh.unl.edu</addrLine>
          </address>
                </distributor>
                <date>2012</date>
                <availability>
                    <p>Scholary Editing: The Annual of the Association for Documentary Editing is
                        freely distributed by the Association for Documentary Editing and the Center
                        for Digital Research in the Humanities at the University of Nebraska-Lincoln
                        and licensed under a Creative Commons Attribution-NonCommercial-ShareAlike
                        3.0 Unported License</p>
                </availability>
            </publicationStmt>
            <seriesStmt>
                <title level="j"
                    >Scholarly Editing: The Annual of the Association for Documentary
                    Editing</title>
                <respStmt>
                    <resp>editor</resp>
                    <name xml:id="ag">Amanda Gailey</name>
                </respStmt>
                <respStmt>
                    <resp>editor</resp>
                    <name xml:id="awj">Andrew Jewell</name>
                </respStmt>
                <idno type="vol">33</idno>
                <idno type="ISSN">2167-1257</idno>
            </seriesStmt>
            <sourceDesc>
                <bibl>
                    <note>Born digital.</note>
                </bibl>
            </sourceDesc>
        </fileDesc>
        <revisionDesc>
            <change when="2012-02-06" who="#awj">markup in TEI XML</change>
        </revisionDesc>
    </teiHeader>
    <text>
        <body>
            <head type="main"><hi rend="italic">The
                    Having of Negroes Is Become a Burden: The Quaker Struggle to Free Slaves in
                    Revolutionary North Carolina</hi>. By Michael J. Crawford. Gainesville:
                    University Press of Florida, 2010. 224 pp. ISBN: 978-0-8130-3470-6. $69.95.</head>
            
                
                <p><hi rend="italic">The Having of Negroes Is Become a Burden:
                    The Quaker Struggle to Free Slaves in Revolutionary North Carolina</hi>, by
                    Michael J. Crawford, provides a selection of documents illustrating the
                    conflict between manumission and state law. The book covers a twenty-five year
                    period (1772&#8211;1797) using thirty-six documents from the Society of
                    Friends, private collections, published county and state records, and
                    Congressional records. A third of the records are transcribed from the North
                    Carolina Friends' Yearly Meeting minutes housed at Guilford College in
                    Greensboro. Nearly a fourth of the selections are taken from the papers of
                    George Walton, a merchant ship captain from Perquimans County, who converted to
                    Quakerism.</p>
                
                <p>After
                    a chronology of principal events and an introduction, the volume is divided
                    into four parts. An editor's note appears at the beginning of each document or
                    group of documents and a different font is used for the actual transcriptions.</p>
                
                <p>Part
                    I "An Individual: George Walton Confronts Slavery," which consists of
                    three documents, recounts Walton's dreams and his interpretations of them. The
                    section also includes letters and journal entries concerning Walton's stand
                    against slavery and his efforts to convince other Quakers to free their slaves.
                    A map appears in this section showing Quaker meetinghouses, but it is very hard
                    to read because of the overlay of words onto a contemporary map. Journal
                    excerpts discuss why Walton declined to serve as a night patroller, a system
                    set up to prevent slave rebellion.</p>
                
                <p>North
                    Carolina Quakers' growing hostility to slavery brought them into conflict with
                    state and local authorities who were worried about the destabilizing effects
                    that the Revolution had on the "peculiar institution." The 1775
                    Yearly Meeting determined that slaveholding was "inconsistant with
                    righteousness" (54) and the following year prohibited Friends from buying
                    and selling slaves. Meanwhile, to prevent slaves from rising up to join the
                    Loyalists, the General Assembly condemned the freeing of slaves and made it
                    illegal to do so. As a result, all freed slaves could be seized and re-sold.
                    The Yearly Meeting contested the law in the court at Edenton to no avail but
                    successfully appealed the decision to the superior court in 1778. The next
                    year, however, the legislature upheld the county court's ruling that "the
                    conduct of the said Quakers in setting their slaves free when our open and
                    declared enemies were endeavoring to bring about an Insurrection of the Slaves,
                    was highly criminal and reprehensible" (67).</p>
                
                <p>Part
                    II, "The Community: The Society of Friends in North Carolina Chooses
                    Manumission," includes nine documents. In 1767 Thomas Nicholson, another
                    devout Quaker from Perquimans County, wrote an open letter to the Friends
                    encouraging them to free their slaves gradually. By 1775 he was urging the
                    immediate emancipation of slaves by the Quakers. His reasoning was based on
                    scripture, which he cited extensively in his journal.</p>
                
                <p>The
                    Yearly Meeting developed a policy against slave trading (1773) which eventually
                    expanded to include a policy against slave ownership (1775). Thomas Newby, one
                    of the wealthiest men in Perquimans County, for example, freed ten of his
                    slaves in 1776. The following year he petitioned the Hertford court to free
                    another slave, but his request was denied. A formal process for freeing slaves
                    was set up by the Yearly Meetings, as shown in extracts from that body's
                    minutes. The Yearly Meeting also sent a memorial to the Meeting for Sufferings
                    in Philadelphia regarding the plight of freedmen who were re-enslaved. It
                    listed their names.</p>
                
                <p>Part
                    III, "The State: North Carolina Thwarts Quaker Manumission," includes
                    eleven documents, primarily legal instruments, concerning North Carolina's
                    restriction of Quaker manumission. Fueled by the fear of slave conspiracies,
                    the legislature passed "An Act to Prevent Domestic Insurrections" in
                    1777. The Yearly Meeting believed that slaves freed prior to the new law were
                    not subject to seizure and resale. A trial took place in which the law was
                    upheld and the ruling went against the freed slaves. The volume includes two
                    accounts of sale listing the names of the freed slaves, their former owners,
                    and the new owners.</p>
                
                <p>Throughout the
                    period, Quakers endured a hostile legislative climate. Opponents of
                    manumission, nevertheless, were not wholly successful. As mentioned previously,
                    the superior court reversed the decision of Edenton District in 1778, but the
                    legislature effectively rebuked that decision the following year with "An
                    Act for Apprehending and selling certain Slaves set free contrary to Law."
                    While "passions on the issues were at a high pitch," (128) several
                    Friends prepared a petition explaining their actions to the legislature, but it
                    was never presented. Another petition was presented in 1788 to no avail. "An
                    Act to Amend an Act Entitled An Act to Prevent Domestic Insurrections' "
                    strengthened enforcement of the law. Yet another bill was proposed in the
                    General Assembly in 1797 that was aimed at "sundry people under pretence
                    of religious motives, [who] send their slaves to the northern and eastern
                    states" (138). It never became law.</p>
                
                <p>The
                    final division in the book, Part IV, "The Nation: African-American Freedom
                    and the Manumission Debate in Congress," focuses on the struggle of
                    Quakers "to get the national government to act against slavery"
                    (142). In 1797, two petitions were presented to that body, one by former slaves
                    and one by the Pennsylvania Yearly Meeting. The former received little
                    attention because it was voted, 50 to 33, that the petition should not even be
                    received for debate. Likewise, although the Pennsylvania memorial was debated
                    strongly in the House of Representatives, it, too, was rejected.</p>
                
                <p>The
                    Epilogue is broken into several subheadings. The first two are "The Yearly
                    Meeting Becomes a Slaveholder," and "Emigration." Three
                    biographies of North Carolina Friends, covering 1776 through 1897, "illustrate
                    the depth and continuity of the North Carolina Quaker tradition of antislavery
                    action" (187). "A Burden Unshed" brings the story full circle,
                    harkening back to George Walton's original dream. "North Carolina Friends
                    . . . like Walton, recognized the dignity of all people and, having the courage
                    of their convictions, strove to make their dreams reality" (192).</p>
                
                <p>The
                    endnotes are extensive, as is the bibliography. It was a bit surprising to this
                    reviewer, however, that more of the original documents housed in the State
                    Archives were not cited, primarily court records, tax lists, and General
                    Assembly Session Records. Secondary sources or Internet resources were used
                    instead. The indexing of the book was excellent. There were a few minor
                    inconsistencies in how certain entries were subdivided. Some had a long string
                    of page numbers listed while others with the same number of page references
                    were divided into subentries. The subentries for "Bible" were
                    inconsistent in that some of the chapters were run-in while most were indented.</p>
                
                <p>Overall,
                    the volume accomplished its goal to show how the consequence of the Quakers' "antislavery
                    activities radiated out from a few individuals to the region, the state, and
                    eventually, the nation" (dust jacket).</p>
                
               
            
            
            
            <signed><name>Donna E. Kelly</name>
                
                <affiliation>North Carolina Office of Archives
                    and History</affiliation></signed>
            
            
            
        </body>
    </text>
</TEI>
