<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
    <teiHeader xml:lang="eng">
        <fileDesc>
            <titleStmt>
                <title level="a" type="main">Review: <hi rend="italic">Reminiscences
                    &amp; Traditions of Boston</hi>. By Hannah Mather Crocker. Edited by Eileen Hunt
                    Botting and Sarah L. Houser.</title>
                
                <author>Beverly Wilson Palmer</author>
            </titleStmt>
            <editionStmt>
                <edition>
                    <date>2012</date>
                </edition>
            </editionStmt>
            <publicationStmt>
                <idno type="file">review.crocker</idno>
                <authority>Scholary Editing: The Annual of the Association for Documentary
                    Editing</authority>
                <address>
          <addrLine>http://www.scholarlyediting.org</addrLine>
        </address>
                <publisher>Association for Documentary Editing</publisher>
                <publisher>University of Nebraska&#8211;Lincoln</publisher>
                <distributor>
                    <name>Center for Digital Research in the Humanities</name>
                    <address>
            <addrLine>319 Love Library</addrLine>
            <addrLine>University of Nebraska&#8211;Lincoln</addrLine>
            <addrLine>Lincoln, NE 68588-4100</addrLine>
            <addrLine>http://cdrh.unl.edu</addrLine>
          </address>
                </distributor>
                <date>2012</date>
                <availability>
                    <p>Scholary Editing: The Annual of the Association for Documentary Editing is
                        freely distributed by the Association for Documentary Editing and the Center
                        for Digital Research in the Humanities at the University of Nebraska-Lincoln
                        and licensed under a Creative Commons Attribution-NonCommercial-ShareAlike
                        3.0 Unported License</p>
                </availability>
            </publicationStmt>
            <seriesStmt>
                <title level="j"
                    >Scholarly Editing: The Annual of the Association for Documentary
                    Editing</title>
                <respStmt>
                    <resp>editor</resp>
                    <name xml:id="ag">Amanda Gailey</name>
                </respStmt>
                <respStmt>
                    <resp>editor</resp>
                    <name xml:id="awj">Andrew Jewell</name>
                </respStmt>
                <idno type="vol">33</idno>
                <idno type="ISSN">2167-1257</idno>
            </seriesStmt>
            <sourceDesc>
                <bibl>
                    <note>Born digital.</note>
                </bibl>
            </sourceDesc>
        </fileDesc>
        <revisionDesc>
            <change when="2012-02-06" who="#awj">markup in TEI XML</change>
        </revisionDesc>
    </teiHeader>
    <text>
        <body>
            <head type="main"><hi rend="italic">Reminiscences
                    &amp; Traditions of Boston</hi>. By Hannah Mather Crocker. Edited by Eileen Hunt
                    Botting and Sarah L. Houser. New England Historic Genealogical Society, 2011. 
                    539 pp. $39.95.  ISBN: 978-0-88082-253-4.</head>
                
            
                
                <p>In her dedication
                    of <hi rend="italic">Reminiscences</hi> to the Massachusetts
                    Historical Society, Hannah Mather Crocker writes, "May it serve as a key
                    to open the door for further investigation of former days" (245).
                    Elsewhere she states "Restore, preserve, and transmit to future ages that
                    they also may be able to look to the rock from whence they were hewn . . . with
                    this wish I commit my reminiscences with antiquarian researches to the candour
                    of the benevolent public" (233, also 94). Crocker sent her manuscript to
                    her friend Henry Moore, who in returning it wrote on May 8, 1829, that he was "wiser
                    than I was when I borrowed it. I hope at some future day to see it in print"
                    (139). Unfortunately Crocker died two months later. Her manuscript eventually
                    made its way to the R. Stanton Avery Special Collections at the New England
                    Historic Genealogic Society but was not published until this year.</p>
                
                <p>As her middle name
                    indicates, Hannah Mather Crocker (1752-1829) descended from the illustrious
                    Mather family, as the granddaughter of Cotton Mather. In addition, her mother,
                    Hannah Hutchinson Mather, was the sister of Thomas Hutchinson, Jr., royal
                    governor of Massachusetts from 1771 to 1774. In 1779 Hannah Mather married
                    Joseph Crocker, a captain in the Massachusetts army from 1777 to 1781 and later
                    a Boston merchant. The couple had ten children, only some of whom lived to
                    adulthood. Left a widow in 1797 with little income from her husband, Crocker
                    maintained her economic independence by selling property she had inherited and
                    gained recognition as a writer in the 1810s. Her <hi rend="italic">Reminiscences</hi> reflects Crocker's desire to compile and record
                    Boston's history from its founding through the 1820s, as well as to demonstrate
                    her literary instincts.</p>
                
                <p>Composed between
                    1822 and 1829, <hi rend="italic">Reminiscences</hi> combines
                    narrative excerpts, poems, biographical sketches, patriotic sentiments,
                    tributes to and from friends, and accounts of historical events. The three
                    parts, Version 1, Version 2, and Appendix, contain lively stories and
                    anecdotes. For example, a certain Thomas Kemble was ordered to stand in the
                    stocks for two hours because he publicly embraced his wife after long
                    separation (10). Crocker relates her own important role in an incident shortly
                    before the Battle of Bunker Hill in June 1775. Writing in the third person ("a
                    young lady"), she describes delivering letters to General Joseph Warren from
                    her father Samuel Mather, then being held hostage by the British (41-43, 198).
                    Similarly, she tells of an escapade from 1765 when, as a thirteen-year old, she
                    helped her uncle Thomas Hutchinson, then lieutenant governor of Massachusetts,
                    escape from her father's house during the Stamp Act riots (91, 152). As one of
                    the many curiosities in the volume, Crocker quotes from a 1641 New England law
                    book which ordered "rebellious children" to be executed if they
                    continued their sinful behavior "after due correction from their parents"
                    (83).</p>
                
                <p>In the helpful and
                    thorough introduction, editor Eileen Hunt Botting offers five ways to
                    appreciate Crocker's reminiscences: 1) as local Boston history which Crocker,
                    with her "elite connections" to the Hutchinson and Mather families,
                    can render in detail; 2) as political history of Boston from the 1620s to the
                    1820s; 3) as women's history, in which Crocker emphasizes women's participation
                    and her own perspective on Boston's political and social events; 4) as family
                    history and genealogy giving information about Bostonians not available
                    elsewhere; and 5) as church history covering the 1740 Great Awakening and the
                    splits and theological differences in various Boston churches (xxxii-xxxv).
                    These subjects overlap; they are not organized in either a thematic or
                    chronological way. For example, several pages describe a series of early Boston
                    physicians (95-98), followed by a list of epitaphs on Copps Hill graves
                    (99-101), followed by anecdotes about London mayor Sir John Calf, General John
                    Burgoyne, and poet John Hawkins (101-102). What are we to make of this
                    compilation? Botting's "reader's guide" (xxxii) to the five prevalent
                    themes is essential to understanding the <hi rend="italic">Reminiscences</hi>.
                </p>
                
                <p>The editors note
                    Crocker's prominence in early women's history. In 1778 she founded St. Ann's
                    Lodge, intended to balance men's Masonic lodges and to establish educational
                    opportunities for women. Boston newspapers published several of her poems on
                    the lodge, which are included in the <hi rend="italic">Reminiscences</hi>
                    (e.g. "An Address to Female Lodges," 259-60) as well as in her <hi rend="italic">A Series of Letters on Free Masonry by a
                        Lady of Boston</hi> published in 1815. Crocker's <hi rend="italic">School of Reform, or Seaman's Safe Pilot to the Cape of Good Hope</hi>
                    (1816) cautioned sailors against immoral behavior from a woman's viewpoint. In
                    her 1818 <hi rend="italic">Observations on the Real Rights
                        of Women</hi>, Crocker "argued for a robust vision of women's informal
                    political participation" (p. xxvi). Crocker's latter work received
                    attention from figures ranging from Thomas Wentworth Higginson in 1859 to Judy
                    Chicago in 1979 ("The Dinner Party," p. xl). Crocker's activism is
                    well represented in the <hi rend="italic">Reminiscences</hi>
                    with statements and poems. For example, a poem "Quid pro quo,"
                    complains about doctors' demand for full pay from women: "As all you do,
                    we plainly see/ Is only done for double fee" (271). Her 1799 "North
                    Square Creed," intended as a vow for husbands, declared, "I do verily
                    believe it is proper and best for every man to believe in every thing his
                    prudent wife wishes him to believe" (258, 357-58). </p>
                
                <p>Versions One (V1)
                    and Two (V2) cover many of the same subjects and the inevitable question arises
                    as to whether there is a need for both of them. The editors defend their
                    decision, stating that V1 "has the more topographical, genealogical, and
                    political analysis of Boston's growth" while V2 emerges "more as a
                    synthetic history of the city and its denizens." They argue that inclusion
                    of both versions "enables the comparative analysis of their content and
                    composition" (xxviii-xxix). Frequent repetition between the two inevitably
                    occurs, sometimes with identical wording and notes (see for example,
                    "Boston Ministers: A Ballad," 121-26, 222-26). An entry on black
                    servant Jack Morey is similar in content but slightly more condensed in V2 (see
                    81-2, 196). Nevertheless, V2 does add some new material (e.g. 172, 186, 193,
                    200). Given the reasonable price of this volume ($39.95), the press apparently did
                    not object to the inclusion of V2 and users now have full access to Crocker's
                    entire text. One wonders, however, if placement of V2 on a website might have
                    been a better strategy, so as not to overwhelm the user with much repetitive
                    material.</p>
                
                <p>The Appendix is
                    like a scrapbook. In this section Crocker displays her poetic skills with 81
                    poems of her own, pasted into the original manuscript. The editors have
                    remarkably located the original publication of some of Crocker's poems, many in
                    the <hi rend="italic">Columbian Centinel</hi>. Crocker also
                    included a number of poems by well-known authors such as Robert Southey and
                    David Garrick. She also gathered those that were published anonymously. The
                    Appendix contains patriotic expressions, some of which are also present in V1
                    and/or V2 (e.g. "Lines on the <hi rend="italic">Independence</hi>, 134 and 285). 
                    "Diverse" (xl) is certainly the appropriate word to describe this
                    section. </p>
                
                <p>Extensive
                    apparatus adds to the merits of the volume. First, the editors have carefully
                    labored to present a text that is readable yet provides comparison with the
                    original. They offer a detailed statement of transcription policies, along with
                    a separate section, "Textual Notes," at the end of the volume listing
                    line by line substitutions. For example where Crocker wrote
                    "epistopalian," the editors have supplied in brackets
                    "Episcopalian." In addition, the Biographical Directory contains
                    brief summations of the figures to whom Crocker frequently refers. Photographs
                    include Crocker's Mather ancestors, along with well-known Boston figures such
                    as Paul Revere and Phyllis Wheatley, a map of Boston's North End, and prominent
                    churches. A fuller selection of photographs of the manuscript volume and samples of Crocker's handwriting could have further highlighted the editors' transcription accomplishment. Lastly, the excellent index contains a variety of
                    topics such as black Americans and smallpox, along with separate entries for
                    individual poems, churches, and Boston buildings. A separate index lists the
                    first lines of all the poetry in the volume. Because of Crocker's scattered
                    presentation, readers will find these indexes indispensable. </p>
                
                <p>Fuller consideration of an
                    annotation policy could have made the <hi rend="italic">Reminiscences</hi>
                    more user-friendly with fewer notes.  Notes to V1 total 465; V2: 367.  A large
                    number of these are, of course, necessary to identify people and events and to
                    define an unfamiliar word such as "gunter" (341).  A note on the
                    historical background to an event on, say, the 1755 Lisbon earthquake
                    illuminates Samuel Mather's poem on the subject (n. 315, p. 119). But many
                    notes could be condensed or omitted. Occasionally the notes give the same
                    information already provided in the introduction (n. 224, p.64 on Esther
                    Forbes) or in the text (n. 323, p. 91). Moreover, notes could be cut to one for
                    a paragraph instead of three or four (as on p. 40, notes 143-45, or p. 84,
                    notes 293-298). An editorial statement that no note will appear when
                    information is unavailable could have eliminated notes 315-16 (p. 87) and notes
                    338, 341 (p. 99), for example. Lastly, italics inserted in brackets in Crocker's
                    text (e.g. Edward H[<hi rend="italic">utchinson</hi>]  p. 8) could have eliminated some notes. 
                    Although many of the editors' notes supply essential explanations, the high
                    number of extraneous ones distracts at times from Crocker's text. </p>
                
                <p> 
                    The editors acknowledge that Crocker's <hi rend="italic">Reminiscences</hi>
                    is "not a polished document" (xli). Instead it is, as already noted,
                    a combination scrapbook and reference work. The reader can well understand the
                    characterization by Esther Forbes, the author of a biography of Paul Revere,
                    who wrote that Crocker's work is a "jumble of reminiscences, chaotic, unchronological"
                    (xxxix). The editors attribute Forbes's 1942 criticism to the fact that the
                    manuscript was extremely hard to read and absorb, a statement that makes us
                    appreciate the careful transcription and editorial attention to Crocker's
                    compendium. Botting and Houser maintain that it "provides new perspectives
                    on the early history of Boston via its unique combination of primary and
                    secondary sources, oral tradition, and first-person witness" (xxix). The <hi rend="italic">Reminiscences</hi> will certainly be a
                    valuable resource for anyone researching early Boston history.  </p>
                
               <signed><name>Beverly Wilson Palmer</name>
                
                <affiliation>Pomona College</affiliation></signed>
                
            
            
        </body>
    </text>
</TEI>
