<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
    <teiHeader xml:lang="eng">
        <fileDesc>
            <titleStmt>
                <title level="m" type="main">Alex Haley's Malcolm X: "The Malcolm X I Knew" and
                    Notecards from <emph>The Autobiography of Malcolm X</emph></title>
                <author>Amy E. Earhart</author>
                <respStmt>
                    <resp>Transcription and encoding</resp>
                    <name xml:id="wr">Amy E. Earhart et al.</name>
                </respStmt>
            </titleStmt>
            <editionStmt>
                <edition>
                    <date>2014</date>
                </edition>
            </editionStmt>
            <publicationStmt>
                <idno type="file">intro.haley</idno>
                <idno type="edition">haley</idno>
                <authority>Scholarly Editing: The Annual of the Association for Documentary
                    Editing</authority>
                <address>
                    <addrLine>http://www.scholarlyediting.org</addrLine>
                </address>
                <publisher>Association for Documentary Editing</publisher>
                <publisher>University of Nebraska&#8211;Lincoln</publisher>
                <distributor>
                    <name>Center for Digital Research in the Humanities</name>
                    <address>
                        <addrLine>319 Love Library</addrLine>
                        <addrLine>University of Nebraska&#8211;Lincoln</addrLine>
                        <addrLine>Lincoln, NE 68588-4100</addrLine>
                        <addrLine>http://cdrh.unl.edu</addrLine>
                    </address>
                </distributor>
                <date>2014</date>
                <availability>
                    <p>Scholarly Editing: The Annual of the Association for Documentary Editing is
                        freely distributed by the Association for Documentary Editing and the Center
                        for Digital Research in the Humanities at the University of Nebraska-Lincoln
                        and licensed under a Creative Commons Attribution-NonCommercial-ShareAlike
                        3.0 Unported License</p>
                </availability>
            </publicationStmt>
            <seriesStmt>
                <title level="j">Scholarly Editing: The Annual of the Association for Documentary
                    Editing</title>
                <respStmt>
                    <resp>editor</resp>
                    <name xml:id="ag">Amanda Gailey</name>
                </respStmt>
                <respStmt>
                    <resp>editor</resp>
                    <name xml:id="awj">Andrew Jewell</name>
                </respStmt>
                <idno type="vol">35</idno>
                <idno type="ISSN">2167-1257</idno>
            </seriesStmt>
            <sourceDesc>
                <bibl>
                    <note>Born digital.</note>
                </bibl>
            </sourceDesc>
        </fileDesc>
        <revisionDesc>
            <change when="2012-07-26" who="#awj">Altered the encoding to match practices in the
                following ways: 1. added @type='main' to head 2. put author's name in byline 3.
                replaced "smart quotes" with straight quotes 4. made encoding match practices for
                footnotes and footnote pointers 5. Added ISSN number to header and altered vol
                number and year 6. added ref tags and URLs to referenced web sites 7. added new
                idnos in publicationStmt </change>
            <change when="2012-10-30" who="aee">Altered introduction text in response to editors'
                suggestions.</change>
            <change when="2012-10-30" who="aee">Revision of text in response to peer
                review.</change>
            <change when="2013-08-20" who="aee">Revision of text in response to peer
                review.</change>
            <change when="2013-10-20" who="aee">Final revision of text.</change>
            <change when="2014-01-20" who="aee">corrected dates of saga, added additional
                information regarding men's magazines</change>
            <change when="2014-02-25" who="aee">Copyediting corrections made</change>
        </revisionDesc>
    </teiHeader>
    <text>
        <front>
            <head type="main">Alex Haley's "The Malcolm X I Knew" and Notecards from <emph>The
                    Autobiography of Malcolm X</emph>
            </head>
            <byline>Amy E. Earhart </byline>
        </front>
        <body>
            <div>

                <p> As a subject specialist in African American literature and a digital humanist, I
                    am dismayed by the dearth of scholarly edited, digitized contemporary African
                    American literary texts. Even extremely visible figures are not well represented
                    by digital scholarly materials, a fact not fully excused by the difficulties of
                    digitizing post-1923 authors due to copyright restrictions. For example, Alex
                    Haley, who brought African American history to the larger American public
                    through <emph>Roots,</emph> has no scholarly digital site dedicated to his work,
                    with his main digital representation resting with the Kunta Kinte-Alex Haley
                    Foundation website, which focuses on African American genealogy, and the Alex
                    Haley Tribute Site, a fan site that compiles portions of Haley's works.<ptr
                        target="#note1" xml:id="nr1" n="1"/> Of course, Haley's case might be
                    exacerbated due to accusations of plagiarism leveled against <emph>Roots;</emph>
                    both Margaret Walker and Harold Courlander brought lawsuits against Haley
                    claiming that he had plagiarized their work. Courlander's 1978 suit was
                    successful and proved that eighty-one passages from <emph>Roots</emph> were
                    copied from Courlander's 1967 book, <emph>The African,</emph> which
                    subsequently led to decreased scholarly interest in Haley.<ptr target="#note2"
                        xml:id="nr2" n="2"/> Malcolm X's work is also largely undocumented, though
                    notable exceptions include Abdul Alkalimat's <ref type="url"
                        target="http://www.brothermalcolm.net/"><emph>Malcolm</emph></ref> website,
                    the most comprehensive digital scholarly resource to date. Online since 1999,
                    the site provides videos, timeline, selected texts, and a comprehensive
                        bibliography.<ptr target="#note3" xml:id="nr3" n="3"/> Additional materials
                    related to Malcolm X appeared online when Manning Marable began to write
                        <emph>Malcolm X: A Life of Reinvention</emph> and launched a support
                    website. Now titled <ref type="url"
                        target="http://www.columbia.edu/cu/ccbh/mxp/"><emph>The Malcolm X Project at
                            Columbia University,</emph></ref> the site shares a varied group of
                    historical and contemporary materials. The site developers also plan to launch a
                    multimedia edition of <emph>The Autobiography of Malcolm X</emph>, a much needed
                    project. </p>
                <p>Because Haley and Malcolm X are critical figures in twentieth-century literature
                    and history, scholars should be invested in the digitization of their primary
                    texts. This edition represents my attempt to intervene in the African American
                    digital canon and to provide a broader set of open-source, scholarly edited,
                    primary materials than previously available. Focused on Haley's Malcolm X work,
                    this set of materials includes an unexamined essay that Haley published shortly
                    after X's death, titled "The Malcolm X I Knew," and notes, forty-one handwritten
                    and thirty-two typed, that were compiled by Haley as he wrote <emph>The
                        Autobiography.</emph> The University of Tennessee, Knoxville, houses the
                    primary repositories of Haley work related to <emph>The Autobiography:</emph>
                    the Alex Haley Papers and the Anne Romaine Papers. Anne Romaine was appointed by
                    Haley to be his biographer, and her papers include substantial information that
                    documents the interaction between X and Haley according to Manning Marable, who
                    used the Romaine Papers extensively for his recent biography of Malcolm X.<ptr
                        target="#note4" xml:id="nr4" n="4"/> While the Romaine Papers offer some
                    insight into Haley's work and are accessible to scholars, the Haley Papers held
                    at the University of Tennessee are notoriously difficult to access, requiring
                    researchers to gain permission from the trustee governing Haley's work for each
                    item of interest. Therefore, the open access release of even some of the
                    materials that Haley used while writing his important work on X, such as the
                    attached notes, adds substantially to scholarly knowledge.</p>
            </div>
            <div>
                <head type="main">Manuscript and Publication Information</head>
                <p>The typed manuscript of the essay and the handwritten and typed notecards from
                    which these materials are transcribed are housed in the Alex Haley Papers held
                    by Cushing Library, Special Collections, at Texas A&amp;M University. During the
                    year and a half of interviews conducted by Haley to gain information for the
                    book, both Haley and Malcolm X would jot down notes on scrap paper, Haley in
                    green ink and X in red.<ptr target="#note5" xml:id="nr5" n="5"/> Haley collected
                    the scribbles, transcribed them into typed and written notes, and eventually
                    pieced together the notes to write <emph>The Autobiography of Malcolm X</emph>,
                    published in November 1965, nine months after X's death. A portion of Haley's
                    typed and handwritten notes are included in this edition. From the contents
                    listed on this set of notecards, and the telltale green ink, it appears that the
                    notes were written by Haley during interviews conducted during the last six to
                    twelve months of X's life. The related essay that is included was originally
                    published by <emph>Saga</emph> magazine in November 1965, the same month
                        <emph>The Autobiography</emph> was published. <emph>Saga</emph> was a pulp
                    men's magazine published by New York's Gambi Publications from 1950 until 1981,
                    and in 1963 it had a circulation of 280,647. A men's adventure magazine similar
                    to other pulps of the same period, including <emph>Adventure</emph>,
                        <emph>Real</emph>, and <emph>True</emph>, <emph>Saga</emph> focused on lurid
                    tales of sex and adventure targeted at working-class men. For example,
                        <emph>Saga</emph>'s submission call in the July 1964 <emph>Writer's
                        Digest</emph> described the magazine as "principally interested in
                    strong-action picture-stories on non-war adventure themes; man against nature,
                    man against beast, man against man. We try to stress the 'man triumphant' idea
                    whenever possible."<ptr target="#note6" xml:id="nr6" n="6"/> Articles such as
                    "Confessions of an Auto Spy," "How Sex Can Take You to the Top," and "Love Among
                    the Beach Boys" are contained in the same volume as Haley's essay along with
                    drawings of scantily clad women and ads promising to remedy baldness. The larger
                    pulp fiction context in which <emph>Saga</emph> resides is a rich area of study
                    but beyond the purview of this essay. There is no indication that scholars are
                    aware of the essay or the small holding of notecards at Texas A&amp;M
                    University, as even Manning's carefully researched recent biography,
                        <emph>Malcolm X: A Life of Reinvention,</emph> does not reference these
                    materials. It is not clear when Haley contracted with <emph>Saga</emph> to
                    publish the essay "The Malcolm X I Knew," but we do know that Haley was in
                    severe financial distress prior to the publication of <emph>The
                        Autobiography</emph> and was looking to quickly publish materials to
                    increase his cash flow.<ptr target="#note7" xml:id="nr7" n="7"/> According to
                    Marable, Haley was slow to produce a finished draft of <emph>The
                        Autobiography</emph> and failed to meet his publisher's deadline of the 1964
                    presidential election. X's break from the Nation of Islam further delayed
                    completion of the volume.<ptr target="#note8" xml:id="nr8" n="8"/> In constant
                    contact with Doubleday, Haley reassured the publisher that the book would not
                    only be complete but would sell. Marable believes that Doubleday, careful to
                    protect their financial investment in the book, was heavily involved with
                    Haley's decision to remove certain controversial statements from the text.
                    Lawyers for Doubleday vetted the materials that Haley submitted, striking and
                    reworking sections deemed problematic, concerned about the potential for libel
                        lawsuits.<ptr target="#note9" xml:id="nr9" n="9"/> Regardless of Haley's
                    attempts to shape the text in a way that Doubleday would approve, the publisher
                    dropped the contract after Malcolm X's death. As David Remnick notes, "The
                    publisher, Nelson Doubleday, fearing for the lives of his staff, cancelled his
                    deal with Haley," leaving Haley in an even more precarious financial
                        situation.<ptr target="#note10" xml:id="nr10" n="10"/> During this same
                    period Haley mined the text for the <emph>Saturday Evening Post</emph> story on
                    Malcolm X entitled "I'm Talking to You White Man." Given his <emph>Post</emph>
                    story and his financial distress, it wouldn't be surprising if Haley mined the
                    volume for another one-off publication in <emph>Saga,</emph> a publication that
                    suggests a quick turnaround as the quality of editing in the magazine is poor,
                    with misspellings of Malcolm X's name common ("Malcom"). The published version
                    in <emph>Saga</emph> is dissimilar to the longer manuscript reproduced in this
                    edition. The final print version of the essay has been heavily cut and is about
                    half the size of the original, with the first seven pages of the manuscript
                    almost entirely missing from the published version. Some stories are included in
                    both documents, including X's boxing match and the encounter with a train
                    porter. Left out of the final document are the more controversial Malcolm X
                    statements, including his take on education, Jews, and race, surprising given
                        <emph>Saga</emph>'s propensity to use the lurid to spur sales. What is of
                    question, though, is why Haley dropped the controversial segments. One would
                    hope to find records of such discussions with the editor of <emph>Saga</emph>,
                    Al Silverman. However, the Silverman Archive, housed at the New York Public
                    Library, has revealed no correspondence between Haley and Silverman. While I
                    have not been able to reproduce the published version of the <emph>Saga</emph>
                    text due to copyright restrictions, the manuscript version should provide new
                    information for scholars interested in Malcolm X and Haley's impact on his
                    legacy. </p>
                <figure>
                    <head>Cover of November 1965 <emph>Saga</emph> magazine.</head>
                    <figDesc>Cover of November 1965 Saga magazine.</figDesc>
                    <graphic url="haley/images/intro.haley.01.jpg"/>
                </figure>

            </div>
            <div>
                <head type="main">Malcolm X and Alex Haley</head>
                <p>It is my hope that the materials here published will prove useful to the
                    interpretation of the complicated relationship between Haley and Malcolm X.
                    Critics from Arnold Rampersad to William Andrews have questioned Haley's
                    political agenda and the shaping of X's representation in <emph>The
                        Autobiography</emph>.<ptr target="#note11" xml:id="nr11" n="11"/> Marable
                    has cautioned that <emph>The Autobiography</emph> was "more Haley's than its
                    author's: because Malcolm died in February 1965, he had no opportunity to revise
                    major elements of what would become known as his political testament." As a
                    "liberal Republican, Haley held the Nation of Islam's racial separatism and
                    religious extremism in contempt, but he was fascinated by the tortured tale of
                    Malcolm's personal life."<ptr target="#note12" xml:id="nr12" n="12"/> Haley was
                    not alone in attempting to control the representation of X. Malcolm X himself
                    was invested in reinvention. He "continuously and astutely refashioned his
                    outward image, artfully redesigning his public style and even language, to
                    facilitate overtures to different people in varied contexts."<ptr
                        target="#note13" xml:id="nr13" n="13"/>
                </p>

                <p>Alex Haley first met Malcolm X when he was interviewing him for a March 1960
                        <emph>Reader's Digest</emph> article, "Mr. Muhammad Speaks." The first
                    meeting of the two men would presage the gulf in understanding that would define
                    their relationship. Haley reported that when he initially met Malcolm X, X
                    noted, "You're another one of the white man's tools sent to spy!"<ptr
                        target="#note14" xml:id="nr14" n="14"/> Haley, recently retired after twenty
                    years in the U.S. Coast Guard, was an aspiring writer. X was the increasingly
                    popular and visible New York minister of the Lost-Found Nation of Islam, a black
                    militant pseudo-Islamic religious group. The two men could not have held more
                    divergent political views. Regardless, Haley continued to focus on X in articles
                    published in the <emph>Saturday Evening Post</emph> and <emph>Playboy</emph>,
                    eventually approaching Malcolm X about a coauthored autobiography. With Nation
                    of Islam leader Elijah Muhammad's permission, X met with Haley for multiple
                    interviews, developing a working relationship that lasted until X's death. In
                    addition to <emph>The Autobiography</emph>, Haley would publish several essays
                    on Malcolm X over the course of his literary career, including "The Malcolm X I
                    Knew" and a 1983 <emph>Essence</emph> magazine article titled "Alex Haley
                    Remembers Malcolm." Haley's interest in X seems to have been as a promising
                    research subject that would generate popular interest and, by extension,
                    publishing contracts for Haley. From X's critique of the pacifist Civil Rights
                    Movement to his infamous "chickens coming home to roost" comment after John F.
                    Kennedy's assassination, Malcolm X proved a visible, controversial, and popular
                    subject. Regardless of the way in which their relationship began, they would
                    share much during the two years that they worked together. In part, their
                    relationship seems to be spurred by X's difficult break from the Nation of Islam
                    in 1964 and subsequent encounter with Islam during his Hajj, his life-changing
                    pilgrimage to Mecca. Even if the two men didn't see eye to eye, Malcolm X shared
                    his experiences with Haley during this crucial period, sending postcards and
                    letters to Haley when X was on his trip to Mecca. In fact, almost every night of
                    X's trip abroad, Betty Shabazz, X's wife, would call Alex Haley to learn of her
                    husband's travels.<ptr target="#note15" xml:id="nr15" n="15"/> While Haley would
                    call Malcolm X a friend in the essay here published, it is not clear if X ever
                    felt the same about Haley. The best indication we have of his feelings toward
                    Haley is a late-night call when X declared that he trusted Haley 70 percent.<ptr
                        target="#note16" xml:id="nr16" n="16"/> The essay and notes provide
                    additional textual evidence that should aid scholars in their examination of the
                    complicated relationship between the men.</p>
            </div>

            <div>
                <head type="main">Interpretive Gaps</head>

                <p>Ever in debate with <emph>The Autobiography</emph> is the control that Haley
                    asserted on the narrative. For example, Garrett A. Felber argues that much of
                    the final shape of the book is contrary to Malcolm X's wishes, particularly the
                    introduction and epilogue.<ptr target="#note17" xml:id="nr17" n="17"/> William
                    Andrews's "Editing 'Minority' Texts" reveals a complicated evolution of the
                    text, noting that the "epilogue more than hinted at interesting tensions, and
                    perhaps even pivotal struggles for control of the text, between the writer and
                    the subject of Malcolm's memoir."<ptr target="#note18" xml:id="nr18" n="18"/>
                    Andrews goes on to situate the "as told to" approach of <emph>The
                        Autobiography</emph> within the context of "a well-established tradition in
                    African American autobiography."<ptr target="#note19" xml:id="nr19" n="19"/>
                    Other scholars including Manning Marable and John Edgar Wideman are very
                    critical of Haley's role in the text creation, viewing the final document as
                    presenting a sanitized version of X's radicalism. The notes provide valuable
                    clues to the construction of <emph>The Autobiography</emph>, crucially important
                    because we now know that three chapters penned by Malcolm X titled "The Negro,"
                    "The End of Christianity," and "Twenty Million Black Muslims" were removed prior
                    to publication. Selections of the missing materials have been read in public and
                    portions of the manuscripts have been briefly viewed by a handful of scholars,
                    but no scholar has read the chapters in their entirety. It is unclear if the
                    chapters will ever be released due to copyright and ownership issues. One of the
                    great mysteries of the missing chapters is X's political agenda post-Mecca.
                    Marable notes: "It seemed rather odd that there's only a fleeting reference to
                    the OAAU (The Organization of Afro-American Unity) inside of the book that's
                    supposed to be his political testament. And I wondered about this. And it seemed
                    like something was missing. Well, as a matter of fact, there is: three chapters.
                    And those three chapters really represent a kind of political testament that are
                    outlined by Malcolm X."<ptr target="#note20" xml:id="nr20" n="20"/> Yet the OAAU
                    is not absent from the notes that Haley took during his interviews. Other notes
                    are equally revealing. While there is only one documented case of Malcolm X
                    supporting labor unions&#8212;a 1962 hospital worker strike&#8212;one note indicates that X
                    thought unions had the potential to create change. Note 54 records that Malcolm
                    X thought that if Martin Luther King "could have had the attitude of the labor
                    leaders, what changes he could have wrought. Now they sit down <sic>at</sic>
                    bargain as equals. Back in the 30s, before Roosevelt, looked upon as scum,
                    radicals, anarchists. Now they are respectable. Labor Building today in
                    Washington overlooks the White House." Notecard 80 mentions the M1 carbine that
                    Malcolm X was famously pictured with in a 1964 issue of <emph>Ebony</emph>
                    magazine. Interpreted as a sign of X's militancy, the note reveals that X had
                    "instructed (his) wife to use" the gun to defend their home from possible
                    attack. The notes also reference passages in <emph>The Autobiography</emph>. For
                    example, Haley recounts one interview session during which X "was gesturing with
                    his passport in his hand; he saw that I was trying to read its perforated number
                    and suddenly he thrust the passport toward me, his neck flushed reddish: 'Get
                    the number straight, but it won't be anything the white devil doesn't already
                    know. He issued me the passport.'"<ptr target="#note21" xml:id="nr21" n="21"/>
                    The passport number is recorded in Haley's hand on notecard 37. As scholars work
                    with the notes, other such gems will emerge, and we will have a better sense of
                    the creation of the final text.</p>

            </div>
            <div>
                <head type="main"> Editorial Approach</head>
                <p>This project grew out of an English/Africana Studies undergraduate course in
                    which I was interested in embedding a hands-on digital project. I am interested
                    in developing new models of student participation in digital humanities research
                    and textual recovery and this project is my first experiment in so doing. The
                    course examined the digitization of a wide set of Africana cultural materials
                    and considered crucial issues of representation, ownership, and access. As the
                    students engaged with the materials, they recognized that Africana materials are
                    underrepresented in the digital literary canon. The Malcolm X project
                    represented one way that they would be able to alter such a discrepancy. Working
                    in small, collaborative groups, students transcribed, edited, researched,
                    applied structural TEI/XML markup, and composed simple notes. For
                    undergraduates, mastering the concept of basic TEI encoding included the
                    understanding of how to represent paragraphs, page breaks, people, and places. I
                    did not ask them to think critically about applying TEI to editorial decisions.
                    Undergraduate student evaluations revealed that students thought the digital
                    project was the highlight of the course and the experience invaluable. Most
                    pointed to the activist nature of the project, of making a difference in the
                    literary field and representing important cultural materials to a larger public.
                    The project was so successful that I decided to ask my graduate students to
                    return to the materials. While the undergraduates had made a first pass through
                    the documents, there was additional proofing, standardization of annotations,
                    and extended TEI markup of editorial items&#8212;such as strikethroughs, additions,
                    and unclear sections&#8212;to complete. As part of a graduate-level class titled
                    "Introduction to Digital Humanities," I teach my students how to encode
                    materials with TEI/XML. Instead of completing exercises, graduate student worked
                    with the Haley materials to add more robust TEI. Stairstepping a project across
                    multiple semesters, classes, and levels of students has allowed a large group of
                    students to participate in an important published project and has also convinced
                    me that applied digital humanities work should be central to the classroom. As
                    project leader, I have rechecked materials for accuracy and consistency,
                    regularized the markup, and added the introduction. Texts have been imaged,
                    transcribed and marked with TEI P5.<ptr target="#note22" xml:id="nr22" n="22"/>
                    We have indicated changes made to the base text and, where possible, identified
                    deletions and strikethroughs.</p>
                <p>The essay and notes are treated with diplomatic transcriptions. We have not
                    altered mistakes or corrected spellings. Undecipherable passages are marked as
                    such with the TEI gap tag and marked as illegible, and strikethroughs,
                    additions, and deletions are noted. While it would have been useful to include
                    the published version of "The Malcolm X I Knew," we could not secure copyright
                    to do so. Therefore, only the typed manuscript version is included. Students
                    provided initial transcriptions, some annotations, and basic TEI. I have added
                    robust annotations and standardized TEI markup. Annotations are included for
                    historical events, people, and places. When possible I have included annotations
                    that connect Haley's notes to the <emph>Autobiography</emph>.</p>

                <p>As I indicated at the start of this essay, contemporary texts are much more
                    difficult to digitize because of copyright and ownership issues than those
                    materials produced before 1923. When this project began, I had doubts that the
                    Haley materials could be published. My search for ownership of Haley's literary
                    rights revealed that his estate had gone bankrupt, and all interests and royalty
                    rights were sold to John Palumbo, a Jacksonville investor, for $10,400.<ptr
                        target="#note23" xml:id="nr23" n="23"/> Palumbo graciously agreed to the
                    publication of the manuscript transcriptions and images of the materials. I
                    thank him for his generosity. I would also like to thank Texas A&amp;M
                    University librarian Rebecca Hankins for her help and support throughout this
                    process. Without her, this edition would not have been brought public. </p>
                <p>Finally, and most importantly, the following participated in the transcription,
                    editing, and markup of the primary source materials: </p>
                <p>
                    <emph>Librarian:</emph>
                </p>
                <p> Sarah Potvin. </p>

                <p>
                    <emph>Graduate students:</emph>
                </p>
                <p> Karen Davis, Amber Dunai, Jessica Durgan, Elizabeth Grumbach, Tess Habbestad,
                    Bailey Kelsey, Glynnis Lagarde, Shawn Moore, Laura Perrings, Noah Peterson, and
                    Sarah Potvin. </p>
                <p><emph>Undergraduate students:</emph></p>
                <p>Maria Acosta, Britany Bennett, Clayton Armstrong, Karen Boyd, Lorena Cardenas,
                    Stephanie Cue, Cedric Dadaille, Manuel De la Llata, Ashlee Guerra, Scott
                    Hamilton, Cassandra Hanks, Kendall Hardgrove, William Hoferer, Nicole Janssen,
                    Tia McKinney, Cooper Mclendon, Charles McWhinney, Anju Mohan, Kevin Monsees,
                    Joshua Montemayor, Parysa Oskouipour, Eric Park, Kerri Prather, Caitlin Red,
                    Lauren Reynolds, Megan Rhodes, Crystal Riles, Maranda Spinn, Stephanie Straight,
                    Jose Torres, John Turner, Yiechia Warren, Alexandra Wentz, and Ryan
                    Williams.</p>
            </div>
        </body>
        <back>
            <div type="notes">
                <note xml:id="note1">Alex Haley, <emph>Roots</emph> (Garden City, NY: Doubleday,
                    1976); "Kunta Kinte&#8211;Alex Haley Foundation: The Genealogy Experience," <ref
                        type="url" target="http://www.kintehaley.org"
                        >http://www.kintehaley.org</ref>; "The Alex Haley Tribute Site," <ref
                        type="url" target="http://www.alex-haley.com"
                        >http://www.alex-haley.com</ref>. </note>
                <note xml:id="note2">Herb Boyd, "Plagiarism and the Roots Suits," <emph>First
                        World</emph> 2, no. 3 (1979): 31&#8211;33, 31&#8211;32. David Chioni Moore, in his review
                    of the Alex Haley <emph>Roots</emph> Papers, notes that the plagiarism
                    controversy seems to have contributed to the novel being ignored by literary
                    critics. See Moore, "Revisiting a Silenced Giant: Alex Haley's
                        <emph>Roots</emph>," <emph>Resources for American Literary Study</emph> 22,
                    no. 2 (1996): 195&#8211;249.</note>
                <note xml:id="note3">"The Malcolm X I Knew" essay does not appear on nor is it
                    referenced by the site.</note>
                <note xml:id="note4">Manning Marable, "Interview with <emph>Democracy Now!</emph>,"
                    February 21, 2005, <ref type="url"
                        target="http://www.democracynow.org/2005/2/21/the_undiscovered_malcolm_x_stunning_new"
                        >http://www.democracynow.org/2005/2/21/the_undiscovered_malcolm_x_stunning_new</ref>.</note>
                <note xml:id="note5">Manning Marable, <emph>Malcolm X: A Life of Reinvention</emph>
                    (New York: Penguin, 2011), 248.</note>
                <note xml:id="note6">Adam Parfrey, <emph>It's a Man's World: Men's Adventure
                        Magazines, The Postwar Pulps</emph> (Los Angeles: Feral House, 2003), 286,
                    287.</note>
                <note xml:id="note7"> Marable writes of the increasingly difficult financial
                    situation of Haley during the completion of <emph>The Autobiography</emph>
                    primarily due to the lack of progress that Haley made on the manuscript. Haley
                    was looking for various sources of income and found one such revenue stream in a
                    "one-shot sale" of a piece of <emph>The Autobiography</emph> for the
                        <emph>Saturday Evening Post</emph>. Marable, <emph>Malcolm X</emph>, 351. It
                    is possible that the <emph>Saga</emph> piece was also a quick way for Haley to
                    earn some income. </note>
                <note xml:id="note8">Marable, <emph>Malcolm X</emph>, 259.</note>
                <note xml:id="note9">See Marable, <emph>Black Routes to Islam</emph>, ed. Aidi
                    Hishaam (New York: Palgrave Macmillan, 2009), 312, and Garrett A. Felber, "'A
                    Writer Is What I Want, Not an Interpreter': Alex Haley and Malcolm X—Conceiving
                    the Autobiographical Self and the Struggle for Authorship," <emph>Souls: A
                        Critical Journal of Black Politics, Culture, and Society</emph> 12 no. 1
                    (2010): 33&#8211;53, 46.</note>
                <note xml:id="note10">David Remnick, "This American Life: The Making and Remaking of
                    Malcolm X," <emph>New Yorker</emph>, April 25, 2011,
                    <ref type="url"
                        target="http://www.newyorker.com/arts/critics/books/2011/04/25/110425crbo_books_remnick"
                        >http://www.newyorker.com/arts/critics/books/2011/04/25/110425crbo_books_remnick</ref>.
                    For correspondence between Haley and Doubleday's Ken McCormick, see Garret A.
                    Felber, "Alex Haley Correspondence (1965)," <emph>Souls: A Critical Journal of
                        Black Politics, Culture, and Society</emph> 12, no. 2 (2010): 182&#8211;85.</note>
                <note xml:id="note11">See the following: William L. Andrews, "Editing 'Minority'
                    Texts," in <emph>The Margins of the Text</emph>, ed. David C. Greetham (Ann
                    Arbor: University of Michigan Press, 1997), 45&#8211;56; Felber, “'A Writer Is What I
                    Want, Not an Interpreter'"; Arnold Rampersad, "The Color of His Eyes: Bruce
                    Perry's <emph>Malcolm</emph> and Malcolm's Malcolm" in <emph>Malcolm X: In our
                        Own Image</emph>, ed. Joe Wood (New York: St. Martin's, 1992), 177&#8211;234; John
                    Edgar Wideman, "Malcolm X: The Art of Autobiography," in Wood, <emph>Malcolm
                        X</emph>, 101&#8211;16. </note>
                <note xml:id="note12"> Marable, <emph>Malcolm X</emph>, 9.</note>
                <note xml:id="note13"> Manning Marable, "Rediscovering Malcolm's Life:  A
                    Historian's Adventures in Living History," in <emph>Souls:  A Critical Journal
                        of Black Politics, Culture, and Society</emph> 7, no. 1 (2005): 20&#8211;35, 27. </note>
                <note xml:id="note14"> Alex Haley, <emph>The Autobiography of Malcolm X</emph>
                    (Chicago: Ballantine, 1987), 383.</note>
                <note xml:id="note15">Marable, <emph>Malcolm X,</emph> 327.</note>
                <note xml:id="note16">Haley, <emph>The Autobiography</emph>, 400.</note>
                <note xml:id="note17">Felber, “'A Writer Is What I Want, Not an
                    Interpreter.'”</note>
                <note xml:id="note18">Andrews, "Editing 'Minority' Texts," 45&#8211;46.</note>
                <note xml:id="note19">Andrews, "Editing 'Minority' Texts," 47.</note>
                <note xml:id="note20"> The OAAU is the Organization of Afro-American Unity, the
                    organization that X founded in 1964 after his trip to Mecca as an international
                    Africanist organization. "African American Historian Manning Marable Dies Days
                    Before Publication of His Biography of Malcolm X," <emph>Democracy Now!</emph>,
                    <ref type="url"
                        target="http://www.democracynow.org/2011/4/4/african_american_historian_manning_marable_dies"
                        >http://www.democracynow.org/2011/4/4/african_american_historian_manning_marable_dies</ref>
                </note>
                <note xml:id="note21">Haley, <emph>The Autobiography,</emph> 388.</note>
                <note xml:id="note22">TEI P5 guidelines are located at
                        <ref>http://www.tei-c.org/Guidelines/P5/.</ref></note>
                <note xml:id="note23">"Haley's Literary Rights Sold to Duval Investor,"
                        <emph>Florida Times-Union,</emph>
                    <ref type="url"
                        target="http://jacksonville.com/tu-online/stories/091002/met_10407259.html"
                        >http://jacksonville.com/tu-online/stories/091002/met_10407259.html</ref>. </note>
            </div>
        </back>
    </text>
</TEI>
