<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<?xml-model href="http://www.tei-c.org/release/xml/tei/custom/schema/relaxng/tei_all.rng" type="application/xml" schematypens="http://relaxng.org/ns/structure/1.0"?><!-- Pointer to the TEI-all schema; change if you are using a custom schema. -->
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
    <teiHeader xml:lang="eng">
        <fileDesc>
            <titleStmt>
                <title level="m" type="main">Science and Art: A Farce in Two Acts (1842)</title>
                <title level="a" type="sub">A Victorian Vision of “Invention” </title>
                <author>Anonymous</author>
                <editor>Rebecca Nesvet</editor>
                <respStmt>
                    <resp>Transcription and encoding</resp>
                    <name xml:id="RN">Rebecca Nesvet</name>
                </respStmt>
            </titleStmt>
            <editionStmt>
                <edition>
                    <date>2017</date>
                </edition>
            </editionStmt>
            <publicationStmt>
                <authority>Scholarly Editing: The Annual of the Association for Documentary
                    Editing</authority>
                <address>
                    <addrLine>http://www.scholarlyediting.org</addrLine>
                </address>
                <publisher>Association for Documentary Editing</publisher>
                <publisher>University of Nebraska&#8211;Lincoln</publisher>
                <distributor>
                    <name>Center for Digital Research in the Humanities</name>
                    <address>
                        <addrLine>319 Love Library</addrLine>
                        <addrLine>University of Nebraska&#8211;Lincoln</addrLine>
                        <addrLine>Lincoln, NE 68588-4100</addrLine>
                        <addrLine>http://cdrh.unl.edu</addrLine>
                    </address>
                </distributor>
                <date><!-- 2017--></date>
                <idno type="file"><!-- Name of XML file --></idno>
                <!-- You will only need to use the following idno if you are creating an edition -->
                <idno type="edition"><!-- Edition name --></idno>
                <availability>
                    <p>Scholarly Editing: The Annual of the Association for Documentary Editing is
                        freely distributed by the Association for Documentary Editing and the Center for
                        Digital Research in the Humanities at the University of Nebraska-Lincoln and
                        licensed under a Creative Commons Attribution-NonCommercial-ShareAlike 3.0
                        Unported License</p>
                </availability>
            </publicationStmt>
            <seriesStmt>
                <title level="j">Scholarly Editing: The Annual of the Association for Documentary
                    Editing</title>
                <respStmt>
                    <resp>2017 issue editor</resp>
                    <name xml:id="nhg">Nicole Gray</name>
                </respStmt>
                <respStmt>
                    <resp>editor</resp>
                    <name xml:id="ag">Amanda Gailey</name>
                </respStmt>
                <respStmt>
                    <resp>editor</resp>
                    <name xml:id="awj">Andrew Jewell</name>
                </respStmt>
                <idno type="vol"><!-- The Journal’s volume number --></idno>
                <idno type="ISSN">2167-1257</idno>
            </seriesStmt>
            <sourceDesc>
                <bibl>
                    <note>Born digital.</note>
                </bibl>
            </sourceDesc>
        </fileDesc>
    </teiHeader>
    <text>
        <front>
                    <head type="main">Science and Art: A Farce in Two Acts</head>
                    <head type="sub">From James Malcolm Rymer’s <emph rend="italic">The Queen’s
                    Magazine</emph> (1842)</head>
                    <byline>Edited by Rebecca Nesvet</byline>
                </front>        
        <body>
        <div>
            <figure type="enlargeOnClick" n="1">
                    <head>Figure 1: The <hi rend="italic">Queen’s Magazine</hi>.</head>
                    <graphic
                        url="https://upload.wikimedia.org/wikipedia/commons/thumb/5/5b/Placeholder.svg/478px-Placeholder.svg.png"/>
                    <figDesc><hi rend="italic">Queen’s Magazine</hi>, vol. 1, no. 5 (August, 1842),
                        n.p. Cambridge University Library.</figDesc>
                </figure>   
            <head>Introduction</head>
            <p>In 1991, the Science Museum in South Kensington, London, mounted an exhibit titled
                    “Making the Difference,” which commemorated the bicentenary of Charles Babbage
                    (1791&#8211;1871), the Victorian inventor of two significant prototypes of the
                    modern computer, the Difference Engine and the Analytical Engine. As the design
                    historian Louise Purbrick has observed, the official poster for “Making the
                    Difference” represented Babbage as a mechanical man, with his “head superimposed
                    on the Difference Engine,” and a “spinal column app[arently] composed of wheels”
                        (14-6).[1]<ptr target="#note1" xml:id="nr1" n="1"/> The Science Museum’s
                    then-Senior Curator Doron Swade also suggests that Babbage was a robot, as his
                    book title <hi rend="italic">The Cogwheel Brain: Charles Babbage and the Quest
                        to Build the First Computer</hi> (2000) invites the reader to imagine wheels
                    spinning not only in Babbage’s engines, but in his brain.[2]<ptr target="#note2"
                        xml:id="nr2" n="2"/>
                </p><p xml:id="p_pdt_rgx_mx">Long before 1991, an obscure play also associated Babbage with mechanical
                    people. Titled <hi rend="italic">Science and Art, a Farce, in Two Acts</hi>,
                    this short play was published anonymously in the August, 1842 number of the
                    obscure periodical <hi rend="italic">The Queen’s Magazine</hi>. In <hi
                        rend="italic">Science and Art</hi>, the fictional London lawyer Jack Freeman
                    falls in love with Maria, ward of a pompous inventor, Patent, who appears to be
                    modeled upon Babbage. To gain access to Patent’s home and court Maria, Freeman
                    masquerades as a mechanical man, or “automaton” (193).[3]<ptr target="#note3"
                        xml:id="nr3" n="3"/> His performance is choreographed by his friend, another
                    unscrupulous lawyer named Dick Lobby, and the confusion of machine with human
                    quickly creates mayhem. </p>
            <p>This comic take on scientific and artistic “invention” raises intriguing questions
                    about the nature and role of the human being during the Victorian industrial
                    revolution and today. Will “automata”&#8212;machines&#8212;replace human labor,
                    displacing many workers of diverse vocations? Does scientific or artistic
                    ingenuity blind the inventor to the needs of fellow humans, at home and in the
                    wider world? To what extent can an invention (again, either scientific or
                    artistic) that exists only as a fragment or even a concept alter the <hi
                        rend="italic">status quo</hi>? Are humans to be distinguished from machines
                    because we have free will, or is there in fact no such thing as a “free man”
                    (pun intended), only compliant automata that happen to breathe? According to a
                    prominent Victorian philosophical discourse, humans are machines or parts of
                        machines.[4]<ptr target="#note4" xml:id="nr4" n="4"/> Therefore, in many
                    ways, the unidentified author of <hi rend="italic">Science and Art</hi> had a
                    finger on the pulse&#8212;or perhaps the crankshaft&#8212;of his age. </p><p>This critical edition of <hi rend="italic">Science and Art</hi>, the first to be published, will
                    demonstrate that the play merits critical attention not only for its engagement
                    with these debates, but for its association with two eminent Victorians, a
                    scientist and an artist, at a pivotal moment in both their careers. One is
                    Babbage, whom Patent strongly resembles, and who in 1842 faced his most serious
                    crisis as an inventor, a crisis that would determine the fate of his unfinished
                    Difference Engine. The other prominent figure in <hi rend="italic">Science and
                        Art</hi>’s genesis is the editor of <hi rend="italic">Science and Art</hi>,
                    James Malcolm Rymer (1814&#8211;42), whose literary art made a considerable
                    impression upon the Victorian reading public. In the mid-1840s through the early
                    1860s, Rymer earned fame for his many “penny bloods,” or cheap, lurid fiction
                    serials targeting working-class readers, which he usually wrote anonymously or
                    pseudonymously. Scholars currently attribute to Rymer several of the most
                    successful and enduring bloods, including the Dracula precursor <hi
                        rend="italic">Varney the Vampyre, or, the Feast of Blood</hi> and the
                    original tale of Sweeney Todd, <hi rend="italic">The String of Pearls, a
                        Romance</hi> (both completed 1847).[5]<ptr target="#note5" xml:id="nr5"
                        n="5"/>
                    <hi rend="italic">Science and Art</hi> can help us to understand the contexts of
                    Rymer’s rise and Babbage’s fall.</p>
                
            
            
            
            </div><div>
                <head>Editor, Author, and Audience</head>
      
                <p><hi rend="italic">Science and Art</hi> is a less advanced composition than
                    Rymer’s bloods, it appeared at a significant moment in his literary development.
                    Rymer was the scion of a literary family that spanned the Romantic and Victorian
                    eras. His father and brothers wrote novels and poetry, painted and engraved
                    visual art, and forged currency.[6]<ptr target="#note6" xml:id="nr6" n="6"/>
                    Initially, he seems to have distanced himself from art and literature by
                    becoming a civil engineer and an inventor; in 1840, he took out a patent for
                    improved furniture castors.[7]<ptr target="#note7" xml:id="nr7" n="7"/> In 1842,
                    he integrated his scientific and artistic knowledge by editing <hi rend="italic"
                        >The Queen’s Magazine</hi>. In April through August, he produced five
                    numbers of this magazine. Its mission was interdisciplinary. In the Prospectus
                    published with the first (April) number, Rymer promised “[t]he Magazine will
                    consist of forty pages of original material, comprising
                    Romance—Poetry—Character—Burlesque […] Music—Art—Science and General
                    Literature.”[8] <ptr target="#note8" xml:id="nr8" n="8"/> He made good on this
                    vow. The magazine’s contents eventually included original fiction, such as the
                    earliest instalments of one of Rymer’s first bloods, (<hi rend="italic">Jane
                        Shore</hi>, completed 1846), as well as poetry, drama, engravings of
                    paintings, and a regular column on “Useful and Important Inventions.” The first
                    (and, ultimately, only) instalment of this column showcased a new, controversial
                    method of engraving, demonstrating the marriage of science and art in Rymer’s
                    consciousness, family, and culture.[9]<ptr target="#note9" xml:id="nr9" n="9"/>
                    <hi rend="italic">Science and Art</hi>, published in the August number, repeats
                    this reconciliation of Rymer’s multiple disciplinary cultures. </p> 
                                                                   <p>Did Rymer not only edit <hi
                        rend="italic">Science and Art</hi>, but write it? It is certainly possible.
                    According to Helen R. Smith’s 2016 catalogue of penny bloods and dreadfuls
                    offered for sale by the antiquarian bookseller Jarndyce, Rymer “edited and
                    likely wrote most” of his magazine’s contents (10, item no. 274). In his
                    surviving personal copy, his name is “substituted” in manuscript “for the
                    supposed poet of ‘Love’s fables’, “George Hillier Fantome.” In the same copy,
                    Rymer manually amends text attributed to “Charles Wellsley” [sic?], possibly
                    indicating that Rymer wrote “Wellsley’s” work.[10]<ptr target="#note10"
                        xml:id="nr10" n="10"/> Moreover, Rymer reuses the title of the <hi
                        rend="italic">Queen’s Magazine</hi> serial “Tales of the Times, by Mask,” in
                    a later publication, suggesting that he might be behind this “Mask.”
                    Suspiciously, Rymer explicitly refused to identify “Mask.” An open letter,
                    supposedly to an anonymous correspondent, “We cannot consistently communicate
                    “in confidence,” to R.R., who Mask is. Who is R.R.?”[11]<ptr target="#note11"
                        xml:id="nr11" n="12"/> However, there is as yet no positive evidence that he
                    composed <hi rend="italic">Science and Art</hi>, so, in the present edition, it
                    must remain anonymous. </p>
                <p>More can conclusively be said about the intended audience of the play, and,
                    indeed, the <hi rend="italic">Queen’s Magazine</hi> as a whole. We have seen
                    that Rymer was a working-class author, who later in his career found great
                    success by targeting working-class readers and the publishers who catered to
                    them. The <hi rend="italic">Queen’s Magazine</hi> (Figure 1) aimed to attract a
                    different readership. While his later fiction filled newspapers priced at one
                    penny, an expense affordable to working-class readers, the <hi rend="italic"
                        >Queen’s Magazine</hi> cost a shilling per number, as its title-page
                    advertises. On the same title-page, Rymer identified himself as a gentleman: “J.
                    Malcolm Rymer, Esq,” an image reinforced in an engraving of him, published in
                    the May, 1842 second number, in which he sits in a leather armchair, wrapped in
                    a dressing gown. Shelves of books stand behind him, and a bound copy of
                    Shakespeare lies at his slippered feet (76). </p><p>The magazine’s textual contents corroborate that Rymer envisioned it as middle-class aspirational
                    literature, while also reaching out to the socioeconomic elite and the wider
                    public. The Prospectus identifies it as “A FAMILY MAGAZINE OF THE HIGHEST
                    CLASS,” and suggests that its audience might even include members of the
                    socioeconomic elite. Rymer informs “respectable Advertisers” that “the <hi
                        rend="italic">Queen’s Magazine</hi> will have a <hi rend="italic"
                        >certain</hi> large circulation in a high class of society, quite
                    independent of the popular patronage it is fairly presumed it will receive from
                    a Public, who at no period of English history were so fitted as now to judge of
                    sterling literary pretensions.” In the first number of the <hi rend="italic"
                        >Queen’s Magazine</hi> (April, 1842), Rymer exhorts his middle-class reading
                    to pursue reform, opposing aristocratic tyranny. In the magazine’s major fiction
                    serial, the historical romance <hi rend="italic">Jane Shore, an Historical
                        Romance, by the Editor,</hi> he contends that “with an intelligent and
                    educated people,” the “incessant petty jealousies” and “eternal feuds” of the
                    “nobility [...] would [...] ensure [...] their extinction as a class” (5). This
                    sort of rhetoric renders Rymer’s shilling periodical a tool of general political
                    reform, which would have impressed the Chartist publishers Edward Lloyd and G.
                    W. M. Reynolds, in whose employment he would shortly thereafter establish
                    himself as one of the definitive authors of penny bloods.</p>
                <p>Rymer evidently designed not just his magazine, but <hi rend="italic">Science and
                        Art</hi> in particular, for middle-class domestic consumption. This “farce”
                    seems not to have been produced in the commercial theatre, as Victorian
                    journalism records no notices for any public performance. Instead, the play
                    seems intended for reading or domestic performance. The nineteenth-century
                    British bourgeoisie had a culture of home theatricals. Charles Dickens
                    maintained an amateur theatre company at Tavistock House in 1851-60, and Charles
                    Lutwidge Dodgson (Lewis Carroll) enjoyed amateur theatricals later in the
                    century. Home theatricals are described in Austen’s novel <hi rend="italic"
                        >Mansfield Park</hi> (1814), Thackeray’s <hi rend="italic">Vanity Fair</hi>
                    (1848), and, across the Atlantic, Louisa May Alcott’s <hi rend="italic">Little
                        Women</hi>, which draws upon the “nursery dramas” put on by Alcott’s family
                    during her 1840s American childhood (Halttunen 236).[12]<ptr target="#note12"
                        xml:id="nr12" n="12"/> According to Michael Meeuwis, Victorian amateur
                    acting “brought theatrical culture into the lives of everyday Victorians.”
                    Acting editions made it possible for amateurs to stage plays “onboard ships, in
                    regimental mess halls,” or “anywhere a relatively small amount of space was
                    available,” including private homes. By the 1860s, “Home Acting” (as one drama
                    manual put it) was promoted as a safe, moral entertainment, in lieu of domestic
                    activities such as “gaming and intoxication” (429&#8211;31).[13]<ptr
                        target="#note13" xml:id="nr13" n="13"/>
                </p><p><hi rend="italic">Science and Art</hi> appears suited by design to “home acting.” The specified
                    settings are all either vague and featureless or domestic. For instance, the
                    first scene takes place in the high-living Freeman’s “lodgings at the Temple.”
                    This impressive landmark is represented by merely a “two chairs and [a] table”
                    (190). Likewise, Freeman meets Maria at the Opera at Covent Garden, but we do
                    not see this momentous meeting. Instead, it is described in retrospect in
                    Freeman’s dialogue with his servant Tom. The play’s depiction of Patent’s
                    premises also suggests authorial acquiescence to the limitations of domestic
                    theatricals. The home of an eccentric inventor of anthropomorphic automata would
                    seem ripe for scenographic creativity. Many of us have grown up entranced by the
                    uncanny clutter of the rundown home automaton workshops in Fritz Lang’s <hi
                        rend="italic">Metropolis</hi>, Ridley Scott’s <hi rend="italic">Blade
                        Runner</hi>, or Tim Burton’s <hi rend="italic">Edward Scissorhands</hi>.
                    Conversely, <hi rend="italic">Science and Art</hi> calls for only “The House of
                    Mr. Patent” (193). No automata, parts, nor tools are explicitly prescribed,
                    excepting the pseudo-automaton played by Freeman, and even his automaton costume
                    seems amateur-proofed. It consists of a “mask and domino,” and the automaton’s
                    mechanical nature appears merely via his stilted walk (197). Any Victorian
                    bourgeois household would have been able to realize this stage effect. Such a
                    community would also be able to cope with the musical requirements of the piece.
                    The script calls for Maria’s song to be performed by or as a “symphony” (201),
                    but in the nineteenth century, this word did not imply a full orchestra. Another
                    meaning was “music in parts,” involving multiple performers, or simply
                    “concerted or harmonious music” (<hi rend="italic">OED</hi>). A few members of a
                    family and their guests could easily provide this incidental music.</p><p>Whether any Victorian amateur actors actually staged <hi rend="italic">Science and Art</hi>, we
                    cannot at present know. It seems not to have been reprinted, and vanished from
                    British culture along with the ill-fated <hi rend="italic">Queen’s
                    Magazine</hi>, leaving Rymer, his creative potential demonstrated, to move on to
                    more commercially successful and enduring literary projects. </p>
                        </div><div>
                            <head>Babbage in 1842</head>
                            <p>Appearing in August 1842,<hi rend="italic">Science and Art</hi>
                    coincided with the final phase of Babbage’s battle with the forces of
                    government, media, and scientific establishment over the fate of his two
                    visionary engines. This very public struggle evidently informed the play’s
                    composition and publication, making <hi rend="italic">Science and Art</hi> an
                    accessible, quirky introduction to the interdisciplinary discourses that
                    contextualize Babbage’s struggle to realize his Engines, as well as proof of the
                    sometime engineer Rymer’s involvement in the very public debate about the fate
                    and significance of the Engines. </p><p>To see this, we must know a bit about Babbage’s life and work through the spring of 1842. Well
                    before that year, Babbage had acquired a reputation for eccentricity. Born to a
                    wealthy family in the coastal town of Totnes, Devonshire in 1791, Babbage
                    matriculated at Cambridge University in 1810, the same year that his nearly
                    exact contemporary Percy Bysshe Shelley matriculated at Oxford. At Cambridge,
                    Babbage became friends with John Herschel, the son and intellectual heir of the
                    German-British astronomer and Royal Society luminary William Herschel.
                    Dissatisfied with Cambridge’s support for mathematics research, Babbage and
                    Herschel founded the Analytical Society, which attempted to revolutionize the
                    notation of the calculus.[14] <ptr target="#note14" xml:id="nr14" n="14"/>
                </p><p>Meanwhile, Babbage dreamt up revolutionary ideas on his own, as well. During this period, he
                    later claimed, he first envisioned his calculating engines&#8211;in a daydream,
                    which Herschel allegedly interrupted by sauntering into the room. Purbrick finds
                    this anecdote a telling bit of self-aggrandizement on Babbage’s part, designed
                    to identify him as an “inventor,” meaning a “lonely dreamer” (9). This type need
                    not fully realize his work to make his mark upon the world, as Samuel Taylor
                    Coleridge contends in the well-known origin story of his poem “Kubla Khan”
                    (1798), a deliberately unfinished fragment supposedly refined from a waking
                    dream. Babbage would have known Coleridge’s writing because he contributed to
                    the <hi rend="italic">Encyclopaedia Metropolitana</hi>, an Eclectically
                    organized compendium which Coleridge had edited in 1817.[15]<ptr
                        target="#note15" xml:id="nr15" n="15"/> The same notion of “invention”
                    informs Mary Shelley’s 1831 introduction to <hi rend="italic">Frankenstein</hi>.
                    “Invention,” Shelley theorized, “does not consist in creating out of void, but
                    out of chaos.” It “consists in the capacity of seizing on the capabilities of a
                    subject, and in the power of moulding and fashioning ideas suggested to it.”[16]
                        <ptr target="#note16" xml:id="nr16" n="16"/> Babbage seems to have agreed:
                    in <hi rend="italic"> On the Economy of Machines and Manufactures,</hi> he
                    divides “invention” into two processes: conceptualization, which he considers
                    the difficult part, and “the execution of the machine itself [...] from working
                    drawings,” which he considers “comparatively an easy task,” which results in
                    failure only when error is introduce at the “preceeding” stage (181).[17]<ptr
                        target="#note17" xml:id="nr17" n="17"/>
                </p><p>However, Babbage also took pride in the potentially revolutionary nature of his calculating
                    engine. He had thought up “the most stupendous monument of mathematical
                    calculation which the world has yet produced,” he told the celebrated scientist
                    Sir Humphry Davy in an 1822 letter. Thanking Davy for his encouragement, Babbage
                    described his Difference Engine as a concept executed up to that point only in
                    fragmentary form. “To bring to perfection the various machinery which I have
                    contrived,” he said: <quote>[...] would require an expense of both time and
                        money which can be known only to those who have have themselves attempted to
                        execute mechanical inventions. Of the greater part of that which has been
                        mentioned, I have at present contented myself with sketches on paper,
                        accompanied by short memorandums, by which I might at any time more fully
                        develop the contrivances; and where any new principles are introduced I have
                        had models executed in order to examine their actions. (45)[18] <ptr
                            target="#note18" xml:id="nr18" n="18"/></quote>In this missive, Babbage
                    claims affinity with legendary geniuses across the disciplines and makes it
                    clear that invention need not involve the inventor in execution. </p><p>Still, he set about to see his plans for the Difference Engine realized in solid metal. In 1823,
                    Babbage obtained a government commission to design and execute the Difference
                    Engine, an automatic calculator which, Babbage claimed, would revolutionize
                    British navigation and global imperialism by providing navigators with
                    machine-compiled and printed mathematical tables unprecedentedly free of human
                    arithmetic all or typographical errors. </p><p>For all this imperialist rhetoric, Babbage remained an underdog, partly on account of his own
                    actions. A key aspect of the Babbage the Victorian public knew was his tendency
                    to provoke established authority. In 1830, Babbage savaged the scientific
                    establishment by condemning the Royal Society as an elitist, ineffectual, and
                    moribund gentleman’s club, in his <hi rend="italic">Reflections on the Decline
                        of Science in England and Some of its Causes</hi> (1830), which set off a
                    firestorm of criticism and defense. In 1831, he helped to found a more inclusive
                    alternative, the British Association for the Advancement of Science. He also
                    updated the Difference Engine and, by 1837, began designing a new and better
                    Analytical Engine, which could perform a wider range of calculations, a
                    “profound conceptual advance[ment]” anticipating the word processor and the
                    computer (Bernstein 36).[19]<ptr target="#note19" xml:id="nr19" n="19"/>
                </p><p>Neither engine was ever completed during Babbage’s lifetime. Funding stalled in 1833, and in
                    1842, Babbage petitioned the government for more, but the project was condemned
                    by the government’s chosen peer reviewer. Royal Astronomer George Biddell Airy
                    judged it an unredeemable folly.[20]<ptr target="#note20" xml:id="nr20" n="20"/>
                    Prime Minister Sir Robert Peel was enraged. “What shall we do,” Peel wrote in
                    August 1842—the month of <hi rend="italic">Science and Art</hi>’s
                    publication—“to get rid of Mr. Babbage and his calculating machines?” (quoted in
                    Swade 135).[21]<ptr target="#note21" xml:id="nr21" n="21"/>
                </p>
                            <p>Defeated and demoralized, Babbage had to buy back from the government
                    the fragmentary Difference Engine’s hand-made precision parts for their value as
                    scrap metal. Assessing the situation in 1854, the astronomer Richard Sheepshanks
                    declared that “[a]n ass between two bundles of hay would be far less divided in
                    mind than a premier”&#8211;Peel&#8211;between two machines,&#8211;one not made,
                    the other not begun, and neither understood.” By this, he meant the fragmentary
                    Difference Engine and the Analytical Engine, the latter of which existed only in
                    Babbage’s papers. Voicing what no doubt others had thought in 1842, Sheepshanks
                    claimed that the British people” have got NOTHING for our £17,000. but Mr.
                    Babbage’s grumbling” (61).[22]<ptr target="#note22" xml:id="nr22" n="22"/>
                </p><p>Other contemporary observers disagreed profoundly with this analysis of Babbage’s work. The most
                    famous critique came from Charles Dickens, who in <hi rend="italic">Little
                        Dorrit</hi> (1857) showed the genius inventor Daniel Doyce vanquished by the
                    bureaucratic idiocy of the government “Circumlocution Office.” Dickens’s thinly
                    disguised portraits of Babbage and Peel speak for themselves. Calling “Doyce” a
                    “notorious rascal,” the Circumlocution Office functionary Meagles finds him
                    “guilty” of being “ingenious” and of “trying to turn his ingenuity to his
                    country’s service,” which “makes him a public offender directly” (133-4). Unlike
                    Babbage, Doyce has “brought” his machine “to perfection a dozen years
                        ago.”[23]<ptr target="#note23" xml:id="nr23" n="23"/> In Dickens’s view,
                    Babbage’s downfall was his genius challenge to the <hi rend="italic">status
                        quo</hi>. </p>
                            <p>Some Victorian reactions implied that whatever the commercial use of
                    Babbage’s engines, were they to be built, his invention, in its conceptual
                    sense, made the automaton possible and demystified thought itself. According to
                    Babbage’s friend Harry Wilmot Buxton’s memoir, Babbage really <hi rend="italic"
                        >had</hi> invented a cogwheel brain. “The marvelous pulp and fibre of a
                    brain had been substituted by brass and iron,” and “he had taught wheel-work to
                    think, or at least to do the office of thought” (quoted in Swade 85).[24]<ptr
                        target="#note24" xml:id="nr24" n="24"/> The implications of this apparent
                    breakthrough were immense. Ketabgian points out that “[u]nlike the static
                    Hobbesian watches of the Enlightenment,” run by cold clockwork, Victorian
                    machines’ “regulation of fire, coal, and steam supported a capacious vision of
                    engines as living instinctive organisms,” as “animal bodies fueled by industrial
                    forces” with “allied natural, mechanical, and psychic energy driving these
                    systems.” Once accustomed to a new landscape defined by such engines and the
                    railways and factories that required them, by machines that seemed “vital,”
                    Victorians including Babbage himself came to see themselves not only as
                    mechanical creatures, but as parts or “prostheses” of larger mechanical bodies,
                    such as the factory, community, or nation. Babbage invoked the machines
                    incorporating and inside ourselves. </p>
                        </div><div>
                            <head>From Babbage to Patent</head>
                     
                            <p>In many particulars, Babbage as he appeared in 1842 finds a comic
                    double in <hi rend="italic">Science and Art</hi>’s Patent. The zeal for wheels
                    is there, as it the failure of his machines to reach the mass production stage.
                    Patent has invented several models of his automata before Lobby, masquerading as
                    a foreign scientist, presents him with the zenith of automaton design in the
                    disguised person of Freeman. Lobby, impersonating the inventor of the automaton,
                    claims to have spent “more than one hundred years” perfecting his design to
                    create “the most excellent and most perfect machine the world ever beheld.” This
                    patience impresses Patent and recalls Babbbage’s slow work on his calculating
                    engines (193). Notably, Babbage’s engines, currently understood as computers,
                    proto-computers, or calculators, were known as automata. Writing to John Wilson
                    Croker, Peel called the Difference Engine a “scientific automaton” (quoted in
                    Swade 36).[25]<ptr target="#note25" xml:id="nr25" n="25"/> So Babbage and Patent
                    invent the same sort of machine. Indeed, while the automaton-Freeman walks as if
                    “full of wheels” (193), the science popularizer Dionysius Lardner, describing
                    the calculating engines in an <hi rend="italic">Edinburgh Review</hi> article
                    that Babbage helped him to prepare, claimed that the “project of a Calculating
                    Engine” aimed to “substitute an automaton for a compositor” and to “throw the
                    powers of wheel-work into thought,” which “could not fail to awaken the
                    attention of the world” (<hi rend="italic">SWCB</hi> 50&#8211;1).[26]<ptr
                        target="#note26" xml:id="nr26" n="26"/> In early twentieth-century America
                    (ca. 1906) Dwight Goddard’s encyclopedia of <hi rend="italic">Eminent Engineers
                        […] Who Did Most to Further Human Progress</hi>, a publication initially
                    commissioned by the Wyman and Gordon Company&#8212;Cleveland and Worcester,
                    Massachusetts-based “manufacturers of drop forgings”&#8212;finds Babbage’s
                    engines labyrinths of “wheels within wheels.” Goddard states that Babbage “spoke
                    of 1,000 columns with 50 wheels each in the store alone, and, besides, many
                    thousand wheels mounted on axles in columns for the mill and a vast machinery of
                    cams and cranks for the control” (253).[27]<ptr target="#note27" xml:id="nr27"
                        n="27"/> Modern scholars agree that the most obvious component of Babbage’s
                    engines are the wheels. In Babbage’s two major Difference Engine models, writes
                    the computer scientist Allan G. Bromley, the originator of the Science Museum’s
                    1985-91 construction of the first complete, function Difference Engine, “the
                    digits of numbers are represented by the positions of wheels (figure wheels)
                    rotating on vertical axes” (30).[28]<ptr target="#note28" xml:id="nr28" n="28"/>
                </p><p>Babbage’s utopian dreaming and overtures to the government are also present in Patent. “One would
                    imagine he thought nothing right in this world, as his invention is always on
                    the rack to make it better,” says Freeman’s friend Dick Lobby. “I don’t know how
                    many machines he has invented,” or “how many schemes he has proposed for the
                    good of the public.” When Freeman asks if they have “turned to any account,”
                    Lobby replies at length, making Patent seem more and more Babbage&#8211;like.
                    “It was not long ago that he published proposals for an automaton manufactory,
                    in which he explained the variety of uses those self-acting machines might be
                    put to, and what an immense saving of expense to the nation to employ them,”
                    Lobby tells Freeman. Frighteningly, “the business of an army, according to the
                    system of modern tactics, might as well be managed by automatons [sic] as real
                    soldiers,” and “this would be a wonderful saving, as it would render unnecessary
                    almost the whole host of army agents, army contractors, and barrack masters,”
                    while fearless machines would be “easily repaired” when damaged by war (192).
                    This parody recalls Ketabgian’s apt characterization of Babbage as an
                    “technophilia[c]” who “idealizes the machine as an empowering prosthesis for
                    humans,” as in his <hi rend="italic">On the Economy of Machinery and
                        Manufactures</hi>, which problematically “bases its guiding principle on the
                    substitution of machinery for human limbs” (18). </p><p>Like Babbage, Patent is a provocateur, though his provocations are unintentional and thereby
                    comedic. Freeman objects to the idea of mechanical soldiers on the grounds that
                    Britain is not a tyranny, and so its living men should be eager to risk their
                    lives to “secure their liberty,” win the “applause of mankind,” and “present the
                    brightest pages of history to admiring posterity.” This is easy for Freeman and
                    Lobby to appreciate; as upper&#8211;class lawyers, they are not likely ever to find
                    themselves in combat. They are far more likely to become the politicians whose
                    choices create the slaughter. Patent’s next attempt to market his automata, to
                    the Royal Navy men stationed at Portsmouth, fails because the hearty British
                    sailors, fearful that automata would deprive them of their employment, threaten
                    to “have him thrown overboard for a rascal” (192). No doubt some early&#8211;1830s
                    compilers of nautical tables would have eagerly dunked Babbage. </p><p>Also like Babbage, Patent can only fund the manufacture of his automata when they do not
                    challenge society as it is and help the corrupt elite to consolidate its power.
                    Patent “offer[s] to manufacture some” automata “for a few wealthy noblemen, who
                    told him that if he could conceive to make them say aye and nay, they would
                    probably take a dozen or two, as they might have use for them upon the
                    dissolution of Parliament” (192). In other words, the aristocracy want
                    mechanical voters that they can program to vote for the parliamentary candidates
                    that they themselves favor, making a mockery of even the extremely limited
                    suffrage of the early Victorian era. This makes him a sad, eerie doppelgänger
                    for Babbage, whose engines appeal to the government only when they help to
                    increase the revenue of Britain’s global empire; revenue enjoyed largely by the
                    elite. </p><p>In fact, Babbage’s political prose writings judge egalitarian government no more important, and
                    perhaps less important, than the right of the elite to their property&#8211;
                    including property that is not earned but inherited. He considered any expansion
                    of voting rights an imposition unless counterbalanced by effectively giving the
                    wealthy more voting power. In his essay “Thoughts upon an Extension of the
                    Franchise” (1865), he dismisses the Chartist’s demand for universal male
                    suffrage by claiming that “the franchise” has only an “imagined popularity with
                    the masses (rather than any examination of its merits and disadvantages).”
                    Whether the elite need likewise to consider the “disadvantages” of voting does
                    not occur to him. He warns of the “danger to be apprehended from the effect of
                    lowering the qualification for suffrage without some countervailing extension in
                    favour of the influence of property,” and judges the United States, then
                    beginning to fall apart at the seams over the issue of slavery, a demonstration
                    of the negative effects of an expanded franchise (237).[29]<ptr target="#note29"
                        xml:id="nr29" n="29"/> How can an automaton actually improve the human
                    condition? Babbage offers few satisfactory answers in 1865, so it is unlikely he
                    was able to resolve the question in 1842. </p><p>The “automaton” delivered by Lobby to Patent actually achieves this elusive aim. It allows
                    Freeman to marry his beloved Maria, the lovers to be reconciled with their
                    respective adult authority figures, and Patent to rejoin human society, putting
                    his wheel&#8211;filled inventions to use in the social ritual of the wedding
                    dance. Furthermore, the coupling of Freeman&#8211;as&#8211;automaton and Maria
                    suggests ideas about the utopian potential of the uncanny confusion of human and
                    machine that theorist Donna Haraway introduced in <hi rend="italic">A Cyborg
                        Manifesto</hi> (1985).[30]<ptr target="#note30" xml:id="nr30" n="30"/> In
                    short, <hi rend="italic">Science and Art</hi>’s purely notional automaton
                    facilitates requited love, and in so doing teaches both Patent and Freeman’s
                    avaricious lawyer uncle that the drive to love—this unique propensity of the
                    human machine—is a feature, not a bug. So is free will, which the aptly named
                    “Freeman” is able to exercise in his matrimonial choice only because he
                    masquerades as an automaton. </p>
                        </div><div>
                            <head>The Hungry Forties</head>
                        
                            <p>While these aspects of <hi rend="italic">Science and Art</hi>
                    anticipate later cultural developments, the play’s presentation of Patent as a
                    pompous, bumbling fool who cannot tell the difference between an automaton and a
                    human being pretending to be one seems a short&#8211;sighted parody of the man
                    who thought up the computer, but on further analysis, holds merit. The entire
                    1840s has long been known as the ‘Hungry Forties’, and although the term was
                    coined only in the twentieth century, it remains apt. Widespread
                    working&#8211;class and indigent hunger preceded the Irish Potato Famine
                    (1845&#8211;7), and dominated both the nation and the national consciousness
                    throughout the period 1840&#8211;9. We cannot “underestimate the political
                    centrality of the debate on hunger” throughout this decade, writes Peter J.
                        Gurney.[31]<ptr target="#note31" xml:id="nr31" n="31"/> Charlotte Boyce adds
                    that it was not only the working&#8211;class and radical press that debated
                    hunger in this decade: it was the entire nation (423).[32]<ptr target="#note32"
                        xml:id="nr32" n="32"/> The causes were many: rural to urban migration that
                    obliterated many workers’ and children’s access to home&#8211;grown food; the
                    oppressive Poor Law and Corn Laws, the latter the target of the Peelite
                    Anti&#8211;Corn Law League; a series of crop failures, and of course the three
                    failed potato harvests of the mid&#8211;1840s. Hunger was a national crisis that
                    it was impossible to ignore. It informed the Chartist movement, with its demands
                    for working&#8211;class suffrage and sustainable standards of living. </p><p>The food crisis was impossible to ignore—unless, perhaps, one had designed a wondrous machine and
                    was monomaniacally focused on getting it built. That was Babbage’s public image
                    in many quarters, whether or not it was his reality. In <hi rend="italic"
                        >Charles Babbage: Pioneer of the Computer</hi> (1982), Babbage's preeminent
                    modern biographer Anthony Hyman makes a charitable understatement: that
                    “Babbage’s industrial interests and the possibilities of commercial application
                    of his calculating machines were quite unattractive” to Peel (191).[33]<ptr
                        target="#note33" xml:id="nr33" n="33"/> Peel had never liked the idea of a
                    calculating engine, and as early as his 1823 letter to Croker had derided
                    Babbage as an inhabitant of “Laputa,” the levitating island of impractical
                    mathematical enthusiasts in Jonathan Swift’s <hi rend="italic">Gulliver’s
                        Travels</hi> (1726).</p>
                <p>We must recall that in the 1830s, Babbage received over £17,000 of public money,
                    and completed no engine, then, in 1842, wanted more money. It may have seemed
                    that, surrounded by his fragmentary wheel&#8211;work, Babbage could not see
                    humanity beyond. </p><p>Echoing some of Babbage’s contemporary critics, Purbrick condemns modern Britain’s “valorization”
                    of the Difference Engine, which she calls “a machine that never worked.” “[I]f a
                    machine has value regardless of function,” she asks, “what kind of object is a
                    machine?” (14). The history of the Difference Engine and the representations of
                    fantasy automata from Hoffmann to <hi rend="italic">Science and Art</hi> and
                    beyond can facilitate important thought about the potential capacities of both
                    machines and humans, and the limitations that structural inequities place upon
                    both machines and humans. </p>
                        </div><div>
                            <head>Beyond Babbage</head>
                      
                            <p>
                    <hi rend="italic">Science and Art</hi> is no mere burlesque of Babbage. It
                    participates in a broader Victorian discourses concerning automata, some of
                    which Ketabgian unpacks. She close&#8211;reads several longer, more complex Victorian
                    literary representations of automata and finds that they tend to conceptualize
                    what it means to be human by dramatizing the “undoing” of “humanness” via the
                    revelation of humanness as “a concept shot through by the mechanical” Many
                    Victorian writers, exposed to the symbolically vital, respiratory activity of
                    the steam engine and other new technologies, came to understand humans as
                    automata of sorts (Ketabgian 1). Contra Swade, it is not just Babbage who is a
                    mechanical being; we all are living machines or else, as members of communities,
                    factories, and nations, we are parts of machines. Like the primary texts that
                    Ketabgian cites, <hi rend="italic">Science and Art</hi> represents the human
                    being this way: as both a surpassingly wonderful machine and a cog in larger
                    structures. This representation might alter the Science Museum’s image of
                    Babbage. Contextualized by Ketabgian’s work, <hi rend="italic">Science and
                        Art</hi> liberates Babbage from his teleological role in relation to
                    digital&#8211;age information technology. Instead, <hi rend="italic">Science and
                        Art</hi> helps us to see Babbage as a central figure in an important
                    Victorian philosophical inquiry concerning human nature in the Industrial Age. </p><p>Moreover, the play participates in a far older discourse of machinery and humanity. Freeman and
                    Lobby’s imposture unintentionally hearkens back to some of the earliest
                    conceptions of machinery in modern British and Continental writing. Jessica
                    Wolfe’s 2004 monograph <hi rend="italic">Humanism, Machinery, and Renaissance
                        Literature</hi> demonstrates that “machinery plays a central role in the way
                    Renaissance humanists reassess their understanding of all manner of instrumental
                    means,” including rhetoric, “courtly dissimulation,” and diplomacy. Pointing out
                    that in the 1550s, the term <hi rend="italic">technologia</hi> referred to what
                    we would now call humanistic artifice, not the construction and manipulation of
                    hardware, Wolfe shows how literature in a variety of genres and languages
                    “represents machinery as simultaneously obfuscating and enlightening”
                        (15).[34]<ptr target="#note34" xml:id="nr34" n="34"/> So does <hi
                        rend="italic">Science and Art</hi>. Patent is impressed by the amazingly
                    anthropomorphic machine and so fails to recognize its humanity. He also fails to
                    recognize the humanity of his ward. This is evident in his insistence that she
                    marry a man she has never met instead of the one she loves. While that conflict
                    is a cliche of the melodrama genre, it gains new life by the play’s focus on the
                    ways in which humans are uncannily indistinguishable from machines: mechanical
                    in their perhaps predictable behaviours, but imbued with individual will that
                    can defy that of the programmer. Ultimately, Patent learns that the most
                    impressive machine is the human being—which is a defining tenet of humanism. In
                    the play’s final moments, Patent embraces a kind of humanism by offering to play
                    his hurdy&#8211;gurdy so that the lovers may dance in celebration of their
                    marriage. A hurdy&#8211;gurdy is a crank&#8211;operated musical instrument
                    containing wheels: an amalgamation of science and art. </p><p><hi rend="italic">Science and Art</hi> also has something important to say about the relations
                    between science and art. In this play, art (Freeman’s masquerade) challenges
                    Science (personified by Patent) but also suggests that the boundaries between
                    these two are porous. A great deal of what passes in Patent’s view for “science”
                    is theatre: the ceremonial histrionics of the Royal Society are a target of the
                    satire, just as they were of Babbage’s own writing and activism. Also, <hi
                        rend="italic">Science and Art</hi> proposes that there is a science to the
                    art of impersonating a machine. Lobby directs Freeman’s acting. “Remember—none
                    of your sighing and sobbing […] you must walk as if your whole body were full of
                    wheels […] Bravo! Well done!” (193). Presumably, Freeman’s execution of these
                    orders transforms him into an uncanny pseudo&#8211;automaton. Acting is an art, but as
                    the lawyer Lobby must have learned along with his oratorical skills, it is also
                    a science because it is governed by discoverable and inalienable laws. </p><p>Such laws also govern stage&#8211;love and courtship in the farce genre. Freeman and Maria obey these
                    laws by falling in love at first sight, defying their respective paterfamilias
                    figures, and ultimately reconciling themselves with these figures to melt into
                    establishment life. They think they are rebels, a ‘free man’ and woman striking
                    out against custom, but instead, custom programs them like calculating engines.
                    Freeman thinks he only pretends to be an automaton, and in that he is wrong.
                    Consequently, <hi rend="italic">Science and Art</hi> articulates that science
                    and art together perform the work of revealing the human in the machine
                    (literally, in Freeman and Lobby’s eventual unmasking) and also the machine in
                    the human—whether that human is the cog&#8211;brained Babbage or a cocky young cog in
                    the machine of London society. </p>
                        </div><div>
                            <head>Editorial Methodology</head>
                        
                            <p>Ketabgian exhorts us to “treat Victorian technology as a realm not
                    only of negation and alienation but also of intense human projection,
                    identification, and transformation,” To realize this goal, she adds, it is vital
                    to accept that industrial&#8211;age humans exist “both in and as machines” (162). <hi
                        rend="italic">Science and Art</hi> advances this proposition, allowing us a
                    glimpse into the contextual complexities of Babbage’s world. For this reason, it
                    ought to be not only read in the twenty&#8211;first century, but staged for the first
                    time. It is my hope that this edition will help students of Victorian culture
                    and theatre artists to achieve these objectives. </p><p>To facilitate this work, I provide the script of <hi rend="italic">Science and Art</hi>, which I
                    transcribed from the copies of the <hi rend="italic">Queen’s Magazine</hi>
                    omnibus at Cambridge University Library and the British Library.[35]<ptr
                        target="#note35" xml:id="nr35" n="35"/> I have encoded the script in
                    accordance with the TEI guidelines for drama. For ease of comprehension, I have
                    silently modernized some features of the play script format, including by doing
                    away with the original’s abbreviated character names. However, I have faithfully
                    transcribed the erratic punctuation of the original, and all typographical
                    features excepting where typographical errors would prevent a cold (unrehearsed)
                    reading of the text that Rymer evidently intended. In those cases, the errors
                    are silently corrected, while the notes supply the original, erroneous text.
                    Words accidentally omitted from the original are marked as such, using the
                    &lt;supplied> tag. To the cast list, I have added character descriptions; they
                    appear in square brackets. For the convenience of performers, researchers, and
                    classroom discussion, I have retained both act and scene divisions and the
                    original <hi rend="italic">Queen’s Magazine</hi> page numbers.</p><p>The notes serve several purposes germane to scholarship, classroom discussion, and and theatrical
                    production. They gloss anachronistic vocabulary, clarify the play’s intersection
                    with the discourse concerning Babbage and his engines, relate the play’s vision
                    of invention to an understanding of “invention” current in the 1830s, and
                    identify points where <hi rend="italic">Science and Art</hi> shares themes,
                    issues, or stylistic features with Rymer’s conclusively attributed work. This
                    editorial method allows the readers both to see where the play fits in his
                    evolution as a writer and to make their own determination as to whether it is
                    the product of his hand, not just his editorial prerogative. </p><p>Finally, I invite contact from theatre companies, academic theatres, and amateur drama groups
                    that might wish to produce or stage&#8211;read <hi rend="italic">Science and
                        Art</hi>, free of royalties. Today’s storytellers are automata: humans with
                    cybernetic prosthetics in the forms of camera&#8211; and tablet&#8211;phones,
                    projecting theatre into domestic spaces via Youtube or, in the spirit of the
                    penny press, the open&#8211;access performed literature platform
                        LibriVox.[36]<ptr target="#note36" xml:id="nr36" n="36"/> Like Babbage’s
                    Engines, the pseudo&#8211;automaton of <hi rend="italic">Science and Art</hi> is
                    long overdue for corporeal, animate realization, in domestic and public spaces. </p>
                
                
                
            
            </div>
                
        </body>
        <back>
            <div type="notes">
                <note xml:id="note1">[1]. Louise Purbrick, “The Dream Machine: Charles Babbage and his
                    Imaginary Computers,” <hi rend="italic">Journal of Design History</hi> 6, no. 1
                    (1993): 9&#8211;23.</note>
                
                <note xml:id="note2">[2]. Doron Swade, <hi rend="italic">The Cogwheel Brain: Charles
                        Babbage and the Quest to Build the First Computer.</hi> London: Little,
                    Brown, 2002.</note>
                
                <note xml:id="note3">[3]. “Science and Art: A Farce, in Two Acts,” <hi rend="italic"
                        >The Queen’s Magazine</hi> 1, no. 5 (August, 1842): 190&#8211;207. Hereafter
                    abbreviated <hi rend="italic">SA.</hi> The masthead and title pages of the
                    magazine consistently misspell the title “Queens’.” I have silently amended the
                    error throughout this publication.</note>
                
                <note xml:id="note4">[4]. Tamara Ketabgian, <hi rend="italic">The Lives of Machines:
                        The Industrial Imaginary in Victorian Literature and Culture.</hi>Ann Arbor:
                    University of Michigan Press, 2011. </note>
                
                <note xml:id="note5">[5]. Robert Mack, <hi rend="italic">The Wonderful and Surprising
                        History of Sweeney Todd: The Life and Times of an Urban Legend.</hi> London:
                    Continuum, 2007, surveys the attribution controversy concerning <hi
                        rend="italic">The String of Pearls </hi>(144&#8211;8). Mack cites Helen R.
                    Smith’s bibliographical breakthrough <hi rend="italic">New light on Sweeney
                        Todd, Thomas Peckett Prest, James Malcolm Rymer and Elizabeth Caroline
                        Grey.</hi> London: Jarndyce, 2002, and <hi rend="italic">The String of
                        Pearls,</hi> edited by Dick Collins for Wordsworth Editions in 2010. Collins
                    was initially sceptical of Smith’s attribution of that text primarily to Rymer,
                    but decided that “the case seems proven” (xiii). Louis James, <hi rend="italic"
                        >Fiction for the Working Man</hi>, Oxford University Press, 1963, cites
                    manuscript evidence to persuasively identify Rymer as the author of <hi
                        rend="italic">Varney the Vampyre</hi> (37).</note>
                
                <note xml:id="note6">[6]. Rebecca Nesvet, “<hi rend="italic">The Spaniard</hi> and
                    Sweeney Todd,” accepted for publication in <hi rend="italic">Notes and
                        Queries</hi>, forthcoming in 2017.</note>
                
                <note xml:id="note7">[7]. <hi rend="italic">The London Journal of Arts, Sciences, and
                        Manufactures, and Repertory of Patent Inventions</hi> 23 (1843): 27.</note>
                
                <note xml:id="note8">[8]. “Prospectus,” <hi rend="italic">Queen’s Magazine</hi> 1,
                    no. 1 (April, 1842): n.p. </note>
                
                <note xml:id="note9">[9]. “Useful and Important Inventions: Mr. E. Palmer’s Patent
                    Electrotint,” <hi rend="italic">Queen’s Magazine</hi> 1, no. 1 (April, 1842):
                    31.</note>
                <note xml:id="note10">[10]. Helen R. Smith, <hi rend="italic">Jarndyce Catalogue of
                        Bloods and Penny Dreadfuls</hi> 219. London: Jarndyce, 2016. </note>
                <note xml:id="note11">[11]. James Malcolm Rymer, “To Correspondents,” <hi
                        rend="italic">The Queen’s Magazine</hi> 1, no. 2 (May, 1842): 32.</note>
                <note xml:id="note12">[12]. Karen Halttunen, “The Domestic Drama of Louisa May
                    Alcott,” <hi rend="italic">Feminist Studies</hi> 10, no. 2 (1984):
                    233&#8211;54.</note>
                <note xml:id="note13">[13]. Michael Meeuwis, “The Theatre&#8211;Royal Back Drawing&#8211;Room:
                    Professionalizing Domestic Entertainment in Victorian Acting Manuals,” <hi
                        rend="italic">Victorian Studies</hi> 54, no. 3 (2012),:427&#8211;37.</note>
                
                <note xml:id="note14">[14]. <hi rend="italic">Science and Reform: Selected Works of
                        Charles Babbage,</hi> edited by Anthony Hyman. Cambridge University Press,
                    1989. Hereafter abbreviated <hi rend="italic">SWCB.</hi></note>
                
                <note xml:id="note15">[15]. <hi rend="italic">Encyclopædia Metropolitana; or,
                        Universal Dictionary of Knowledge,</hi> edited by Samuel Taylor Coleridge,
                    Edward Smedley, Hugh James Rose, and Henry John Rose. London, 1817&#8211;45.
                    Coleridge was succeeded as editor by the other editors named, and died in 1834.
                    Babbage’s contribution appeared in the sixth volume (1826).</note>
                <note xml:id="note16">[16]. Mary Shelley, <hi rend="italic">Frankenstein.</hi>
                    London: Colburn and Bentley 1831.  <ref type="url"
                        target="http://www.rc.umd.edu/editions/frankenstein/1831v1/intro">Romantic
                        Circles</ref> 2009. Accessed on September 15, 2016.</note>
                <note xml:id="note17">[17]. Charles Babbage, “On the Economy of Machines and
                    Manufactures, pp. 169&#8211;267,” <hi rend="italic">SWCB</hi>127&#8211;201. In
                    this manifesto, Babbage recycled material from “On the General Principles which
                    Regulate the Application of Machinery to Manufacture and the Mechanical Arts,”
                        <hi rend="italic">Encyclopaedia Metropolitana, </hi> (1829): 8, pp.
                    1&#8211;84. See Ana Millàn Gasca, in “Organization and Mathematics: A Look into
                    the Prehistory of Industrial Engineering,” <hi rend="italic">Technological
                        Concepts and Mathematical Models in the Evolution of Modern Engineering
                        Systems: Controlling, Managing, Organizing </hi>, edited by Mario Lucertini,
                    Ana Millàn Gasca, and Fernando Nicolò. Basel: Springer, 2012: 21&#8211;78 (30). </note>
                <note xml:id="note18">[18]. Babbage, “Letter to Sir Humphry Davy, Bar[one]t, pp.
                        3&#8211;12,”<hi rend="italic">SWCB</hi> 43&#8211;51.</note>
                <note xml:id="note19">[19]. Jeremy Bernstein, <hi rend="italic">The Analytical Engine: Computers Past Present, and Future</hi>, New York: Random House, 1964. </note>
                <note xml:id="note20">[20]. George Biddell Airy, letter to Henry Goulbourn,
                    September 1842, quoted and d[iscussed in Swade 142.</note>
                <note xml:id="note21">[21]. Robert Peel, letter to William Buckland, 31 August 1842.
                    British Library Additional Manuscript 40,514, fol. 223. Buckland was a
                    geologist. Quoted and discussed in Swade (135-6).</note>
                
                <note xml:id="note22">[22]. Richard Sheepshanks, <hi rend="italic">A Letter to the
                        Board of Visitors of the Greenwich Royal Observatory, in Reply to the
                        Calumnies of Mr. Babbage at their Meeting in June, 1853, and in his Book
                        Entitled The Exposition of 1851.</hi> London: G. Barclay, 1854. </note>
                <note xml:id="note23">[23]. Charles Dickens, <hi rend="italic">Little Dorrit</hi>. Edited by Stephen Wall and Helen Small. Revised Edition. London: Penguin, 2003.</note>
                <note xml:id="note24">[24]. Harry Wilmot Buxton, <hi rend="italic">Memoir of the life
                        and labours of the late Charles Babbage Esq., F.R.S.</hi> Cambridge: MIT
                    Press, 1988. Buxton’s observation is discussed at length in Christopher D.
                    Green, <ref type="url"
                        target="http://www.yorku.ca/christo/papers/babbage-berlin.htm">“Was
                        Babbage’s Analytical Engine an Instrument of Psychological Research?”
                    </ref>, an abridgement of “Charles Babbage, the Analytical Engine, and the
                    Possibility of a 19th&#8211;Century Cognitive Science,” <hi rend="italic">The
                        Transformation of Psychology.</hi> Edited by C.D. Green et al. Washington,
                    DC: American Psychological Association Press, 2001 (133&#8211;152). Accessed on
                    September 15, 2016.</note>
                <note xml:id="note25">[25]. Robert Peel, letter to John Wilson Croker, March 8,
                    1823, reproduced in <hi rend="italic">The Croker Papers</hi>, edited by L.J.
                    Jennings, 3 vols., London: Clowes, 1884. Volume 1, 262&#8211;3. Quoted in Swade
                    36.</note>
                <note xml:id="note26">[26]. Dionysius Lardner, “Babbage’s Calculating Engine.” <hi
                        rend="italic">Edinburgh Review</hi> 120 (1834): 263&#8211;327, in <hi
                        rend="italic">SWCB</hi> 51&#8211;109.</note>
                <note xml:id="note27">[27]. Dwight Goddard, <hi rend="italic">Eminent Engineers: Brief
                        Biographies of Thirty&#8211;two of the Inventors and Engineers who did most to
                        further mechanical progress, by Dwight Goddard, Member of the American
                        Society of Mechanical Engineers.</hi> N.p., “1905” [1906]. Drop forging is a
                    “process of shaping metal and increasing its strength,” typically by dropping
                    one die onto metal positioned on top of another, stationary, die (<hi
                        rend="italic">Britannica</hi>).</note>
                <note xml:id="note28">[28]. Allan G. Bromley, “Charles Babbage’s Analytical Engine,
                    1838” <hi rend="italic">IEEE Annals of the History of Computing</hi> 20, no. 4
                    (1998): 29&#8211;45.</note>
                <note xml:id="note29">[29]. “Extension of the Franchise, pp. 3&#8211;8,” <hi rend="italic">SWCB</hi>,
                    237&#8211;41.</note>
                <note xml:id="note30">[30]. Donna Haraway, “A Cyborg Manifesto: Science, Technology,
                    and Socialist&#8211;Feminism in the Late Twentieth Century,”  <hi rend="italic"
                        >Simians, Cyborgs and Women: The Reinvention of Nature</hi> (New York;
                    Routledge, 1991), 149&#8211;181. </note>
                <note xml:id="note31">[31]. Peter J. Gurney, “’Rejoicing in Potatoes’: The Politics of
                    Consumption in England during the ‘Hungry Forties’” <hi rend="italic">Past and
                        Present</hi> 203, no. 1 (2009): 99&#8211;136.</note>
                <note xml:id="note32">[32]. Charlotte Boyce, “Representing the ‘Hungry Forties’ in
                    Image and Verse: The Politics of Hunger in Early&#8211;Victorian Periodicals”
                        <hi rend="italic">Victorian Literature and Culture</hi> 40 (2012):
                    421&#8211;49.</note>
                <note xml:id="note33">[33]. Anthony Hyman, <hi rend="italic">Charles Babbage,
                        Pioneer of the Computer.</hi> Princeton University Press, 1982.</note>
                <note xml:id="note34">[34]. Jessica Wolfe, <hi rend="italic">Humanism, Machinery, and
                        Renaissance Literature.</hi> Cambridge University Press, 2004. </note>
                <note xml:id="note35">[35]. One additional copy of the <hi rend="italic">Queen’s
                        Magazine</hi> exists in a public collection. Wilson Library at the
                    University of North Carolina acquired this volume in October 2016. It was
                    Rymer’s copy, and is distinguished by his manuscript annotations and
                    corrections, and also by defacement. Someone cut out Rymer’s engraved portrait,
                    leaving a roughly square hole in the center of page 76 of no. 2 (May, 1842). <!--I am waiting to examine this copy shortly; it is currently en route from London to Chapel Hill.--></note>
                <note xml:id="note36">[36]. Hugh McGuire, et al. <ref type="url"
                        target="http://www.librivox.org"><hi rend="italic">LibriVox: Acoustical
                            Liberation of Books in the Public Domain.</hi></ref>2005&#8211;present.
                    Accessed on September 15, 2016.</note>
            </div>
        </back>
 
 
    </text>
</TEI>
