<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<?oxygen RNGSchema="http://www.scholarlyediting.org/scholarlyediting.rng" type="xml"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xml:lang="eng">
    <teiHeader>
        <fileDesc>
            <titleStmt>
                <title level="a" type="main">Review: <hi rend="italic">Ovid’s Revisions: The Editor
                    as Author. </hi> Edited by Francesca K. A. Martelli.</title>
                <author key="Nobles, Heidi">Heidi Nobles</author>
            </titleStmt>
            <editionStmt>
                <edition>
                    <date>2016</date>
                </edition>
            </editionStmt>
            <publicationStmt>
                <idno type="file">review.ovid</idno>
                <authority>Scholary Editing: The Annual of the Association for Documentary
                    Editing</authority>
                <address>
 <addrLine>http://www.scholarlyediting.org</addrLine>
</address>
                <publisher>Association for Documentary Editing</publisher>
                <publisher>University of Nebraska&#8211;Lincoln</publisher>
                <distributor>
                    <name>Center for Digital Research in the Humanities</name>
                    <address>
<addrLine>319 Love Library</addrLine>
<addrLine>University of Nebraska&#8211;Lincoln</addrLine>
<addrLine>Lincoln, NE 68588-4100</addrLine>
<addrLine>http://cdrh.unl.edu</addrLine>
 </address>
                </distributor>
                <date>2016</date>
                <availability>
                    <p>Scholary Editing: The Annual of the Association for Documentary Editing is
                        freely distributed by the Association for Documentary Editing and the Center
                        for Digital Research in the Humanities at the University of Nebraska-Lincoln
                        and licensed under a Creative Commons Attribution-NonCommercial-ShareAlike
                        3.0 Unported License</p>
                </availability>
            </publicationStmt>
            <seriesStmt>
                <title level="j">Scholarly Editing: The Annual of the Association for Documentary
                    Editing</title>
                <respStmt>
                    <resp>editor</resp>
                    <name xml:id="ag" key="Gailey, Amanda A.">Amanda Gailey</name>
                </respStmt>
                <respStmt>
                    <resp>editor</resp>
                    <name xml:id="awj" key="Jewell, Andrew W.">Andrew Jewell</name>
                </respStmt>
                <idno type="vol">37</idno>
                <idno type="ISSN">2167-1257</idno>
            </seriesStmt>
            <sourceDesc>
                <bibl>
                    <note>Born digital.</note>
                </bibl>
            </sourceDesc>
        </fileDesc>
        <revisionDesc>
            <change when="2016-03-21">
                <name xml:id="ga_ki" key="Kirilloff, Gabi">Gabi Kirilloff</name> markup in TEI
                XML</change>
        </revisionDesc>
    </teiHeader>
    <text>
        <body>
            <head type="main"><hi rend="italic">Ovid’s Revisions: The Editor as Author.</hi>
                Francesca K. A. Martelli. Cambridge: Cambridge University Press, 2014. 260 pp. ISBN:
                9781107037717. $95.</head>
            <p>The relationship between editor and author is often fraught with tension, raising
                questions of who controls the published text and what authorship actually means. In
                    <hi rend="italic">Ovid’s Revisions: The Editor as Author</hi>, Francesca K. A.
                Martelli, an assistant professor of classics at UCLA, engages issues of editorial
                practice and authorial identity by considering a body of work by Publius Ovidius
                Naso (43 BCE–ca. 18 CE), the Roman poet most of us know today as Ovid. As Martelli
                demonstrates, a striking feature of Ovid’s work is his career-long practice of
                revising his own work and drawing readers’ attention to those revisions. Through
                looking across five of Ovid’s major works, Martelli makes visible a wide range of
                editorial practice still quite relevant today, as well as the import of that work
                for authors and readers alike.</p>
            <p>Martelli opens her volume with a substantive discussion of revision as transformative
                for texts and authors, recognizing trends in authorship studies and related fields
                that stress such concepts as distributed, or collaborative, authorship and the
                socially constructed aspects of the author. Yet Ovid’s work, she notes, offers a
                window into the complexity of even a so-called single author, revealing ways in
                which authorial revision serves to multiply the author’s identity, making the
                singular into a plural by having the author fill multiple roles, certainly, and by
                revising who the author “is” over the course of a career, due to maturation and
                construction.</p>
            <p>Challenging assumptions, too, that revision “always aims at improvement” (4),
                Martelli claims that Ovid’s work shows a sense of value in revision for revision’s
                sake. This view of revision as play, of multiple drafts as equally valid, unsettles
                an editorial approach based on determining either an author’s original or final
                intention. The text does not originate in one singular moment, in other words, but
                across time. In this sense, revision is not a corrective but an extension. Such a
                view promotes efforts to produce collected parallel works or edited volumes that
                preserve, rather than collapse or redact, differences among drafts.</p>
            <p>Martelli notes Ovid’s transparency about the revisions of his own works through, for
                example, prefaces that contextualize not only the individual works they frame but
                also their place in Ovid’s larger body of work, and through making available
                overlapping written material. This project allows Martelli to “plot some of the
                narratives of revision that run through” his work (29), looking at diverse editorial
                approaches—“the <hi rend="italic">Amores</hi> foreshortens, the <hi rend="italic"
                    >Ars Amatoria</hi> extends, the <hi rend="italic">Fasti</hi> supplements <hi
                    rend="italic">and</hi> foreshortens, the <hi rend="italic">Tristia</hi>
                re-routes, the <hi rend="italic">Ex Ponto</hi> collates” (33)—and the effects of
                such approaches on texts and readers.</p>
            <p>Martelli devotes each of chapters 2–6 to Ovid’s revisions in connection with one of
                the works listed above. Chapter 2 observes that the <hi rend="italic">Amores</hi>
                (the work scholars usually date as the chronological first of Ovid’s enduring works)
                opens with a preface that describes the work as a revised (and shortened) version.
                Today’s readers have no access to a previous version—if one truly existed. Martelli,
                though, considers that even the <hi rend="italic">idea</hi> that the work is a
                revision influences ways of reading the text, including building admiration for the
                author (who can both create a longer work and do the difficult work of editing the
                work down). In addition, seeing the work as an abridged second edition promotes
                reader curiosity about what exists in the extended version. Ovid’s editorial choices
                and Martelli’s observations reveal rhetorical power in prefatory and other ancillary
                materials, which shape readers’ expectations and interpretations of the central
                text.</p>
            <p>Ancillary content, though, is not the only editorial material that wields
                hermeneutical influence, as evidenced in Martelli’s third chapter. There, she turns
                to considering editorial additions to the main text (as opposed to reductions). The
                    <hi rend="italic">Ars Amatoria</hi> is, she notes, “a text that appears to have
                some difficulty reaching or finding its ending” (68). The “original” poem is a
                two-book work, but Ovid added two addendums—the text known as <hi rend="italic">Ars
                    3</hi> and the <hi rend="italic">Remedia Amoris</hi>. Martelli argues that these
                “mobile” endings build narrative tension in this work devoted to sexual desire (the
                text is essentially instructions on seduction and resisting seduction) by weaving
                between desire and the death of desire.</p>
            <p>Chapter 3 discusses additions that extend a work’s ending, and chapter 4 demonstrates
                that texts that seem unfinished may actually be self-contained. Chapter 4 focuses on
                    <hi rend="italic">Fasti</hi>, a six-book poem built around the recently modified
                Roman calendar, yet glaring for its treatment of only the first six months. Common
                interpretation sees the truncated poem as unfinished, and this incompletion is
                usually attributed to Emperor Augustus’s banishing Ovid from Rome to Tomis in 8 CE
                for causes unknown. Martelli counters this interpretation, observing that since the
                poem shows indications of revision throughout with no attempts to produce additional
                content, we have ample reason to view the poem as complete. In doing so, we can
                recognize a significant function of the poem—Ovid’s challenge to the Roman calendar
                itself and the power structures that determine even public experiences of time.
                Although editors face pressures to produce works that appear complete according to
                genre expectations, those same editors may take note of the effects texts can create
                in readers by breaking those expectations. The <hi rend="italic">Fasti</hi> example
                can also serve to reinforce the opposite claim, given widely accepted
                interpretations that the poem <hi rend="italic">is</hi> incomplete. To expand
                possibilities, we can consider the <hi rend="italic">Fasti</hi> in connection with
                Martelli’s earlier examples—that is, allowing authors and editors to experiment with
                meaningful form, but providing at least some hints toward interpretation in
                ancillary materials such as prefaces or addenda.</p>
            <p>Chapter 5 analyzes <hi rend="italic">Tristia</hi>, which, Martelli argues, “brings to
                the fore Ovid’s role as editor, not just of this particular text, but also of his
                larger textual output and identity” (146). Each of the five books comprising the
                poem—written during Ovid’s exile—is presented as a stand-alone work, and the
                differing revisions lead to variations in the authorial vision among the books. Of
                particular interest to those who may be most familiar with Ovid in connection to his
                most famous work, the <hi rend="italic">Tristia</hi> overlaps with the epilogue of
                the <hi rend="italic">Metamorphoses</hi>, rewriting that epilogue multiple times,
                yet standing independent. This practice, Martelli writes, “breaks down the
                distinctions between” Ovid’s works, “as the revision of one work is made to overlap
                with the composition of another, and the different authorial identities that these
                two works produce are made to coexist within the ‘same’ textual space” (32).</p>
            <p>For editors working with bodies of independent works that overlap in
                content—repeating ideas or even passages—the intersection between Ovid’s <hi
                    rend="italic">Tristia</hi> and <hi rend="italic">Metamorphoses</hi> provides an
                example of how revising and modifying one work inescapably influences the meaning of
                others, challenging editors to read any revisions they make in a more varied context
                than a single volume or collection.</p>
            <p>The <hi rend="italic">Tristia</hi> also complicates Ovidian authorship while raising
                questions about authorial self-presentation and editorial transparency. This poem
                functions in many ways as a monument or monuments to prominent names (from Ennius,
                Lucretius, and Horace, to Homer, et al.). At the same time, it is a rare exception
                in Ovid’s own body of work because he leaves his name off the title pages, while
                instead incorporating himself into the text (making references, for example, to the
                image of his face on a ring and to an epitaph for his tombstone). “In exile,”
                Martelli writes, “Ovid empties his authorial name of its performative force, in the
                knowledge that that name now has a new referent” (165). As we near the end of
                Martelli’s volume, then, we see significant developments in the function of Ovid’s
                authorship. And although the point of Martelli’s project is considering Ovid’s
                self-editing, more traditional editors also face decisions about how much to expose
                or conceal their participation in the “final” text. Ovid’s example of how and why he
                alters his approach to transparency in the <hi rend="italic">Tristia</hi> can serve
                as an entry point for other editors in selecting their own approaches to this
                persistent challenge.</p>
            <p>Martelli next examines the <hi rend="italic">Epistulae ex Ponto</hi>, a collection of
                letters from Ovid to a series of readers. The evident editorializing and revising of
                this collection—despite Ovid’s claims to the contrary—show him crafting the audience
                with whom he wishes to participate, a strategy that all editors must consider when
                selecting textual interventions. He chooses, for instance, to address private
                individuals in domestic realms, rather than reaching out to a public audience, even
                while knowing that this private/public distinction was a fiction, since he edited
                the collection for publication. Ovid was attempting to secure immortality not
                through his literary fame but through the “continuing support of his friends in
                Rome” (224), seeking to extend his identity through the world outside the text.
                Whether editing standard volumes (i.e., intervening directly in texts prior to their
                publication as ostensibly cohesive single-authored works) or producing editions that
                note alterations and/or provide commentary, traditional textual editors also make
                their decisions based on audience—and not necessarily obvious audiences, but
                audiences they select through their own approaches.</p>
            <p>In all these chapters, Martelli grounds her arguments thoroughly in the texts
                themselves, pursuing close readings of her texts with attention to the features and
                functions of specific lines. In her epilogue, she returns to her broader inquiry
                into authorship, citing authorial revision as both “reinforc[ing] the identity of
                the author” and “mark[ing the] author’s disappearance” (230). She also considers the
                editorial moves Ovid makes in the above five works in the context of his other works
                (the <hi rend="italic">Metamorphoses</hi>, <hi rend="italic">Heroides</hi>, and <hi
                    rend="italic">Ibis</hi>).</p>
            <p>Taken as a whole, Martelli’s work in this volume marks a valuable contribution to
                classical studies while simultaneously furthering urgent conversations in the realms
                of editorial theory, studies in authorship and publishing, and textual studies. Work
                in these latter fields that draw on this book might return to consider differences
                in editorial practice when revising one’s own work versus the work of others; the
                shifting identity of any given author; the possibilities and limitations of
                representing multiple versions of a text in edited editions; how making editorial
                revision transparent to readers may influence reading interpretation and experience;
                how authors shape their own audiences; and how authors endure or disappear. Such
                queries, tied to Martelli’s thoughtful scholarship in these pages, hold potential
                for lively and transformative discussion in the decades to come.</p>
            <signed>
                <name>Heidi Nobles</name>
                <affiliation>Texas Christian University</affiliation>
            </signed>
        </body>
    </text>
</TEI>
