<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<?oxygen RNGSchema="http://www.scholarlyediting.org/scholarlyediting.rng" type="xml"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xml:lang="eng">
    <teiHeader>
        <fileDesc>
            <titleStmt>
                <title level="a" type="main">Recent Editions</title>
                <title level="a" type="sub">2016</title>
                <author key="Hickman, Ellen C.">Ellen C. Hickman</author>
            </titleStmt>
            <editionStmt>
                <edition>
                    <date>2016</date>
                </edition>
            </editionStmt>
            <publicationStmt>
                <idno type="file">review.recenteditions2016</idno>
                <authority>Scholary Editing: The Annual of the Association for Documentary
                    Editing</authority>
                <address>
 <addrLine>http://www.scholarlyediting.org</addrLine>
</address>
                <publisher>Association for Documentary Editing</publisher>
                <publisher>University of Nebraska&#8211;Lincoln</publisher>
                <distributor>
                    <name>Center for Digital Research in the Humanities</name>
                    <address>
<addrLine>319 Love Library</addrLine>
<addrLine>University of Nebraska&#8211;Lincoln</addrLine>
<addrLine>Lincoln, NE 68588-4100</addrLine>
<addrLine>http://cdrh.unl.edu</addrLine>
 </address>
                </distributor>
                <date>2016</date>
                <availability>
                    <p>Scholary Editing: The Annual of the Association for Documentary Editing is
                        freely distributed by the Association for Documentary Editing and the Center
                        for Digital Research in the Humanities at the University of Nebraska-Lincoln
                        and licensed under a Creative Commons Attribution-NonCommercial-ShareAlike
                        3.0 Unported License</p>
                </availability>
            </publicationStmt>
            <seriesStmt>
                <title level="j">Scholarly Editing: The Annual of the Association for Documentary
                    Editing</title>
                <respStmt>
                    <resp>editor</resp>
                    <name xml:id="ag" key="Gailey, Amanda A.">Amanda Gailey</name>
                </respStmt>
                <respStmt>
                    <resp>editor</resp>
                    <name xml:id="awj" key="Jewell, Andrew W.">Andrew Jewell</name>
                </respStmt>
                <idno type="vol">37</idno>
                <idno type="ISSN">2167-1257</idno>
            </seriesStmt>
            <sourceDesc>
                <bibl>
                    <note>Born digital.</note>
                </bibl>
            </sourceDesc>
        </fileDesc>
        <revisionDesc>
            <change when="2016-03-21"><name xml:id="lkw" key="Kirilloff, Gabi">Gabi Kirilloff</name>
                markup in TEI XML</change>
        </revisionDesc>
    </teiHeader>
    <text>

        <front>
            <head type="main">Recent Editions</head>

            <byline>Compiled by Ellen C. Hickman</byline>
        </front>
        <body>
            <p>This annual bibliography of documentary editions recently published in the fields of
                American and British history, literature, and culture is generally restricted to
                scholarly first editions of English-language works.</p>
            <list type="simple">
                <item><p>ADAMS FAMILY. <hi rend="italic">Adams Family Correspondence, Volume 12:
                            March 1797 to April 1798.</hi> Edited by Sara Martin, C. James Taylor,
                        Neal E. Millikan, Amanda A. Mathews, Hobson Woodward, Sara B. Sikes, Gregg
                        L. Lint, and Sara Georgini. Harvard University Press. 2015. 688 pp. $95.
                        ISBN: 9780674504660. This volume opens with John Adams’s inauguration and
                        closes just after details of the XYZ affair are made public in America.
                        Abigail’s letters demonstrate her role as an unofficial member of the
                        administration. John Quincy and Thomas Boylston Adams offer insights into
                        political turmoil in France and court life in Berlin following the
                        coronation of Frederick William III.</p></item>
                <item><p>AMERICAN INDIANS. <hi rend="italic">A Call for Reform: The Southern
                            California Indian Writings of Helen Hunt Jackson.</hi> Edited by Valerie
                        Sherer Mathes and Phil Brigandi. University of Oklahoma Press. 2015. 232 pp.
                        $29.95. ISBN: 9780806143637. Journalist, novelist, and scholar Helen Hunt
                        Jackson (1830–85) remains one of the most influential and popular writers on
                        the struggles of American Indians. This volume collects for the first time
                        seven of her most important articles, which served as the basis for
                        Jackson’s 1884 novel, <hi rend="italic">Ramona</hi>. Includes an
                        introduction and annotation</p></item>
                <item><p>AMERICAN INDIANS. <hi rend="italic">Through Indian Sign Language: The Fort
                            Sill Ledgers of Hugh Lenox Scott and Iseeo, 1889–1897.</hi> Edited by
                        William C. Meadows. University of Oklahoma Press. 2015. 520 pp. $55. ISBN:
                        9780806147277. Hugh Lenox Scott, who would one day serve as chief of staff
                        of the US Army, spent a portion of his early career at Fort Sill in Indian
                        and, later, Oklahoma Territory. There he commanded an all-Indian cavalry
                        unit. From members of this unit, in particular a Kiowa soldier named Iseeo,
                        Scott collected three volumes of information on American Indian life and
                        culture—a body of ethnographic material conveyed through Plains Indian Sign
                        Language and recorded in handwritten English. The Scott ledgers contain an
                        array of historical, linguistic, and ethnographic data—a wealth of
                        primary-source material on Southern Plains Indian people.</p></item>
                <item><p>AMERICAN WEST. <hi rend="italic">Before Custer: Surveying the Yellowstone,
                            1872.</hi> Edited by M. John Lubetkin. Arthur H. Clark Company. 2015.
                        328 pp. $34.95. ISBN: 9780870624315. The Northern Pacific Railroad set out
                        in 1872 to survey the Yellowstone Valley. An emissary from the Lakota chief
                        Sitting Bull had warned two surveying expeditions not to enter the valley.
                        Much to the surprised dismay of US Army strategists and railroad executives,
                        the Indians repeatedly harassed army forces of nearly a thousand men. These
                        previously unpublished documents provide firsthand accounts of the survey’s
                        three-month struggle and the parallel story of the Panic of 1873, which
                        developed out of the Northern Pacific’s thwarted expansion.</p></item>
                <item><p>AMERICAN WEST. <hi rend="italic">The Great Medicine Road, Part 2:
                            Narratives of the Oregon, California, and Mormon Trails, 1849.</hi>
                        Edited by Michael L. Tate. Arthur H. Clark Company. 2015. 320 pp. $39.95.
                        ISBN: 9780870624377. This second installment of a projected four-part
                        collection includes memoirs and diaries from seven travelers who journeyed
                        west after the discovery of gold in California.</p></item>
                <item><p>ART. <hi rend="italic">My Dear BB: The Letters of Bernard Berenson and
                            Kenneth Clark, 1925–1959.</hi> Edited by Robert Cumming. Yale University
                        Press. 2015. 584 pp. $45. ISBN: 9780300207378. This book makes available,
                        for the first time, the complete correspondence between two of the most
                        influential figures in the twentieth-century art world, and gives a new and
                        unique insight into their lives and motivations. The letters are arranged
                        into ten chronological sections, each accompanied by biographical details
                        and providing the context for the events and personalities referred
                    to.</p></item>
                <item><p>AUBREY, JOHN. <hi rend="italic">John Aubrey: Brief Lives with an Apparatus
                            for the Lives of our English Mathematical Writers.</hi> Edited by Kate
                        Bennett. Oxford University Press. 2015. 2 vols. 1,897 pp. $399. ISBN:
                        9780199689538. This is the first scholarly edition of Aubrey’s <hi
                            rend="italic">Brief Lives</hi> since 1898, the first to include the
                        complete text of the three <hi rend="italic">Brief Lives</hi> manuscripts
                        (including censored and deleted material, title pages, antiquarian notes,
                        and the indexes), and the first to provide a full general and critical
                        introduction and comprehensive commentary. The work is here presented as an
                        antiquarian and collaborative text, containing the autograph papers of
                        biographical subjects and the annotations of those among whom the
                        manuscripts circulated.</p></item>
                <item><p>AUDEN, W. H. <hi rend="italic">The Complete Works of W. H. Auden: Prose,
                            Volume V, 1963–1968.</hi> Edited by Edward Mendelson. Princeton
                        University Press. 2015. 604 pp. $65. ISBN: 9780691151717. <hi rend="italic"
                            >Prose, Volume VI, 1969–1973.</hi> 2015. 856 pp. $65. ISBN:
                        9780691164588. Volume 5 contains Auden’s most personally revealing essays,
                        the ones in which he wrote for the first time about the full history of his
                        family life, his sexuality, and the development of his moral and religious
                        beliefs. Includes many unpublished speeches and lectures. Volume 6 contains
                        the full text of the only book that Auden regarded as an autobiography, <hi
                            rend="italic">A Certain World</hi>. It also features late essays and
                        reviews.</p></item>
                <item><p>BENTHAM, JEREMY. <hi rend="italic">The Collected Works of Jeremy Bentham:
                            The Book of Fallacies.</hi> Edited by Philip Schofield. Oxford
                        University Press. 2015. 640 pp. $150. ISBN: 9780198719816. The present
                        edition of <hi rend="italic">The Book of Fallacies</hi> is the first that
                        follows Bentham’s own structure for the work, and includes a great deal of
                        material, both in terms of the fallacies themselves and the illustrative
                        matter, that previous versions of the work have omitted.</p></item>
                <item><p>BERLIN, ISAIAH. <hi rend="italic">Affirming: Letters, 1975–1997.</hi>
                        Edited by Henry Hardy and Mark Pottle. Random House UK. 2015. 704 pp. $75.
                        ISBN: 9781784740085. In this final volume, Berlin is as prolific a
                        correspondent as ever, but the publication of new essay collections produces
                        a striking change in tone, as readers seek clarification of his ideas. He
                        dwells on pluralism of values and cultures, political liberalism, the
                        defense of democracy, and the challenge posed by fundamentalism. But there
                        is also a generous leavening of gossip to friends, reflections on music, the
                        arts, and artists, as well as a fascination with the variety of
                        humankind.</p></item>
                <item><p>BERNARD, FRANCIS. <hi rend="italic">The Papers of Francis Bernard, Governor
                            of Colonial Massachusetts, 1760–69. Volume 4: 1768.</hi> Edited by Colin
                        Nicolson. University of Virginia Press. 2015. 600 pp. $49.50. ISBN:
                        9780985254346. Governor Francis Bernard’s historical reputation rests on his
                        role in pushing the American colonists toward revolution. In 1768 the
                        colonists and their governor vied to control information flowing to London.
                        But it was Bernard who triumphed in the war of information, convincing the
                        British government to send British troops to Boston to avert a possible
                        insurrection and support the civil government.</p></item>
                <item><p>BERNARD, FRANCIS. <hi rend="italic">The Papers of Francis Bernard, Governor
                            of Colonial Massachusetts, 1760–69. Volume 5: 1768–69.</hi> Edited by
                        Colin Nicolson. University of Virginia Press. 2015. 500 pp. $49.50. ISBN:
                        9780985254353. British Regulars marched into Boston at midday on Saturday,
                        October 1, 1768; the troops were there to deter rioters, cow radicals, and
                        support the civil government. Despite rumors to the contrary, there was no
                        revolt to crush. No one expected war in 1769, but it was no longer
                        unthinkable to Bostonians living alongside British soldiers or to British
                        politicians discussing the allegedly treasonable activities of Bostonians.
                        Their differences hinged on what Bernard had been telling the British
                        government. This fifth volume examines the evidence and debates as they
                        unfolded in Boston and London.</p></item>
                <item><p>BOYLE, KAY. <hi rend="italic">Kay Boyle: A Twentieth-Century Life in
                            Letters.</hi> Edited by Sandra Spanier. University of Illinois Press.
                        2015. 848 pp. $40. ISBN: 9780252039317. One of the Lost Generation
                        modernists who gathered in 1920s Paris, Boyle published more than forty
                        books, including fifteen novels, eleven collections of short fiction, eight
                        volumes of poetry, three children’s books, and various essays and
                        translations. Yet her achievements can be even better appreciated through
                        the letters she wrote between 1919 and 1992 to the literary and cultural
                        titans of her time.</p></item>
                <item><p>BRAGG, ALICE AND SIR LAWRENCE. Crystal Clear: The Autobiographies of Sir
                        Lawrence and Lady Bragg. Edited by A. M. Glazer and Patience Thomson. Oxford
                        University Press. 2015. 448 pp. $59.95. ISBN: 9780198744306. Previously
                        unpublished autobiographies of Alice Bragg and her husband, William Lawrence
                        Bragg, who along with his father developed a whole new branch of science:
                        X-ray crystallography. Their autobiographies complement each other to give a
                        rounded picture of the real personalities behind their public
                        appearance.</p></item>
                <item><p>BURNEY, FRANCES. <hi rend="italic">The Additional Journals and Letters of
                            Frances Burney, Volume I: 1784–1786.</hi> Edited by Stewart Cooke.
                        Oxford University Press. 2015. 480 pp. $200. ISBN: 9780199658114. This is
                        the first of two volumes of <hi rend="italic">The Additional Letters and
                            Journals of Frances Burney</hi>, which will present materials not
                        included in existing series of Burney materials. Written at the height of
                        Burney’s fame as a novelist, the journals and letters included in this
                        volume detail the loss of her friendship with Hester Thrale upon the
                        latter’s marriage, and the growth of her friendships with William and
                        Frederica Lock and Mary Delany. Also includes Burney’s unique record of the
                        final days of Samuel Johnson’s life and an appreciation of his life and
                        work.</p></item>
                <item><p>CALIFORNIA. <hi rend="italic">The Army Surveys of Gold Rush California:
                            Reports of Topographical Engineers, 1849–1851.</hi> Edited by Gary
                        Clayton Anderson and Laura Lee Anderson. Arthur C. Clark Company. 2015. 256
                        pp. $34.95. ISBN: 9780870624308. As the army’s topographical engineer in
                        California from 1849 to 1851, George Horatio Derby wrote detailed reports on
                        the region, its people, its resources, and its geography. Derby’s reports
                        and journals appear here alongside those of other surveyors; these documents
                        offer views of the environment, natural resources, geography, and early
                        settlement, as well as the effects of disease on Native and white
                        populations.</p></item>
                <item><p>CANADA. <hi rend="italic">The Writings of David Thompson, Volume 2: The
                            Travels, 1848 Version, and Associated Texts.</hi> Edited by William E.
                        Moreau. McGill-Queen’s University Press. 2015. 436 pp. $44.95. ISBN:
                        9780773545519. The second in a planned three volumes of Thompson’s writings,
                        this edition completes the Canadian surveyor and fur trader’s
                        autobiographical narrative. In the 1848 <hi rend="italic">Travels</hi>,
                        Thompson describes his most enduring historical legacy—the extension of the
                        fur trade across the Continental Divide between 1807 and 1812. Like its
                        companion <hi rend="italic">Volume 1</hi>, this work presents an entirely
                        new transcription of Thompson’s manuscript and includes an introductory
                        essay and annotation.</p></item>
                <item><p>CARROLL, LEWIS. <hi rend="italic">The Pamphlets of Lewis Carroll, Volume 5:
                            Games, Puzzles, and Related Pieces.</hi> Edited by Christopher Morgan.
                        University of Virginia Press. 2015. 394 pp. $75. ISBN: 9780930326029.
                        Charles Lutwidge Dodgson, “Lewis Carroll,” was not only the author of the
                        beloved <hi rend="italic">Alice</hi> tales but an inveterate and talented
                        creator of puzzles and games in both the recreational mathematics and
                        wordplay fields. Collected together for the first time in this book, his
                        charming and humorous creations are no longer hidden in obscure Victorian
                        magazines, rare antiquarian books, and sporadic, incomplete
                    collections.</p></item>
                <item><p>CIVIL WAR. <hi rend="italic">A Rebel War Clerk’s Diary at the Confederate
                            States Capital, Volume 1: April 1861–July 1863.</hi> Edited by James I.
                        Robertson Jr. University Press of Kansas. 2015. 480 pp. $45. ISBN:
                        9780700621231. <hi rend="italic">Volume 2: August 1863–April 1865.</hi>
                        2015. 608 pp. $50. ISBN: 9780700621248. The wartime diary of John Beauchamp
                        Jones, clerk in the War Department of the Confederacy, was first published
                        in 1866. This is the first republishing to include an editorial introduction
                        and notes. The day-by-day uninterrupted four-year chronicle includes unique
                        materials on the Civil War drawn from Jones’s access to confidential files,
                        command-level conversations, official correspondence, revelations, rumors,
                        statistics, weather reports, and personal opinion in the Confederate War
                        Department.</p></item>
                <item><p>CIVIL WAR. <hi rend="italic">A Yankee Scholar in Coastal South Carolina:
                            William Francis Allen’s Civil War Journals.</hi> Edited by James Robert
                        Hester. University of South Carolina Press. 2015. 344 pp. $49.95. ISBN:
                        9781611174960. Allen served from late 1863 through mid-1864 as a member of
                        the “Gideonite band” of businessmen, missionaries, and teachers who migrated
                        to the South Carolina Sea Islands as part of the Port Royal Experiment.
                        After the war, from April through July 1865, he served as assistant
                        superintendent of schools in Charleston. In his journals from this time, he
                        recorded events and impressions of hundreds of people, especially ex-slaves,
                        fellow Gideonites, Union soldiers and officials, and
                    ex-Confederates.</p></item>
                <item><p>COBDEN, RICHARD. <hi rend="italic">The Letters of Richard Cobden, Volume
                            IV: 1860–1865.</hi> Edited by Anthony Howe and Simon Morgan. Oxford
                        University Press. 2015. 552 pp. $225. ISBN: 9780199211982. Fourth and final
                        volume of this critical edition of the letters of the prominent
                        nineteenth-century British politician. This volume deals with Cobden’s
                        search for a permanent political legacy, both at home and abroad, including
                        his success in negotiating the Anglo-French Commercial Treaty of 1860, his
                        involvement in smoothing Anglo-American relations at the time, and his work
                        toward the enfranchisement of the working classes.</p></item>
                <item><p>CONSTITUTION, UNITED STATES. <hi rend="italic">The Documentary History of
                            the Ratification of the Constitution. Volume 11, Ratification of the
                            Constitution by the States: Maryland, No. 1.</hi> Edited by John P.
                        Kaminski, Charles H. Schoenleber, Gaspare J. Saladino, Jonathan M. Reid,
                        Timothy D. Moore, Johanna E. Lannér-Cusin, Margaret R. Flamingo, and David
                        P. Fields. Wisconsin Historical Society Press. 2015. 512 pp. $95. ISBN:
                        9780870206856. <hi rend="italic">Volume 12, Ratification of the Constitution
                            by the States: Maryland, No. 2.</hi> Wisconsin Historical Society Press.
                        2015. 592 pp. $95. ISBN: 9780870206863. These two volumes document
                        Maryland’s public and private debates about the Constitution.</p></item>
                <item><p>DARWIN, CHARLES. <hi rend="italic">The Correspondence of Charles Darwin,
                            Volume 22: 1874.</hi> Edited by Frederick Burkhardt and James A. Secord.
                        Cambridge University Press. 2015. 904 pp. $152. ISBN: 9781107088726. Volume
                        22 of the definitive edition of Darwin’s correspondence includes letters
                        from 1874, the year in which he completed his research on insectivorous
                        plants and published second editions of <hi rend="italic">Descent of
                            Man</hi> and <hi rend="italic">Coral Reefs</hi>. The year also saw an
                        acrimonious dispute between Darwin and St. George Jackson Mivart as a result
                        of an anonymous review the latter had written in which he criticized
                        Darwin’s son George.</p></item>
                <item><p>DAVIS, JEFFERSON. <hi rend="italic">The Papers of Jefferson Davis, Volume
                            14: 1880 to 1889.</hi> Edited by Lynda Lasswell Crist and Suzanne Scott
                        Gibbs. Louisiana State University Press. 2015. 688 pp. $150. ISBN:
                        9780807159095. The final volume of <hi rend="italic">The Papers of Jefferson
                            Davis</hi> follows the former president of the Confederacy through the
                        completion of his two monumental works on the history of the Confederate
                        States of America. In the first, <hi rend="italic">The Rise and Fall of the
                            Confederate Government</hi> (1881), Davis sought to recast the
                        Confederacy as a just and moral nation that was constitutionally correct in
                        standing up for its rights. Himself the subject of heated debates about why
                        the Confederacy lost, Davis also used the book to castigate Confederate
                        government and military officials who he believed had failed the cause.
                        Later, <hi rend="italic">A Short History of the Confederate States</hi>
                        (1890) attempted to burnish the image of the former Confederacy and to
                        refute accusations of intentional mistreatment of Union
                    prisoners.</p></item>
                <item><p>DICKINSON, EMILY. <hi rend="italic">Dickinson in Her Own Times: A
                            Biographical Chronicle of Her Life, Drawn from Recollections,
                            Interviews, and Memoirs by Family, Friends, and Associates.</hi> Edited
                        by Jane Donahue Eberwein, Stephanie Farrar, and Christanne Miller.
                        University of Iowa Press. 2015. 214 pp. $55. ISBN: 9781609383916. Even
                        before the first books of her poems were published in the 1890s, friends,
                        neighbors, and even apparently strangers knew Emily Dickinson was a writer
                        of remarkable verses. Featuring both well-known documents and material
                        printed or collected here for the first time, this book offers a broad range
                        of writings that convey impressions of Dickinson in her own time and for the
                        first decades following the publication of her poems.</p></item>
                <item><p>DOYLE, RICHARD. <hi rend="italic">The Illustrated Letters of Richard Doyle
                            to His Father, 1842–1843.</hi> Edited by Grant F. Scott. Ohio University
                        Press. 2015. 440 pp. $79.95. ISBN: 9780821421857. Before he joined the staff
                        of <hi rend="italic">Punch</hi> and designed its iconic front cover,
                        illustrator Richard “Dicky” Doyle was a young man whose father (political
                        caricaturist John Doyle) charged him with sending a weekly letter, even
                        though they lived under the same roof. This volume collects the fifty-three
                        illustrated missives in their entirety for the first time. The sketches
                        offer a fresh perspective on major social and cultural events of London
                        during the early 1840s by a keen observer not yet twenty years
                    old.</p></item>
                <item><p>EDISON, THOMAS A. <hi rend="italic">The Papers of Thomas A. Edison, Volume
                            8: New Beginnings, January 1885–December 1887.</hi> Edited by Paul B.
                        Israel, Louis Carlat, Theresa M. Collins, Alexandra R. Rimer, and Daniel J.
                        Weeks. Johns Hopkins University Press. 2015. 1,032 pp. $115. ISBN:
                        9781421417493. At this time Edison’s inventive activities took off in new
                        directions, including practical projects (such as wireless and high-capacity
                        telegraph systems) and futuristic ones (exploring forms of electromagnetic
                        energy and the convertibility of one to another). Inside two years, he would
                        travel widely, remarry, leave New York City for a suburban setting, and
                        construct a winter laboratory and second home in Florida.</p></item>
                <item><p>EINSTEIN, ALBERT. <hi rend="italic">The Collected Papers of Albert
                            Einstein, Volume 14: The Berlin Years: Writings and Correspondence,
                            April 1923–May 1925.</hi> Edited by Diana Kormos Buchwald, József Illy,
                        Ze’ev Rosenkranz, Tilman Sauer, and Osik Moses. Princeton University Press.
                        2015. 1,208 pp. $140. ISBN: 9780691164106. The more than one thousand
                        letters and several dozen writings included in this volume cover the years
                        immediately before the final formulation of new quantum mechanics. The
                        discovery of the Compton effect in 1923 vindicates Einstein’s light quantum
                        hypothesis. Einstein attempts to reformulate a unified theory of the
                        gravitational and electromagnetic fields. In early November 1923, Einstein
                        flees overnight to the Netherlands in the wake of threats on his life and
                        anti-Semitic rioting in Berlin. In 1925 he undertakes a seven-week tour of
                        Argentina, Uruguay, and Brazil and delivers lectures, meets with heads of
                        state, and visits major institutions. During this period Einstein has a
                        falling out with family members over how to invest part of the Nobel Prize
                        money.</p></item>
                <item><p>ELIOT, T. S. <hi rend="italic">The Letters of T. S. Eliot, Volume 5:
                            1930–1931.</hi> Edited by Valerie Eliot and John Haffenden. Yale
                        University Press. 2015. 928 pp. $85. ISBN: 9780300211795. During this period
                        the acclaimed American-born writer earnestly embraced his newly avowed
                        Anglo-Catholic faith, a decision that earned him the antagonism of friends
                        like Virginia Woolf and Herbert Read and caused further estrangement with
                        his wife, Vivien. In 1930 Eliot composed the poems <hi rend="italic"
                            >Ash-Wednesday</hi> and <hi rend="italic">Marina</hi> and published <hi
                            rend="italic">Coriolan</hi> the following year. He also interacted with
                        important literary figures as director of the British publishing house Faber
                        and Faber and editor of <hi rend="italic">The Criterion.</hi></p></item>
                <item><p>ENGLAND. <hi rend="italic">The Building Accounts of the Savoy Hospital,
                            London, 1512–1520.</hi> Edited by Charlotte A. Stanford. Boydell and
                        Brewer. 2015. 490 pp. $99. ISBN: 9781783270668. Founded by Henry VII, the
                        Savoy hospital was a landmark of early Tudor London. Published for the first
                        time here, the building-accounts record provides detailed evidence of the
                        structure, as well as of the hundreds of craftsmen and laborers who toiled
                        to complete it. Includes an introduction, notes, and a glossary of building
                        terms.</p></item>
                <item><p>GIROUX, ROBERT. <hi rend="italic">The Letters of Robert Giroux and Thomas
                            Merton.</hi> Edited by Patrick Samway. University of Notre Dame Press.
                        2015. 408 pp. $29. ISBN: 9780268017866. From the time they first met as
                        undergraduates at Columbia College in New York in the mid-1930s, the noted
                        editor Robert Giroux and the Trappist monk and writer Thomas Merton became
                        friends. These letters capture their personal and professional relationship,
                        extending from the time of the 1948 publication of Merton’s <hi
                            rend="italic">The Seven Storey Mountain</hi> until a few months before
                        Merton’s death in 1968. Giroux not only edited twenty-six of Merton’s books
                        but served as an adviser to Merton as he dealt with unexpected problems with
                        his religious superiors.</p></item>
                <item><p>GORE-BOOTH, EVA. <hi rend="italic">The Political Writings of Eva
                            Gore-Booth.</hi> Edited by Sonja Tiernan. Oxford University Press. 2015.
                        244 pp. $110. ISBN: 9780719088742. Gore-Booth was an important Irish
                        political activist. This is the first time her writings have been published
                        together. The volume includes an array of letters, political pamphlets,
                        newspaper articles, and poetry relating to key aspects of Irish and British
                        events of the early twentieth century.</p></item>
                <item><p>HEMINGWAY, ERNEST. <hi rend="italic">The Letters of Ernest Hemingway,
                            Volume 3: 1926–1929.</hi> Edited by Rena Sanderson, Sandra Spanier, and
                        Robert W. Trogdon. Cambridge University Press. 2015. 731 pp. $45. ISBN:
                        9780521897358. Volume 3 includes many previously unpublished letters from a
                        period when Hemingway emerges from the literary Left Bank of Paris and moves
                        into the American mainstream. In this period he publishes <hi rend="italic"
                            >Torrents of Spring</hi> and <hi rend="italic">The Sun Also Rises</hi>,
                        and completes <hi rend="italic">A Farewell to Arms</hi>. These letters
                        reflect landmark events in his personal life, including the dissolution of
                        his first marriage, his remarriage, the birth of his second son, and the
                        suicide of his father.</p></item>
                <item><p>HOPKINS, GERARD MANLEY. <hi rend="italic">The Collected Works of Gerard
                            Manley Hopkins, Volume 3: Diaries, Journals, and Notebooks.</hi> Edited
                        by Lesley Higgins. Oxford University Press. 2015. 480 pp. $150. ISBN:
                        9780199534005. Entries extend from September 1863, during Hopkins’s second
                        term at Oxford, until February 1875, while studying theology as a Jesuit in
                        Wales, and from February 1884 until July 1885, while Hopkins was living in
                        Dublin as a classics professor at University College and fellow of the Royal
                        University of Ireland.</p></item>
                <item><p>HUGHES, LANGSTON. <hi rend="italic">Selected Letters of Langston
                            Hughes.</hi> Edited by Arnold Rampersad and David Roessel. Knopf. 2015.
                        480 pp. $35. ISBN: 9780375413797. This is the first comprehensive selection
                        from the correspondence of Langston Hughes. Arranged by decade and linked by
                        expert commentary, the volume guides us through Hughes’s journey in all its
                        aspects: personal, political, practical, and literary. His letters range
                        from those written to family members, friends, fellow artists, critics, and
                        readers.</p></item>
                <item><p>JAMES, HENRY. <hi rend="italic">The Complete Letters of Henry James,
                            1878–1880: Volume 2.</hi> Edited by Pierre A. Walker and Greg W.
                        Zacharias. University of Nebraska Press. 2015. 296 pp. $95. ISBN:
                        9780803269859. This volume documents the full establishment of James as a
                        professional writer and critic on both sides of the Atlantic, as he
                        publishes the novel <hi rend="italic">Confidence</hi> and the literary
                        biography <hi rend="italic">Hawthorne</hi> and begins work on <hi
                            rend="italic">Washington Square</hi> and <hi rend="italic">The Portrait
                            of a Lady</hi>. James also visits Paris, Florence, Rome, and Naples,
                        begins his friendship with Constance Fenimore Woolson, and deepens his
                        attachment to London and to his acquaintances there.</p></item>
                <item><p>JAY, JOHN. <hi rend="italic">The Selected Papers of John Jay, Volume 4:
                            1785–1788.</hi> Edited by Elizabeth M. Nuxoll. University of Virginia
                        Press. 2015. 872 pp. $95. ISBN: 9780813936369. Volume 4 opens in January
                        1785 as Jay assumes office as secretary for foreign affairs and explores his
                        actions in this role, including his efforts to implement the peace treaty
                        with Great Britain, facilitate American trade, and renegotiate an intrusive
                        consular treaty with France. It documents his promotion of constitutional
                        change as the weaknesses of the Confederation thwart diplomacy and his
                        written defenses of the proposed Constitution. The volume closes as Jay
                        takes a leave of absence from office to support ratification of the
                        Constitution as delegate to the New York ratifying convention.</p></item>
                <item><p>JEFFERS, ROBINSON. <hi rend="italic">The Collected Letters of Robinson
                            Jeffers, with Selected Letters of Una Jeffers: Volume 3, 1940–1962.</hi>
                        Edited by James Karman. Stanford University Press. 2015. 1,024 pp. $95.
                        ISBN: 9780804794671. This third and final volume of Jeffers’s correspondence
                        spans the mid-twentieth century. In these decades Jeffers published four
                        important books, experienced the rewards of being a successful dramatist,
                        and endured the loss of his wife, Una.</p></item>
                <item><p>JEFFERSON, THOMAS. <hi rend="italic">The Papers of Thomas Jefferson, Volume
                            41: 11 July to 15 November 1803.</hi> Edited by Barbara B. Oberg, James
                        P. McClure, Elaine Weber Pascu, Tom Downey, Martha J. King, and W. Bland
                        Whitley. Princeton University Press. 2015. 856 pp. $125. ISBN:
                        9780691164205. The Louisiana Purchase dominates the months covered in this
                        volume. The French government’s offer to transfer the Louisiana Territory to
                        the United States brings Jefferson enthusiastic congratulations, but the
                        reality of getting the agreement with France approved and implemented raises
                        many weighty questions. With the widening of the country’s borders,
                        Jefferson’s project to send an exploratory party westward seems even
                        timelier.</p></item>
                <item><p>JEFFERSON, THOMAS. <hi rend="italic">The Papers of Thomas Jefferson,
                            Retirement Series, Volume 11: 19 January to 31 August 1817.</hi> Edited
                        by J. Jefferson Looney, Robert F. Haggard, Julie L. Lautenschlager, Ellen C.
                        Hickman, and Andrea R. Gray. Princeton University Press. 2015. 792 pp. $125.
                        ISBN: 9780691164113. During this time Jefferson devotes much time and energy
                        to founding Central College, the predecessor of the University of Virginia,
                        and begins the process of raising funds and purchasing land. Jefferson also
                        prepares a legal brief for his chancery suit against the directors of the
                        Rivanna Company. After years of disagreements and failed negotiations, he
                        composes and revises a lengthy legal statement of his claim to the property
                        in dispute.</p></item>
                <item><p>JENNINGS, SIR IVOR. <hi rend="italic">Constitution-Maker: Selected Writings
                            of Sir Ivor Jennings.</hi> Edited by H. Kumarasingham. Cambridge
                        University Press. 2015. 306 pp. $80. ISBN: 9781107091115. Sir Ivor Jennings
                        (1903–65), Downing Professor of Law at the University of Cambridge, was one
                        of the twentieth century’s most famous and significant constitutional
                        scholars. Beyond his prestigious roles in Britain, Jennings was also
                        influential internationally as an advisor on constitutional questions during
                        the 1950s and 1960s. This volume brings together unpublished letters,
                        memoranda, diaries, and confidential evaluations of constitutional issues,
                        political elites, and critical events in Ceylon, Ethiopia, India, Malta,
                        Malaysia, Nepal, New Zealand, Pakistan, Rhodesia, Singapore, South Africa,
                        and Sudan.</p></item>
                <item><p>JONSON, BEN. <hi rend="italic">Ben Jonson’s Walk to Scotland: An Annotated
                            Edition of the ‘Foot Voyage.’</hi> Edited by James Loxley, Anna
                        Groundwater, and Julie Sanders. Cambridge University Press. 2014. 256 pp.
                        $99. ISBN: 9781107003330. At the heart of this book is a previously
                        unpublished account of Ben Jonson’s celebrated walk from London to Edinburgh
                        in the summer of 1618. This unique firsthand narrative provides an insight
                        into where Jonson went, whom he met, and what he did on the way. Includes
                        annotation and a series of contextual essays on topics including evidence of
                        provenance and authorship.</p></item>
                <item><p>MADISON, JAMES. <hi rend="italic">The Papers of James Madison, Presidential
                            Series, Volume 8: July 1814–18 February 1815.</hi> Edited by Angela
                        Kreider, J. C. A. Stagg, Anne Mandeville Colony, Katharine E. Harbury, and
                        Mary Parke Johnson. University of Virginia Press. 2015. 760 pp. $85. ISBN:
                        9780813936949. Volume 8 of the <hi rend="italic">Presidential Series</hi>
                        covers the final months of the War of 1812, as Madison awaited the outcome
                        of peace negotiations at Ghent while defending the country against British
                        invasion, warding off government bankruptcy, and preparing to meet armed
                        resistance in New England. The volume closes with Madison receiving a copy
                        of the Treaty of Ghent on February 14, 1815.</p></item>
                <item><p>MERTON, THOMAS. <hi rend="italic">See</hi> GIROUX, ROBERT.</p></item>
                <item><p>METAPHYSICAL SOCIETY. <hi rend="italic">The Papers of the Metaphysical
                            Society, 1869–1880: A Critical Edition.</hi> Edited by Catherine
                        Marshall, Bernard Lightman, and Richard England. Oxford University Press.
                        2015. 3 vols. 1,488 pp. $550. ISBN: 9780199643035. The Metaphysical Society
                        was founded in 1869 as a private club which gathered together a latter-day
                        clerisy. Building on the tradition of the Cambridge Apostles, they elected
                        talented members from across the Victorian intellectual spectrum: bishops, a
                        cardinal, philosophers, men of science, literary figures, and politicians.
                        The papers they produced are key primary sources that shed new light on the
                        ideas of their authors on the burning subjects of the day.</p></item>
                <item><p>MILTON, JOHN. <hi rend="italic">The Complete Works of John Milton, Volume
                            VI: Vernacular Regicide and Republican Writings.</hi> Edited by N. H.
                        Keeble and Nicholas McDowell. Oxford University Press. 2014. 832 pp. $170.
                        ISBN: 9780199218059. Fourth of a projected eleven-volume edition, this
                        volume brings together Milton’s English writing in prose on the political
                        issues that exercised him throughout his life: civil and religious liberty,
                        republicanism and the constitution of a free commonwealth, the rights and
                        duties of citizens, resistance of tyranny and the role of military force in
                        securing national stability.</p></item>
                <item><p>NEWMAN, JOHN HENRY. <hi rend="italic">John Henry Newman: A Portrait in
                            Letters.</hi> Edited by Roderick Strange. Oxford University Press. 2015.
                        608 pp. $49.50. ISBN: 9780199604142. John Henry Newman was one of the most
                        eminent of Victorians and an intellectual pioneer for an age of doubt and
                        unsettlement. His teaching transformed the Victorian-era Church of England,
                        yet many still want to know more of Newman’s personal life. Newman’s printed
                        correspondence runs to thirty-two volumes, and this single volume offers a
                        way through the maze, with letters that illustrate both the well-known and
                        less familiar aspects of Newman’s personality.</p></item>
                <item><p>OLMSTED, FREDERICK LAW. <hi rend="italic">Frederick Law Olmsted: Plans and
                            Views of Public Parks.</hi> Edited by Charles E. Beveridge, Lauren
                        Meier, and Irene Mills. Johns Hopkins University Press. 2015. 448 pp.
                        $74.95. ISBN: 9781421410869. Illustrated with over 470 images, this book
                        reveals Olmsted’s design concepts for more than seventy public park projects
                        through a rich collection of sketches, studies, lithographs, paintings,
                        historical photographs, and comprehensive descriptions.</p></item>
                <item><p>OLMSTED, FREDERICK LAW. <hi rend="italic">The Papers of Frederick Law
                            Olmsted, Volume 9: The Last Great Projects, 1890–1895.</hi> Edited by
                        David Schuyler, Gregory Kaliss, and Jeffrey Schlossberg. Johns Hopkins
                        University Press. 2015. 1,104 pp. $110. ISBN: 9781421416038. This final
                        volume covers the last six years of Olmsted’s professional career. In this
                        period he was involved in a number of major ongoing projects, including the
                        Boston, Buffalo, and Rochester park systems, the campus plan for Stanford
                        University, and numerous private estates. In the 1890s Olmsted and his
                        partners were also appointed landscape architects for the World’s Columbian
                        Exposition in Chicago, and Olmsted worked on designs for the grounds of the
                        Biltmore estate near Asheville, North Carolina.</p></item>
                <item><p>PUGIN, A. W. N. <hi rend="italic">The Collected Letters of A. W. N. Pugin,
                            Volume 5: 1851 to 1852.</hi> Edited by Margaret Belcher. Oxford
                        University Press. 2015. 800 pp. $250. ISBN: 9780198713913. This is the final
                        volume of correspondence of the leading architect in the Gothic Revival in
                        England. Subjects in this volume include the international exhibition held
                        in the Crystal Palace, Pugin’s letters and pamphlets in support of the
                        Catholic Church, and Pugin’s design work in a broad range of mediums. The
                        volume also includes some letters that have come to light too late for
                        inclusion in their proper chronological places and some texts of doubtful
                        authenticity.</p></item>
                <item><p>RICHARDSON, SAMUEL. <hi rend="italic">The Correspondence of Samuel
                            Richardson: Correspondence Primarily on Sir Charles Grandison
                            (1750–1754).</hi> Edited by Betty A. Schellenberg. Cambridge University
                        Press. 2015. 336 pp. $130. ISBN: 9780521832182. Richardson produced his
                        final work of fiction, the epistolary novel <hi rend="italic">The History of
                            Sir Charles Grandison</hi>, in 1753. These letters from the period 1750
                        to 1754 discuss Richardson’s completion of the work, incorporate his
                        responses to the Irish piracy of the novel, and his exchanges with anonymous
                        fans, including those who attacked the novel’s tolerance for Catholicism and
                        those who pleaded for a sequel.</p></item>
                <item><p>RICHARDSON, SAMUEL. <hi rend="italic">The Correspondence of Samuel
                            Richardson: Correspondence with Sarah Wescomb, Frances Grainger and
                            Laetitia Pilkington.</hi> Edited by John A. Dussinger. Cambridge
                        University Press. 2014. 450 pp. $130. ISBN: 9780521830348. This volume
                        contains Richardson’s correspondence with three very different young women.
                        Sarah Wescomb and Frances Grainger, two young, unmarried correspondents,
                        sought paternal advice from the middle-aged author and in the process
                        contested stances taken in his novels. Laetitia Pilkington, an accused
                        adulteress, offers poignant glimpses into an impoverished woman’s struggles
                        to survive in Grub Street.</p></item>
                <item><p>ROSSETTI, DANTE GABRIEL. <hi rend="italic">The Correspondence of Dante
                            Gabriel Rossetti, Volume 10: Index, Undated Letters and
                            Bibliography.</hi> Edited by William E. Fredeman. Boydell and Brewer.
                        2015. 395 pp. $220. ISBN: 9781843843955. Volume 10 is the first-ever
                        analytical and biographical index to all Rossetti’s letters from 1835 to
                        1852. It augments partial indexes in previous volumes, giving subject
                        entries and mini-précis descriptions of annotation.</p></item>
                <item><p>RUSSELL, BERTRAND. <hi rend="italic">The Collected Papers of Bertrand
                            Russell, Volume 5: Toward Principia Mathematica, 1905–08.</hi> Edited by
                        Gregory H. Moore. Routledge. 2014. 1,072 pp. $355. ISBN: 9780415820981. This
                        volume finds Russell focused on writing <hi rend="italic">Principia
                            Mathematica</hi> from 1905 to 1908. Eight previously unpublished papers
                        shed light on his different versions of a substitutional theory of logic,
                        with its elimination of classes and relations. A recurring issue for him was
                        whether a type hierarchy had to be part of a substitutional theory. In
                        mid-1907 he began writing up the final version of <hi rend="italic"
                            >Principia</hi>, now using a ramified theory of types, and eleven
                        unpublished drafts from 1907 to 1908 deal with this. Numerous letters show
                        his thoughts on the process.</p></item>
                <item><p>SANTA FE TRAIL. <hi rend="italic">Over the Santa Fe Trail to Mexico: The
                            Travel Diaries and Autobiography of Dr. Rowland Willard.</hi> Edited by
                        Joy L. Poole. Arthur H. Clark Company. 2015. 320 pp. $29.95. ISBN:
                        9780870624391. One of the first Anglo-Americans to record his travels to New
                        Mexico, Dr. Rowland Willard (1794–1884) journeyed west on the Santa Fe Trail
                        in 1825 and then down the Camino Real into Mexico, taking notes along the
                        way. This edition of the young physician’s travel diaries and subsequent
                        autobiography is a rich historical source on the two trails and the practice
                        of medicine in the 1820s.</p></item>
                <item><p>SANTAYANA, GEORGE. <hi rend="italic">The Works of George Santayana, Volume
                            7, Book 4. The Life of Reason or the Phases of Human Progress: Reason in
                            Art.</hi> Edited by Marianne S. Wokeck and Martin A. Coleman. MIT Press.
                        2015. 336 pp. $75. ISBN: 9780262029605. In this fourth book of <hi
                            rend="italic">The Life of Reason</hi>, Santayana writes that art is
                        perfectly native to human endeavor; it is the paradigm of all productive
                        activity. He argues that the conduct of the life of reason is the supreme
                        art.</p></item>
                <item><p>SKINNER FAMILY. <hi rend="italic">The Belles of Williamsburg: The Courtship
                            Correspondence of Eliza Fisk Harwood and Tristrim Lowther Skinner,
                            1839–1849.</hi> Edited by Mary Maillard. Amazon Digital Services. 2015.
                        497 pp. $35. ASIN: B00QY2GO3A. This correspondence between Eliza Fisk
                        Harwood of Virginia and Tristrim Lowther Skinner of Edenton, North Carolina,
                        charts Eliza’s education, coming of age, courtships, and engagement, and
                        Tristrim’s practical education in the management of the Skinner family’s
                        farms. At the age of twenty-one, Eliza married Trim and left her childhood
                        home to help take charge of a Carolina plantation.</p></item>
                <item><p>SMITH, JOSEPH. <hi rend="italic">The Joseph Smith Papers. Journals, Volume
                            3: May 1843–June 1844.</hi> Edited by Andrew H. Hedges, Alex D. Smith,
                        and Brent M. Rogers. Church Historian’s Press. 2015. 680 pp. $57.95. ISBN:
                        9781629721477. This third and final volume of the <hi rend="italic"
                            >Journals</hi> series features journal entries from the last year of
                        Joseph Smith’s life. Topics include Smith’s teaching on humanity’s potential
                        to become like God, the establishment of the Council of Fifty, Smith’s
                        candidacy for United States president, and the escalating conflict against
                        Smith and the church. Appendixes provide detailed, contemporary accounts
                        from Willard Richards and William Clayton of the murder of Smith and his
                        brother Hyrum.</p></item>
                <item><p>SMITH, JOSEPH. <hi rend="italic">The Joseph Smith Papers. Revelations and
                            Translations, Volume 3, Part 1: Printer’s Manuscript of the Book of
                            Mormon, 1 Nephi 1–Alma 35.</hi> Edited by Royal Skousen and Robin Scott
                        Jensen. Church Historian’s Press. 2015. 576 pp. $89.99. ISBN: 9781629720609.
                            <hi rend="italic">Volume 3, Part 2: Printer’s Manuscript of the Book of
                            Mormon, Alma 36–Moroni 10.</hi> Edited by Royal Skousen and Robin Scott
                        Jensen. Church Historian’s Press. 2015. 447 pp. $89.99. ISBN: 9781629720616.
                        This work presents the most complete early text of the Book of Mormon: the
                        printer’s manuscript. Each page of the manuscript is presented as a
                        high-resolution photograph and accompanied by a color-coded transcript that
                        shows which scribe made each change to the manuscript. Part 1 contains
                        introductory and explanatory materials, the copyright and preface pages of
                        the printer’s manuscript, and the text of the Book of Mormon from 1 Nephi
                        through Alma 35. Part 2 contains the text of the Book of Mormon from Alma 36
                        through Moroni, statements of Book of Mormon witnesses, and reference
                        material including a chronology, a biographical register, and a table
                        documenting how the printer’s manuscript was used in printing the 1830 and
                        1837 editions of the Book of Mormon.</p></item>
                <item><p>SOUTH AMERICA. <hi rend="italic">The Improbable Conquest: Sixteenth-Century
                            Letters from the Río de la Plata.</hi> Edited by Pablo García Loaeza and
                        Victoria L. Garrett. Penn State University Press. 2015. 144 pp. $24.95.
                        ISBN: 9780271065489. This volume offers translations of a series of
                        little-known letters from the chaotic Spanish conquest of the Río de la
                        Plata region. These letters were written by a wide variety of individuals,
                        including clergy, military officers, and the region’s first governor, Pedro
                        de Mendoza. There is also an exceptional contribution from Isabel de
                        Guevara, one of the few women involved in the conquest to have recorded her
                        experiences. Includes an introduction, timeline, and a glossary of difficult
                        and archaic Spanish terms.</p></item>
                <item><p>STEPHEN, JAMES FITZJAMES. <hi rend="italic">Selected Writings of James
                            Fitzjames Stephen: On Society, Religion, and Government.</hi> Edited by
                        Thomas E. Schneider. Oxford University Press. 2015. 450 pp. $180. ISBN:
                        9780199585717. Stephen (1829–1894) is remembered as a judge and legal
                        historian. He is less well remembered for his journalism, though it earned
                        him a reputation among his contemporaries as one of the most trenchant
                        writers on topics ranging across the social, religious, political, moral,
                        and philosophical questions debated in his time. Only a small proportion of
                        these writings were collected during his lifetime, and very little has been
                        republished since his death. The essays in this volume are drawn mostly from
                        Stephen’s unsigned contributions to the <hi rend="italic">Saturday Review</hi>, with additions,
                        both signed and unsigned, from other periodicals, extending from the 1850s
                        to the 1880s.</p></item>
                <item><p>STUART, ELIZABETH, QUEEN OF BOHEMIA. <hi rend="italic">The Correspondence
                            of Elizabeth Stuart, Queen of Bohemia, Volume I: 1603–1631.</hi> Edited
                        by Nadine Akkerman. Oxford University Press. 2015. 840 pp. $250. ISBN:
                        9780199551071. First chronological volume of the first complete edition of
                        the letters of Elizabeth Stuart (1596–1662), Electress Palatine of the Rhine
                        and Queen of Bohemia, daughter of King James I of England and Anna of
                        Denmark. Includes keys to several cipher codes, translations of all letters
                        in French, and annotation.</p></item>
                <item><p>THURMAN, HOWARD WASHINGTON. <hi rend="italic">The Papers of Howard
                            Washington Thurman, Volume 3: The Bold Adventure, September 1943–May
                            1949.</hi> Edited by Walter Earl Fluker. University of South Carolina
                        Press. 2015. 456 pp. $59.95. ISBN: 9781611175417. Volume 3 documents
                        Thurman’s founding and leadership of the Fellowship Church for All Peoples
                        in San Francisco, California: the nation’s first major interracial,
                        interfaith church. The war years showed Thurman new possibilities and
                        strains in American culture. Amid the uncertainty of this period, Thurman
                        embarked on his great interfaith experiment as pastor to a small group of
                        people who were primarily middle class, with at least as many white as black
                        people, in a city that in 1940s America was far from the mainstream of black
                        life. His letters, essays, and sermons show Thurman struggling to define and
                        maintain the interracial character and practice of Fellowship Church,
                        building its programs and membership while constantly wrestling with
                        financial and location problems and preserving its separation from other
                        organizations, most notably the Communist Party and its adult education
                        program, the California Labor School.</p></item>
                <item><p>TWAIN, MARK. <hi rend="italic">Autobiography of Mark Twain, Volume 3: The
                            Complete and Authoritative Edition.</hi> Edited by Benjamin Griffin,
                        Harriet E. Smith, Victor Fischer, Michael Barry Frank, Amanda Gagel, Sharon
                        K. Goetz, Leslie Diane Myrick, and Christopher M. Ohge. University of
                        California Press. 2015. 792 pp. $45. ISBN: 9780520279940. Final volume of
                        the complete and critically reconstructed autobiography. Created from March
                        1907 to December 1909, these dictations present Mark Twain at the end of his
                        life: receiving an honorary degree from Oxford University; railing against
                        Theodore Roosevelt; founding numerous clubs; incredulous at an exhibition of
                        the Holy Grail; credulous about the authorship of Shakespeare’s plays;
                        relaxing in Bermuda; and observing new technologies. Twain also commemorates
                        his daughter Jean, who died in 1909. Includes the previously unpublished
                        “Ashcroft-Lyon Manuscript,” Twain’s indictment of his “putrescent pair” of
                        secretaries.</p></item>
                <item><p>UNIVERSITY COLLEGE, OXFORD. <hi rend="italic">Early Records of University
                            College, Oxford.</hi> Edited by R. H. Darwall-Smith. Boydell and Brewer.
                        2015. 440 pp. $60. ISBN: 9780904107272. University College claims to be the
                        oldest college in Oxford, tracing its origins to an endowment of 1249. This
                        book brings together the great majority of pre-1550 documents, other than
                        its account rolls, from the college’s archives, providing a sourcebook for
                        its early history. With notes and translations.</p></item>
                <item><p>USSR. <hi rend="italic">The Maisky Diaries: Red Ambassador to the Court of
                            St James’s, 1932–1943.</hi> Edited by Gabriel Gorodetsky. Yale
                        University Press. 2015. 448 pp. $40. ISBN: 9780300180671. The terror and
                        purges of Stalin’s Russia in the 1930s discouraged Soviet officials from
                        leaving documentary records, let alone keeping personal diaries. A
                        remarkable exception is the unique diary assiduously kept by Ivan Maisky,
                        the Soviet ambassador to London between 1932 and 1943. This selection from
                        Maisky’s diary, never before published in English, grippingly documents
                        Britain’s drift to war during the 1930s, appeasement in the Munich era,
                        negotiations leading to the signature of the Ribbentrop–Molotov Pact,
                        Churchill’s rise to power, the German invasion of Russia, and the intense
                        debate over the opening of the second front.</p></item>
                <item><p>WASHINGTON, GEORGE. <hi rend="italic">The Papers of George Washington,
                            Presidential Series, Volume 18: 1 April–30 September 1795.</hi> Edited
                        by Carol S. Ebel. University of Virginia Press. 2015. 896 pp. $95. ISBN:
                        9780813936451. International issues occupying Washington at this time
                        include peace agreements with Morocco and Algiers, the fall of the
                        Netherlands to France, and the ratification of the 1794 Treaty of Amity,
                        Commerce, and Navigation with Great Britain. Domestically, Washington had to
                        deal with several high-level governmental resignations and oversaw
                        instructions to General Anthony Wayne that culminated in the Treaty of
                        Greenville with the northwest Indians and agreed to the negotiation of a new
                        treaty between Georgia and the Creek Indians. While away from Mount Vernon,
                        he dispatched meticulous letters to his farm manager.</p></item>
                <item><p>WASHINGTON, GEORGE. <hi rend="italic">The Papers of George Washington,
                            Revolutionary War Series, Volume 23: 22 October–31 December 1779.</hi>
                        Edited by William M. Ferraro. University of Virginia Press. 2015. 904 pp.
                        $95. ISBN: 9780813936956. As October 1779 became November, Washington
                        curtailed preparations for a combined Franco-American assault against the
                        British forces in New York City before the end of the year, and instead
                        concentrated on settling his army for winter and arranging for his wife,
                        Martha, to join him at winter camp at Morristown.</p></item>
                <item><p>WHITMAN, WALT. <hi rend="italic">Walt Whitman’s Selected Journalism.</hi>
                        Edited by Douglas A. Noverr and Jason Stacy. University of Iowa Press. 2015.
                        320 pp. $29.95. ISBN: 9781609383152. Long before he was a celebrated poet,
                        Walt Whitman was a working journalist. By the time he published the first
                        edition of <hi rend="italic">Leaves of Grass</hi> in 1855, Whitman had
                        edited three newspapers and published thousands of reviews, editorials, and
                        human-interest stories in newspapers in and around New York City. Yet for
                        decades, much of his journalism has been difficult to access or even find.
                        This volume thematically and chronologically organizes a compelling
                        selection of Whitman’s journalism from the late 1830s to the Civil
                    War.</p></item>
                <item><p>WORLD WAR II. <hi rend="italic">From Wright Field, Ohio, to Hokkaido,
                            Japan: General Curtis E. LeMay’s Letters to His Wife Helen,
                            1941–1945.</hi> Edited by Benjamin Paul Hegi and Alfred F. Hurley.
                        University of North Texas Press. 2015. 455 pp. $34.95. ISBN: 9781680400014.
                        General LeMay’s activities in World War II are well documented, but his
                        personal history is less thoroughly recorded. Throughout the war he wrote
                        hundreds of letters to his wife, Helen, and daughter, Jane. They are
                        published for the first time in this volume, with narrative essays
                        buttressed by both official and unofficial sources and supplemented with
                        extensive footnotes.</p></item>
                <item><p>YOUNG, BRIGHAM. <hi rend="italic">The Prophet and the Reformer: The Letters
                            of Brigham Young and Thomas L. Kane.</hi> Edited by Matthew J. Grow and
                        Ronald W. Walker. Oxford University Press. 2015. 568 pp. $39.95. ISBN:
                        9780195397734. Brigham Young first met Thomas L. Kane on the plains of
                        western Iowa in 1846. Young came to rely on Kane, twenty-one years his
                        junior, as his most trusted outside adviser, making Kane the most important
                        non-Mormon in the history of the Mormon church. In return, no one influenced
                        the direction of Kane’s life more than Young. The letters exchanged by the
                        two offer crucial insights into Young’s personal life and views as well as
                        his actions as a political and religious leader.</p></item>
            </list>
        </body>
    </text>
</TEI>
