<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<?xml-model href="http://www.tei-c.org/release/xml/tei/custom/schema/relaxng/tei_all.rng" type="application/xml" schematypens="http://relaxng.org/ns/structure/1.0"?>

<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
    <teiHeader xml:lang="eng">
        <fileDesc>
            <titleStmt>
                <title level="m" type="main">Extracts from <hi rend="italics">The Young
                    Idea</hi></title>
                <author>Mary Isbell</author>
                <author>Teresa Navarro</author>
                <author>Katelyn Sahagian</author>
            </titleStmt>
            <publicationStmt>
                <authority>Scholarly Editing: The Annual of the Association for Documentary
                    Editing</authority>
                <address>
                    <addrLine>juxta</addrLine>
                    <addrLine>http://www.scholarlyediting.org</addrLine>
                </address>
                <publisher>Association for Documentary Editing</publisher>
                <publisher>University of Nebraska&#8211;Lincoln</publisher>
                <distributor>
                    <name>Center for Digital Research in the Humanities</name>
                    <address>
                        <addrLine>319 Love Library</addrLine>
                        <addrLine>University of Nebraska&#8211;Lincoln</addrLine>
                        <addrLine>Lincoln, NE 68588-4100</addrLine>
                        <addrLine>http://cdrh.unl.edu</addrLine>
                    </address>
                </distributor>
                <date>2015</date>
                <availability>
                    <p>Scholarly Editing: The Annual of the Association for Documentary Editing is
                        freely distributed by the Association for Documentary Editing and the Center
                        for Digital Research in the Humanities at the University of Nebraska-Lincoln
                        and licensed under a Creative Commons Attribution-NonCommercial-Share Alike
                        3.0 Unported License</p>
                </availability>
                <idno type="file">2016preface.youngidea</idno>
                <idno type="edition">youngidea</idno>
            </publicationStmt>
            <seriesStmt>
                <title level="j">Scholarly Editing: The Annual of the Association for Documentary
                    Editing</title>
                <respStmt>
                    <resp>editor</resp>
                    <name xml:id="ag">Amanda Gailey</name>
                </respStmt>
                <respStmt>
                    <resp>editor</resp>
                    <name xml:id="awj">Andrew Jewell</name>
                </respStmt>
                <idno type="vol">37</idno>
                <idno type="ISSN">2167-1257</idno>
            </seriesStmt>
            <sourceDesc>
                <bibl>
                    <author>Mary Isbell</author>
                    <author>Teresa Navarro</author>
                    <author>Katelyn Sahagian</author>
                    <title level="m" type="main">Extracts from <hi rend="italics">The Young
                            Idea</hi></title></bibl>
            </sourceDesc>
        </fileDesc>
    </teiHeader>

    <text>

        <front>

            <head type="main">2016 Preface</head>
            <head type="sub"><title>Extracts from <hi rend="italics">The Young
                Idea</hi></title></head>
            <lb/>
            <byline>Mary Isbell</byline>
            
        </front>

        <body>
            <div type="section">
                
                <p>Handwritten shipboard newspapers are not often mentioned in discussions about
                    Victorian periodical culture. When I found extracts from <hi rend="italics">The
                        Young Idea</hi> while conducting dissertation research at the National
                    Maritime Museum in Greenwich, I immediately wanted to share this artifact online
                    to encourage scholarly conversation. I am grateful to the many scholars who have
                    helped me to make this a reality, beginning with Dino Felluga, who encouraged me
                    to speak with the project manager at NINES (Networked Infrastructure for
                    Nineteenth-Century Electronic Scholarship) when he learned about my project. My
                    plan was to create a simple website to share my transcriptions from <hi
                        rend="italics">The Young Idea</hi>, but Dana Wheeles very wisely encouraged
                    me to learn more about the Text Encoding Initiative (TEI) before proceeding.</p>
                <p>I got my first introduction to the TEI from an inspiring presentation by Laura
                    Mandell during the 2013 meeting of the Melville Electronic Library Project
                    (MELCamp). I began this edition in earnest under the guidance of Beth Luey,
                    Mary-Jo Kline, and Daniel Feller during the 2013 Institute for Editing
                    Historical Documents. I am tremendously grateful to the Association for
                    Documentary Editing for funding that early training. I continued my training
                    under the inimitable Julia Flanders during a seminar on "Advanced TEI Concepts"
                    at the 2014 Digital Humanities Summer Institute (DHSI). This seminar helped me
                    refine my approach to this edition and provided a more thorough understanding of
                    the Text Encoding Initiative. I am grateful to DHSI for a tuition scholarship to
                    participate in the seminar and Interdisciplinary Performance Studies at Yale
                    (IPSY) for funding my travel to Victoria BC; I thank Joseph Roach especially for
                    his enthusiastic support of this project </p>
                <p>I am incredibly grateful for my two co-editors on this project, Teresa Navarro
                    and Katelyn Sahagian, undergraduates at the University of New Haven who brought
                    tremendous energy and enthusiasm to the tasks of transcription and proofreading
                    in the Summer of 2015. I was able to collaborate with these two students through
                    the support of the University of New Haven's Summer Undergraduate Research
                    Fellowship (SURF) program. After years researching this little-known material on
                    my own, I was thrilled to hear their commentary on Reverend Bampfield's
                    atrocious handwriting and the contributors' fascination with puns. It has also
                    been tremendously gratifying to show them how their painstaking work
                    transcribing and encoding has been transformed into a digital edition.</p>
                <p>The permissions costs associated with including archival images in digital
                    editions remains one of the most significant barriers to the creation of
                    open-access digital editions. I am tremendously grateful, therefore, to Joseph
                    Roach and the Andrew W. Mellon Foundation for enabling me to purchase a rare
                    copy of McArthur's lithograph edition so I can reproduce images here free of
                    charge. I am also grateful to Nova Jones (a descendant of Robert Dexter, who
                    served aboard HMS <hi rend="italics">Chesapeake</hi>) for alerting me to this
                    edition after reading about my project online. Images of Bampfield's extracts
                    from <hi rend="italics">The Young Idea</hi> are reproduced in this edition with
                    the generous permission of the National Maritime Museum at Greenwich.</p>
                <p>I would like expecially to thank Amanda Gailey, Andrew Jewell, and the staff of
                        <hi rend="italics">Scholarly Editing</hi> for their guidance and careful
                    attention as I worked on this project over several years. Their assistance in
                    developing this interface not only makes the seven issues of this edition
                    possible, but it provides a model for the publication of future issues. I liken
                    the expertise of the team at Scholarly Editing to the talent of Paul Jerrard,
                    the lithographer whose craft made it possible for A.D. McArthur to share his
                    handwritten newspaper with the public in 1867. The complexities of our
                    publication technologies have changed dramatically, and I am grateful to have
                    been taught how to publish data in a format that can accomodate technological
                    advances we have not yet imagined. </p>
            </div>


        </body>

    </text>
</TEI>
