<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<?xml-model href="http://www.tei-c.org/release/xml/tei/custom/schema/relaxng/tei_all.rng" type="application/xml" schematypens="http://relaxng.org/ns/structure/1.0"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
    <teiHeader xml:lang="eng">
        <fileDesc>
            <titleStmt>
                <title level="m" type="main">Extracts from <hi rend="italics">The Young
                    Idea</hi></title>
                <author>Mary Isbell</author>
                <author>Teresa Navarro</author>
                <author>Katelyn Sahagian</author>
            </titleStmt>
            <publicationStmt>
                <authority>Scholarly Editing: The Annual of the Association for Documentary
                    Editing</authority>
                <address>
                    <addrLine>juxta</addrLine>
                    <addrLine>http://www.scholarlyediting.org</addrLine>
                </address>
                <publisher>Association for Documentary Editing</publisher>
                <publisher>University of Nebraska&#8211;Lincoln</publisher>
                <distributor>
                    <name>Center for Digital Research in the Humanities</name>
                    <address>
                        <addrLine>319 Love Library</addrLine>
                        <addrLine>University of Nebraska&#8211;Lincoln</addrLine>
                        <addrLine>Lincoln, NE 68588-4100</addrLine>
                        <addrLine>http://cdrh.unl.edu</addrLine>
                    </address>
                </distributor>
                <date>2015</date>
                <availability>
                    <p>Scholarly Editing: The Annual of the Association for Documentary Editing is
                        freely distributed by the Association for Documentary Editing and the Center
                        for Digital Research in the Humanities at the University of Nebraska-Lincoln
                        and licensed under a Creative Commons Attribution-NonCommercial-Share Alike
                        3.0 Unported License</p>
                </availability>
                <idno type="file">intro.youngidea</idno>
                <idno type="edition">youngidea</idno>
            </publicationStmt>
            <seriesStmt>
                <title level="j">Scholarly Editing: The Annual of the Association for Documentary
                    Editing</title>
                <respStmt>
                    <resp>editor</resp>
                    <name xml:id="ag">Amanda Gailey</name>
                </respStmt>
                <respStmt>
                    <resp>editor</resp>
                    <name xml:id="awj">Andrew Jewell</name>
                </respStmt>
                <idno type="vol">36</idno>
                <idno type="ISSN">2167-1257</idno>
            </seriesStmt>
            <sourceDesc>
                <bibl>
                    <author>Mary Isbell</author>
                    <author>Teresa Navarro</author>
                    <author>Katelyn Sahagian</author>
                    <title level="m" type="main">Extracts from <hi rend="italics">The Young
                            Idea</hi></title></bibl>
            </sourceDesc>
        </fileDesc>
    </teiHeader>
    <text>
        <front>
            <head type="main">Editorial Introduction</head>
            <head type="sub"><title>Extracts from <hi rend="italics">The Young
                Idea</hi></title></head>
            <lb/>
            <byline>Mary Isbell</byline>
            
        </front>
        <body>
            <div type="section">
                <p>"Newspapers are not generally regarded on board men-of-war with a friendly eye,”
                    explains A.D. McArthur in his preface to the 1867 lithograph edition of <hi
                        rend="italics">The Young Idea: A Naval Journal edited on board H.M.S. <hi
                            rend="italics">Chesapeake</hi> in 1857, 1858, &amp; 1859</hi>. McArthur
                    edited <hi rend="italics">The Young Idea</hi>, an illustrated weekly paper,
                    while serving as a clerk aboard the <hi rend="italics">Chesapeake</hi>; his
                    preface goes on to explain that officers viewed shipboard periodicals as
                    vehicles of insubordination. Along with the insight it provides into
                    contributors’ impressions of the foreign ports they visit (including Calcutta,
                    Trincomalee, Aden, and Singapore) and their role in protecting British
                    interests, <hi rend="italics">The Young Idea</hi> offers a detailed account of
                    day-to-day life aboard a British warship. It includes, for example, an editorial
                    remembrance of a sailor killed by a falling piece of rigging and a “letter to
                    the editor” complaining that five gentlemen awakened the inhabitants of
                    “forecastle street” singing “Annie Laurie” at the top of their lungs and then
                    evaded the guardian of the night who tried to interrupt their revelry. But the
                    very form through which we encounter such accounts demonstrates how the presence
                    of a handwritten newspaper influenced shipboard life by creating a community
                    that could mourn and chastise in a publication that circulated aboard the
                    ship.</p>
                <p>Because shipboard newspapers could unsettle the hierarchy of Victorian naval
                    vessels, they were often suppressed or censored. <note>Vanessa Histon Roberts
                        explains in “Publishing and Printing on board ships” (The Mariner’s Mirror
                        74 (1988): 329-34) that Clements Markham edited a journal during the
                        Franklin expedition entitled Minavilins, which was supressed (Roberts
                        331).</note>The handful that we know about are not available in the forms in
                    which they originally circulated, making it much more challenging to understand
                    how these papers were produced and distributed. We have McArthur’s 1867
                    lithograph edition, but the actual pages of <hi rend="italics">The Young
                        Idea</hi> are not extant. We also have extracts from <hi rend="italics">The
                        Young Idea</hi> that were transcribed into the diary of the ship’s chaplain,
                    J.W.L. Bampfield. Beyond offering a second witness to the manuscript pages (a
                    rare find!), Bampfield’s extracts also provide a partial marked list of the
                    paper’s contributors because he included the author’s initials after almost
                    every contribution he transcribed.<note>Bampfield, J.W.L. Mss. Copy kept by the
                        shop's chaplain the Rev. J.W.L. Bampfield. National Maritime Museum, NWT
                        3.</note>
                    <figure>
                        <graphic url="TYI0005.jpg"/>
                        <head>Figure 1: Title page for McArthur's 1867 Edition</head>
                        <p>Author's personal collection</p>
                    </figure>
                    <figure>
                        <graphic url="BETYI1021.jpg"/>
                        <head>Figure 2: First page of Bampfield'd Extracts</head>
                        <p>Bamfield, J.W.L. Mss. Journal kept by the ship's chaplain the Rev. J.W.L.
                            Bamfield. National Maritime Museum, NWT 3</p>
                    </figure></p>
                <p>My primary goal in undertaking this edition was to learn why and how McArthur
                    prepared <hi rend="italics">The Young Idea</hi> for publication in 1867. The
                    reason for producing the lithograph edition is fairly straightforward. As
                    McArthur explains in the <ref target="1867preface.youngidea" type="html">preface to his
                        1867 edition</ref>, he “yielded to the solicitation of friends” to give The
                    Young Idea “afresh to the world” (n.p.). McArthur’s preface also indicates that
                    the lithographed edition was funded through a subscription supported by Harry
                    Edmund Edgell, the commanding officer of the <hi rend="italics">Chesapeake</hi>
                    (and the entire squadron) for the majority of the cruise chronicled in <hi
                        rend="italics">The Young Idea</hi>. The <hi rend="italics"><hi
                            rend="italics">Chesapeake</hi></hi> was sold for parts in 1867, so it
                    seems likely that Admiral Edgell (named as a primary supporter of the lithograph
                    edition in McArthur’s Preface) and other officers who served aboard the <hi
                        rend="italics">Chesapeake</hi> would be motivated to contribute to a
                    subscription toward a beautiful lithograph edition that would commemorate their
                    time aboard the vessel before she was broken up.</p>
                <p>To answer the trickier question of how McArthur prepared this edition for
                    publication, I have encoded significant variants between McArthur’s lithograph
                    edition (the base text for this edition) and Bampfield’s handwritten extracts
                    from the manuscript pages. I have concluded that while lithography could have
                    been used to create a facsimile edition (that is, an edition that reproduces as
                    closely as possible the pages exactly as they appeared in the original
                    manuscript newspaper), McArthur’s lithograph edition is not a facsimile. Though
                    he does not announce it as explicitly as Bampfield does, McArthur pulled
                    extracts from the manuscript newspaper and re-created the appearance of the
                    paper with those extracts. The editors of a similarly produced edition of <hi
                        rend="italics">The Illustrated Arctic News</hi> (1852) actually apologize in
                    their preface for omitting “a few articles” fearing the bad taste of the arctic
                    public might lead a more general readership to “object on the score of
                        raciness.”<note>Osborne, Sherard and George F. McDougall. Editors. <hi
                            rend="italics">Illustrated Arctic News</hi>, Published on board H.M.S.
                        Resolute: in search of the Expedition under Sir John Franklin. London:
                        Ackermann, 1852</note></p>
                <p>Hyperlinked annotations throughout this edition support my contention that
                    McArthur had a heavily edited version of <hi rend="italics">The Young Idea</hi>
                    published in 1867, but the clearest evidence is the fact that McArthur includes
                    an article that he wrote about the arrival of letters from home as the first
                    contribution to the ninth issue of his lithograph edition, though it appears as
                    the first entry of the eighth issue in Bampfield’s extracts. This suggests that
                    McArthur was selecting, rearranging, and editing individual contributions for
                    the lithograph edition. Readers of this digital edition can click on the title
                    of each contribution (or the first sentence where there is no title) to learn
                    how Bampfield’s extracts differ from the base text. Readers will also find
                    hyperlinked lines within particular contributions where significant divergences
                    from Bampfield’s extracts occur (the most notable section of divergence in this
                    edition occurs in the article entitled “Up the Hooghly.” </p>
                <p>Of course, this edition for <hi rend="italics">Scholarly Editing</hi> necessarily
                    provides only a section of McArthur’s full, 58-issue lithograph edition. I have
                    extracted issues 7 (January 23, 1858) through 13 (March 6, 1858), which were
                    written and circulated during the ship's time harbored off the coast of
                    Calcutta. I have also included McArthur’s preface to the lithograph edition
                    because it provides a detailed introduction to this unique example of a
                    handwritten newspaper. Issues 7-13 document day-to-day life aboard a naval
                    vessel (receiving letters from home, disturbances aboard the ship, cricket
                    matches between the crew of the <hi rend="italics">Chesapeake</hi> and other
                    British vessels, etc.), but they stand alone in the sense that they provide a
                    cohesive narrative of sailors' experiences in Calcutta in the wake of what was
                    then referred to as the Indian Mutiny.<note>In Rule of Darkness (1988), Patrick
                        Brantlinger explains that “among both British and Indian historians, debate
                        still focuses on whether the uprising was only an army “mutiny,” or a “civil
                        rebellion” as well, or, as Indian nationalists have held it to be, “the
                        first Indian war of independence” (200-201). I follow Brantlinger and refer
                        to the conflict as “the Mutiny.”</note></p>
                <p>The seventh issue begins with the editor's reflections on the disappointing
                    announcement that the crew of the <hi rend="italics">Chesapeake</hi> would not
                    fight to put down the rebellion (other sailors had seen direct combat and the
                    sailors aboard the <hi rend="italics">Chesapeake</hi> knew about these famous
                    naval brigades that fought on land). This issue also includes a detailed
                    contribution on first impressions of Calcutta. The eighth issue begins with an
                    editorial "Try Again," reflecting on the failure of the first attempt to lay an
                    Atlantic telegraph cable and the crack discovered in Big Ben ("his metal was too
                    thin, his tongue was too thick"), reminding us that when in port these sailors
                    followed with great attention the events back home in England. The tenth issue
                    is probably the richest. Extracts from a narrative of the siege at Lucknow
                    appear alongside reports of a regatta in which the <hi rend="italics"
                        >Chesapeake</hi> competed and a fascinating review of the <hi rend="italics"
                        >Chesapeake</hi> sailor amateurs' debut performance at the Calcutta Lyric
                    Theatre, a theatrical performance mounted to benefit the widows and orphans of
                    those killed during the mutiny. The sailors were criticized harshly by the drama
                    critic for an English-language newspaper printed in Calcutta (<hi rend="italics"
                        >The Hurkaru</hi>) and officers aboard the <hi rend="italics"
                        >Chesapeake</hi> responded to this affront with an article in <hi
                        rend="italics">The Young Idea</hi> and a letter to the editor of <hi
                        rend="italics">The Englishman</hi>, a rival newspaper to <hi rend="italics"
                        >The Hurkaru</hi>. The twelfth issue begins with an editorial speculating on
                    where the ship will travel next (reports at that time were that the <hi
                        rend="italics">Chesapeake</hi> would convey Lady Canning to Madras), and a
                    detailed account of the wedding of the granddaughter of Rajah Behadoor, with
                    careful attention given to narrating the unfamiliar marriage ceremony. The
                    thirteenth issue reflects back on the experiences in Calcutta and one
                    contributor revisits the brutal review of the sailors' theatrical performance,
                    including the prologue delivered on that occasion. </p>
                <p>McArthur’s preface makes clear that he published in an effort to chronicle the
                    existence of a handwritten newspaper aboard a naval vessel. This digital edition
                    shares that goal and, in so doing, contributes to scholarly conversations about
                    handwritten newspapers, a growing field of scholarly inquiry.<note>For more on the topic, see: Droste, Heiko.
                        “Degrees of Publicity. Handwritten Newspapers in the Seventeenth and
                        Eighteenth Centuries.” <hi rend="italics">LIR.journal</hi>1.1 (2012): 67–83;
                        Salmi-Niklander; Kirsti. "Monologic, Dialogic, Collective: Modes of Writing
                        in Hand-written Newspapers." <hi rend="italics">White Field, Black Seeds:
                            Nordic Literacy Practices in the Long Nineteenth Century.</hi> Helsinki:
                        Finnish Literature Society, 2013. 76-88; and Smith, Michael Ray, Quentin
                        Schultze, and Roy Alden Atwood. <hi rend="italics">A Free Press in
                            FreeHand.</hi> Grand Rapids: Edenridge Press, 2011.</note> While
                    researchers have devoted some attention to shipboard publishing and
                        printing,<note>Roberts, Vanessa Histon. “Publishing and Printing on Board
                        Ships.” <hi rend="italics">Mariner’s Mirror</hi> 74 (1988): 329-34; Barwick,
                        G.F. “Books Printed at Sea” The Library 2.2 (1899): 163-6; Stam, David H.
                        and Deirdre C. Stam. “Bending Time: The Function of Periodicals in
                        Nineteenth-Century Polar Naval Expeditions.” <hi rend="italics">Victorian
                            Periodicals Review.</hi> 41.4 (2008): 301-322.</note> the only
                    scholarship that mentions <hi rend="italics">The Young Idea</hi> concerns Paul
                    Jerrard, the publisher of the 1867 edition.<note>Leathlean, Howard. “Paul
                        Jerrard: Publisher of ‘Special Presents.’” <hi rend="italics">The Book
                            Collector</hi>. 40.2 (1991): 169-96.</note>This critical edition uses
                    the 1867 lithograph edition as its base text. All material in this edition has
                    been double keyed, meaning two people have transcribed the
                    source material and the transcriptions have been collated to locate and correct
                    errors in transcription. Abbreviations have been transcribed and expanded.
                    Superscript has not been encoded consistently: whether 19<hi rend="superscript"
                        >th</hi> or 19th, it will appear in the edition as 19th. Column breaks and
                    the running header have been transcribed and encoded, but do not appear in the
                    edition. Double hyphens appear frequently in the source texts to indicate that a
                    word has been continued onto a new line. Because this edition provides an image
                    of each page, these double hyphens have not been transcribed. Hyperlink annotations
                    have been provided to help readers learn about people, places, and ships
                    mentioned in the text. Annotions have also been included to present information
                    gleaned from the analysis of variation between McArthur's lithograph edition and
                    Bampfield's extracts. Where possible, these notes combine information from
                    Bampfield's marked list of contributors with data from the muster books for the
                        <hi rend="italics">Chesapeake</hi> to provide insight into the authorship of
                    individual contributions. As described above, these notes also explain how the
                    base text differs from Bampfield's extracts. Users can view these notes by
                    clicking on the title of each contribution (or the first line of the
                    contribution if there is not title).</p>
            </div>
        </body>
    </text>
</TEI>
