<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<?xml-model href="http://www.tei-c.org/release/xml/tei/custom/schema/relaxng/tei_all.rng" type="application/xml" schematypens="http://relaxng.org/ns/structure/1.0"?>
<?xml-model href="http://www.tei-c.org/release/xml/tei/custom/schema/relaxng/tei_all.rng" type="application/xml"
	schematypens="http://purl.oclc.org/dsdl/schematron"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"
   xmlns:mi="http://www.newhaven.edu/thedigitalyoungidea/ns/1.0">
   <teiHeader>
      <fileDesc>
         <titleStmt>
            <title>Personography for The Digital Young Idea</title>
         </titleStmt>
         <publicationStmt>
            <authority>Scholarly Editing: The Annual of the Association for Documentary
               Editing</authority>
            <idno type="file">personography.youngidea</idno>
            <idno type="edition">youngidea</idno>
            <address>
               <addrLine>http://www.scholarlyediting.org</addrLine>
            </address>
            <publisher>Association for Documentary Editing</publisher>
            <publisher>University of Nebraska&#8211;Lincoln</publisher>
            <distributor>
               <name>Center for Digital Research in the Humanities</name>
               <address>
                  <addrLine>319 Love Library</addrLine>
                  <addrLine>University of Nebraska&#8211;Lincoln</addrLine>
                  <addrLine>Lincoln, NE 68588-4100</addrLine>
                  <addrLine>http://cdrh.unl.edu</addrLine>
               </address>
            </distributor>
            <date>2016</date>
            <availability>
               <p>Scholarly Editing: The Annual of the Association for Documentary Editing is freely
                  distributed by the Association for Documentary Editing and the Center for Digital
                  Research in the Humanities at the University of Nebraska-Lincoln and licensed
                  under a Creative Commons Attribution-NonCommercial-ShareAlike 3.0 Unported
                  License</p>
            </availability>
         </publicationStmt>
         <seriesStmt>
            <title level="j">Scholarly Editing: The Annual of the Association for Documentary
               Editing</title>
            <respStmt>
               <resp>editor</resp>
               <name xml:id="ag">Amanda Gailey</name>
            </respStmt>
            <respStmt>
               <resp>editor</resp>
               <name xml:id="awj">Andrew Jewell</name>
            </respStmt>
            <idno type="vol">37</idno>
            <idno type="ISSN">2167-1257</idno>
         </seriesStmt>
         <sourceDesc>
            <p>This personography draws primarily on the Dictionary of National Biography and on the
               Muster Book of the H.M.S. Chesapeake held at the National Archives at Kew, UK.
               Bibliographic information provided in each note.</p>
         </sourceDesc>

      </fileDesc>
   </teiHeader>
   <text>
      <body>
         <listPerson>
            <person>
               <persName xml:id="A_D_McArthur">Alexander D. McArthur</persName>
               <note>Alexander D. McArthur, a clerk, joined the <hi rend="italic">Chesapeake</hi> on
                  December 9, 1857. He was born on December 25, 1835 in Woolwich, Kent, making him
                  twenty-one when he came aboard. Census records for the town of Woolwich in 1851 reveal the
                  family of John McAurthur, a captain in the Royal Marines, who lived with his wife
                  Mary E., a son James (a gentleman, aged 29), a son John (no occupation, aged 27),
                  a son Henry (a clerk in the wine trade, aged 17), a son Alexander D (a scholar,
                  aged 15), a son Hanibal (no occupation, aged 13), and a servant Esther Johnson
                  (aged 20).</note>
               <bibl>Muster Book of Her Majesty's Ship Chesapeake Commencing 1st January 1858 Ending
                  31st March 1858," National Archives at Kew (ADM 38/2884)</bibl>
               <bibl>Census Returns of England and Wales, 1851. Kew, Surrey, England: The National
                  Archives of the UK (TNA): Public Record Office (PRO), 1851.</bibl>
            </person>

            <person>
               <persName xml:id="J_W_L_Bampfield">John William Lewis Bampfield</persName>
               <note>Reverend John William Lewis Bampfield joined the <hi rend="italic"
                     >Chesapeake</hi> on July 24, 1857 and was a regular contributor to and
                  supporter of <hi rend="italic">The Young Idea</hi>. While his age is not recorded
                  in the muster book, census records reveal that Bampfield was born in June of 1823,
                  so he was in his midthirties during the cruise. He was commissioned as chaplain
                  aboard a different royal naval vessel in Port Royal, Jamaica before his arrival
                  aboard the <hi rend="italic">Chesapeake</hi>. His detailed journal provides an
                  additional witness to <hi rend="italic">The Young Idea</hi>, providing fascinating
                  points of contrast from the facsimile edition that McArthur had printed in 1867
                  and offering hints about the authorship of contributions through his inclusion of
                  the initials of authors (a marked list). </note>
            </person>
            <person>
               <persName xml:id="Edgell">Harry Edmund Edgell</persName>
               <note>Harry Edmund Edgell joined the <hi rend="italic">Chesapeake</hi> as commodore
                  after the period chronicled in the issues included in this edition. He was an
                  enthusiastic supporter of <hi rend="italic">The Young Idea</hi>. In <hi
                     rend="italics">"Martello Tower" in China, and the Pacific in H.M.S. "Tribune,"
                     1856-60</hi> (London: George Allen, 1902), Francis Martin Norman recounts
                  Edgell's enthusiastic support for a shipboard theatrical aboard H.M.S. <hi
                     rend="italic">Tribune</hi> in 1857, when he was captain of the ship. Edgell
                  composed the prologue for the play and painted the drop scene (50). The National
                  Maritime Museum at Greenwich (NMM) holds over 300 watercolors by Edgell, including
                  some undertaken during the cruise chronicled in <hi rend="italic">The Young
                     Idea</hi>. The NMM's biographical note on Edgell reads as follows: "Edgell was
                  promoted to lieutenant in 1828, to commander in 1837 and to captain in 1846. He
                  was appointed to command the Tribune in 1855 when she was in the Crimea. During
                  this commission she went to the Pacific and finally to China. In 1857 Edgell was
                  the Senior Naval Officer at Hong Kong and he transferred into the Bittern tender
                  commanding the gun boats on the Canton River during the hostilities with the
                  Chinese. In 1858 he was given command of the squadron in Indian waters, during
                  which time he commanded the <hi rend="italic">Chesapeake</hi> and later the
                  Retribution. The latter returned to England and was paid off in 1860. Edgell had
                  no further active employment and was promoted on the retired list, reaching the
                  rank of vice-admiral in 1871."</note>
            </person>
            <person>
               <persName xml:id="Watson">Commodore Rundle Burges Watson</persName>
               <note>From “Watson, Rundle Burges” by <bibl><author>by J. K. Laughton, rev. Andrew
                        Lambert</author></bibl> in <bibl><title>Oxford Dictionary of National
                        Biography</title></bibl>: <quote>"Watson, Rundle Burges (1809–1860), naval
                     officer, was the eldest son of Captain Joshua Rowley Watson (1772–1810). He
                     entered the navy in November 1821, and was promoted lieutenant on 7 October
                     1829. [. . .] On 23 December 1842 he was advanced to post rank, and on 24
                     December was made a CB. [. . .] In December 1852 [Watson] was appointed to the
                     new steam frigate <hi rend="italic">Impérieuse</hi> (50 guns), then, and for
                     some years later, considered one of the finest ships in the navy. In 1854 she
                     was sent into the Baltic in advance of the fleet, Watson being senior officer
                     of the squadron of small vessels appointed to watch the breaking up of the ice,
                     and to see that no Russian warships got to sea. It was an arduous service well
                     performed. The <hi rend="italic">Impérieuse</hi> continued with the flying
                     squadron in the Baltic during the campaigns of 1854 and 1855, and until the
                     signing of peace in March 1856. As the senior officer of the frigate squadron,
                     and generally on detached service, Watson demonstrated the highest standards of
                     seamanship, judgement, and leadership. After the peace the <hi rend="italic"
                        >Impérieuse</hi> was sent to the North American station; she returned to
                     England and was paid off early in 1857. From May 1856 until his death Watson
                     was naval aide-de-camp to the queen. In June 1859 he was appointed
                     captain-superintendent of Sheerness Dockyard, where he died on 5 July 1860. An
                     officer of great ability, Watson was one of the last great sailing-ship
                     captains, and the first frigate captain of the steam era."</quote></note>
            </person>
            <person>
               <persName xml:id="Campbell">Sir Colin Campbell</persName>
               <note>From “Campbell [formerly Macliver], Colin, Baron Clyde” by <bibl><author>H. M.
                        Stephens, rev. Roger T. Stearn</author></bibl>, <bibl><title>Oxford
                        Dictionary of National Biography</title></bibl>:
                     <quote>"Campbell [formerly Macliver], Colin, Baron Clyde (1792–1863), army
                     officer, born Macliver, the eldest son of John Macliver (d. 22 December 1858,
                     aged ninety-two), a carpenter in Glasgow—whose father's Ardnave estate was
                     forfeited following the Jacobite rising of 1745—and his wife,
                     Agnes, née Campbell, of the Campbells of Islay, was born at John Street,
                     Glasgow, on 20 October 1792. His mother died when he was a boy, and her
                     brother, Colonel John Campbell, paid for Colin's education. He attended Glasgow
                     grammar school and Gosport military academy. In 1807 Colonel Campbell took him
                     to the duke of York as candidate for a commission. The duke assumed he was
                     ‘another of the clan’ and his name was entered as Campbell, which he
                     thenceforth used. [. . .] In March 1857 Campbell was offered command of the
                     expedition then forming for China, which he refused. On 11 July arrived the
                     news of the outbreak of the Indian mutiny and the death of General Anson, the
                     commander-in-chief in India. That day Lord Panmure offered Campbell the
                     command-in-chief. He accepted, and started next day for India. He arrived at
                     Calcutta in August, and heard at once the news of the recovery of Delhi by
                     Major-General Archdale Wilson, and of Havelock's capture of Cawnpore, and his
                     preparations for the first relief of Lucknow. Campbell hurried to Cawnpore the
                     troops intended for the China expedition, which Lord Elgin had wisely sent to
                     Calcutta, and assembled there also picked troops from the army which had taken
                     Delhi. After two months of hard work organizing the troops and clearing Lower
                     Bengal, he took command of the army at the Alambagh, and, leaving General C. A.
                     Windham to hold Cawnpore, started on 9 November with 4700 men and 32 guns to
                     save the British (under Outram and Havelock) at Lucknow. His force, largely
                     European troops—and including the 93rd and Captain William Peel's naval
                     brigade—reached Lucknow, stormed the sikandarabagh (16 November), then broke
                     through to Outram and Havelock in the residency. Campbell evacuated the Lucknow
                     garrison and its many dependents (11–23 November), leaving a force under Outram
                     holding the Alambagh, 3 miles south of Lucknow. On 30 November Campbell reached
                     Cawnpore and sent the rescued on steamers to Calcutta. [. . .] Campbell decided
                     that a thorough defeat of the mutineers in Oudh must be the first major step
                     towards re-establishing British rule. By March 1858 he had assembled 25,000 men
                     for this purpose, and then began his campaign. After ten days' hard fighting he
                     finally recaptured Lucknow on 19 March, and then by a series of operations in
                     Oudh and Rohilkhand pacified—with the usual executions and reprisals—the north
                     of India by May. He then paused in his own personal exertions from ill health;
                     but it was because of his careful organization that Sir Hugh Rose was able to
                     muster an adequate army for the campaign in central India, and because of his
                     planning that the campaign was finally successful. In India grand strategy was
                     decided, partly on political grounds, by Lord Canning, the governor-general. [.
                     . .] Campbell made some mistakes: for example, his preventing Outram cutting
                     off the mutineers' retreat after their defeat at Lucknow in March 1858, and his
                     appointment of the notoriously bungling Brigadier-General R. Walpole to command
                     in Rohilkhand. Nevertheless, overall Campbell was a successful commander. The
                     mutiny further enhanced his reputation, and also enriched him by prize money.
                     On 14 May 1858 he was promoted general; on 15 January 1858 he was made colonel
                     of his favourite 93rd highlanders. In late 1858 and early 1859 there was
                     indiscipline among the East India Company's European troops over their transfer
                     to the queen's service. Campbell sympathized with their grievances and advised
                     concession and that the men ‘be liberally dealt with’. [. . .] In June 1861, on
                     the foundation of the order, he was appointed a knight companion of the Order
                     of the Star of India, and on 3 July 1858 he was made Baron Clyde of Clydesdale.
                     His health was failing, and so on 4 June 1860 he left India."</quote></note>
            </person>
            <person>
               <persName xml:id="Pratt">Archdeacon Pratt</persName>
               <note>From “Pratt, John Henry” by <bibl><author>Anita McConnell</author></bibl> in
                        <bibl><title>Oxford Dictionary of National Biography</title></bibl>:
                     <quote>“Pratt, John Henry (bap. 1809, d. 1871), Church of England clergyman and
                     mathematician, was baptized on 30 June 1809 at St Mary Woolnoth, London, one of
                     two sons of Josiah Pratt (1768–1844), Church of England clergyman, and his
                     wife, Elizabeth, formerly Jowett. He was educated at Oakham School, Rutland,
                     and entered Gonville and Caius College, Cambridge, in 1829, graduating BA in
                     1833 as third wrangler. He was elected to a fellowship, and proceeded MA in
                     1836. After taking orders he was appointed through the influence of Daniel
                     Wilson, bishop of Calcutta, a chaplain of the East India Company in 1838. He
                     became Wilson's domestic chaplain and in 1850 archdeacon of
                  Calcutta.”</quote></note>
            </person>
            <person>
               <persName xml:id="Ye_Mingchen">Commisioner Yeh</persName>
               <note>From <hi rend="italics">Deadly Dreams</hi>: <quote>"Ye Mingchen (1809-59). He
                     became governor of Guangdong in 1847 and imperial commissioner for foreign
                     affairs and concurrently governor-general of Guangdong and Guangxi in 1852. He
                     was to be captured by the British during the Arrow War and exiled to India,
                     where he starved himself to death."</quote> (6).<bibl><author>J. Y.
                        Wong</author><title>Deadly Dreams: Opium, Imperialism, and the Arrow War
                        (1856-1860) in
                        China</title><pubPlace>Cambridge</pubPlace><publisher>Cambridge University
                        Press</publisher><date>1998</date></bibl></note>
            </person>
            <person>
               <persName xml:id="Sir_Henry_Havelock">General Havelock</persName>
               <note>From “Havelock, Sir Henry” by <bibl><author>James Lunt</author></bibl> in
                        <bibl><title>Oxford Dictionary of National Biography</title></bibl>:
                     <quote>“Havelock, Sir Henry (1795–1857), army officer, was born on Easter day,
                     5 April 1795, at Ford Hall, Bishopwearmouth, near Sunderland, second son of
                     William Havelock (1757–1837), shipbuilder and shipowner, and Jane, daughter of
                     John Carter, solicitor, of Stockton-on-Tees. […] Henry was thrown on his own
                     resources in 1814, having quarrelled with his father, but with his brother
                     William's help, and against his father's wishes, he joined the army. William
                     had already done so and had distinguished himself at Waterloo. Havelock joined
                     the 95th foot (Rifle brigade) and was commissioned second lieutenant on 30 July
                     1815, spending the next eight years at home on garrison duties. He was
                     fortunate to serve under Captain (later Major-General Sir) Harry Smith, a truly
                     professional soldier, who encouraged Havelock to study his profession. He
                     decided to try his fortunes in India (where his brothers William and Charles
                     Frederick were already serving), but not before he had made intensive studies
                     in Hindustani and Persian at the Oriental Institute; he then exchanged into the
                     13th foot (Somerset light infantry) which was under orders for India. He was
                     now a lieutenant but dependent solely on his pay in an army ruled by purchase
                     of promotion. He sailed for India on 3 January 1823 […] On 20 June 1854
                     Havelock obtained his regimental lieutenant-colonelcy and brevet colonelcy. He
                     had left his family in Bonn when he returned to India at the end of 1851. War
                     with Persia was declared on 1 November 1856, and early in 1857 Havelock was
                     given a brigade in a force commanded by Brigadier-General Sir James Outram, an
                     officer of the East India Company. Havelock drew up the plan for the successful
                     attack on Muhammarah, but the war petered out when a peace treaty was signed in
                     Paris on 4 March 1857. Havelock then returned to India, arriving back in Bombay
                     on 20 May to find that the Bengal native army had broken out into mutiny.
                     Travel overland being unsafe, he took the first available ship for Calcutta but
                     was wrecked off Ceylon. He eventually reached Calcutta via Madras on 17 June.
                     He was at once given command of a column to be sent up-country to relieve
                     Cawnpore where the garrison was besieged in makeshift entrenchments. Thereafter
                     he was to support Sir Henry Lawrence who was under siege in the residency
                     compound in Lucknow. Havelock's appointment was not universally approved in
                     Calcutta, but as Lady Canning, wife of the governor-general, was to comment:
                     General Havelock is not in fashion, but all the same we believe he will do
                     well. No doubt he is fussy and tiresome, but his little, old, stiff figure
                     looks as active and fit for use as if he were made of steel. (Pollock, 153)
                     Havelock's force consisted of the 64th foot (North Staffords), four companies
                     of the 78th highlanders (Seaforths), two companies of the 84th (York and
                     Lancaster) regiment, and a detachment of the 1st Madras European fusiliers (an
                     East India Company regiment), the balance of which was in Allahabad under
                     Lieutenant-Colonel J. G. Neill. There was a scratch collection of gunners to
                     serve the six guns, twenty assorted officers and civilians to form the few
                     cavalry, and some native irregulars. In total the force amounted to fewer than
                     2000 all ranks. […] The relief column entered Cawnpore on 17 July, too late to
                     save the hard-pressed garrison or the women and children who had been butchered
                     on the orders of the treacherous Nana Sahib. Lucknow must be the next
                     objective, and on 25 July they crossed the flooded Ganges and set foot in Oudh.
                     […] The relieving force had to fight hard to reach the residency, which it did
                     before it grew dark on 25 September. Outram had been wounded, though not
                     seriously, and Neill was killed. Harry Havelock distinguished himself, but his
                     left arm was broken. He was lucky to escape when the sepoys set about killing
                     the convoy of wounded. He was to return later. Outram was put to bed in the
                     residency, assuming the command the next day, and Havelock was taken to dinner
                     by Mrs Inglis, wife of Colonel John Inglis who had commanded the beleaguered
                     garrison after the death of Sir Henry Lawrence. Havelock had believed the
                     garrison was running short of supplies and was surprised to sit down to a
                     dinner of beef cutlets, with mock turtle soup and champagne. Lucknow had been
                     relieved at a cost of 535 men killed and wounded. Carts for the evacuation of
                     women, children, and wounded were impossible to obtain. It was clear that a
                     retreat to Cawnpore would be a difficult, if not impossible, operation. Outram,
                     with Havelock's agreement, decided to remain in the residency and reinforce its
                     garrison. They knew that the newly arrived commander-in-chief, Sir Colin
                     Campbell, was gathering together a substantial force for Lucknow's relief. It
                     was a wise decision. Campbell finally arrived on 16 November after hard
                     fighting. Outram and Havelock went to meet him and were greeted as ‘Sir James’
                     and ‘Sir Henry’, the first time Havelock learned that he had been made a KCB.
                     There was also a letter from the duke of Cambridge telling Havelock he had been
                     promoted major-general. This was wonderful news, but Havelock was daily growing
                     weaker as a result of dysentery, added to the effects of six months'
                     campaigning in a difficult climate. Nursed by Harry, one arm in a sling, and
                     his faithful aide-de-camp Hargood, Havelock was quietly slipping away. At 9.30
                     a.m. on Monday, 24 November 1857, he finally did so, in the arms of his son, to
                     whom his last words supposedly were, ‘Harry, see how a Christian can die’
                     (Pollock, 252). Campbell had already decided to evacuate the residency, leaving
                     a substantial force under Outram at the Alambagh as a base for a future attack.
                     By the day of Havelock's death the evacuation was virtually complete. They
                     buried him in the garden of the Alambagh, under a mango tree on which Harry
                     carved the letter ‘H’, and took careful measurements of the grave before
                     smoothing it down. It is there to this day.”</quote></note>
            </person>
            <person>
               <persName xml:id="Edward_Southwell_Sotheby">Captain Sotheby</persName>
               <note>From “Sotheby, Sir Edward Southwell” by <bibl><author>by L. G. C. Laughton,
                        rev. Andrew Lambert</author></bibl> in <bibl><title>Oxford Dictionary of
                        National Biography</title></bibl>: <quote>“Sotheby, Sir Edward Southwell
                     (1813–1902), naval officer, born at Clifton, Bristol, on 14 May 1813. […] In
                     July 1857 the Pearl, with the frigate Shannon (Captain William Peel), was sent
                     from Hong Kong to Calcutta on the receipt of news of the outbreak of the Indian
                     mutiny. While on passage, the Pearl rescued the crew of the wrecked transport
                     Transit. Sotheby himself took command of the Pearl's brigade; they were
                     thirteen times mentioned in dispatches relating to the operations in Oudh, and
                     received the thanks of both houses of parliament and of the governor-general of
                     India. Sotheby was made a CB and served as an extra aide-de-camp to the queen
                     (1858–67).”</quote></note>
            </person>
            <person>
               <persName xml:id="Sir_William_Peel">Captain Peel</persName>
               <note>From “Peel, Sir William” by <bibl><author>by J.K. Laughton, rev. Andrew
                        Lambert</author></bibl> in <bibl><title>Oxford Dictionary of National
                        Biography</title></bibl>:<quote>"Peel, Sir William (1824–1858), naval
                     officer, third and favourite son of Sir Robert Peel, second baronet (1788–1850)
                     [and] prime minister. [...] On 13 September 1856 [Peel] commissioned the
                     Shannon, a powerful 50-gun steamfrigate, for service in China. She did not sail
                     until the following March. At Singapore she was met by the news of the Indian
                     mutiny, and took Lord Elgin up to Hong Kong, arriving on 2 July. Admiral Sir
                     Michael Seymour sent the Shannon back to Calcutta on July 16, with Elgin on
                     board, together with a detachment of marines and soldiers. At Calcutta, Peel
                     formed a naval brigade. On 14 August he left the ship with 450 men, six
                     24-pounder Bengal artillery guns, and two 8 inch howitzers. At Allahabad on 20
                     October he was reinforced by a party of 120 men, and from then on was present
                     in all the principal operations. The coolness of his bravery was everywhere
                     remarkable, and his formidable battery gave most efficient service: the huge
                     guns were, under his orders, moved and worked as though they were light field
                     pieces. On 21 January 1858 he was nominated a KCB and an aidede-camp to the
                     queen. In 1858 Peel's brigade employed six naval 8 inch guns from the Shannon.
                     Peel mounted these massive weapons, weighing 65 cwt each, on carriages locally
                     constructed by the sailors. They provided the firepower to overcome the massive
                     walls of Indian forts, and to keep down British casualties. In the second
                     relief of Lucknow on 9 March 1858 Peel was severely wounded in the thigh by a
                     musket bullet, which was cut out from the opposite side of the leg. Still very
                     weak, he reached Cawnpore on his way to England, and there, on 20 April, he
                     contracted smallpox, of which he died on 27 April, aged
                  thirty-three."</quote></note>
            </person>
            <person>
               <persName xml:id="Beauchamp_Seymour">Seymour</persName>
               <note>From “Seymour, Frederick Beauchamp Paget, Baron Alcester” by <bibl><author>by
                        J.K. Laughton, rev. Andrew Lambert</author></bibl> in <bibl><title>Oxford
                        Dictionary of National Biography</title></bibl>:<quote>"Seymour, Frederick
                     Beauchamp Paget, Baron Alcester (1821–1895), naval officer, was born in London
                     on 12 April 1821. He was the son of Colonel Sir Horace Beauchamp Seymour and
                     his first wife, Elizabeth Malet, née Palk (d. 1827), daughter of Sir Lawrence
                     Palk, bt; his grandfather was Lord Hugh Seymour, and his uncle Sir George
                     Francis Seymour. He received his early education at Eton College, and entered
                     the navy in January 1834. [...] In May 1855 [Seymour] was appointed to the
                     floating battery Meteor, which he took out to the Crimea, and brought back to
                     Portsmouth in the early summer of 1856. In July 1857 he commissioned the
                     Pelorus, which he commanded for nearly six years on the Australian station.
                     Between January and April 1858 the Pelorus provided a naval brigade in Burma,
                     playing a vital role in preventing the spread of the mutiny from India. From
                     1860 to 1861 he commanded the naval brigade in New Zealand during the war
                     there, for which he was made a CB on 16 July 1861."</quote></note>
            </person>
            <person>
               <persName xml:id="Outram">Outram</persName>
               <note>From “Outram, Sir James (1803-1863)" in <bibl><title>Encyclopedia
                        Britannica</title></bibl>"<quote>English general, and one of the heroes of
                     the Indian Mutiny, was the son of Benjamin Outram of Butterley Hall,
                     Derbyshire, civil engineer, and was born on the 29th of January 1803. His
                     father died in 1805, and his mother, a daughter of Dr James Anderson, the
                     Scottish writer on agriculture, removed in 1810 to Aberdeenshire. From Udny
                     school the boy went in 1818 to the Marischal College, Aberdeen; and in 1819 an
                     Indian cadet ship was given him. [. . .] Appointed in 1857, with the rank of
                     lieutenant-general, to command an expedition against Persia, he defeated the
                     enemy with great slaughter at Khushab, and conducted the campaign with such
                     rapid decision that peace was shortly afterwards concluded, his services being
                     rewarded by the grand cross of the Bath. From Persia he was summoned in June to
                     India, with the brief explanation — "We want all our best men here." It was
                     said of him at this time that "a fox is a fool and a lion a coward by the side
                     of Sir J. Outram." Immediately on his arrival in Calcutta he was appointed to
                     command the two divisions of the Bengal army occupying the country from
                     Calcutta to Cawnpore; and to the military control was also joined the
                     commissioner ship of Oudh. Already the mutiny had assumed such proportions as
                     to compel Havelock to fall back on Cawnpore, which he only held with
                     difficulty, although a speedy advance was necessary to save the garrison at
                     Lucknow. [. . .] After the capture of Lucknow he was gazetted
                     lieutenant-general. In February 1858 he received the special thanks of both
                     houses of parliament, and in the same year the dignity of baronet with an
                     annuity of £1000."</quote></note>
            </person>
            <person>
               <persName xml:id="Charlotte_Canning">Canning</persName>
               <note>From “Canning [née Stuart], Charlotte Elizabeth, Countess Canning” by
                        <bibl><author>by K.D. Reynolds</author></bibl> in <bibl><title>Oxford
                        Dictionary of National Biography</title></bibl><quote>"Canning [née Stuart],
                     Charlotte Elizabeth, Countess Canning (1817–1861), courtier and vicereine of
                     India, was born at the British embassy in Paris on 31 March 1817, the elder of
                     the two daughters of Sir Charles Stuart, later Baron Stuart de Rothesay
                     (1779–1845), diplomatist, and his wife, Lady Elizabeth Yorke (1789– 1867),
                     daughter of the third earl of Hardwicke. Like her sister Louisa [see Beresford,
                     Louisa, marchioness of Waterford], Charlotte Stuart was celebrated for her
                     beauty, piety, and artistic talent. [. . .] At eighteen she married, on 5 September 1835, Charles John
                     Canning (1812–1862), only surviving son of the prime minister, George Canning,
                     and heir to his mother's viscountcy. [...] In June 1855 Lord Canning accepted
                     the post of governor-general of India. ‘[I] will not take any part in the
                     decision but only be ready to follow like a dog,' [. . .] his wife
                     wrote, rather dispiritedly. They left London in November, travelling to
                     Calcutta via Paris, Malta, and Egypt, pausing in Bombay, Ceylon, and Madras
                     before reaching their destination on 29 February 1856. [. . .] The year of the
                     Indian mutiny, 1857, put a tremendous emotional and physical strain on the
                     Cannings. Charlotte was kept well away from the dangerous areas, but she
                     gathered information assiduously, keeping the queen informed in detail of the
                     events as they unfolded, and was able to dispel some of the worst atrocity
                     stories: ‘there is not a particle of evidence of the poor women having been
                     “ill-used” anywhere’, she wrote. [. . .](Death, murder, starvation, and
                     the mutilation of corpses did not compare to the horror felt at the idea of
                     interracial rape.) To Lady Canning, the queen was able regularly to express her
                     complete confidence in the beleaguered Canning, who was under continual
                     pressure from the British at home and in India to exact a bloody retribution.
                     Canning was able to rely on his wife to communicate with his colleagues in
                     Britain when the pressures of the situation overwhelmed his correspondence.
                     [. . .] The revolt over, Canning was elevated to an
                     earldom, the government of India was removed from the hands of the East India
                     Company, and the governor-generalship was transformed into a viceroyalty. The
                     new vicereine travelled widely throughout India, from Madras in the south, to
                     the borders of Tibet in the north. She sketched and painted as she went, and
                     wrote detailed accounts of her travels to her family and to the queen. Despite
                     the difficulties, she had come to enjoy India, but was looking forward to her
                     frequently postponed return to England, which was set for January 1862. In
                     October 1861 she journeyed through Darjeeling, to the borders of Sikkim, and
                     saw Mount Everest, but her mind was on home and planning for the future there.
                     She returned to Calcutta on 8 November, clearly suffering from ‘jungle fever’,
                     or malaria. Four days later she was confined to bed, and shortly afterwards her
                     mind started wandering, and she died at 2.30 in the morning of 18
                     November."</quote></note>
            </person>
            <person>
               <persName xml:id="George_Horner">George Horner</persName>
               <note>George Horner, a bandsman, joined the <hi rend="italic">Chesapeake</hi> on
                  August 12, 1857. He was born in London in 1817. The muster book for the <hi
                     rend="italic">Chesapeake</hi> claims to offer the first entry for George
                  Horner, perhaps meaning this was his first time at sea.<bibl>Muster Book of Her
                     Majesty's Ship Chesapeake Commencing 1st January 1858 Ending 31st March 1858,"
                     National Archives at Kew (ADM 38/2884)</bibl></note>
            </person>
            <person>
               <persName xml:id="Charles_Stewart">Charles Stewart</persName>
               <note>Charles Stewart, an ordinary seaman, joined the <hi rend="italic"
                     >Chesapeake</hi> on May 23, 1857. He was born in London and served aboard HMS
                  Gladiator just before joining the <hi rend="italic">Chesapeake</hi>. He was born
                  in 1834.<bibl>Muster Book of Her Majesty's Ship Chesapeake Commencing 1st January
                     1858 Ending 31st March 1858," National Archives at Kew (ADM
                  38/2884)</bibl></note>
            </person>
            <person>
               <persName xml:id="Thomas_Walsh">Thomas Walsh</persName>
               <note>Thomas Walsh, an ordinary seaman, joined the <hi rend="italic">Chesapeake</hi>
                  on August 15, 1857. He was born in London in 1834 and served aboard HMS Cressy
                  just before joining the <hi rend="italic">Chesapeake</hi>.<bibl>Muster Book of Her
                     Majesty's Ship Chesapeake Commencing 1st January 1858 Ending 31st March 1858,"
                     National Archives at Kew (ADM 38/2884)</bibl></note>
            </person>
            <person>
               <persName xml:id="Robert_Wilkinson">Robert Wilkinson</persName>
               <note>Robert Wilkinson, a private in the Royal Marines, joined the <hi rend="italic"
                     >Chesapeake</hi> on July 25, 1857. He was born in Sitchfield,
                     Staffordshire.<bibl>Muster Book of Her Majesty's Ship Chesapeake Commencing 1st
                     January 1858 Ending 31st March 1858, held by the National Archives at Kew (ADM
                     38/2884)</bibl></note>
            </person>
            <person>
               <persName xml:id="Henry_Underhill">Henry Underhill</persName>
               <note>Henry Underhill, an ordinary seaman from Alesford, was thirty-six when he came aboard the <hi
                     rend="italic">Chesapeake</hi>.<bibl>Muster Book of Her Majesty's Ship Chesapeake
                     Commencing 1st January 1858 Ending 31st March 1858," National Archives at Kew
                     (ADM 38/2884)</bibl>
               </note>
            </person>
            <person>
               <persName xml:id="John_Welsh">John Welsh</persName>
               <note>John Welsh, an ordinary seaman, joined the <hi rend="italic">Chesapeake</hi> on
                  February 20, 1857. He was born in Mayo<bibl>Muster Book of Her Majesty's Ship
                     Chesapeake Commencing 1st January 1858 Ending 31st March 1858," National
                     Archives at Kew (ADM 38/2884)</bibl></note>
            </person>
            <person>
               <persName xml:id="Henry_Montagu">Henry Montagu</persName>
               <note>Henry Montagu, yeoman of signals, joined the <hi rend="italic">Chesapeake</hi>
                  on July 28, 1857, after serving aboard <hi rend="italic">HMS President</hi>. He was born in St. Hilliers,
                  Jersey (the Channel Islands) in 1826, making him thirty-two at the time of the
                     performance.<bibl>Muster Book of Her Majesty's Ship Chesapeake Commencing 1st
                     January 1858 Ending 31, March 1858," National Archives at Kew (ADM
                     38/2884)</bibl></note>
            </person>
            <person>
               <persName xml:id="Isaac_Wright">Isaac Wright</persName>
               <note>Isaac Wright, an ordinary sailor 2nd class, joined the <hi rend="italic"
                     >Chesapeake</hi> on September 4, 1857. He was born in Sunderland in 1835,
                  making him twenty-three at the time of the performance.<bibl>Muster Book of Her Majesty's
                     Ship Chesapeake Commencing 1st January 1858 Ending 31st March 1858," National
                     Archives at Kew (ADM 38/2884)</bibl></note>
            </person>
            <person>
               <persName xml:id="Henry_Hamilton">Henry Hamilton</persName>
               <note>C. R. B. Hamilton (the only Hamilton in the musters) was a naval cadet who
                  served aboard <orgName ref="Colossus">HMS Colossus</orgName> before joining the
                     <hi rend="italic">Chesapeake</hi> on July 23, 1857. He was born in County
                  Tyrone, Ireland in December of 1842, making him fifteen at the time the
                     performance<bibl>Muster Book of Her Majesty's Ship Chesapeake Commencing 1st
                     January 1858 Ending 31st March 1858, held by the National Archives at Kew (ADM
                     38/2884)</bibl></note>
            </person>
            <person>
               <persName xml:id="James_Brown">James Browne</persName>
               <note>James Brown, an ordinary seaman, joined the <hi rend="italic">Chesapeake</hi>
                  on July 23, 1857, after serving aboard <orgName ref="Cuckoo">HMS Cuckoo</orgName>
                  until February 3, 1857. He was born at Sheerness on the 17th of January 1829,
                  making him twenty-eight at the time of the performance<bibl>Muster Book of Her Majesty's
                     Ship Chesapeake Commencing 1st January 1858 Ending 31st March 1858," National
                     Archives at Kew (ADM 38/2884)</bibl></note>
            </person>
            <person>
               <persName xml:id="William_Connell">William T Connell</persName>
               <note>William T. Connell, an ordinary seaman, joined the <hi rend="italic"
                     >Chesapeake</hi> on July 31 1857, after serving aboard <orgName ref="Eurydice"
                     >HMS Eurydice</orgName> until 17 June 1857. He was born in London in 1835,
                  making him twenty-seven at the time of the performance.<bibl>Muster Book of Her Majesty's
                     Ship Chesapeake Commencing 1st January 1858 Ending 31st March 1858," National
                     Archives at Kew (ADM 38/2884)</bibl></note>
            </person>
            <person>
               <persName xml:id="Taylor">Edward Taylor</persName>
               <note>Edward Taylor, assistant engineer 3rd class (a commissioned officer), joined
                  the <hi rend="italic">Chesapeake</hi> on July 25, 1857. His age was not recorded
                  in the muster book<bibl>Muster Book of Her Majesty's Ship Chesapeake Commencing
                     1st January 1858 Ending 31st March 1858," National Archives at Kew (ADM
                     38/2884)</bibl></note>
            </person>
            <person>
               <persName xml:id="Brownrigg">Charles J. Brownrigg</persName>
               <note>Charles J. Brownrigg, a mate (a commissioned officer), joined the <hi
                     rend="italic">Chesapeake</hi> on August 4th, 1857. His age was not recorded in
                  the muster book.<bibl>Muster Book of Her Majesty's Ship Chesapeake Commencing 1st
                     January 1858 Ending 31st March 1858," National Archives at Kew (ADM
                     38/2884)</bibl></note>
            </person>
            <person>
               <persName xml:id="Wilkinson">Wilkinson</persName>
               <note>Mr. Wilkinson, a clerk (a subordinate officer), joined the <hi rend="italic"
                     >Chesapeake</hi> on July 23, 1857 after serving aboard HMS Majestic. He was
                  born in Suffolk in 1836, which would make him twenty-two at the time of the cricket match
                  in Calcutta<bibl>Muster Book of Her Majesty's Ship Chesapeake Commencing 1st
                     January 1858 Ending 31st March 1858," National Archives at Kew (ADM
                     38/2884)</bibl></note>
            </person>
            <person>
               <persName xml:id="Shortt">John Shortt</persName>
               <note>John Shortt, a subordinate officer, joined the <hi rend="italic"
                     >Chesapeake</hi> on July 23, 1857, after serving aboard HMS Euridice. He was
                  born in Bombay in 1838, making him twenty at the time of this cricket match in
                     Calcutta.<bibl>Muster Book of Her Majesty's Ship Chesapeake Commencing 1st
                     January 1858 Ending 31st March 1858, held by the National Archives at Kew (ADM
                     38/2884)</bibl></note>
            </person>
            <person>
               <persName xml:id="Reynolds">S. Reynolds</persName>
               <note>S. Reynolds, an ordinary seaman, joined the <hi rend="italic">Chesapeake</hi>
                  on September 4, 1857. He was born in Landport (Portsmouth) in 1839, making him nineteen
                  at the time of the cricket match in Calcutta.<bibl>Muster Book of Her Majesty's
                     Ship Chesapeake Commencing 1st January 1858 Ending 31st March 1858," National
                     Archives at Kew (ADM 38/2884)</bibl></note>
            </person>
            <person>
               <persName xml:id="Theobald">C.B. Theobald</persName>
               <note>C. B. Theobald, a naval cadet, joined the <hi rend="italic">Chesapeake</hi> on
                  July 24, 1857. He was born in Mark's Tey, Essex, in 1843, making him fifteen at the time
                  of the cricket match in Calcutta.<bibl>Muster Book of Her Majesty's Ship
                     Chesapeake Commencing 1st January 1858 Ending 31st March 1858," National
                     Archives at Kew (ADM 38/2884)</bibl></note>
            </person>
            <person>
               <persName xml:id="Cooper">Cooper</persName>
               <note>There are three different members of the ship's company with the last name
                  Cooper. The only thing we can tell about the "Cooper" referenced in the cricket
                  match is that he was not a commissioned officer, but an ordinary
                     seaman.<bibl>Muster Book of Her Majesty's Ship Chesapeake Commencing 1st
                     January 1858 Ending 31st March 1858," National Archives at Kew (ADM
                     38/2884)</bibl></note>
            </person>
            <person>
               <persName xml:id="Chute">Charles T. Chute</persName>
               <note>Charles T. Chute, a subordinate officer, joined the <hi rend="italic"
                     >Chesapeake</hi> on July 23, 1857, after serving aboard Euridice. He was born
                  in London in 1841, making him seventeen at the time of the cricket match in
                     Calcutta.<bibl>Muster Book of Her Majesty's Ship Chesapeake Commencing 1st
                     January 1858 Ending 31st March 1858, held by the National Archives at Kew (ADM
                     38/2884)</bibl></note>
            </person>
            <person>
               <persName xml:id="Bew">James Bew</persName>
               <note>James Bew, an experienced seaman, joined the <hi rend="italic">Chesapeake</hi>
                  on August 1, 1857. He was born in 1833, making him twenty-five at the time of the cricket
                  match in Calcutta.<bibl>Muster Book of Her Majesty's Ship Chesapeake Commencing
                     1st January 1858 Ending 31st March 1858," National Archives at Kew (ADM
                     38/2884)</bibl></note>
            </person>
            <person>
               <persName xml:id="Oxley">C.L. Oxley</persName>
               <note>C. L. Oxley, a midshipman, joined the <hi rend="italic">Chesapeake</hi> on July
                  29, 1857. He was born in 1841, making him seventeen at the time of the cricket match in
                     Calcutta.<bibl>Muster Book of Her Majesty's Ship Chesapeake Commencing 1st
                     January 1858 Ending 31st March 1858," National Archives at Kew (ADM
                     38/2884)</bibl></note>
            </person>
            <person>
               <persName xml:id="Behadoor">Rajah Behadoor</persName>
               <note>Still searching for biographical details on Rajah Behadoor</note>
            </person>
            <person>
               <persName xml:id="Hope">Hope</persName>
               <note>Hope played for the "squadron's eleven" and does not appear in the Chesapeake muster
                  book, which means he likely belonged to another ship in the squadron.<bibl>Muster
                     Book of Her Majesty's Ship Chesapeake Commencing 1st January 1858 Ending 31st
                     March 1858," National Archives at Kew (ADM 38/2884)</bibl></note>
            </person>
            <person>
               <persName xml:id="Haswell">Haswell</persName>
               <note>Haswell served aboard <hi rend="italic">Himalaya</hi> until he was injured and
                  replaced by Piers.<bibl>Muster Book of Her Majesty's Ship Chesapeake Commencing
                     1st January 1858 Ending 31st March 1858," National Archives at Kew (ADM
                     38/2884)</bibl></note>
            </person>
            <person>
               <persName xml:id="Kelly">Lieutenant Edward Kelly</persName>
               <note>Lieutenant Edward Kelly does not appear in the muster book of HMS <hi
                     rend="italic">Chesapeake</hi>. <bibl>Muster Book of Her Majesty's Ship
                     Chesapeake Commencing 1st January 1858 Ending 31st March 1858," National
                     Archives at Kew (ADM 38/2884)</bibl></note>
            </person>
            <person>
               <persName xml:id="Parkin">George H. Parkin</persName>
               <note>George H. Parkin was named acting commander of HMS <hi rend="italic"
                     >Chesapeake</hi> on February 1, 1858, and he came aboard on February 25 after
                  serving aboard <hi rend="italic">Roebuck</hi>. <bibl>Muster Book of Her Majesty's Ship Chesapeake
                     Commencing 1st January 1858 Ending 31st March 1858," National Archives at Kew
                     (ADM 38/2884)</bibl></note>
            </person>
            <person>
               <persName xml:id="Piers">S.B. Piers</persName>
               <note>S. B. Piers, a commander, joined the <hi rend="italic">Chesapeake</hi> on July
                  28, 1857. He was discharged on January 22, 1858, to serve aboard HMS <hi
                     rend="italic">Himalaya</hi> when Vice Captain Haswell was
                     invalided.<bibl>Muster Book of Her Majesty's Ship Chesapeake Commencing 1st
                     January 1858 Ending 31st March 1858," National Archives at Kew (ADM
                     38/2884)</bibl></note>
            </person>

         </listPerson>
      </body>
   </text>
</TEI>
