<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<?xml-model href="file:/Users/misbell/Dropbox/IsbellExtractsfromTYIScholarlyEditing2016/Revised%20Files%20November%202015/out/2015Schemawithvaluerestritions.rng" type="application/xml" schematypens="http://relaxng.org/ns/structure/1.0"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xmlns:mi="http://www.newhaven.edu/ns/nonTEI">
    <teiHeader>
        <fileDesc>
            <titleStmt>
                <title level="m" type="main">1867 Preface to The Young Idea</title>
                <author>A.D. McArthur</author>
                <editor>Mary Isbell</editor>
                <respStmt>
                    <resp>Transcription, encoding, schema design, collation, and notes</resp>
                    <name xml:id="initials">Mary Isbell</name>
                </respStmt>
                <respStmt>
                    <resp>Transcription and encoding</resp>
                    <name>Teresa Navarro</name>
                </respStmt>
                <respStmt>
                    <resp>Transcription and encoding</resp>
                    <name>Katelyn Sahagian</name>
                </respStmt>
                
            </titleStmt>
            <editionStmt>
                <edition>
                    <date>2016</date>
                </edition>
            </editionStmt>
            <publicationStmt>
                <authority>Scholarly Editing: The Annual of the Association for Documentary
                    Editing</authority>
                <idno type="file">preface.youngidea</idno>
                <idno type="edition">youngidea</idno>
                <address>
                    <addrLine>http://www.scholarlyediting.org</addrLine>
                </address>
                <publisher>Association for Documentary Editing</publisher>
                <publisher>University of Nebraska&#8211;Lincoln</publisher>
                <distributor>
                    <name>Center for Digital Research in the Humanities</name>
                    <address>
                        <addrLine>319 Love Library</addrLine>
                        <addrLine>University of Nebraska&#8211;Lincoln</addrLine>
                        <addrLine>Lincoln, NE 68588-4100</addrLine>
                        <addrLine>http://cdrh.unl.edu</addrLine>
                    </address>
                </distributor>
                <date>2016</date>
                <availability>
                    <p>Scholarly Editing: The Annual of the Association for Documentary Editing is
                        freely distributed by the Association for Documentary Editing and the Center
                        for Digital Research in the Humanities at the University of Nebraska-Lincoln
                        and licensed under a Creative Commons Attribution-NonCommercial-ShareAlike
                        3.0 Unported License</p>
                </availability>
            </publicationStmt>
            <seriesStmt>
                <title level="j">Scholarly Editing: The Annual of the Association for Documentary
                    Editing</title>
                <respStmt>
                    <resp>editor</resp>
                    <name xml:id="ag">Amanda Gailey</name>
                </respStmt>
                <respStmt>
                    <resp>editor</resp>
                    <name xml:id="awj">Andrew Jewell</name>
                </respStmt>
                <idno type="vol"><!-- The Journal's volume number --></idno>
                <idno type="ISSN">2167-1257</idno>
            </seriesStmt>
            <sourceDesc>
                <biblStruct>
                    <monogr>
                        <editor>A.D. McArthur</editor>
                        <title>The Young Idea: A Naval Journal Edited on Board the H.M.S. Chesapeake
                            in 1857, 1858 &amp; 1859 </title>
                        <idno type="callno">Edition created from copy in editor's private
                            collection, only other known copy held at British Library:
                            1757.a.20/</idno>
                        <imprint>
                            <date>1867</date>
                            <biblScope>
                                <!-- type="pubPlace" -->
                                <ref type="address">170 Fleet Street, London, England</ref>
                                <name type="publisher">Paul Jerrard &amp; Son</name>
                            </biblScope>
                            <note type="project">First known transcription from 1867 facsimile
                                edition. paragraph breaks, column breaks, and page breaks have been
                                preserved within the transcription. Abbreviations and spellings have
                                been maintained within the transcriptions, and the full word and
                                corrected or modern spellings have been provided. Images of the
                                original pages have been provided in order to show the original page
                                layout. Words or phrases that are deemed indecipherable have been
                                noted as "unclear." To provide further information as to the context
                                of the extracts, notations have been provided.</note>
                        </imprint>
                    </monogr>
                </biblStruct>
            </sourceDesc>
        </fileDesc>
    </teiHeader>
    <text>
        <body>
            <pb n="TYI0009" facs="TYI0009"/>
            <div type="paratext">
                <head>
                    <figure>
                        <figDesc>A bodiless head facing to the left is blowing wind on seven boats.
                            Each boat has a letter to spell out the word "Preface."</figDesc>
                        <graphic url="TYI0009a.jpg"/>
                    </figure>
                </head>
                <p>The Young Idea! what a funny name, what does it mean? I fancy I hear some one
                    exclaim, as they take up this volume; and that reminds me that perhaps a few
                    words of explanation as to the title and object of this work would not be
                    amiss.</p>
                
                <p>The good ship <mi:shipName ref="shipography.xml#Chesapeake"
                    >“Chesapeake”</mi:shipName>, newly commissioned, was speeding on her way to
                    the burning coasts of India in the last month of 1857, and all hands were shaken
                    into their proper places by a voyage of 52 days from England to the Cape, where
                    we had touched for a day or two; when a party of young Officers were skylarking
                    outside the midshipmen’s berth, vainly endeavouring to dispel the monotony of
                    the voyage, and suddenly one proposed that a newspaper should be got up, and
                    amidst the roar of delight which greeted the proposal, it was further carried
                    “nemine dissentiente” That I should be the Editor of the same. <quote
                        source="officer">“What is it to be called?”</quote> asked one, <quote
                            source="officer">‘“Chesapeake Times”’</quote> cried one; <quote
                                source="officer">‘Steerage Gazette’</quote>, shouted another, while various
                    other appellations were offered, but all agreed that they were common, and this
                    must be something uncommon - <quote source="officer">“What do you say to the
                        “Young Idea”</quote>? at last proposed one, <quote source="officer">“Yes!
                            Yes! that will do”</quote>, they shouted, <note><p>The title for the
                                newspaper is taken from James Thomson's <hi rend="italic">Seasons</hi>,
                                a collection of poems that was incredibly popular with Victorian
                                readers. The particular line is from "Spring": Delightful task! to rear
                                the tender thought, To teach the young idea how to shoot (Spring l.
                                1149-1150).</p> McArthur explains the metaphor in the first issue of the
                                paper as follows:<quote>
                                    <p>Everything must have a beginning; whether it be one to astonish by
                                        its graudeur, and perfectness; or to promote mere commonplace
                                        expressions of pleasure; or what is still more frequently the case,
                                        to receive a casual glance, and to be cast from our minds as
                                        unworthy a second thought: yet, how often do we see, that the latter
                                        class of endeavours, will, in the end, be more successful than those
                                        which promised so much at first, but which finally lose their power
                                        as they proceed.</p>
                                    <p>Even so, let us hope, — altho’ our columns may contain naught of
                                        great promise, when first displayed to the criticising world; that
                                        every week we may gain greater strength, and afford greater
                                        pleasure, and amusement to our readers.</p>
                                    <p> We may be allowed to compare the opening of this Journal to the
                                        sowing of a seed, which, when put into the ground <cb/> is of no
                                        present worth, but which by due care and attention being paid to its
                                        culture, shoots up and increases in growth every day till its
                                        flowers burst forth and well repay the labour bestowed upon its
                                        infancy.</p>
                                    <p> We, then, require that this “Young Idea” may be “taught to” “shoot”
                                        by all those who have any consideration for its advancement, and
                                        they will by assisting, and giving their valuable help, act as
                                        gardeners, in rearing from this feeble commencement, a source of
                                        never ending pastime.</p>
                                    <p> To Critics, we would say one or two words’ let them not nip the bud,
                                        and thus destroy the flower, but rather, repair any faults by adding
                                        their tribute to the pages of the “Young Idea.”</p>
                                </quote></note><quote source="officer">“we’ll teach it to shoot.”</quote>
                    and thus it was that the Chesapeake Journal was christened with the title of the
                    “Young Idea.” </p>
                
                <p>And now, as to its object. Newspapers are not generally regarded on board
                    men-of-war, with a friendly eye by the Officers in command, on account of the
                    opportunity which they afford the Juniors of quizzing them, and the Superior
                    Officers, and making impertinent remarks upon their acts, thus setting
                    discipline at defiance;— but when I took the editorial pen, it was my fixed
                    determination to exclude all such emanations, and to fill the weekly sheet with
                    nothing but what was amusing without being personal, “with narratives of
                    pleasure trips, descriptions of places visited, entertaining anecdotes and
                    instructive information, and with such general matter as in future years should
                    bring to remembrance the occurrences of by-gone days: in spite of my resolve,
                    however, I found my paper met with much opposition at first, but through the aid
                    of my dear friend the Reverend <persName ref="personography.xml#J_W_L_Bampfield"
                        >J.W. Bampfield</persName>, the Chaplain, whose sole delight appeared to be
                    in contributing to the pleasure of those around him, the paper gradually became
                    a great favorite with all, and was eagerly looked for on the Saturday Evenings
                    as the Daily Papers are at home on the morning of their publication. Far beyond
                    the anticipation of many, this little Journal went on from week to week, at
                    times hindered by some uncontrollable circumstances, but still progressing; when
                    a change in my duties, on the occasion of the “Chesapeake” becoming the Flagship
                    in China <note>McArthur was promoted to assistant paymaster and secretary clerk.
                        <bibl>Muster Book of Her Majesty's Ship Chesapeake Commencing 1st April
                            1859 Ending 30th June 1859, held by the National Archives at Kew (ADM
                            38/2886)</bibl></note>, rendered it a matter of impossibility for one to
                    continue its production, and it was with regret of no slight nature that I found
                    myself under the<pb n="TYI0010" facs="TYI0010"/> necessity of ceasing to issue
                    it; the more especially as the new and varied scenes of the “Celestial Empire”
                    opened up a never failing source of interest and amusement. </p>
                
                <p>There will, doubtless, be found many terms and expressions herein, unintelligible
                    to fair readers, (may there be many such) and others whose education has not
                    been on the stormy deep, for an explanation of which I must refer them to the
                    first Naval man they meet, as it would be more than I could undertake here; and
                    some few other remarks which were only to be understood by those who were
                    associated with them, I have endeavoured to explain in a short appendix at the
                    end of the work.</p>
                
                <p>And now, when some years have fled, and the events which these pages record have,
                    perhaps, faded from recollection, I have yielded to the solicitation of friends,
                    and have given it afresh to the world. I make no apology for its many faults,
                    for I am content to leave it to the kindly criticism of those into whose hands
                    it may fall, hoping that to them it may prove as great source of pleasure as it
                    did to those for whom its pages were first penned.</p>
                
                <p>I cannot conclude without expressing my hearty thanks to those who have aided me
                    in the reproducing this work; more especially to my kind friend, Admiral
                    <persName ref="personography.xml#Edgell">Edgell</persName>, CB, to whom I am
                    greatly indebted not merely for much interest and trouble taken in endeavouring
                    to obtain subscribers, but also for the aid he gave me with his own pen as a
                    Contributor to the Journal. There is also one other to whom I must especially
                    return my sincere thanks for his hearty co-operation and valuable assistance,
                    without which my efforts must have been vain; to his pen may be traced much that
                    is best worth reading in these pages,- and it is with great pleasure that I
                    offer this tribute of my esteem and regard, to my dear friend the Rev<hi
                        rend="superscript">d</hi><persName ref="personography.xml#J_W_L_Bampfield"
                            >John W.L. Bampfield.</persName>
                </p>
                
                <p>And now, with these few prefatory remarks, I launch my “Young Idea” upon the sea
                    of Public Opinion, — knowing full well the many storms which ruffle that vast
                    expanse — and despatch it with these simple sailing directions, <quote>“Omnibus
                        placeto.”</quote><lb/><placeName ref="placeography.xml#Balham">Balham</placeName><lb/>July 1867<lb/><figure>
                            <figDesc>A hand is seen placing a book with the title "Young Idea" out into
                                the water. The book has been made into a small sailboat. The water is
                                labeled "PUBLIC OPINION"</figDesc>
                            <graphic url="TYI0010a.jpg"/>
                        </figure></p>
            </div>
        </body>
    </text>
    
</TEI>
