<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<?oxygen RNGSchema="http://www.scholarlyediting.org/scholarlyediting.rng" type="xml"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xml:lang="eng">
    <teiHeader>
        <fileDesc>
            <titleStmt>
                <title level="a" type="main">Recent Editions</title>
                <title level="a" type="sub">2015</title>
                <author key="Hickman, Ellen C.">Ellen C. Hickman</author>
            </titleStmt>
            <editionStmt>
                <edition>
                    <date>2015</date>
                </edition>
            </editionStmt>
            <publicationStmt>
                <idno type="file">review.recenteditions2015</idno>
                <authority>Scholary Editing: The Annual of the Association for Documentary
                    Editing</authority>
                <address>
 <addrLine>http://www.scholarlyediting.org</addrLine>
</address>
                <publisher>Association for Documentary Editing</publisher>
                <publisher>University of Nebraska&#8211;Lincoln</publisher>
                <distributor>
                    <name>Center for Digital Research in the Humanities</name>
                    <address>
<addrLine>319 Love Library</addrLine>
<addrLine>University of Nebraska&#8211;Lincoln</addrLine>
<addrLine>Lincoln, NE 68588-4100</addrLine>
<addrLine>http://cdrh.unl.edu</addrLine>
 </address>
                </distributor>
                <date>2015</date>
                <availability>
                    <p>Scholary Editing: The Annual of the Association for Documentary Editing is
                        freely distributed by the Association for Documentary Editing and the Center
                        for Digital Research in the Humanities at the University of Nebraska-Lincoln
                        and licensed under a Creative Commons Attribution-NonCommercial-ShareAlike
                        3.0 Unported License</p>
                </availability>
            </publicationStmt>
            <seriesStmt>
                <title level="j">Scholarly Editing: The Annual of the Association for Documentary
                    Editing</title>
                <respStmt>
                    <resp>editor</resp>
                    <name xml:id="ag" key="Gailey, Amanda A.">Amanda Gailey</name>
                </respStmt>
                <respStmt>
                    <resp>editor</resp>
                    <name xml:id="awj" key="Jewell, Andrew W.">Andrew Jewell</name>
                </respStmt>
                <idno type="vol">36</idno>
                <idno type="ISSN">2167-1257</idno>
            </seriesStmt>
            <sourceDesc>
                <bibl>
                    <note>Born digital.</note>
                </bibl>
            </sourceDesc>
        </fileDesc>
        <revisionDesc>
            <change when="2015-02-19"><name xml:id="lkw" key="Kirilloff, Gabi">Gabi Kirilloff</name>
                markup in TEI XML</change>
        </revisionDesc>
    </teiHeader>
    <text>

        <front>
            <head type="main">Recent Editions</head>

            <byline>Compiled by Ellen C. Hickman</byline>
        </front>
        <body>
            <p>This annual bibliography of documentary editions recently published in the fields of
                American and British history, literature, and culture is generally restricted to
                scholarly first editions of English-language works.</p>


            <list type="simple">
                <item><p>ADAMS, JOHN. <hi rend="italic">Papers of John Adams, Volume 17:
                            April–November 1785</hi>. Edited by Gregg L. Lint, C. James Taylor, Sara
                        Georgini, Hobson Woodward, Sara B. Sikes, Amanda A. Matthews, and Sara
                        Martin. Belknap Press of Harvard University Press. 2014. 768 pp. $95. ISBN:
                        9780674728950. In this volume Adams began his work as minister to Great
                        Britain while continuing to serve as minister to the Netherlands and as one
                        of the joint commissioners charged with negotiating commercial treaties with
                        the nations of Europe and North Africa. He protected American credit,
                        petitioned for the release of impressed sailors, championed the needs of the
                        American Episcopal Church, and laid the groundwork for negotiations with the
                        Barbary States.</p></item>

                <item><p>ADAMS, LOUISA CATHERINE. <hi rend="italic">A Traveled First Lady: Writings
                            of Louisa Catherine Adams</hi>. Edited by Margaret A. Hogan and C. James
                        Taylor. Belknap Press of Harvard University Press. 2014. 416 pp. $35. ISBN:
                        9780674048010. These excerpts from diaries and memoirs recount Louisa
                        Catherine Adams’s early years in London and Paris, her courtship and
                        marriage to John Quincy Adams, her time in the lavish courts of Berlin and
                        St. Petersburg as a diplomat’s wife, and her years aiding John Quincy’s
                        political career in Washington.</p></item>

                <item><p>AMERICAN REVOLUTION. <hi rend="italic">Naval Documents of the American
                            Revolution, Volume 12: American Theater, April 1, 1778–May 31, 1778;
                            European Theater, April 1, 1778–May 31, 1778</hi>. Edited by Michael J.
                        Crawford. Defense Department, Navy, Naval History and Heritage Command.
                        2013. 1,029 pp. $99. ISBN: 9780945274728. This work synthesizes edited
                        documents, including correspondence, ship logs, muster rolls, orders, and
                        newspaper accounts, that provide a comprehensive understanding of the war at
                        sea in the spring of 1778. In this period the British consolidate their
                        strength in the Mid-Atlantic, and the Americans threaten British shipping in
                        European waters and gain a powerful ally as France prepares to enter the
                        war.</p></item>

                <item><p>AMERICAN WEST. <hi rend="italic">Before the Big Bonanza: Dan De Quille’s
                            Early Comstock Accounts</hi>. Edited by Donnelyn Curtis and Lawrence I.
                        Berkove. University of Missouri Press. 2014. 320 pp. $60. ISBN:
                        9780826220387. Using the pen name Dan De Quille, in 1876 William Wright
                        published <hi rend="italic">The Big Bonanza</hi>, the best-known contemporary account of the
                        Comstock Lode mines. Previously, however, in nearly fifty newspaper accounts
                        from 1860 to 1863, De Quille had already begun to document the development
                        of the early Comstock. These accounts are collected here in a single edition
                        for the first time.</p></item>

                <item><p>AMERICAN WEST. <hi rend="italic">The Great Medicine Road, Part 1:
                            Narratives of the Oregon, California, and Mormon Trails, 1840–1848</hi>.
                        Edited by Michael L. Tate. University of Oklahoma Press. 2014. 356 pp.
                        $39.95. ISBN: 9780870624285. Between 1841 and 1866 more than 500,000 people
                        followed trails to Oregon, California, and the Salt Lake Valley. This
                        collection of travelers’ accounts of their journeys in the 1840s, the first
                        volume in a new series of trail narratives, comprises excerpts from pioneer
                        and missionary letters, diaries, journals, and memoirs—many previously
                        unpublished—accompanied by biographical information and historical
                        background.</p></item>

                <item><p>APPALACHIA. <hi rend="italic">Once I Too Had Wings: The Journals of Emma
                            Bell Miles, 1908–1918</hi>. Edited by Steven Cox. Ohio University Press.
                        2014. 352 pp. $59.95. ISBN: 9780821420867. Emma Bell Miles (1879–1919) was a
                        published writer, poet, naturalist, and artist with a keen perspective on
                        Appalachian life and culture. Between 1908 and 1918 Miles kept a series of
                        journals in which she recorded the natural wonders and local customs of
                        Walden’s Ridge in southeast Tennessee. She documented the difficulties of
                        mountain life, the plight of women in rural communities, the effect of
                        disparities in class and wealth, and her struggles with
                    tuberculosis.</p></item>

                <item><p>ASQUITH, MARGOT. <hi rend="italic">Margot Asquith’s Great War Diary,
                            1914–1916: The View from Downing Street</hi>. Edited by Michael Brock
                        and Eleanor Brock. Oxford University Press. 2014. 568 pp. $49.95. ISBN:
                        9780198229773. Margot Asquith was the wife of Prime Minister Herbert Henry
                        Asquith. Her diary evokes the wartime milieu, as experienced in 10 Downing
                        Street, and describes the political battles that lay behind the warfare on
                        the Western Front. Her writing includes character sketches of acquaintances
                        such as Lloyd George, Churchill, and Kitchener. This volume brings together
                        a wealth of previously unpublished source material with an introductory
                        essay.</p></item>

                <item><p>BACON, ANNE. <hi rend="italic">The Letters of Lady Anne Bacon</hi>. Edited
                        by Gemma Allen. Cambridge University Press. 2014. 312 pp. $80. ISBN:
                        9781107056541. The letters of Lady Anne Bacon (1528–1610), mother of
                        philosopher Francis Bacon, are made accessible for the first time in this
                        edition. Her correspondence sheds light not only on the activities of early
                        modern elite women but also on well-known Elizabethan figures, including her
                        children, her privy councillor relatives, and controversial figures,
                        including the Earl of Essex. Translations of Lady Anne’s frequent use of
                        Latin, Greek, and Hebrew reveal the impact of her humanist education on her
                        correspondence.</p></item>

                <item><p>BECKETT, SAMUEL. <hi rend="italic">The Letters of Samuel Beckett, Volume 3:
                            1957–1965</hi>. Edited by George Craig, Martha Dow Fehsenfeld, Dan Gunn,
                        and Lois More Overbeck. Cambridge University Press. 2014. 816 pp. $50. ISBN:
                        9780521867955. This volume of Beckett’s correspondence covers the years when
                        he is striving to find a balance between the demands of his growing fame and
                        his need for peace and silence for writing. In this period Beckett launches
                        into work for radio, film, and later, into television. He also returns to
                        writing fiction, with his first major piece for a decade, <hi rend="italic"
                            >Comment c’est (How It Is)</hi>. More than ever, he devotes many letters
                        to explaining his work in progress.</p></item>

                <item><p>BRADBURY, RAY. <hi rend="italic">The Collected Stories of Ray Bradbury: A
                            Critical Edition. Volume 2, 1943–1944</hi>. Edited by Jonathan R. Eller.
                        Kent State University Press. 2014. 576 pp. $75. ISBN: 9781606351956. <hi
                            rend="italic">The Collected Stories of Ray Bradbury</hi> series returns
                        to the earliest surviving forms of Bradbury’s oldest published tales and
                        seeks to restore the author’s earliest intentions by searching through
                        long-lost typescripts, elusive magazine issues, and thousands of textual
                        variants. This volume contains twenty-five stories, including eight that
                        Bradbury never placed in his own story collections.</p></item>

                <item><p>BURNEY, FRANCES. <hi rend="italic">The Court Journals and Letters of
                            Frances Burney, Volume III and IV: 1788</hi>. Edited by Lorna J. Clark.
                        Oxford University Press. 2014. 824 pp. $350. ISBN: 9780199688142. The third
                        and fourth of six volumes that will present in their entirety Frances
                        Burney’s journals and letters from July 1786, when she assumed the position
                        of Keeper of the Robes to Queen Charlotte, to her resignation in July 1791.
                        The edition removes the overlay of deletions and additions made by Burney in
                        later life or by subsequent editors.</p></item>

                <item><p>CARTER, THOMAS HENRY. <hi rend="italic">A Gunner in Lee’s Army: The Civil
                            War Letters of Thomas Henry Carter</hi>. Edited by Graham T. Dozier.
                        University of North Carolina Press. 2014. 392 pp. $39.95. ISBN:
                        9781469618746. In May 1861 Virginian Thomas Henry Carter (1831–1908) raised
                        an artillery battery and joined the Confederate army. Carter rose to be
                        among the senior artillerists in Lee’s Army of Northern Virginia. During the
                        war, Carter wrote more than one hundred letters to his wife that discuss his
                        interactions with prominent officers and give observations on military
                        operations, with notes on the home front and the debate over the impressment
                        and arming of slaves.</p></item>

                <item><p>CHAPLIN, CHARLIE. <hi rend="italic">A Comedian Sees the World</hi>. Edited
                        by Lisa Stein Haven. University of Missouri Press. 2014. 224 pp. $29.95.
                        ISBN: 9780826220400. The first full edition of Charlie Chaplin’s memoir of
                        his 1931–32 tour of Europe. Originally published as a series of articles,
                        this edition includes an introduction and notes to supplement Chaplin’s
                        writings and enhance the narrative. The memoir is one of his earliest
                        writings, and marks Chaplin’s transition to becoming vocally political.
                        Chaplin met with numerous politicians, celebrities, and world leaders in his
                        travels.</p></item>

                <item><p>CIVIL WAR. <hi rend="italic">A Documentary History of the American Civil
                            War Era, Volume 3: Judicial Decisions, 1857–1866</hi>. Edited by Thomas
                        C. Mackey. University of Tennessee Press. 2014. 553 pp. $65. ISBN:
                        9781621900054. <hi rend="italic">Volume 4: Judicial Decisions,
                            1867–1896</hi>. 2014. 642 pp. $70. ISBN: 9781621900405. This series is
                        the first comprehensive collection of public policy actions, political
                        speeches, and judicial decisions related to the Civil War. Volume 3 contains
                        some of the classic judicial decisions of the time, such as the 1857
                        decision in <hi rend="italic">Dred Scott</hi> and the 1861 <hi rend="italic"
                            >Ex parte Merryman</hi> decision as well as more obscure decisions.
                        Volume 4 includes <hi rend="italic">Plessy v. Ferguson</hi> and other
                        postwar decisions. Volumes include headnotes and introductory
                    essays.</p></item>

                <item><p>COCHISE. <hi rend="italic">Cochise: Firsthand Accounts of the Chiricahua
                            Apache Chief</hi>. Edited by Edwin R. Sweeney. University of Oklahoma
                        Press. 2014. 320 pp. $49.95. ISBN: 9780806144320. Much of what is known of
                        Cochise is drawn from military reports, eyewitness accounts, letters, and
                        numerous interviews the usually reticent chief granted in the last decade of
                        his life. This volume brings together the most revealing of these documents
                        to provide a nuanced, multifaceted portrait of the Apache leader. In
                        particular, the interviews, many printed here for the first time, are the
                        closest thing to autobiographical material on this notable man.</p></item>

                <item><p>DARWIN, CHARLES. <hi rend="italic">The Correspondence of Charles Darwin,
                            Volume 21: 1873</hi>. Edited by Frederick Burkhardt and James A. Secord.
                        Cambridge University Press. 2014. 826 pp. $145. ISBN: 9781107052147. This
                        volume includes letters from 1873, the year in which Darwin received
                        responses to his work on human and animal expression. He also continued his
                        work on carnivorous plants and plant movement, finding unexpected
                        similarities between the plant and animal kingdoms, raised a subscription
                        for his friend Thomas Henry Huxley, and decided to employ a scientific
                        secretary for the first time—his son Francis.</p></item>

                <item><p>DAVIS, EMILIE. <hi rend="italic">Emilie Davis’s Civil War: The Diaries of a
                            Free Black Woman in Philadelphia, 1863–1865</hi>. Edited by Judith
                        Giesberg. Penn State University Press. 2014. 160 pp. $16.95. ISBN:
                        9780271063683. Davis was a free African American woman who lived in
                        Philadelphia during the Civil War. She worked as a seamstress and attended
                        the Institute for Colored Youth. Her daily entries from 1863 to 1865 discuss
                        her own and her community’s reactions to events such as the Battle of
                        Gettysburg, the Emancipation Proclamation, and the assassination of
                        President Lincoln, as well as the minutiae of social life in Philadelphia’s
                        black community.</p></item>

                <item><p>DE MAN, PAUL. <hi rend="italic">The Paul de Man Notebooks</hi>. Edited by
                        Martin McQuillan. Edinburgh University Press. 2014. 224 pp. $162. ISBN:
                        9780748641048. This anthology collects thirty-six texts and papers from the
                        de Man archive, including essays on art and literature, translations,
                        critical fragments, research plans, interviews, and reports on the state of
                        comparative literature. Contains a number of substantial, previously
                        unpublished and untranslated texts by de Man.</p></item>

                <item><p>DUNCAN, ROBERT. <hi rend="italic">The Collected Writings of Robert Duncan,
                            Book 3: The Collected Later Poems and Plays</hi>. Edited by Peter
                        Quartermain. University of California Press. 2014. 928 pp. $49.95. ISBN:
                        9780520259294. This second volume of Duncan’s collected poetry and plays
                        presents authoritative annotated texts of both collected and uncollected
                        work from his middle and late writing years (1958–1988), with commentaries
                        on each of the five books from this period.</p></item>

                <item><p>DUNCAN, ROBERT. <hi rend="italic">The Collected Writings of Robert Duncan,
                            Book 4: The Collected Essays and Other Prose</hi>. Edited by James
                        Maynard. University of California Press. 2014. 592 pp. $60. ISBN:
                        9780520267732. This volume gathers a far-reaching selection of Duncan’s
                        prose writings, including most of his longer and better known essays along
                        with other prose that has never been widely available. Ranging in original
                        publication dates between 1940 and 1985, the forty-one titles reveal his
                        impressions of poets whose work he admired.</p></item>

                <item><p>EIGHTEENTH CENTURY. <hi rend="italic">The Correspondence of William
                            Stukeley and Maurice Johnson, 1714–1754</hi>. Edited by Diana Honeybone
                        and Michael Honeybone. Lincoln Record Society. 2014. 342 pp. $70. ISBN:
                        9780901503985. Presents both sides of a correspondence between two
                        remarkable Lincolnshire friends, the antiquaries William Stukeley
                        (1687–1765) and Maurice Johnson (1688–1755). The two wrote on a wide range
                        of topics, including current affairs, political scandals, financial
                        disasters like the South Sea Bubble, and the threat of Jacobite invasions.
                        The letters reflect cultural life: the founding of the British Museum,
                        operatic performances, and activities of the Royal Society and Society of
                        Antiquaries.</p></item>

                <item><p>ELIZABETH I. <hi rend="italic">A Knight of Malta at the Court of Elizabeth
                            I: The Correspondence of Michel de Seure, French Ambassador,
                            1560–62</hi>. Edited by David Potter. Cambridge University Press. 2014.
                        204 pp. $80. ISBN: 9781107092938. The reports of French ambassadors from the
                        1560s are only preserved in fragments, and until recently it was believed
                        that nothing survived of the reports of Michel de Seure, ambassador to
                        England from February 1560 to February 1562. Collected here, these shed
                        light on the difficulties of negotiating with Elizabeth I, her
                        preoccupations in 1560–61, and French opinions on her policy.</p></item>

                <item><p>FRANKLIN, BENJAMIN. <hi rend="italic">The Papers of Benjamin Franklin,
                            Volume 41: September 16, 1783, through February 29, 1784</hi>. Edited by
                        Ellen R. Cohn, Jonathan R. Dull, Robert P. Frankel Jr., Kate M. Ohno,
                        Philipp Ziesche, Alicia K. Anderson, Allegra Di Bonaventura, Alysia M. Cain,
                        Adrina M. Garbooshian, and Michael Sletcher. Yale University Press. 2014.
                        760 pp. $115. ISBN: 9780300203745. After the signing of the definitive peace
                        treaty on September 3, 1783, Franklin’s official duties as minister
                        plenipotentiary diminished. With his new leisure time Franklin followed
                        scientific developments, advised the French government on schemes for civic
                        improvement, and wrote three of his most remarkable pieces about what it
                        meant to be American.</p></item>

                <item><p>GARVEY, MARCUS. <hi rend="italic">The Marcus Garvey and Universal Negro
                            Improvement Association Papers, Volume XII: The Caribbean Diaspora,
                            1920–1921</hi>. Edited by Robert A. Hill, John Dixon, Mariela Haro
                        Rodriguez, and Anthony Yuen. Duke University Press. 2014. 480 pp. $120.
                        ISBN: 9780822357377. Volume XII covers a period of twelve months, from the
                        opening of the UNIA’s historic first international convention in New York in
                        August 1920 to Garvey’s return to the United States in July 1921 after an
                        extended tour of Cuba, Jamaica, Panama, Costa Rica, and Belize. This period
                        was the moment of the movement’s political apotheosis, as well as the moment
                        when the finances of Garvey’s Black Star Line went into free
                    fall.</p></item>

                <item><p>GODWIN, WILLIAM. <hi rend="italic">The Letters of William Godwin, Volume
                            II: 1798–1805</hi>. Edited by Pamela Clemit. Oxford University Press.
                        2014. 640 pp. $160. ISBN: 9780199562626. This edition publishes for the
                        first time all the letters of this social thinker, novelist, and philosopher
                        of the late eighteenth and early nineteenth centuries. Letters in this
                        volume show Godwin still well connected but increasingly embattled as a
                        public intellectual, as a political radical, and as an author.</p></item>

                <item><p>GOSS, ALEXANDER. <hi rend="italic">The Correspondence of Alexander Goss,
                            Bishop of Liverpool, 1856–1872</hi>. Edited by Peter Doyle. Boydell and
                        Brewer. 2014. 442 pp. $80. ISBN: 9780902832282. These letters illustrate the
                        complex issues facing the newly established Catholic hierarchy in England
                        and Wales. Bishop Alexander Goss was closely involved in the struggles to
                        assert diocesan independence from Westminster and undue interference by Rome
                        and was a determined upholder of his episcopal rights.</p></item>

                <item><p>HALL, MARGARET. <hi rend="italic">Letters and Photographs from the Battle
                            Country: The World War I Memoir of Margaret Hall</hi>. Edited by
                        Margaret R. Higonnet. University of Virginia Press. 2014. 248 pp. $34.95.
                        ISBN: 9781936520077. In August 1918 Massachusetts-born Margaret Hall set out
                        to work with the American Red Cross in France, then in the grips of the
                        First World War. After Hall returned to the United States, she wrote a
                        memoir that she shared privately with friends and family. Published here for
                        the first time, Hall’s words offer a firsthand account of life on the
                        Western Front in those last months of the war and its immediate aftermath.
                        The book features dozens of Hall’s striking and never-before-published
                        photographs.</p></item>

                <item><p>HEMINGWAY, ERNEST. <hi rend="italic">The Letters of Ernest Hemingway,
                            Volume 2: 1923–1925</hi>. Edited by Sandra Spanier, Albert J. DeFazio
                        III, and Robert W. Trogdon. Cambridge University Press. 2013. 604 pp. $40.
                        ISBN: 9780521897341. This volume of Hemingway’s letters illuminates his
                        literary apprenticeship in the milieu of expatriate Paris in the 1920s. We
                        witness the development of his friendships with the likes of Sylvia Beach,
                        F. Scott Fitzgerald, and John Dos Passos and his emergence from the tutelage
                        of Ezra Pound and Gertrude Stein. Hemingway publishes his first three books,
                        including <hi rend="italic">In Our Time</hi> (1925), and discovers a passion
                        for Spain and the bullfight, transforming his experiences into fiction as
                            <hi rend="italic">The Sun Also Rises</hi> (1926). The volume features
                        many previously unpublished letters and a humorous sketch that was rejected
                        by <hi rend="italic">Vanity Fair</hi>. </p></item>

                <item><p>HOPKINS, GERARD MANLEY. <hi rend="italic">The Collected Works of Gerard
                            Manley Hopkins, Volume VII: The Dublin Notebook</hi>. Edited by Lesley
                        J. Higgins and Michael F. Suarez. Oxford University Press. 2014. 336 pp.
                        $160. ISBN: 9780199534029. Hopkins’s “Dublin Notebook” provides intimate and
                        rare access to the Jesuit poet’s private, poetic, religious, and academic
                        thoughts and words during his final years in Dublin. It is a unique
                        repository of personal memoranda, drafts of poems, lecture outlines,
                        spiritual meditation notes, and academic notes, and sheds new light on the
                        circumstances that produced Hopkins’s “Sonnets of Desolation” in the
                        mid-1880s. Includes a digitized facsimile of the manuscript and a detailed
                        transcription of each page.</p></item>

                <item><p>HUTCHINSON, THOMAS. <hi rend="italic">The Correspondence of Thomas
                            Hutchinson, Volume 1: 1740–1766</hi>. Edited by John W. Tyler and
                        Elizabeth Dubrulle. University of Virginia Press. 2014. 630 pp. $49.50.
                        ISBN: 9780985254322. Hutchinson was the leading spokesman in colonial
                        America for opposition to the Revolutionary movement. Because of his
                        Loyalist sympathies, his letters have until now remained unpublished. This
                        first volume of the only fully annotated edition of his correspondence
                        begins with his emergence on the political stage in 1740 and covers the
                        events of the French and Indian War, his controversial appointments as
                        lieutenant governor and chief justice, and the Stamp Act riots.</p></item>

                <item><p>IRISH HISTORY. <hi rend="italic">The Bordeaux-Dublin Letters, 1757:
                            Correspondence of an Irish Community Abroad</hi>. Edited by Louis
                        Cullen, John Shovlin, and Thomas Truxes. Oxford University Press. 2014. 330
                        pp. $110. ISBN: 9780197265628. The book presents 125 letters carried aboard
                        a ship captured at sea in 1757, in the midst of the Seven Years’ War. Most
                        of the letters lay unopened for 250 years until they were rediscovered in
                        the United Kingdom’s National Archives in 2011. The letters from members of
                        the Irish community in Bordeaux and their relatives, friends, and trading
                        partners in Ireland communicate the concerns and understandings of ordinary
                        people in a diasporic community during wartime.</p></item>

                <item><p>ISHERWOOD, CHRISTOPHER. <hi rend="italic">The Animals: Love Letters between
                            Christopher Isherwood and Don Bachardy</hi>. Edited by Katherine
                        Bucknell. Farrar, Straus and Giroux. 2014. 528 pp. $30. ISBN: 9780374105174.
                        The English novelist and screenwriter Christopher Isherwood was already
                        famous as an author when he met Don Bachardy, a California teenager, on the
                        beach in Santa Monica in 1952. Within a year they began to live together as
                        an openly gay couple, defying convention in the closeted world of Hollywood.
                        Isherwood was forty-eight; Bachardy was eighteen. <hi rend="italic">The
                            Animals</hi> illuminates their extraordinary partnership, which lasted
                        until Isherwood’s death in 1986—despite the age gap, affairs and jealousy,
                        the pressures of celebrity, and the disdain of twentieth-century America for
                        love between two men.</p></item>

                <item><p>JAMES, HENRY. <hi rend="italic">The Complete Letters of Henry James,
                            1878–1880, Volume 1.</hi> Edited by Pierre A. Walker and Greg W.
                        Zacharias. University of Nebraska Press. 2014. 384 pp. $90. ISBN:
                        9780803254244. In this volume James establishes himself as a professional
                        author in control of his career and as an important social figure in London.
                        He learns to negotiate, pitting one publisher against another, establishes a
                        working relationship with the Macmillan publishing house, and cultivates
                        reviewers. James also negotiates terms for and begins planning <hi
                            rend="italic">The Portrait of a Lady</hi>.</p></item>

                <item><p>JEFFERSON, THOMAS. <hi rend="italic">The Papers of Thomas Jefferson, Volume
                            40: 4 March to 10 July 1803</hi>. Edited by Barbara B. Oberg, James P.
                        McClure, Elaine Weber Pascu, Tom Downey, Martha J. King, and W. Bland
                        Whitley. Princeton University Press. 2014. 848 pp. $115. ISBN:
                        9780691160375. This volume opens on the first day of Jefferson’s third year
                        as president as he confronts the potential consequences of the cession of
                        Louisiana to France. On 3 July, word reaches Jefferson that France has
                        agreed to the sale of the entire Louisiana Territory. Having received
                        congressional approval to send an expedition to locate a continental route
                        to the Pacific, Jefferson drafts instructions and a cipher for Meriwether
                        Lewis and arranges for the needed instruments.</p></item>

                <item><p>JEFFERSON, THOMAS. <hi rend="italic">The Papers of Thomas Jefferson:
                            Retirement Series, Volume 10: 1 May 1816 to 18 January 1817</hi>. Edited
                        by J. Jefferson Looney, Robert F. Haggard, Julie L. Lautenschlager,
                        Christine Sternberg Patrick, and Ellen C. Hickman. Princeton University
                        Press. 2014. 800 pp. $115. ISBN: 9780691160474. During this time Jefferson
                        privately suggests substantial amendments to Virginia’s constitution. He
                        calculates the latitude of Poplar Forest and Willis’s Mountain, works to
                        bring Destutt de Tracy’s <hi rend="italic">Treatise on Political
                            Economy</hi> into print, and recommends revisions to a forthcoming
                        biography of Patrick Henry. The Baron de Montlezun and Francis Hall provide
                        informative firsthand accounts of Jefferson at Monticello.</p></item>

                <item><p>KAMBALPOSH, YUSUF KHAN. <hi rend="italic">Between Worlds: The Travels of
                            Yusuf Khan Kambalposh</hi>. Translated by Mushirul Hasan and Nishat
                        Zaidi. Oxford University Press. 2014. 216 pp. $90. This book is an edited
                        and annotated translation of <hi rend="italic">Tarikh-i-Yusufi</hi> by Yusuf
                        Khan Kambalposh (ca. 1830–90) who traveled to several places in North Africa
                        and Europe. Translated for the first time from Urdu to English, it describes
                        in detail the socioeconomic conditions of Europe and contrasts it with the
                        conditions in areas under European control.</p></item>

                <item><p>KING, MARTIN LUTHER, JR. <hi rend="italic">The Papers of Martin Luther
                            King, Jr., Volume VII: To Save the Soul of America, January 1961–August
                            1962</hi>. Edited by Clayborne Carson and Tenisha Hart Armstrong.
                        University of California Press. 2014. 752 pp. $75. ISBN: 9780520282698. This
                        volume covers King’s early relationship with John F. Kennedy and his efforts
                        to remain relevant in a protest movement growing increasingly massive and
                        militant. As the initial Freedom Ride catapulted King into the national
                        spotlight in May 1961, tensions with student activists affiliated with the
                        Student Nonviolent Coordinating Committee were exacerbated after King
                        refused to participate in subsequent freedom rides. During 1962 King worked
                        diligently to improve the effectiveness of the Southern Christian Leadership
                        Conference and undertook a full schedule of appearances, teaching, and
                        protesting.</p></item>

                <item><p>LANGFORD, GLADYS. <hi rend="italic">A Free-Spirited Woman: The London
                            Diaries of Gladys Langford, 1936–1940</hi>. Edited by Patricia
                        Malcolmson and Robert Malcolmson. Boydell and Brewer. 2014. 231 pp. $45.
                        ISBN: 9780900952555. Gladys Langford (born 1890) was a free spirit, an
                        aspiring writer, an inveterate attender of plays, concerts, and films, and
                        an astute and sometimes acerbic observer of everyday life in 1930s London.
                        Her diary is a portrait of social life and London’s public world; she writes
                        of her quirky friends, her family and straitened family background, her
                        schoolboys in Hoxton, and her numerous Jewish acquaintances.</p></item>

                <item><p>LOUVERTURE, TOUSSAINT. <hi rend="italic">The Memoir of General Toussaint
                            Louverture</hi>. Translated and edited by Philippe R. Girard. Oxford
                        University Press. 2014. 192 pp. $55. ISBN: 9780199937226. This volume is an
                        annotated, scholarly, multilingual edition of the only lengthy text
                        personally written by Haitian revolutionary Toussaint Louverture: the
                        memoirs he wrote shortly before his death in the French prison of Fort de
                        Joux. The translation is based on an original copy in Louverture’s hand,
                        never before published.</p></item>

                <item><p>MADISON, JAMES. <hi rend="italic">The Papers of James Madison, Secretary of
                            State Series, Volume 10: 1 July 1805–31 December 1805</hi>. Edited by
                        Mary A. Hackett, J. C. A. Stagg, Anne Mandeville Colony, Katharine E.
                        Harbury, and Mary Parke Johnson. University of Virginia Press. 2014. 764 pp.
                        $85. ISBN: 9780813935713. In this volume Madison contended with the failed
                        negotiations between Spain and the United States to settle boundaries, Great
                        Britain’s refusal to respond to US complaints of the impressment of seamen
                        and violations of neutral trade, reports from territorial governors,
                        detailed accounts of the June 1805 treaty negotiations between the United
                        States and Tripoli, and the arrival of the Tunisian ambassador. James and
                        Dolley Madison spent three months of this period together in Philadelphia;
                        also included is correspondence between the Madisons written after James’s
                        return to Washington.</p></item>

                <item><p>MAILER, NORMAN. <hi rend="italic">Selected Letters of Norman Mailer</hi>.
                        Edited by J. Michael Lennon. Random House. 2014. 896 pp. $40. ISBN:
                        9781400066230. Compiled by Mailer’s authorized biographer and organized by
                        decade, this edition features the most fascinating of his missives from 1940
                        to 2007 and includes letters to family and friends, to fans and fellow
                        writers, to political figures, and to cultural icons. Many of the letters
                        are published for the first time.</p></item>

                <item><p>MONROE, JAMES. <hi rend="italic">The Papers of James Monroe, Volume 5:
                            Selected Correspondence and Papers, January 1803–April 1811</hi>. Edited
                        by Daniel Preston and Cassandra Good. ABC-CLIO/Greenwood Press. 2014. 826
                        pp. $115. ISBN: 9780313319822. Following an introductory essay, the subjects
                        covered include Monroe’s involvement in treaty negotiations with England,
                        Spain, and France—most notably, concerning the Louisiana Purchase; his
                        candidacy in the 1808 presidential election; and his appointment as
                        secretary of state in 1811. The documents in this volume illuminate the
                        decisions made by American, British, French, and Spanish leaders during this
                        period, especially regarding events leading up to the War of
                    1812.</p></item>

                <item><p>NEHRU, JAWAHARLAL. <hi rend="italic">Selected Works of Jawaharlal Nehru,
                            Second Series, Volume 52: 1–30 September 1959</hi>. Edited by Madhavan
                        K. Palat. Oxford University Press. 2014. 366 pp. $50. ISBN: 9780199451272.
                            <hi rend="italic">Volume 53: 1–31 October 1959</hi>. 2014. 606 pp. $65.
                        ISBN: 9780199451289. <hi rend="italic">Volume 54: 1–30 November 1959</hi>.
                        2014. 726 pp. $70. ISBN: 9780199451296. <hi rend="italic">Volume 55: 1–31
                            December 1959</hi>. 2014. 521 pp. $65. ISBN: 9780199451302. <hi
                            rend="italic">Volume 56: 1–25 January 1960</hi>. 2014. 485 pp. $55.
                        ISBN: 9780199453696. <hi rend="italic">Volume 57: 26 January–28 February
                            1960</hi>. 2014. 585 pp. $60. ISBN: 9780199455201. <hi rend="italic">The
                            Selected Works of Jawaharlal Nehru</hi> is the most important and
                        authoritative source on Nehru’s life, work, and thought. With extensive
                        annotations, it provides a panorama of home and the world as seen from the
                        center of power in India by an acutely sensitive observer and a skillful
                        statesman.</p></item>

                <item><p>PACHECO, ALBINO MANOEL. <hi rend="italic">A Journey from Tete to Zumbo (Uma
                            Viagem de Tete ao Zumbo)</hi>. Edited by Malyn Newitt. Oxford University
                        Press. 2013. 220 pp. $75. ISBN: 9780197265604. Albino Manoel Pacheco was
                        sent in 1861–62 to reestablish the Portuguese settlement at Zumbo at a time
                        when Livingstone’s Zambesi Expedition was still active in the region. His
                        account of this expedition has long been recognized to be of exceptional
                        importance, though it can only be found in obscure nineteenth-century
                        publications. This edition and translation makes Pacheco’s account fully
                        available for Portuguese and English readers for the first time.</p></item>

                <item><p>PAINE, THOMAS. <hi rend="italic">Selected Writings of Thomas Paine</hi>.
                        Edited by Ian Shapiro and Jane E. Calvert. Yale University Press. 2014. 720
                        pp. $18. ISBN: 9780300167450. Contains Paine’s <hi rend="italic">Common
                            Sense</hi> in its entirety, including the oft-ignored Appendix, as well
                        as selections from his other major writings: <hi rend="italic">The American
                            Crisis</hi>, <hi rend="italic">Rights of Man</hi>, and <hi rend="italic">The Age of Reason</hi>. It also includes
                        several of Paine’s shorter essays. All the documents have been transcribed
                        directly from the originals. Includes historical essays.</p></item>

                <item><p>PERRY, MATTHEW CALBRAITH. <hi rend="italic">With Commodore Perry to Japan:
                            The Journal of William Speiden Jr., 1852–1855</hi>. Edited by John A.
                        Wolter, David A. Ranzan, and John J. McDonough. Naval Institute Press. 2013.
                        320 pp. $39.95. This edition offers a personal account of Commodore Matthew
                        Calbraith Perry’s expedition to Japan through the eyes of a sixteen-year-old
                        purser’s clerk of the USS <hi rend="italic">Mississippi</hi>. The journal
                        covers the political mission of the Perry expedition, the opening of
                        relations with Japan, and the social history of a naval warship.</p></item>

                <item><p>RICHARDSON, SAMUEL. <hi rend="italic">The Correspondence of Samuel
                            Richardson: Correspondence with Aaron Hill and the Hill Family</hi>.
                        Edited by Christine Gerrard. Cambridge University Press. 2014. 434 pp. $130.
                        ISBN: 9780521872737. Contains Richardson’s correspondence with Aaron Hill,
                        the poet, dramatist, and entrepreneur. These letters offer insight into the
                        compositional processes of the two <hi rend="italic">Pamela</hi> novels and
                        of Richardson’s later novels, <hi rend="italic">Clarissa</hi> and <hi
                            rend="italic">The History of Sir Charles Grandison</hi>. The volume also
                        includes Richardson’s correspondence with Hill’s literary
                    daughters.</p></item>

                <item><p>RICHARDSON, SAMUEL. <hi rend="italic">The Correspondence of Samuel
                            Richardson: Correspondence with George Cheyne and Thomas Edwards</hi>.
                        Edited by David E. Shuttleton and John A. Dussinger. 2014. 552 pp. $130.
                        ISBN: 9780521822855. This volume consists of Richardson’s letters with Dr.
                        George Cheyne and Thomas Edwards, which are marked by their medical content
                        and by their generally unguarded character. Cheyne elicits some of the
                        novelist’s most significant statements concerning his own literary practice
                        and tastes. Edwards draws Richardson into expressing insights as a close
                        reader of poetry and prose.</p></item>

                <item><p>RONAN, PETER. <hi rend="italic">“A Great Many of Us Have Good Farms”: Agent
                            Peter Ronan Reports on the Flathead Indian Reservation, Montana,
                            1877–1887</hi>. Edited by Robert J. Bigart. Salish Kootenai College
                        Press. 2014. 448 pp. $24.95. ISBN: 9781934594100. Letters of Peter Ronan,
                        the government agent for the Salish and Kootenai tribes of the Flathead
                        Indian Reservation in Montana. In this period the tribes worked hard to stay
                        out of the Nez Perce War, and the Bitterroot Valley Salish struggled to
                        preserve their right to their traditional homeland. Includes an 1884
                        photographic tour of the reservation and a biographical sketch of
                    Ronan.</p></item>

                <item><p>RONAN, PETER. <hi rend="italic">Justice to Be Accorded to the Indians:
                            Agent Peter Ronan Reports on the Flathead Indian Reservation, Montana,
                            1888–1893</hi>. Edited by Robert J. Bigart. Salish Kootenai College
                        Press. 2014. 448 pp. $24.95. ISBN: 9781934594117. In this volume of Ronan’s
                        letters, the Salish and Kootenai tribes navigated growing economic and legal
                        crises. Tribal farms and cattle herds expanded to make up for declining
                        hunting and gathering resources. Includes biographical sketches of tribal
                        leaders.</p></item>

                <item><p>SALEM WITCH TRIALS. <hi rend="italic">Records of the Salem Witch-Hunt</hi>.
                        Edited by Bernard Rosenthal. Cambridge University Press. 2013. 1012 pp. $55.
                        ISBN: 9781107689619. This book represents the first comprehensive record of
                        all legal documents pertaining to the Salem witch trials, in chronological
                        order. Numerous newly discovered manuscripts, as well as records published
                        in earlier books that were overlooked in other editions, offer a
                        comprehensive narrative account of the events of 1692–93. All legal records
                        are newly transcribed. With a historical introduction, a legal introduction,
                        and a linguistic introduction.</p></item>

                <item><p>SANTAYANA, GEORGE. <hi rend="italic">The Works of George Santayana, Volume
                            7, Book 2. The Life of Reason or the Phases of Human Progress: Reason in
                            Society</hi>. Edited by Marianne S. Wokeck and Martin A. Coleman. MIT
                        Press. 2013. 306 pp. $65. ISBN: 9780262019590. In this second book of <hi
                            rend="italic">The Life of Reason</hi>, Santayana analyzes several
                        distinctive forms of human association, from political and economic orders
                        to forms of friendship, to determine what possibilities they provide for the
                        life of reason. He considers, among other topics, love and the affinity for
                        the ideal, the family, aristocracy and democracy, the constituents of
                        genuinely free friendship, patriotism, and the ideal society of kindred
                        spirits.</p></item>

                <item><p>SANTAYANA, GEORGE. <hi rend="italic">The Works of George Santayana, Volume
                            7, Book 3. The Life of Reason or the Phases of Human Progress: Reason in
                            Religion</hi>. Edited by Marianne S. Wokeck and Martin A. Coleman. MIT
                        Press. 2014. 400 pp. $75. ISBN: 9780262028325. In this third book, Santayana
                        offers a naturalistic interpretation of religion. Santayana analyzes four
                        characteristic religious concerns: piety, spirituality, charity, and
                        immortality.</p></item>

                <item><p>SCHENKER, HEINRICH. <hi rend="italic">Heinrich Schenker: Selected
                            Correspondence</hi>. Edited by Ian Brent, David Bretherton, and William
                        Drabkin. Boydell and Brewer. 2014. 561 pp. $99. ISBN: 9781843839644. The
                        work of important music theorist Heinrich Schenker (1868–1935) has shaped
                        the teaching of music theory in the United States profoundly and influenced
                        theorists throughout the world. Living and working in Vienna, Schenker
                        maintained a correspondence with a large circle of professional musicians,
                        writers, music critics, institutions, administrators, patrons, friends, and
                        pupils. This volume represents a concise edition of some of the theorist’s
                        most important and revelatory letters and diary entries translated into
                        English.</p></item>

                <item><p>SCOTLAND. <hi rend="italic">Edinburgh Housemails Taxation Book,
                            1634–1636</hi>. Edited by Aaron Allen and Cathryn Spence. Boydell and
                        Brewer. 2014. 668 pp. $70. ISBN: 9780906245392. In 1633 plans were made for
                        a new one-time tax on house-rent, or “mail,” intended to pay the stipends of
                        Edinburgh’s clergy. The inventory that was taken in preparation for
                        assessing taxes survives in manuscript form in the Edinburgh City Archives.
                        Although it seems the tax was never actually collected, it left a detailed
                        record of the socioeconomic and political structures of Edinburgh. The
                        record gives information on landlords, tenants, rental, and annuity for over
                        900 businesses and 3,900 houses.</p></item>

                <item><p>SMITH, JOSPEH. <hi rend="italic">The Joseph Smith Papers. Documents, Volume
                            3: February 1833–March 1834</hi>. Edited by Gerrit J. Dirkmaat, Brent M.
                        Rogers, Grant Underwood, Robert J. Woodford, and William G. Hartley. Church
                        Historian’s Press. 2014. 627 pp. $54.95. ISBN: 9781609079871. Contains
                        minutes, revelations, letters, architectural and city plans, priesthood
                        licenses, legal documents, and an effort to classify the scriptures by
                        topic. Covering a time when opposition to Smith and his followers was
                        intensifying in Ohio and Missouri, this volume includes documents relating
                        to the building of temples, the establishment of the city of Zion, the
                        formation of the first high council, and the expulsion of the Saints from
                        Jackson County, Missouri. Also includes documents that contain teachings
                        distinctive to Mormon theology.</p></item>

                <item><p>STEPHEN, JAMES FITZJAMES. <hi rend="italic">The Selected Writings of James
                            Fitzjames Stephen: The Story of Nuncomar and the Impeachment of Sir
                            Elijah Impey</hi>. Edited by Lisa Rodensky. Oxford University Press.
                        2013. 416 pp. $160. ISBN: 9780199236183. <hi rend="italic">The Story of
                            Nuncomar and the Impeachment of Sir Elijah Impey</hi> (1885) examines
                        some of the most controversial events of eighteenth-century English colonial
                        legal history from the point of view of Victorian England’s most important
                        legal authority. Stephen argues that far from being the victim of a
                        judicially engineered execution, Nuncomar (a powerful Indian accused of
                        forgery and conspiracy) received a fair trial at the Supreme Court in
                        Bengal. This new edition of Stephen’s text (the first since the work was
                        originally published) includes an introduction, table of dates, glossary,
                        index, and extensive explanatory notes.</p></item>

                <item><p>STEPHEN, JAMES FITZJAMES. <hi rend="italic">The Selected Writings of James
                            Fitzjames Stephen: A General View of the Criminal Law of England</hi>.
                        Edited by K. J. M. Smith. Oxford University Press. 2014. 416 pp. $165. ISBN:
                        9780199660834. Published in the summer of 1863, <hi rend="italic">A General
                            View of the Criminal Law</hi> is an account of the nature, substance,
                        and functioning of the criminal law in mid-Victorian England. </p></item>

                <item><p>SWIFT, JONATHAN. <hi rend="italic">Journal to Stella: Letters to Esther
                            Johnson and Rebecca Dingley, 1710–1713</hi>. Edited by Abigail Williams.
                        Cambridge University Press. 2014. 898 pp. $130. ISBN: 9780521841665. <hi
                            rend="italic">Journal to Stella</hi> offers a detailed commentary on
                        Swift’s experiences in London in 1710–13, and evidence of his evolving
                        relationship with Esther Johnson, or Stella. The edition offers
                        transcriptions of the manuscript portion of the letters, based on the latest
                        digital image analysis techniques. These will represent the text for the
                        first time, complete with Swift’s purposeful obliterations. Includes a
                        biographical appendix.</p></item>

                <item><p>TOMLINSON, WILL. <hi rend="italic">The Printer’s Kiss: The Life and Letters
                            of a Civil War Newspaperman and His Family</hi>. Edited by Patricia A.
                        Donohoe. Kent State University Press. 2014. 288 pp. $39.95. ISBN:
                        9781606352168. This compilation of letters and newspaper columns written
                        from 1844 to 1864 tells the story of controversial Ohio newspaper editor
                        Will Tomlinson and his family. The correspondence illuminates topics such as
                        survival in the borderlands during the Civil War, camp life, guerilla
                        warfare, and contains commentary on political and military events,
                        journalism in the mid-1800s, and the roles of women and children.</p></item>

                <item><p>TURNER, HENRY MCNEAL. <hi rend="italic">Freedom’s Witness: The Civil War
                            Correspondence of Henry McNeal Turner</hi>. Edited by Jean Lee Cole.
                        West Virginia University Press. 2013. 288 pp. $68.99. ISBN: 9781935978602.
                        In a series of columns published in the African American newspaper <hi
                            rend="italic">The Christian Recorder</hi>, the young charismatic
                        preacher Turner described his experience of the Civil War from the
                        perspective of a civilian observer in Washington, DC, and later, as one of
                        the Union army’s first black chaplains.</p></item>

                <item><p>TWAIN, MARK. <hi rend="italic">A Family Sketch and Other Private
                            Writings</hi>. Edited by Benjamin Griffin. University of California
                        Press. 2014. 200 pp. $25.95. ISBN: 9780520280731. This book publishes some
                        of Twain’s private writings for the first time. He began to write “A Family
                        Sketch” in response to the early death of his eldest daughter, Susy, but the
                        manuscript grew to become an account of the entire household. Also includes
                        his record of the children’s sayings—“Small Foolishnesses”—and the related
                        manuscript “At the Farm.” The volume also contains selections from his wife
                        Livy’s 1885 diary and an authoritative edition of Susy’s biography of her
                        father, written when she was a teenager.</p></item>

                <item><p>TWAIN, MARK. <hi rend="italic">Mark Twain on Potholes and Politics: Letters
                            to the Editor</hi>. Edited by Gary Scharnhorst. University of Missouri
                        Press. 2014. 224 pp. $35. ISBN: 9780826220462. A frequent outlet for Mark
                        Twain’s wit was in letters to the editors of various newspapers and
                        periodicals. More than one hundred of these letters on a wide range of
                        topics are included in this volume.</p></item>

                <item><p>WALLIS, JOHN. <hi rend="italic">Correspondence of John Wallis (1616–1703),
                            Volume IV (1672–April 1675)</hi>. Edited by Philip Beeley and Christoph
                        J. Scriba. Oxford University Press. 2014. 656 pp. $325. ISBN: 9780198569480.
                        This volume of the complete correspondence of Oxford mathematician John
                        Wallis contains over eighty previously unpublished letters, and covers key
                        scientific debates of the early 1670s on topics such as the method of
                        tangents and the theory of tides.</p></item>

                <item><p>WELLES, GIDEON. <hi rend="italic">The Civil War Diary of Gideon Welles,
                            Lincoln’s Secretary of the Navy</hi>. Edited by William E. Gienapp and
                        Erica L. Gienapp. University of Illinois Press. 2014. 880 pp. $45. ISBN:
                        9780252038525. Welles’s detailed diary has become one of the key documents
                        for understanding the inner workings of the Lincoln administration.
                        Supplementary materials include biographies of the members of Lincoln’s
                        cabinet, the retrospective Welles wrote after leaving office covering the
                        period missing from the diary proper, and letters regarding naval matters
                        and international law.</p></item>

                <item><p>WILDER, LAURA INGALLS. <hi rend="italic">Pioneer Girl: The Annotated
                            Autobiography</hi>. Edited by Pamela Smith Hill. South Dakota State
                        Historical Society Press. 2014. 472 pp. $44.95. ISBN: 9780984504176. Hidden
                        away since 1930, Laura Ingalls Wilder’s original autobiography reveals the
                        true stories of her pioneering life. The book features over one hundred
                        images, eight fully researched maps, and hundreds of annotations based on
                        census data and other records, newspapers of the period, and other primary
                        documents. This original version of Wilder’s autobiography served as the
                        basis of her successful series of children’s books.</p></item>

                <item><p>WILKES, JOHN. <hi rend="italic">The Diaries of John Wilkes, 1770–1797</hi>.
                        Edited by Robin Eagles. Boydell and Brewer. 2014. 383 pp. $60. ISBN:
                        9780900952548. John Wilkes became a significant force for change in
                        journalism and politics, first as a Whig MP for Aylesbury, later for
                        Middlesex. Having gained attention as proprietor of the opposition paper,
                        the <hi rend="italic">North Briton</hi>, he underwent a remarkable fall from
                        grace, eventually being imprisoned for libel. After his release Wilkes was
                        the focus of various reform movements; his diaries chart his daily
                        activities from his release from prison in 1770 to a few weeks before his
                        death.</p></item>
                
                <item><p>WORLD WAR I: <hi rend="italic">The World War I Diary of José de la Luz
                            Sáenz</hi>. Edited by Emilio Zamora. Texas A&amp;M University Press.
                        2014. 528 pp. $50. ISBN: 9781623491130. A teacher in South Texas before and
                        after the war, Sáenz’s patriotism, his keen observations of the
                        discrimination he and his friends faced both at home and in the field, and
                        his unwavering dedication to the cause of equality have for years made this
                        book a valuable resource for scholars. This first translated English edition
                        includes an introduction and annotation.</p></item>
                
                <item><p>WRIGHT, RICHARD. <hi rend="italic">Byline Richard Wright: Articles from the
                            Daily Worker and New Masses</hi>. Edited by Earle V. Bryant. University
                        of Missouri Press. 2014. 362 pp. $60. ISBN: 9780826220202. Assembles more
                        than one hundred articles Wright wrote on a wide range of subjects in the
                        1930s for the <hi rend="italic">Daily Worker</hi>, the newspaper that served as the voice of the
                        American Communist Party. Also includes two essays published in <hi rend="italic">New Masses</hi>.
                        With an introduction and contextualizing commentary.</p></item>
            </list>
        </body>
    </text>
</TEI>
