<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<?oxygen RNGSchema="http://www.scholarlyediting.org/scholarlyediting.rng" type="xml"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xml:lang="eng">
    <teiHeader>
        <fileDesc>
            <titleStmt>
                <title level="a" type="main">Review: <hi rend="italic">The Eleanor Roosevelt Papers,
                        Vol. 2: The Human Rights Years, 1949–1952. </hi>. Edited by Allida
                    Black.</title>
                <author key="Leahy, Christopher">Christopher Leahy</author>
                <author key="Leahy, Sharon Williams">Sharon Williams Leahy</author>
            </titleStmt>
            <editionStmt>
                <edition>
                    <date>2015</date>
                </edition>
            </editionStmt>
            <publicationStmt>
                <idno type="file">review.roosevelt</idno>
                <authority>Scholary Editing: The Annual of the Association for Documentary
                    Editing</authority>
                <address>
 <addrLine>http://www.scholarlyediting.org</addrLine>
</address>
                <publisher>Association for Documentary Editing</publisher>
                <publisher>University of Nebraska&#8211;Lincoln</publisher>
                <distributor>
                    <name>Center for Digital Research in the Humanities</name>
                    <address>
<addrLine>319 Love Library</addrLine>
<addrLine>University of Nebraska&#8211;Lincoln</addrLine>
<addrLine>Lincoln, NE 68588-4100</addrLine>
<addrLine>http://cdrh.unl.edu</addrLine>
 </address>
                </distributor>
                <date>2015</date>
                <availability>
                    <p>Scholary Editing: The Annual of the Association for Documentary Editing is
                        freely distributed by the Association for Documentary Editing and the Center
                        for Digital Research in the Humanities at the University of Nebraska-Lincoln
                        and licensed under a Creative Commons Attribution-NonCommercial-ShareAlike
                        3.0 Unported License</p>
                </availability>
            </publicationStmt>
            <seriesStmt>
                <title level="j">Scholarly Editing: The Annual of the Association for Documentary
                    Editing</title>
                <respStmt>
                    <resp>editor</resp>
                    <name xml:id="ag" key="Gailey, Amanda A.">Amanda Gailey</name>
                </respStmt>
                <respStmt>
                    <resp>editor</resp>
                    <name xml:id="awj" key="Jewell, Andrew W.">Andrew Jewell</name>
                </respStmt>
                <idno type="vol">36</idno>
                <idno type="ISSN">2167-1257</idno>
            </seriesStmt>
            <sourceDesc>
                <bibl>
                    <note>Born digital.</note>
                </bibl>
            </sourceDesc>
        </fileDesc>
        <revisionDesc>
            <change when="2015-02-19">
                <name xml:id="ga_ki" key="Kirilloff, Gabi">Gabi Kirilloff</name> markup in TEI
                XML</change>
        </revisionDesc>
    </teiHeader>
    <text>
        <body>
            <head type="main"><hi rend="italic">The Eleanor Roosevelt Papers, Vol. 2: The Human
                    Rights Years, 1949–1952</hi>. Edited by Allida Black. Charlottesville:
                University of Virginia Press, 2012. lxv + 1,135 pp. ISBN 978-0-8139-3141-8.
                $125.</head>
            <p>The goal of the present volume of this magnificent series, editor Allida Black tells
                us, is to demonstrate Eleanor Roosevelt’s “increased influence not only within the
                United Nations but also within the State Department and the international diplomatic
                community.” Against the backdrop of the early Cold War and President Truman’s second
                term, the documents in this volume “give voice” to ER’s “political and social
                priorities and to the often stinging criticism her leadership provoked from
                politicians, clergy, and the general public” (xxxiii). Truly out of her husband
                FDR’s shadow by 1949, ER played “multiple, potentially conflicting roles—diplomat,
                political pundit, advice columnist, activist, and party leader” (xxxiii). The 311
                documents included here (with 542 additional documents excerpted primarily in the
                annotated notes of the book) attest to her energy and vision, her successes and
                failures, and her significance. “Most of all, they reflect the actions she took (and
                did not take) to promote human rights at home and abroad” (xxxiii). Arguably the
                most important First Lady in American history, Eleanor Roosevelt remains the most
                influential <hi rend="italic">former</hi> First Lady, and she merits the publication
                of the edition under review here as well as the series of which it is a part.</p>
            <p>The Eleanor Roosevelt Papers Project, based at George Washington University, has
                partnered with the Franklin D. Roosevelt Library in Hyde Park, New York, the
                National Historical Publications and Records Commission (NHPRC), the National
                Endowment for the Humanities (NEH), and the Eleanor Roosevelt National Historic
                Site. It has been a massive undertaking. Eleanor Roosevelt was a prolific writer and
                left behind thousands of sources in print, radio, film, and television. Material has
                been found in more than 600 collections among 263 archives in all fifty states and
                nine foreign nations. The staff of the <hi rend="italic">Papers</hi> has collected
                more than 130,000 documents, with 33,546 of that number falling within the period
                covered by the present volume. These documents include correspondence to and from
                ER, many of her “My Day” columns that were syndicated in America’s newspapers, “If
                You Ask Me” excerpts that were published in her regular magazine column, and
                transcripts from television and radio interviews and press conferences. This volume,
                like its predecessor, includes such varied written sources because the editors
                wanted to “create an edition mirroring the various ways ER made her voice heard”
                (xxxviii).</p>
            <p>The staggering bulk of ER’s papers, as well as the perpetual enemy of all documentary
                projects—constraints of time and cost—necessitated a high degree of selectivity on
                the part of the editorial staff. The series makes no claim to being a comprehensive
                documentary edition; indeed, such an edition is likely impossible. The director of
                the project consulted with the NHPRC and other Roosevelt scholars and with their
                concurrence sought to “produce a highly selective edition designed to present an
                authoritative resource on Eleanor Roosevelt’s political and human rights record and
                to encourage further research on her life and the issues she addressed” (xxxviii).
                The series, therefore, focuses solely on ER’s public life and does not include
                documents of an exclusively private nature. The editorial team “weeded out any
                material that did not discuss politics, policy, world events, philosophy, faith,
                social justice, or government” (xxxviii). As they finalized the selection of
                documents, they did so according to four criteria. First, a document had to
                illustrate one of the key events, themes, or issues of ER’s public life. Second,
                ER’s distinctive voice had to be revealed and the document had to afford insight
                into her decision-making process. Third, the document had to have a demonstrable
                impact on politics, public policy, and public opinion. Fourth, it had to provide
                important information ER used to frame her stance on an issue.</p>
            <p>The attention paid to these criteria yields a volume that covers a wide range of
                events and details ER’s involvement in many of the seminal issues of the time
                period. Her correspondence, in particular, attests to the “serious treatment she
                received from those in power” (xxxvii). Much of that correspondence necessarily
                deals with America’s role in the world. For example, there are some two dozen
                documents that address the newly created state of Israel. The reader learns that ER
                lauded Israel’s “achievement” in creating a democracy in the Middle East that she
                hoped would “serv[e] as an example to all the other countries in the area” (629).
                She was outspoken in her support of an American financial commitment to Israel and
                lobbied the Truman administration—partly through correspondence with the president
                himself—to play an active role in getting the Arab states to sign a peace treaty
                with Israel. ER corresponded regularly with Secretary of State Dean Acheson on such
                matters as economic aid to foreign nations, the role of the United States in the
                United Nations, and the creation of NATO, which she initially opposed but came to
                support once she read the text of the pact. Several documents deal with the Korean
                War and make clear that ER considered American participation a Cold War
                imperative.</p>
            <p>On the domestic front, many of the documents in this volume address the burgeoning
                civil rights movement. Highlighting ER’s support of civil rights for African
                Americans (and for Native Americans) makes sense in a collection focused primarily
                on her commitment to human rights both in the United States and abroad. Other
                documents demonstrate ER’s involvement with the Democratic Party. In particular, she
                addressed Adlai Stevenson’s campaign for president in 1952, warning the candidate in
                a “My Day” column that he sounded “a little too academic” on the campaign trail. As
                the campaign progressed, ER grew increasingly frustrated with Stevenson, as his
                penchant for talking down to his listeners and his lackluster fundraising efforts
                raised doubts in her mind about whether he would make an effective president. One
                Democratic candidate ER endorsed without apparent reservation was Congressman John
                F. Kennedy, who was running for the United States Senate in Massachusetts. A letter
                in this volume from Robert Sargent Shriver, a key Kennedy aide (and future
                brother-in-law), solicits ER’s public endorsement of the young candidate, a request
                she granted in a “My Day” column.</p>
            <p>The editors “strove to reproduce the documents as accurately as possible, though
                [they] did not attempt to create facsimiles” (xli). Luckily, much of the material
                they sifted through was either typed or published, and the handwritten
                correspondence tended to be legible. Emendations are relatively minor, and the
                process and rationale for altering an original document are explained fully at the
                beginning of the volume. The editors do not list all the emendations made in the
                text, but they summarize the classes of alterations they have made. Spelling,
                capitalization, and punctuation are reproduced exactly as they appear in the
                original documents, except in cases of obvious typographical errors (they provide
                the proper spelling), antiquated hyphenation usage (they remove the hyphen), or
                excluded periods at the end of sentences (they add the period). The editors also
                provide opening or closing quotation marks where they are missing and remove
                superfluous marks. Dashes have been standardized as em dashes no matter how they
                were presented in the original document. Ellipses are presented as they appear in
                the originals. The paragraphing of the original documents is preserved, unless the
                beginning of a paragraph is not indented; in such cases, the editors have supplied
                an indentation. Finally, standardization has been imposed in the presentation of
                letters: salutations are presented flush to the left, on their own line, above the
                body of the letter. Closings and signatures have been centered at the bottom of the
                letter. Telegrams reproduced in the volume are provided using all capital letters,
                like the originals.</p>
            <p>To establish the text of the documents, the editors transcribed the “My Day” columns
                from the final wire-service copy ER provided to the syndicate for publication.
                Excerpts from the “If You Ask Me” columns are taken from the original published
                magazine in which they appeared. If several copies of a letter exist, the editors
                reproduce the recipient’s copy, presumably because they judge it as more accurate
                than the copy ER may have retained for her files. When a recipient’s copy could not
                be located, the document contained in ER’s files is used. If an audio recording of a
                speech ER delivered, or of a radio or television program in which she participated,
                was available, the editors use their own transcription of that recording. When no
                such recording exists, they use a transcript prepared at the time or employ a
                contemporary press account. The United Nations summary records published in the
                volume come from the UN’s official document collection. Official State Department
                records housed in the National Archives have provided the editors with the
                memoranda, minutes, and press releases related to ER’s work at the UN on behalf of
                the State Department.</p>
            <p>Most of the documents the editors chose to include in the volume are heavily
                annotated, often with a level of detail that makes the annotations lengthier than
                the documents themselves. This is often invaluable to researchers and will please
                many scholars who are accustomed to working with archival manuscript sources that do
                not provide them with the context for what they are reading. On the other hand, some
                might complain that, with space at a premium, it is far more important to publish as
                many documents as possible, even if it means sacrificing annotations. Experts in the
                field likely do not need discursive annotations, and the general audience interested
                in Eleanor Roosevelt may find them a tedious distraction. The editors have obviously
                made a concerted effort to flesh out all the details relevant to the documents they
                have published. While annotating documents is usual practice for projects of this
                nature, the editors of <hi rend="italic">The Eleanor Roosevelt Papers</hi> have
                surpassed everything these reviewers have seen and set a new scholarly standard that
                will be difficult to match.</p>
            <p>In our view, the annotations are beneficial because they allow the editors to paint a
                more complete picture of the events and people ER writes about in her documents,
                whether that source is a letter or one of the “My Day” columns. The researcher is
                able to see ER’s perspective but is also able to understand when she reached that
                perspective because of misinformation or personal feelings that may have clouded her
                judgment. For example, in January 1949, ER offered her support to Dr. Miriam Van
                Waters, the superintendent of the Framingham Reformatory in Massachusetts, who was
                relieved of her duties in December 1948. ER was certain the Massachusetts
                Commissioner of Correction had dismissed Van Waters because of the progressive
                methods of prison management she employed. Were someone to read only the excerpts of
                letters ER sent on the matter, that person might come to the conclusion that ER was
                correct in her assessment of the situation and adopt her sympathy for Van Waters as
                his or her own. Annotations related to the incident, however, indicate through a
                letter written to ER that Van Waters had been dismissed for an abuse of her
                authority. Moreover, this correspondent also informed ER that “Framingham had
                employed progressive penal methods before Van Waters’s arrival” (20–21), thus
                rendering ER’s interpretation of what had happened incorrect. The Van Waters example
                is one of many in the <hi rend="italic">Papers</hi> that demonstrate the editors’
                aim of “depict[ing] her vision and her prejudices, her convictions and her doubts,
                her patience and her anger, her prescience and her miscalculations” (xxxiii). The
                end result is a glimpse of ER’s personality and a fuller understanding of the type
                of woman she was. So, even though the editors have chosen to fill the volume with
                documents that only reflect ER’s public life, they have humanized her and made her
                more approachable.</p>
            <p>The volume is also easy to use. The descriptive titles provided for most documents
                allow for quick scanning of topics. Numbers assigned to each document are
                cross-referenced throughout the book. The lengthy index has been constructed with
                care and is notable for its usefulness and accuracy. The ultimate measure of success
                for a volume of edited documents, however, is its utility in helping scholars to
                craft a more well-rounded assessment of the subject in question. <hi rend="italic">The Eleanor
                Roosevelt Papers</hi>—projected to include five volumes in total—will undoubtedly force a
                reconsideration of ER’s life and career after she left the White House in April
                1945. The historiography of this precedent-setting First Lady will just as surely be
                altered in significant ways.</p>
            <signed>
                <name>Christopher Leahy</name>
                <affiliation>Keuka College, Coeditor, The Papers of Julia Gardiner Tyler</affiliation>
                <name>Sharon Williams Leahy</name>
                <affiliation><ref target="http://historypreserve.com" type="url">HistoryPreserve.com</ref>, Coeditor, The Papers of Julia Gardiner Tyler</affiliation>
            </signed>
        </body>
    </text>
</TEI>
