<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<?xml-model href="http://www.tei-c.org/release/xml/tei/custom/schema/relaxng/tei_all.rng" type="application/xml" schematypens="http://relaxng.org/ns/structure/1.0"?>
<?xml-model href="http://www.tei-c.org/release/xml/tei/custom/schema/relaxng/tei_all.rng" type="application/xml"
	schematypens="http://purl.oclc.org/dsdl/schematron"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
    <teiHeader>
        <fileDesc>
            <titleStmt>
                <title level="m"><hi rend="italic">Lo Stufaiuolo</hi> by Anton Francesco Doni: A
                    Scholarly Edition </title>
                <author>Anton Francesco Doni</author>

                <editor>Elena Pierazzo</editor>

            </titleStmt>
            <editionStmt>
                <edition>
                    <date>2015</date>
                </edition>
            </editionStmt>
            <publicationStmt>
                <authority>Scholarly Editing: The Annual of the Association for Documentary
                    Editing</authority>
                <idno type="file">intro.stufaiuolo</idno>
                <idno type="edition">stufaiuolo</idno>
                <address>
                    <addrLine>http://www.scholarlyediting.org</addrLine>
            </address>
                <publisher>Association for Documentary Editing</publisher>
                <publisher>University of Nebraska&#8211;Lincoln</publisher>
                <distributor>
                    <name>Center for Digital Research in the Humanities</name>
                    <address>
                        <addrLine>319 Love Library</addrLine>
                        <addrLine>University of Nebraska&#8211;Lincoln</addrLine>
                        <addrLine>Lincoln, NE 68588-4100</addrLine>
                        <addrLine>http://cdrh.unl.edu</addrLine>
                    </address>
                </distributor>
                <date>2015</date>
                <availability>
                    <p>Scholarly Editing: The Annual of the Association for Documentary Editing is
                        freely distributed by the Association for Documentary Editing and the Center
                        for Digital Research in the Humanities at the University of Nebraska-Lincoln
                        and licensed under a Creative Commons Attribution-NonCommercial-Share Alike
                        3.0 Unported License</p>
                </availability>
            </publicationStmt>
            <seriesStmt>
                <title level="j">Scholarly Editing: The Annual of the Association for Documentary
                    Editing</title>
                <respStmt>
                    <resp>editor</resp>
                    <name xml:id="ag">Amanda Gailey</name>
                </respStmt>
                <respStmt>
                    <resp>editor</resp>
                    <name xml:id="awj">Andrew Jewell</name>
                </respStmt>
                <idno type="vol">36</idno>
                <idno type="ISSN">2167-1257</idno>
            </seriesStmt>
            <sourceDesc>

                <bibl>
                    <note>Born digital.</note>
                </bibl>

            </sourceDesc>
        </fileDesc>
        <revisionDesc>
            <listChange>
                <change>
                    <date>2014-11-23T16:57:25Z</date>
                    <name>Elena Pierazzo</name>
                </change>
            </listChange>
        </revisionDesc>
    </teiHeader>
    <text>
        <front>
            <head type="main"><hi rend="italic">Lo Stufaiuolo</hi> by Anton Francesco Doni</head>
            <head type="sub">A Scholarly Edition</head>
            <byline>Elena Pierazzo</byline>
        </front>
        <body>

            <p>The critical reception of Anton Francesco Doni (Florence 1513–Monselice 1574) has
                known ups and downs. His works were authentic best sellers during his lifetime, with
                him constantly producing sequels and reprints to satisfy high demand; this success
                was also helped by Doni’s engagement with the booming print industry in Venice, in
                particular through his collaboration with avant-garde printers such as Gabriel
                Giolito de’ Ferrari and Francesco Marcolini. But by the turn of the sixteen century,
                however, a few years after his death his works were almost completely forgotten, at
                least in Italy.<note place="foot" xml:id="ftn1" n="1"> Doni had considerable success
                    in France, with many of his works translated and published well into the
                    seventeenth century. See, for instance, Giovanna Rizzarelli, “Traduzione e
                    mediazione tra Francia e Italia. Gabriel Chappuys e ‘Les dix plaisans
                    dialogues,’” in <hi rend="italic">Dissonanze concordi. Temi, questioni e
                        personaggi intorno ad Anton Francesco Doni</hi>, ed. G. Rizzarelli
                    (Bologna, il Mulino, 2013), 375–404. </note> The establishment of the
                Counter-Reformation’s control over the print industry and changes in literary taste
                meant that Doni’s works were only sought after by lexicographers who appreciated his
                inventive Florentine language. In all his productions Doni displayed a great
                awareness of his own language—the language spoken in Florence at the time—and
                advocated for its use for literary purposes. This was in contrast to the
                contemporary linguistic theories championed by Pietro Bembo, who promoted the use of
                the Florentine language used two centuries earlier by Petrarch and Boccaccio. </p>
            <p>Doni’s language has been studied for centuries by scholars and authors alike, both of
                whom have been fascinated by his vivid and flamboyant expression. His main works
                were also cannibalized by the authors of the most important Italian dictionary of
                the early modern period, that is the <hi rend="italic">Vocabolario degli Accademici
                    della Crusca</hi>. This literary misfortune lasted well into the twentieth
                century, with the few critical contributions that were produced focusing only on
                what scholars considered the most “serious” and “engaged” part of his production,
                namely the religious and the utopian works. It was not until 1988 with the seminal
                work by Giorgio Masi<note place="foot" xml:id="ftn2" n="2"> G. Masi, “‘Quelle
                    Discordanze sì Perfette’. Anton Francesco Doni 1551–1553,” in <hi rend="italic"
                        >Atti e Memorie dell’Accademia Toscana di Scienze e Lettere</hi>, 53, n.s.
                    39 (1988), 9–112. </note> that he started to return to favor. In contrast,
                the last thirty years or so have seen Doni’s critical fortune constantly on the
                rise, with monographs and new editions being published.<note place="foot"
                    xml:id="ftn3" n="3"> See, for instance, Giorgio Masi, ed., <hi rend="italic"
                        >“Una Soma di Libri”: L’Edizione delle Opere di Anton Francesco Doni</hi>,
                    Atti del seminario, Pisa, 14 Ottobre 2002 (Firenze: Leo Olschki Editore,
                    2008).</note> Considered at times a bohemian intellectual, a plagiarist, a
                heretic, a compiler without originality, and a utopist, Doni’s intellectual profile
                has puzzled more than one scholar. When I prepared my edition of the <hi
                    rend="italic">Zucca</hi>, published in 2003,<note place="foot" xml:id="ftn4"
                    n="4"> A. F. Doni, <hi rend="italic">Le Novelle, Tomo II: La Zucca</hi>, ed. E.
                    Pierazzo (Roma: Salerno Editrice 2003).</note> I did not even attempt a critical
                evaluation of the man, of the writer, or of the work itself: Doni and Doni’s
                production is to be taken “as is” and all labels mentioned above apply and certainly
                some more. Mid-sixteenth-century Italy was a period of great intellectual and
                cultural fervor: the classical culture that characterized so much of the fifteenth
                century was now considered boring and passé (“pedantic”) by a generation of young
                “hungry” intellectuals that used the roaring print industry to promote themselves on
                the cultural market. This classical culture was then stripped and repackaged in bits
                and pieces through the wholesale, unashamed plundering of quotations, as Paolo
                Cherchi has magisterially demonstrated.<note place="foot" xml:id="ftn5" n="5"> Paolo
                    Cherchi, <hi rend="italic">Polimatia di Riuso: Mezzo secolo di Plagio,
                        1539–1589</hi> (Roma: Bulzoni, 1998).</note></p>
            <p>The <hi rend="italic">Stufaiuolo</hi> (the “Spa-tender” or the “Spa-man,” more or
                less) is the only play we know from Doni's proteiform and extensive production. It
                is preserved in two autograph manuscripts, both beautifully crafted fair copies,
                written in 1557 (Camerino: Biblioteca Valentiniana di Camerino, MS 2 [henceforth
                V]) and 1559 (Florence: Biblioteca Mediceo-Riccardiana, MS 1184 [henceforth R]),
                respectively. The play more or less follows the traditional plot of many classical
                comedies: an old and a young man compete for the love of an honest young woman, then
                by means of a series of recognitions, identities are recovered, lost children are
                found, and everything ends in a string of weddings. What strikes the modern reader
                about this comedy is the number of sex crimes perpetrated or plotted: in rapid
                succession we witness a rape, sexual harassment, and incest. To be fair the latter
                is not consummated, since the girl in question is discovered to be the daughter of
                her seducer before any sexual act could take place, in the darkness of an alcove,
                after a candle has been fetched in order for the characters' identities to be
                ascertained by the means of some providential markings on their bodies. As for the
                other two sex crimes, there is little redemption. The rape is plotted as a rape (“Il
                letto, il buio, la comodità, la fragilità, i danari, la fede del secreto fanno gran
                violenza”: MS V, act II, scene 2); only because two women have changed place does
                the victim find out that her rapist is in fact the man she loves, and so a remedial
                wedding is quickly organized. Though we usually refrain from judging
                sixteenth-century Italy by today’s morality and values, this the comedy stands out
                for its sexual content even for the time. The only obvious precedent is perhaps
                Machaivelli’s <hi rend="italic">Mandragola</hi>, which displays a similar case of
                rape “redressed,” so to speak, and indeed this parallel is just one hint of how the
                    <hi rend="italic">Stufaiuolo</hi> draws on the <hi rend="italic">Mandragola</hi>
                as a model; the <hi rend="italic">Stufaiuolo</hi> in fact contains a few direct
                quotations from Machiavelli's masterpiece. </p>
            <p>The plot of the comedy is fairly strightforward, despite the obligatory exchange
                of clothing and faked identities. The eponymous character is Gottardo, the owner and
                tender of a “stufa,” a sort of spa where people go regularly to bathe, have their
                hair and nails cut, or have leeches applied. In Renaissance Italy, such spas were
                traditionally owned by Germans, and in fact Gottardo (in German, Gotthard) declares
                himself to be “di razza tedesca” (that is, German). His stufa in Venice is where most of the plot
                takes place. Messer Niccolò, a middle-aged Venetian lawyer, is married to the
                beautiful young Laura, whose family is unknown. He is constantly unfaithful to her,
                and the lack of proper intimacy with her husband makes her miserable. Laura confides
                her sorrows to Maddalena, a very smart and capable housekeeper; Maddalena is also
                the confidante of Taddea, Niccolò's widowed sister, who is hopelessly in love with a
                young merchant, Vincenzo. But Vincenzo fancies Laura instead. Maddalena is soon
                discovered to be the wife of a rich exile, Cesare; they have both left Genoa and
                lost two children, a boy and a girl, in the process. Cesare discloses to Maddalena
                that he is in love with Laura, and Maddalena agrees to help him to obtain her.
                Niccolò fancies a beautiful German courtesan, Druda, who is the girlfriend and
                business partner of the Stufaiuolo, the spa-tender. </p>
            <p>All the action happens in one night: Niccolò goes to the spa to take a bath but plans
                to force Druda to submit to his will instead; while he is in the bath, however,
                Vincenzo steals his clothes and goes to his house to rape Laura. Meanwhile Laura
                plots to catch her husband at the spa and leaves the house with Maddalena, leaving
                Taddea in her bed instead. At the spa, Maddalena convinces Druda to allow Laura to
                get in Druda's bed, making sure that Niccolò is kept out, and sends Cesare to join
                Laura in bed. While in bed with Cesare, Laura, instructed by Maddalena, shows Cesare
                a few moles on her body, whereupon he recognizes her as his—and
                Maddalena’s—estranged daughter. In the meantime Maddalena discovers Vincenzo in bed
                with Taddea and, again by means of moles, recognizes him to be her other lost child;
                Maddalena makes Vincenzo marry Taddea, Cesare confronts Niccolò about his behavior
                and then all turns into happiness and weddings: Vincenzo and Taddea, the Stufaiuolo
                and Druda, and Bigio and Caterina, both servants of Niccolò. The latter couple,
                Bigio and Caterina, are also responsible for most of the comic moments of the play:
                in particular, Caterina’s speeches are laced with sexual double entendres. Other
                slapstick moments are provided by Messer Niccolò, who fits perfectly the stereotype
                of the old man in love. </p>
            <p>All the action takes place during the period of carnival, accentuating the
                carnivalesque plot. The dizzying exchanges of identity and clothing, including the
                moment when the servants dress up in their masters’ garments, cannot but remind today’s
                reader of Bakhtin’s interpretational framework. </p>
            <p>The dating of the <hi rend="italic">Stufaiuolo</hi> is not clear: while the two
                manuscripts date to 1557 and 1559, respectively, there are reasons to believe that
                the work was instead composed before 1551, if not even earlier. The <hi
                    rend="italic">Stufaiuolo</hi> is in fact mentioned in the <hi rend="italic"
                    >Zucca</hi>, which was published in 1551, in the <hi rend="italic">Chiacchera
                    Ultima </hi>(Ic 16 9). In this passage Doni also mentioned that the play had
                been staged by Antonio Carafulla (nicknamed “Piè d’Oca”).<note place="foot"
                    xml:id="ftn6" n="6"> Doni,<hi rend="italic"> La Zucca</hi>, 192: “L’autorità del
                    Carafulla, strione della mi a comedia dello <hi rend="italic">Stufaiuolo</hi>
                    .”</note> Carafulla was a very famous Florentine actor, and since Doni left
                Florence in 1547, it is likely that the play was indeed composed and staged before
                that date. A Florentine origin also seems more plausible than a Venetian one: given
                the ridicule of Niccolò, a Venetian magistrate, it is more likely that the play was
                not conceived while in Venice but in Florence, with Venice representing a
                recognizable and yet conveniently “other” location that was apt to be ridiculed.
                This could also explain why the <hi rend="italic">Stufaiuolo</hi> was not printed
                during Doni’s stay in Venice but was circulated as a manuscript from 1557, the year
                when Doni left the city.</p>
            <p>The two versions present interesting differences in content and style. The earlier
                one, transmitted by the manuscript preserved in the Biblioteca Valentiniana of
                Camerino, seems close to the stage script, characterized as it is by movement,
                dance, acrobatics, and by shorter speeches and heavy sexual innuendo. The version
                transmitted by the manuscript preserved in the Biblioteca Mediceo-Riccardiana of
                Florence, on the other hand, is more literary, barely mentions dance, reduces the
                sexual subtext, and seems instead conceived for reading, probably aloud, as I will
                argue shortly.<note place="foot" xml:id="ftn7" n="7">Namely towards the end of the section “A Comparison of the Two
                    Witnesses.”</note> The two versions have their individuality, then, even if they
                look very much alike at first sight. The characters are the same, the number of
                speeches is more or less identical, and the underlying content does not change at
                all, besides the differences mentioned above. However, the collation of the two
                versions reveals thousands of variants, with the largest number of differences
                residing at the micro level of the language. For instance, at the lexical level many
                words in one version are substituted with synonyms in the other—a phenomenon that
                applies particularly to adjectives—and there is considerable diversification in the
                so-called accidentals: punctuation, orthography, capitalization, cases, word
                spacing, and so on, the importance of which will be discussed below. Rewriting that
                takes place between the two preserved versions is what one might call a “variation
                on a theme,” to use musical terminology, a tactic deployed by Doni throughout his
                whole career.<note place="foot" xml:id="ftn8" n="8"> See, among others, G. Masi,
                    “‘Quelle Discordanze sì Perfette.’”</note></p>
            <p>Both manuscripts are pristine fair copies: Doni was a gifted calligrapher and skilled
                at drawing (as shown in Figure 1), and the third phase of his career is
                characterized by the production of highly decorated and sophisticated manuscripts
                which were sent to rich noblemen in the hope of receiving financial support.</p>
            <figure type="enlargeOnClick">
                <head>Figure 1: Frontispieces of the two manuscripts, the Valentiniano to the left
                    and the Riccardiano to the right.</head>
                <graphic url="media/image1-combined.jpg"/>

            </figure>
            <p>Doni had worked as resident editor for three different publisher-printers and had
                become a printer himself, but in the last phase of his life (1556–1572) he almost
                completely dropped his engagement with printing and devoted himself to the
                production of manuscripts. He conceived these as handcrafted works, produced with
                painstaking attention to detail, intended for the dedicatee only, and reminiscent
                more of the epistolary model than the publishing one. In this way literature seems
                to become a private affair between the author and his unique reader, and this author
                aims to cash in on the exclusivity of the experience rather than on its diffusion.
                This phenomenon is particularly evident for the <hi rend="italic">Ville</hi>,
                another series of manuscripts/works that are completely rewritten from one copy to
                the next. Each time the dedicatee is changed, the work undergoes a rewriting that
                includes changing even the title: the <hi rend="italic">Villa Fucchera </hi>get its
                title from Jacob Fuegger, the famous banker; the <hi rend="italic">Villa
                    Attavanta</hi> gets its title from Pandolfo Attavanti; the <hi rend="italic"
                    >Villa Montecuccola</hi> is so entitled from Lodovico Montecuccoli, while the
                lost <hi rend="italic">Villa Saracca</hi> might get its name from Giovan Battista
                Saracco to whom Doni dedicated <hi rend="italic">Il Cancellieri</hi>: <hi
                    rend="italic">Libro dell’Eloquenza</hi>.<note place="foot" xml:id="ftn9" n="9">
                    See Elena Pierazzo, “Dalle <hi rend="italic">Nuove Pitture </hi>al <hi
                        rend="italic">Seme della Zucca</hi>,” in Masi, <hi rend="italic">“Una Soma
                        di Libri</hi>,” 271–97, especially appendix 2, “Nota sulla datazione delle
                        <hi rend="italic">Ville</hi>,” 295–97.</note></p>
            <p>Despite this manuscript work, Doni’s experience as a printer was not forgotten. With
                these manuscripts we could say that we have completed the circle of remediation. The
                early days of printing saw the attempts of printers to imitate manuscripts in order
                to make them more attractive to a class of snobbish intellectuals who were nurtured
                by the freshly rediscovered classics. With the <hi rend="italic">Stufaiuolo</hi>,
                almost exactly one century later, it is the manuscript that imitates print. This is
                evident from the very beginning, since both versions are provided with a
                frontispiece and benefit from the most modern book architecture and layout. Features
                such as dramatis personae and the division and numbering of acts and scenes had been
                gradually introduced in Venetian publishing houses around the end of the
                1530s,<note place="foot" xml:id="ftn10" n="10">For instance, the edition of the <hi rend="italic">Suppositi</hi> by
                    Ludovico Ariosto, published in Rome in 1524, is presented in divided scenes but
                    not yet with stage directions or dramatis personae. The latter, however, is
                    presented in the edition of the <hi rend="italic">Lena</hi> by the same author,
                    published in 1535 in Venice by Francesco Bindone Matteo Pasini. </note> and were
                slowly spreading throughout the rest of Europe. These innovations are evident in the
                vernacular plays before they were integrated into the editions of classics; as late
                as 1576 a Parisian edition of Plautus’s <hi rend="italic">Comedies</hi> still did not
                include a dramatis personae.</p>
            <p>The layout of the <hi rend="italic">Stufaiuolo</hi> is extremely regular and
                painstakingly controlled. The manuscripts are beautifully decorated with drop
                capitals, head- and tailpieces, cartouches and cadels. This type of decoration is a
                sort of branding of Doni’s work and can be found in most of his autograph
                manuscripts; for instance, one can see them in <hi rend="italic">I Numeri</hi>, <hi
                    rend="italic"> La Villa Fucchera</hi>, and <hi rend="italic">Le Nuove Pitture
                    </hi>.<note place="foot" xml:id="ftn11" n="11"> A. F. Doni, <hi rend="italic">I
                        Numeri</hi>, ed. A. Del Fante (Roma: Bulzoni, 1981). <hi rend="italic">La
                        Villa Fucchera</hi> is available as a digital facsimile (from microfilm)
                    from the website of the Bayerische Staats Bibliothek, Cod. ital. 36 (see
                    website). The facsimile edition of the <hi rend="italic">Le Nuove Pitture</hi>
                    has been recently published by Sonia Maffei: <hi rend="italic">Le nuove pitture
                        del Doni fiorentino: libro primo consacrato al mirabil signore Donno Aloise
                        da Este illustrissimo et reverendissimo: Biblioteca apostolica Vaticana, MS
                        Patetta 364</hi>, edizione a cura di Sonia Maffei; cura del testo,
                    presentazione, trascrizione, commento e saggio critico di Sonia Maffei; con una
                    nota musicale di Virgilio Bernardoni e una nota linguistica di Carlo Alberto
                    Girotto (Napoli: La stanza delle Scritture, 2006).</note> The latter is a
                particularly fine specimen, with Doni decorating an accompanying musical piece where
                the notes are represented by little bells, rattles, flowers, and mice. </p>
            <div type="section">
                <head type="main">The Current Edition</head>

                <p>The <hi rend="italic">Stufaiuolo</hi> was published for the first time in 1861 by
                    Salvatore Bongi.<note place="foot" xml:id="ftn12" n="12">
                        <hi rend="italic">Lo Stufaiolo Commedia in Prosa di Anton Francesco
                            Doni</hi> (Lucca: B. Canovetti, 1861). In her catalogue, Cecilia
                        Ricottini Marsili-Libelli relates the unverified presence of another
                        autograph of <hi rend="italic">Stufaiuolo</hi> at the Biblioteca Melziana,
                        which is allegedly dedicated to Ottavio Farnese (Cecilia
                        Marsili-Ricottini-Libelli, <hi rend="italic">Anton Francesco Doni: Scrittore
                            e Stampatore</hi> [Firenze: Sansoni Antiquariato, 1960], pp. 186);
                        however, Salvatore Bongi denies its existence as well as the existence of a
                        printed edition in Venice from 1585. There is no way to ascertain the
                        existence of such a manuscript since the Biblioteca Melziana was severely
                        damaged during the Second World War, and only a small portion of its
                        holdings survives as a collection in the Biblioteca Braidense in Milan. Yet
                        it is not implausible for Doni to have made more than two versions of the
                        manuscript, since he made up to four copies of his <hi rend="italic"
                            >Ville</hi> .</note> This edition was then reprinted in 1863 within a
                    larger collection of <hi rend="italic">Novelle</hi>,<note place="foot"
                        xml:id="ftn13" n="13">
                        <hi rend="italic">Tutte le Novelle, Lo Stufaiuolo, Commedia e la Mula e la
                            Chiave, dicerie di Antonfrancesco Doni</hi> (Milano, G. Daelli Editore,
                        1863): see Ricottini Marsili-Libelli, 189–90.</note> and again probably in
                        1916.<note place="foot" xml:id="ftn14" n="14"> Doni, <hi rend="italic"
                            >Scritti</hi> (Roma: Istituto Editoriale Italiano, [1916?]). The date of
                        publication is postulated by Ricottini Marsili-Libelli, 220–21.</note> All
                    these editions are based on the Riccardiano manuscript alone; the current
                    edition will be the first that takes into consideration the Valentiniano
                    manuscript. </p>
                <div type="sub-section">
                    <head type="sub">The witnesses</head>

                    <p>The Valentiniano manuscript (V) is preserved in pristine condition, still in
                        its original binding, which is decorated with gold penwork, similarly to the
                        manuscript of the <hi rend="italic">Nuove Pitture</hi> preserved in the
                        Vatican Library, MS Patetta 364.<note place="foot" xml:id="ftn15" n="15">
                            The binding is probably similar to that of <hi rend="italic">La</hi>
                            <hi rend="italic">Villa Fucchera</hi>; however, because of the bad
                            quality of the available images, it is not possible to tell whether
                            there is a gold decoration on the cover.</note></p>
                    <figure type="enlargeOnClick">
                        <head rend="italic">Figure 2: Valentiniano manuscript, upper cover</head>
                        <graphic n="1003" width="10.16cm" height="14.36511111111111cm"
                            url="media/image3.jpg" rend="inline"> </graphic>
                    </figure>

                    <p>The codex has been recently restored by the “Laboratorio di Restauro del
                        libro S. Maria di Rosano,” as indicated by the label pasted onto one of the
                        flyleaves. The flyleaves themselves were probably added during this
                        restoration, since they are not mentioned in the library catalogue of
                            1993.<note place="foot" xml:id="ftn16" n="16"> Giacomo Boccanegra and
                            Daniela Branciani, <hi rend="italic">Inventari dei Manoscritti delle
                                Biblioteche d’Italia, Vol. CVII: Camerino Biblioteca Comunale
                                Valentiniana</hi> (Firenze: Leo S. Olschki Editore, 1993), 12.
                        </note> No trace has been found of the musical score of the interludes that,
                        according to the dedication, was supposed to have accompanied the
                        manuscript; the codex is intact and nothing seems to be missing from it.
                        However, the score could have been bound separately from the play, as
                        it may have been more practical to have them detachable in order to
                        facilitate reading the text aloud with the musical performance at the same
                        time.</p>
                    <p>The frontispiece (f. 2r) contains a note of ownership: “Francisci Liberati”,
                        who has not been otherwise identified; the style of the handwriting suggests
                        the note was written in the late sixteenth-seventeenth century. The
                        manuscript was bought by Milziade Santoni, librarian and curator at the
                        Biblioteca Valentiniana, on May 9, 1880, from Rossi, a book dealer in Rome.
                        Enclosed with the manuscript is a page of the catalogue by Rossi on which
                        the sale price is reported to be 250 lire, a considerable price for the
                        time. A letter of authentication by Prospero Viani, dated Bologna 1870, is
                        similarly enclosed; this letter is mentioned in Rossi’s catalogue entry and
                        was probably commissioned by the dealer prior to the sale. The discrepancy
                        of the dates (letter 1870, purchased 1880), together with an annotation by
                        Santoni under the catalogue cutting that declares that the manuscript went
                        unsold for a while, suggests that the final price may have be considerably
                        reduced, but it is still unlikely to have been a trivial purchase. The
                        reasons why Santoni bought it are unknown: he was mainly interested in local
                        history and numismatics and held no evident interest in plays or the type of
                        literature produced by Doni.<note place="foot" xml:id="ftn17" n="17"> A
                            profile of the figure of Milziade Santoni can be read in his obituary by
                            B. Feliciangeli in “Atti e memorie della Regia Deputazione di Storia
                            Patria per le provincie delle Marche,” 1907, 5:109–28.</note> A detailed
                        description of the manuscript can be found <ref type="v_msDesc">here</ref>.
                        <!-- link to be fixed --></p>
                    <p>The copy in the Biblioteca Mediceo–Riccardiana (R) has lost its original
                        binding and is now part of a miscellaneous codex of which it is the first
                        item, ff. 1–24.<note place="foot" xml:id="ftn18" n="18"> Salomone
                            Morpurgo, <hi rend="italic">I Manoscritti della Biblioteca Riccardiana
                                di Firenze: Manoscritti Italiani</hi> (Roma, 1900), 1:235–39.
                        </note> The frontispiece (f. 2r) contains a note of ownership: “Questa
                        commedia e del S. Cav. Raff(aell)o di Lionardo Carnesecchi” (Figure 3).</p>
                    <figure type="enlargeOnClick">
                        <head>Figure 3: Possession note in R, f. 2r.</head>
                        <graphic n="1004" width="14.640277777777778cm" height="1.2286972222222223cm"
                            url="media/image4.png" rend="inline"/>
                    </figure>

                    <p>Raffaello di Lionardo Carnesecchi (1547–1621) was senator of the Grand Duchy
                        of Tuscany. It is not clear how Carnesecchi gained possession of the
                        manuscript. The dedicatee, to whom the manuscript was probably sent, was
                        Giacomo Piccolomini; he was Duke of Montemarciano in the Marche region but
                        probably lived in Siena where his son Alfonso, the famous outlaw, is
                        reported to have been born.<note place="foot" xml:id="ftn19" n="19">Alfonso
                            Piccololomini (Siena ca. 1550–Florence 1591) was a mercenary who then
                            became a renegade and an outlaw, leading for years a group of bandits,
                            until his capture and successive execution.</note> After Alfonso’s
                        execution, his possessions in Montemarciano were confiscated by the Pope,
                        while those in Siena were seized by the Grand Duke of Tuscany, so it is
                        possible that the accession of Carnesecchi was a consequence of the
                        dispersion of the Piccolomini estate after the execution of Alfonso (1591).
                        Carnesecchi died in 1615. Next, we know the manuscript was possessed by
                        Anton Maria Salvini, a famous linguist and intellectual of the time, a
                        member of the Accademia della Crusca and initial impetus behind the fourth
                        edition of the <hi rend="italic">Vocabolario </hi>(1729–38); this ownership
                        confirms the interest of linguists in the work of Doni. Salvini died in
                        1729; after his death, his heirs negotiated the sale of his library to
                        Gabriello Riccardi, the bibliophile of the Riccardi family whose personal
                        library became the original installment of the Biblioteca Riccardiana (later
                            Mediceo-Riccardiana).<note place="foot" xml:id="ftn20" n="20"> Guglielmo
                            Bartoletti, “I Manoscritti Riccardiani Provenienti dalla Libreria di
                            Anton Maria Salvini,” <hi rend="italic">Atti e Memorie dell’Accademia
                                Toscana di Scienza e Lettere</hi> “La Colombaria” 74, n.s. 60
                            (2009): 121–49.</note> The shelf mark of the <hi rend="italic"
                            >Stufaioulo</hi>, MS 1184, is still the one originally attributed by
                        Gabriello Riccardi. </p>
                    <p> It is not clear how the <hi rend="italic">Stufaiuolo</hi> ended up bound
                        with the other items that compose the miscellanea. The codex has been
                        foliated on the lower right corner with the help of a mechanical numerator,
                        a practice in use in the library between the 1950s and the 1960s. However,
                        an earlier handwritten foliation on the upper right corner shows that the
                        miscellanea was once ordered differently, with the current f. 232, which
                        corresponds to the beginning of the current item 7, a collection of
                            letters,<note place="foot" xml:id="ftn21" n="21"> Morpurgo, <hi
                                rend="italic">I Manoscritti</hi>, 237.</note> foliated as 1; the <hi
                            rend="italic">Stufaiuolo</hi> started then at f. 354 which, is now f. 1.
                        The miscellanea was given its present configuration in 1858 when it was
                        rebound by G. Berti.<note place="foot" xml:id="ftn22" n="22"> This
                            information comes from the Biblioteca Mediceo-Riccardiana’s archive and
                            has been kindly provided by the librarian there.</note> A detailed
                        description of the manuscript can be found <ref type="r_msDesc"
                        >here</ref>.</p>

                </div>
                <div type="sub-section">
                    <head type="sub">A comparison of the two witnesses </head>

                    <p>The text of the two manuscripts is very similar in some way and very
                        different in others. Apart from a few substantial variants that concern
                        principally the characters of Caterina and Bigio, whose carnivalesque
                        potential is strongly reduced in the shift from the Valentiniano (V) to the
                        Riccardiano (R), as we will see shortly, most of the variants are lexical
                        and orthographical. The tables below demonstrates this situation.</p>
                    <table>
                        <head>Table 1</head>
                        <row>
                            <cell role="label"> Valentiniano </cell>
                            <cell role="label"> Riccardiano </cell>
                        </row>
                        <row>
                            <cell>parecchi mesi</cell>
                            <cell>sei mesi</cell>
                        </row>
                        <row>
                            <cell>quà</cell>
                            <cell>qui a canto</cell>
                        </row>
                        <row>
                            <cell>lunga et lentamente</cell>
                            <cell>lenta, o lunga</cell>
                        </row>
                        <row>
                            <cell>cosa</cell>
                            <cell>Masseritia</cell>
                        </row>
                        <row>
                            <cell>drizzata</cell>
                            <cell>Rizzata</cell>
                        </row>
                        <row>
                            <cell>fuori uscito sconosciuto </cell>
                            <cell>fuori uscito della sua terra</cell>
                        </row>
                        <row>
                            <cell>sta al governo</cell>
                            <cell>sta per governo</cell>
                        </row>
                        <row>
                            <cell>in casa</cell>
                            <cell>della casa</cell>
                        </row>
                        <row>
                            <cell>scambiamenti di panni</cell>
                            <cell>rubamenti di panni</cell>
                        </row>
                        <row>
                            <cell>si traveston</cell>
                            <cell>si travestiscon</cell>
                        </row>
                        <row>
                            <cell>bella tirata</cell>
                            <cell>bella rinvoltura</cell>
                        </row>
                        <row>
                            <cell>inparerete</cell>
                            <cell>v’insegnerà</cell>
                        </row>
                        <row>
                            <cell>Tollererete</cell>
                            <cell>Imparerete a tollerare</cell>
                        </row>
                    </table>

                    <p>The following provides only a sample from the prologue, where one can also
                        find more substantial variants, but these consist only in paraphrases of the
                        same concept, and do not much add to or change the meaning of the
                        readings:</p>
                    <table>
                        <head>Table 2</head>
                        <row>
                            <cell role="label"> Valentiniano </cell>
                            <cell role="label"> Riccardiano </cell>
                        </row>
                        <row>
                            <cell>Signori Spettatori Illustrissimi magnifici, reali, et come voi
                                volete</cell>
                            <cell>Signori spettatori</cell>
                        </row>
                        <row>
                            <cell>queste bellissime donne</cell>
                            <cell>queste nobilissime et bellissime donne</cell>
                        </row>
                        <row>
                            <cell>ha presa la mia lingua</cell>
                            <cell>ha presa la lingua</cell>
                        </row>
                        <row>
                            <cell>nata in Italia come me</cell>
                            <cell>nata in Italia</cell>
                        </row>
                        <row>
                            <cell>Senza dirvi che la carne tira. Non si dice egli per proverbio,
                                tagliami le mani, e i piei: et gettami fra miei</cell>
                            <cell>per tenere del sangue del paese, meglio sodisfó all’apetito suo:
                                et poi</cell>
                        </row>
                        <row>
                            <cell>Hora, per non havermi lasciato mio padre possession, sto
                                qui</cell>
                            <cell>Hora io sto qui</cell>
                        </row>
                        <row>
                            <cell>et per una porta </cell>
                            <cell>insieme per una porta</cell>
                        </row>
                        <row>
                            <cell>riceve i nudi stufati</cell>
                            <cell>accomoda da ogni parte ne I letti I nudi stufati</cell>
                        </row>
                        <row>
                            <cell>hora state fermi et datemi dolcemente udienza</cell>
                            <cell>Porgetemi voi donne/ da un canto et voi huomini dall’altro
                                garbatamente udienza</cell>
                        </row>
                        <row>
                            <cell>hora in comedia ridotto</cell>
                            <cell>hora ridotto in Commedia</cell>
                        </row>
                    </table>

                    <p>Another set of comparisons consists of graphic or morphological
                        variation:<note place="foot" xml:id="ftn23" n="23">For a discussion about graphic and other types of
                            variation, see the “The Digital Edition: Layout and
                            Tools” section.</note>
                    </p>
                    <table>
                        <head>Table 3</head>
                        <row>
                            <cell role="label"> Valentiniano </cell>
                            <cell role="label"> Riccardiano </cell>
                        </row>
                        <row>
                            <cell>bellissime</cell>
                            <cell>bellißime</cell>
                        </row>
                        <row>
                            <cell>Todesca</cell>
                            <cell>Tedesca </cell>
                        </row>
                        <row>
                            <cell>apicco</cell>
                            <cell>appicco</cell>
                        </row>
                        <row>
                            <cell>ch’ella ha</cell>
                            <cell>che l’ha</cell>
                        </row>
                        <row>
                            <cell>Comedia</cell>
                            <cell>Commedia</cell>
                        </row>
                        <row>
                            <cell>menar</cell>
                            <cell>menare</cell>
                        </row>
                        <row>
                            <cell>indietro</cell>
                            <cell>in dietro</cell>
                        </row>
                        <row>
                            <cell>sta</cell>
                            <cell>stá</cell>
                        </row>
                        <row>
                            <cell>et</cell>
                            <cell>&amp;</cell>
                        </row>
                        <row>
                            <cell>lei </cell>
                            <cell>essa</cell>
                        </row>
                        <row>
                            <cell>credete</cell>
                            <cell>crediate</cell>
                        </row>
                    </table>

                    <p>Some patterns of correction can be detected, but these are only general
                        tendencies and lack the consistency that one normally attributes to a
                        campaign of revision. For instance, V seems to prefer apocopate words, while
                        R tends to avoid them (Table 3 menar ] menare); V presents a certain number
                        of degeminate consonants, while R has them doubled (V Comedia ] R Commedia;
                        apicco ] appicco). Counterexamples are V honore ] R honor (act I, scene 2); V cottone ]
                        R cotone (act V, scene 5).</p>
                    <p>In some parts the text is completely rewritten, almost word for word,
                        nevertheless without altering the meaning. This is the case, for instance,
                        in this speech by Cesare (act IV, scene 5):</p>
                    <table>
                        <head>Table 4</head>
                        <row>
                            <cell role="label"> Valentiniano </cell>
                            <cell role="label"> Riccardiano </cell>
                        </row>
                        <row>
                            <cell>Ogni cosa <hi rend="underline">s’aconcerà</hi>: lasciate dire a me
                                che comincerò con le brusche, e poi verremo alle <hi
                                    rend="underline">dolcezze</hi>, all’amicizie e parentadi. Doh
                                vecchio senza <hi rend="underline">cervello</hi>, è questa ora <hi
                                    rend="underline">d’un</hi> pari vostro <hi rend="underline"
                                    >d’andare </hi>in maschera <hi rend="underline">a
                                torno</hi>?</cell>
                            <cell>Ogni cosa <hi rend="underline">si acconcerà</hi>: lasciate dire a
                                me che <hi rend="underline">io</hi> comincerò con le brusche, e poi
                                verremo alle <hi rend="underline">dolci parole</hi>, all’amicizie e
                                parentadi. Doh vecchio senza <hi rend="underline">pensieri</hi>, è
                                questa ora <hi rend="underline">da un</hi> pari vostro <hi
                                    rend="underline">a ritrovarsi</hi> in maschera?</cell>
                        </row>
                    </table>

                    <p>As one can see, the meaning is only slightly altered: Cesare calls Niccolò
                        “brainless” in V and “thoughtless” in R, where the latter is a slightly less
                        offensive epithet. This form of rewriting is applied throughout the text.
                        Another example is the following, where Maddalena is speaking:</p>
                    <table>
                        <head>Table 5</head>
                        <row>
                            <cell role="label"> Valentiniano </cell>
                            <cell role="label"> Riccardiano </cell>
                        </row>
                        <row>
                            <cell>O che <hi rend="underline">bello</hi> accidente! Andiamo dentro,
                                    <hi rend="underline">che voi udirete cose nuove</hi>, e Laura
                                    <hi rend="underline">si ha </hi>da riempire <hi rend="underline"
                                    >anch’ella</hi> d’un <hi rend="underline">maggior</hi> diletto,
                                e voi e tutti! Or ditemi <hi rend="underline">un poco</hi>, che fu
                                di messer vecchio?</cell>
                            <cell>
                                <p>O che <hi rend="underline">nuovo</hi> accidente! Andiamo dentro
                                        <hi rend="underline">e lo intenderete</hi>. Laura <hi
                                        rend="underline">poi s’ha</hi> da riempire d’un <hi
                                        rend="underline">nuovo</hi> diletto, e voi e tutti! Or
                                    ditemi, che fu di messer vecchio?</p>
                            </cell>
                        </row>
                    </table>

                    <p>Here the most notable change is that the “bello” and “maggior” of V both
                        become “nuovo” in R, the reason for which is obscure; on the other hand V
                        has “cose nuove” which is suppressed in R.</p>
                    <p>Other differences lie in the number and quality of the speeches. For instance
                        in act II, scene 2, the dialogue between Caterina and Bigio is more granular
                        in V where there are twenty-five utterances against the twenty in R. In act
                        II, scene 4, in the dialogue between Niccolò and Bigio, we note in V the
                        repetition of the same structure (“N: Conficcasti tu tutte le finestre, come
                        io ti dissi? B: Messer sì! N: Quella del tetto? B: Messer sì. N: Quella
                        della volta? B: Messer sì. N: Quella del granaio?”); in R the answers of
                        Bigio are more varied (“B: Messer sì. [. . .] B: La fu la prima. [. . .] B: Messer
                        sì.”). The version of V is in general less compact and allows for some
                        repetition, while that of R is more literary and efficient; however, the
                        rhythm of the anaphoric repetitions of V would probably hold the scene
                        better.</p>
                    <p>As anticipated above, a major difference is created by the different handling
                        of the characters of the two servants, Caterina and Bigio. In V, all the
                        speeches of Caterina are sexually connoted; this characteristic is more or
                        less maintained in R but with a much smaller dose of innuendo and explicit
                        sexual reference. For instance, in the first act, Caterina goes to fetch
                        Taddea on behalf of Laura, her mistress, and lets her enter the house via
                        the back door. The door and key are a fairly common sexual metaphor, and
                        here this is played at all levels. Taddea expresses her surprise at being
                        lead via the back door, and here is Caterina’s reply, in both versions (V on
                        the left):</p>
                    <table>
                        <head>Table 6</head>
                        <row>
                            <cell>Bisogna accomodarsi a’ tempi, cara madonna! Il vecchio vuol la
                                porta dinanzi a suo diminio e vuol vedere e sapere chi va e chi
                                viene; noi che abbiamo qualche vogliuzza di comperare delle cosette,
                                non volete voi che ce la possiamo cavare? La sarebbe bella che
                                sempre avessimo a stare a bocca secca!</cell>
                            <cell>
                                <p>Bisogna accomodarsi a’ tempi, cara madonna! Il vecchio vuole
                                    aprire e serrare la porta dinanzi come gli piace: che volete che
                                    noi stiamo in prigione? La sarebbe bella!</p>
                            </cell>
                        </row>
                        <row>
                            <cell>Ell’è una comodità non conosciuta e vi potrete usandola dar
                                qualche spasso senza esser vergognata che i vicini vi stieno a
                                sindacare o a vedervi.</cell>
                            <cell>
                                <p>Ell’è una comodità non conosciuta: a me ha ella giovato più
                                    volte.</p>
                            </cell>
                        </row>
                    </table>

                    <p>The sexual innuendo can be found in the readings of R too, yet it could have
                        been missed if it were not for the more explicit version of V where key
                        words like “vogliuzza,” “bocca secca,” “spasso,” and “vergognata” provide a
                        more obvious hint.</p>
                    <p>Even more clear is the example of act IV, scene 4, where Caterina proposes to
                        Bigio; he initially refuses since he will not marry her without a dowry, but
                        then she convinces him by revealing that she receives the income of an
                        “estate”:</p>
                    <table>
                        <head>Table 7</head>
                        <row>
                            <cell>
                                <p><hi rend="bold">Caterina</hi>: Ha’ lo tu a sapere ora! Con un
                                    orto apiccato a quello, con fichi e nespole, e altri frutti che
                                    sono quasi insalvatichiti per non avere un ortolano che ci
                                    attenda, gagliardo, di buon nerbo, a modo mio: o frutterebbe
                                    bene!</p>
                                <p><hi rend="bold">Bigio</hi>: Seccosi eh? Io ti torrò, e lavorerò a
                                    mano ciò che vi è, e annesterò quei frutti che diventeranno
                                    dimestichi e saporiti.</p>
                                <p><hi rend="bold">Caterina</hi>: Se tu provederai qualche marza
                                    rigogliosa, la farà una prova grande, perch’egli è terreno
                                    smosso, soffice soffice, e per tal segnale vi fanno naturalmente
                                    i fichi lardegli tanto lunghi.</p>
                            </cell>
                            <cell>
                                <p><hi rend="bold">Caterina</hi>: Con un pezzo d’orto (o che terreno
                                    grasso!), con nespole e fichi lardegli tanto lunghi. E se io ci
                                    avessi tenuto sempre un ortolano di buon nerbo, farebbe tanta
                                    rendita ora che te ne staresti agiato largamente; ma egli è
                                    bisognato che io ci abbi messo a chi io mi sono abbattuta, in
                                    modo che la maggior parte del tempo e’ si sta sodo.</p>
                                <p><hi rend="bold">Bigio</hi>: Se così è, ti torrò e metterovvi di
                                    bei nesti.</p>
                                <p><hi rend="bold">Caterina</hi>: Se tu provederai qualche marza
                                    rigogliosa, la si appiccherà bene.</p>
                            </cell>
                        </row>
                    </table>

                    <p>The sexual metaphor is obvious in both readings, but in V it is more
                        developed and explicit.</p>
                    <p>The version of V also contains references to dance and acrobatics, which were
                        common components of sixteenth-century theatre. It is again Caterina who
                        brings the festive element in act IV, scene 4: “S’io mi metto a ballare o
                        che salti! Guarda capriuola che è questa”; the speech is missing in R. Again
                        in act IV, scene 5, she runs away, dancing and singing: “Va’ là Bigio in
                        qualche luogo andren noi: tantara tantararan ta ta! O che buon tempo!”
                        Again this speech is missing from R. One could conclude here that the
                        version of V seems closer to the stage than R is: acrobatics, dance, and
                        sexual puns and innuendos heavily characterized the staged plays of the
                        time. We know that the <hi rend="italic">Stufaiuolo</hi> was first composed
                        probably a decade before the oldest preserved witness (V), and that Doni
                        presumably kept it in a drawer during his stay in Venice. V was written in
                        1557, immediately after Doni left Venice and at a moment when he was trying
                        to establish himself in the Emilia Romagna.<note place="foot" xml:id="ftn24"
                            n="24"> In 1558 he obtained permission to open a printing house in
                            Ancona, but then he left the city, probably because of the injunction
                            issued by the Church that all clergy should return to their convent.
                            Emilia Romagna and the Marche were in fact part of the State of the
                            Church. <hi rend="italic">Dizionario Biografico degli Italiani</hi>
                            (Roma: Istituto dell’Enciclopedia Italiana, 1960),  vol. 41 (1992),
                            158&#8211;67.</note> It is probably no coincidence, then, that this version
                        is dedicated to Pier Donato Cesi, president of Emilia Romagna, and therefore
                        a quick reworking of a text Doni already had at hand could have served this
                        need for patronage. Such an assessment agrees with the observation that the
                        linguistic face of R seems more polished than that of V: if we assume that
                        Doni prepared the version of V quickly from the staged version, then we
                        would expect more linguistic consistency in R than in V. The analysis of the
                        manuscript also suggests relatively rapid production, as toward the end of V
                        Doni becomes less accurate with his writing. One can compare, for instance,
                        the following two specimens, where the first shows Doni’s writing at f. 5r
                        and the second at f. 17v. It is evident that the writing of the second
                        specimen is more rapid and less accurate; the ascenders lean toward the
                        right and the pen is lifted less, a sign of faster writing. </p>
                    <figure type="enlargeOnClick">
                        <head rend="italic">Figure 4: Specimens from V, ff. 5r (top) and 17v
                            (bottom).</head>
                        <graphic n="1005" width="14.640277777777778cm" height="0.7960833333333334cm"
                            url="media/image5-6.png" rend="inline"/>
                        <!--<graphic n="1006" width="14.640277777777778cm" height="0.8217833333333333cm"
                    url="media/image6.png" rend="inline"/>-->
                    </figure>

                    <p>The R version is more controlled from a linguistic and codicological point of
                        view; for instance, no noticeable difference can be spotted between the
                        style of writing on the first and the last page. This greater accuracy
                        reflects on the content too: R’s text is more mature and reads better than
                        V. Repetition and ambiguities are avoided and the text is in general tidier,
                        all of which is consistent with a text intended for reading rather than for
                        staging. On the other hand, however, it is also less lively and interesting,
                        as demonstrated by the samples discussed earlier. </p>
                </div>
            </div>
            <div type="section">
                <head type="main">The Digital Edition: Layout and Tools</head>

                <p>The analysis of the peculiarities of the different witnesses determined which
                    kind of edition to produce. It was clear from the first survey of the
                    manuscripts that a critical edition of the <hi rend="italic">Stufaiuolo</hi>
                    could not be produced by conflating the variant readings of the two versions.
                    Each version had a different aim, and the amount of variation between the two
                    was so great that the two witnesses had to be considered each on its own. When
                    it comes to multiple published versions, one should always consider that the
                    author considered each one “the work” at a given time and that it was, if not
                    “perfect,” then at least good enough to circulate under his or her name. That is
                    also the opinion of Cesare Segre, who in turn builds on the theories of
                    Gianfranco Contini.<note place="foot" xml:id="ftn25" n="25"> Cesare Segre, “Il
                        problema delle redazioni plurime,” in <hi rend="italic">La filologia
                            testuale e le scienze umane</hi>, Convegno internazionale organizzato in
                        collaborazione con l'Associazione Internazionale per gli Studi di Lingua e
                        Letteratura Italiana (Roma, 19–22 aprile 1993) (Roma: Accademia Nazionale
                        dei Lincei, 1994), 175–87.</note> An alternative to an eclectic edition
                    could have been to choose for publication only one of the two versions, but
                    which one? The earlier and “shabby” one, which is also so much more lively and
                    interesting, or the later one, providing a more mature version of the work? This
                    was a decision I could not make. Or, rather, the decision was to publish both,
                    producing therefore a synoptic edition. The choice of the medium also proposed
                    itself spontaneously: which publishing house would have supported a synoptic
                    edition of an obscure play of the sixteenth century? It was relatively simple to
                    secure the rights to publish the complete facsimile of the two manuscripts, the
                    aesthetic value of which is second only to their importance as documents;
                    however, only the digital medium would be able to support a synoptic edition
                    featuring a digital facsimile for each of the witnesses, given the very high
                    cost and little prospect for financial return that a print edition would
                    entail.</p>
                <p>There was another reason why the digital edition imposed itself as the only
                    possible editorial output. Anton Francesco Doni’s language has been praised,
                    sampled, and admired by readers and scholars, yet it is very little studied.
                    Most of his production is preserved only in printed, not handwritten, works;
                    therefore, it is always difficult to establish how much of the language on the
                    printed page is actually Doni’s own choice. Fortunately the small corpus of
                    autograph works makes it possible for us to study Doni’s accidentals without the
                    risk of being misled by the filter of the typesetters. However, perhaps not
                    surprisingly, the editions of his autograph works have privileged content over
                    language; the editions of <hi rend="italic">I Numeri</hi>, <hi rend="italic">Le
                        Ville</hi>, and <hi rend="italic">Le Nuove Pitture</hi> all present the
                    texts in a modernized reading version, leaving any reader interested in the
                    language to resort to direct inspection of the facsimile (except for the edition
                    of <hi rend="italic">Le Ville</hi>, which does not include a facsimile edition
                    at all); a few autographs remain unpublished. One of the main purposes of this
                    edition was to provide the reader with easy access to Doni’s language, including
                    his inconsistencies in orthography, as well as a reading edition that can appeal
                    to a wider readership. The deciding factor, therefore, was a digital edition’s
                    capability of providing multiple perspectives on the same text. </p>
                <p>In this respect, I hope that readers will allow me a personal anecdote. When I
                    started to work on the <hi rend="italic">Stufaiuolo</hi>, more years ago than I
                    would like to remember, I had just begun my engagement with text encoding and
                    Digital Humanities. This had started only as a temporary job, yet the
                    opportunities offered by text encoding and the TEI hooked me with the
                    possibility of encoding the same feature in more than one way at the same time,
                    particularly both original and regularized spellings. I have called this a
                    paradigmatic encoding and the editions resulting from such practice paradigmatic
                        editions.<note place="foot" xml:id="ftn26" n="26">E. Pierazzo, “Digital
                        Documentary Editions and the Others,” <hi rend="italic">Scholarly
                            Editing</hi> 35 (2014),
                            <ref type="url" target="http://www.scholarlyediting.org/2014/essays/essay.pierazzo.html">http://www.scholarlyediting.org/2014/essays/essay.pierazzo.html</ref>.</note> The
                    realization of this possibility, of preserving the original appearance of a text
                    while providing a reading edition, was the reason I chose digital editing, for
                    better or worse, as my form for all future intellectual endeavors. In the case
                    of the <hi rend="italic">Stufaiuolo</hi>, digital editing has also allowed me to
                    measure, quantitatively, the amount of editorial work involved in producing a
                    reading edition, which in turn has helped me to reflect on the heuristics of
                    editing overall. Let us consider the text of V, for instance. It is made of
                    about 11,500 words; the number of editorial interventions required to transform
                    a diplomatic edition into a (rather conservative) reading edition amounted to
                    4,821;
                    to this, one might add the regularization of u/v and U/V, which for this edition
                    has been done silently given the complete consistency of their usage (namely
                    only “u” for lowercase and “V” for uppercase, whatever their orthographic
                    value); adding this brings the total number of editorial interventions to
                    6,652,
                    that is to say, more than one for every other word, and this in a text that has
                    a very modern linguistic aspect. Traditional paper-based editions cope with
                    these normalizations by giving a summary notice of them in the introduction; a
                    TEI-XML framework, in contrast, allows the editor to record each normalization
                    where it occurs, namely within the text, making the editorial work much more
                    transparent and accountable. Furthermore, the practice of encoding each
                    editorial intervention allows these interventions to be categorized, enabling in
                    turn better insight into the editorial work.</p>
                <p>In the present edition, each editorial intervention has been encoded using
                    TEI-XML, which allows for registering the original reading as well as the
                    editorial transformation; the latter has also been categorized according to the
                    following types. </p>

                <p><list type="bulleted">
                        <head>Latinisms</head>
                        <item><hi rend="italic">lat</hi>: orthographical Latinism </item>
                        <item><hi rend="italic">lat-h</hi>: etymological or pseudo-etymological “h.”
                            Subset of Latinisms. Pseudo-etymological has its own label because of
                            its preponderance among orthographic Latinisms.</item>
                    </list></p>

                <p><list type="bulleted">
                        <head rend="bold">Spelling</head>
                        <item><hi rend="italic">diacritic-i</hi>: editorially removed overabundant
                            diacritic “i”</item>
                        <item><hi rend="italic">mp-mb</hi>: editorially regularized “np” and “nb”
                            into “mp” and “mb”</item>
                        <item><hi rend="italic">graphematic</hi>: editorially regularized graphemes
                            (“j” to “i," “&amp;” to “e,” “ß” to “ss”)</item>
                        <item><hi rend="italic">spelling</hi>: editorially regularized other
                            irregular spellings</item>
                    </list></p>

                <p><list type="bulleted">
                        <head rend="bold">Word separation</head>
                        <item><hi rend="italic">w-separation</hi>: editorially added spaces between
                            words, or more rarely, editorially deleted spaces between parts of words
                        </item>
                    </list></p>

                <p><list type="bulleted">
                        <head rend="bold">Diacritics</head>
                        <item><hi rend="italic">accent-add</hi>: editorially added accent</item>
                        <item><hi rend="italic">accent-del</hi>: editorially suppressed
                            accent</item>
                        <item><hi rend="italic">dir-acc</hi>: accent direction editorially
                            regularized </item>
                        <item><hi rend="italic">apo-add</hi>: editorially added apostrophe</item>
                        <item><hi rend="italic">apo-del</hi>: editorially suppressed
                            apostrophe</item>
                    </list></p>

                <p><list type="bulleted">
                        <head rend="bold">Capitalization</head>
                        <item><hi rend="italic">U2l-reg:</hi> uppercase to lowercase to match modern
                            use</item>
                        <item><hi rend="italic">l2U-reg</hi>: lowercase to uppercase to match modern
                            use</item>
                        <item><hi rend="italic">U2l-pc</hi>: uppercase to lowercase due to
                            editorially changed punctuation</item>
                        <item><hi rend="italic">l2U-pc</hi>: lowercase to uppercase due to
                            editorially changed punctuation</item>
                    </list></p>
                <p>A few words are necessary to justify the editorial choices made here. In moving
                    from diplomatic to reading versions, among the aforementioned normalizations, I
                    have not regularized double consonants according to modern use. This is normal
                    for editions of autograph material from the fifteenth and sixteenth centuries in
                    Italian Studies where the tradition is to try to intrude as little as possible
                    into the habits of the author.<note place="foot" xml:id="ftn27" n="27">See A. Stussi, <hi rend="italic"
                            >Introduzione Agli Studi di Filologia Italiana</hi> (Bologna: Il Mulino
                        1995), 150–54 (chap. 4, §§2.2–2.3).</note> For the same reason, words have
                    been separated or joined only in cases of linguistic ambiguity. In addition, a
                    single consonant has been kept even when for the editorially joined words the
                    modern use would have required a double consonant; therefore, forms such as "de
                    la" and "a Dio" have been rendered as "dela" and "adio." This practice is
                    consistent with the purpose of this edition, which is to showcase as much as
                    possible the linguistic patina of the author who was inconsistent and oscillated
                    among different graphic possibilities. The orthography and graphic affordances
                    of Renaissance Italy were much larger than those of modern Italian, and these
                    included the use of different allographs. Doni shows irregular and unambiguous
                    variation in three allographic forms: the use of the ampersand "&amp;" for the
                    conjunction "e" (also realized as "et" and "e"), the use of long "j" for simple
                    "i," and the use of "sharp s" ("ß") for double "s." Doni seems to have used the
                    forms interchangeably and without obvious rationale, and so these forms could
                    have been silently normalized here. However, it is not clear if the "sharp s" is
                    a ligature or a grapheme (as it was in German). Furthermore, given the almost
                    complete absence of any statistical assessment of the incidence of this form,
                    ampersands, or the long "j" in the language of sixteen century (or of any
                    century, probably) I have therefore preferred to retain these distinctions in
                    the diplomatic version. The irregular variation in these forms is in contrast
                    with the use of "u" versus "v" in these witnesses, which consistently follows
                    regular usage of the time and is therefore silently normalized in this
                    edition. </p>
                <p>As well as the texts, then, this edition also provides statistical data about the
                    incidence of all marked phenomena as well as lists all occurrences of
                    normalization, making it possible for the reader to not only read the text in its
                    original linguistic aspect but also appreciate the impact of editorial work on
                    the final text. The lists, accessible from each version of the edition, are
                    given in order of the frequency of each phenomena.</p>
                <p>Another purpose of the encoding was to be able to study the entire
                    paragraphematic system of the text. For this reason every authorial punctuation
                    mark, as well as each instance of punctuation newly introduced by the editor,
                    has been encoded. Also marked are the so-called soft hyphens used at line breaks
                    to indicate that a word will continue on the next line; this latter category is
                    particularly interesting since Doni also used such hyphens between some complete
                    words, not only between parts of words (and in both cases they can also take the
                    form of an equals sign). An account of the paragraphematic system and its
                    pattern can be found <ref target="#paragr">further
                    below</ref>.</p>
                <p>The digital edition therefore presents each of the two versions in a triple
                    format: the facsimile, diplomatic, and reading editions. The comparison between
                    the two versions is performed by <ref type="url"
                        target="http://juxtacommons.org/shares/jcoN9g">Juxta Commons</ref>, software
                    developed within the NINES project, that allows for a dynamic comparison between
                    two or more witnesses of any given work. The comparison is performed between the
                    two diplomatic editions; this choice facilitates comparison among the so-called
                    accidentals of the texts rather than only at the level of substantive variants.
                    Although doing so increases the number of variants, it also reveals the lack of
                    consistency in Doni’s orthographic choices, providing better insight into the
                    orthographic writing habits of the time.</p>

                <div type="sub-section" xml:id="paragr">
                    <head type="sub">The Paragraphematic System</head>

                    <p>The signs used by Doni in this manuscript are as follows: &lt;. , ; : :~ .~ (
                        )&gt;. He uses punctuation in a very modern way; one could easily read the
                        text today with his punctuation intact. Of the 2,573 authorial punctuation
                        marks, 768 (29 percent) have been retained by the editor for the reading
                        edition. However, Doni employs two signs that do not have a direct
                        correspondence in the modern paragraphematic system: a sign for the period,
                        which looks like the combination of a colon and a tilde (:~), and a sign the
                        appearance of which is in between a question and an exclamation mark (Figure
                        5). This is the so-called <hi rend="italic">punctus interrogativus</hi>, the
                        ancestor of our question mark, and in the reading edition it has been mostly
                        translated into a question mark but sometimes as an exclamation mark.<note
                            place="foot" xml:id="ftn28" n="28">
                            A late medieval <hi rend="italic">Ars Punctandi</hi> that has been
                                attributed to Coluccio Salutati and Petrarch, among others,
                                describes it as follows: “<hi rend="italic">punctus planus et super
                                    ipsum punctus longus ad modum cornu</hi>.” Rosario Coluccia,
                                “Teorie e Practiche Interpuntive nei Volgari d’Italia,” in <hi
                                    rend="italic">Storia della Punteggiatura in Europa</hi>, ed.
                                Bice Mortara Garavelli (Roma-Bari: Laterza, 2008), 65–98; 96. 
                        </note> To be precise, in the text of V, of the 170 occurrences of this
                        sign, 50 have been converted into an exclamation mark, 101 to a question
                        mark, 6 to a comma, 9 to a period, 2 to a colon, and 1 to a semicolon. In the
                        text of R, of the 169 occurrences, 48 have been converted into an
                        exclamation mark, 109 to a question mark, 7 to a comma, and 4 to a period. </p>
                    <figure>
                        <head rend="italic">Figure 5: Four specimens of the punctus interrogativus
                            mark. The first two are from V, f. 4r; the second two from R, f. 5r. </head>
                        <graphic url="media/image7-combined.jpg"/>
                    </figure>

                    <p>For want of something better, this sign has been rendered in the diplomatic
                        edition with a digraph made of a period and a tilde (.~); this latter sign
                        is attested for instance in the manuscript of the <hi rend="italic"
                            >Andria</hi> by Machiavelli.<note place="foot" xml:id="ftn29" n="29">
                            Brian Richardson, “Dalla metà del Quattrocento alla metà del
                            Cinquecento,” in Mortara Garavelli, <hi rend="italic">Storia</hi>, 113.
                        </note></p>
                    <p>Both accents and apostrophes are used; as for the former, only acute accents
                        are found. With respect to modern usage, many monosyllabic words that in
                        modern Italian do not require accents receive them in our manuscripts (nó,
                        quá, stá), while others that have them today lack them in Doni’s text (piu,
                        di, la). Apostrophes are used in case of truncated words (son’, cercar’,
                        amorevol’) but are missing in pronouns and verbs (e &gt; e’, se &gt; se’,
                        vo &gt; vo’).</p>
                    <p>Perhaps the most puzzling aspect of Doni’s paragraphematic system is offered
                        by the hyphens and equals signs he used at the ends of lines in between
                        complete words (also called <hi rend="italic">semipunctus</hi>), rather than
                        only between parts of the words that are divided by the break. An
                        inexhaustive yet extensive investigation into contemporary printed and
                        manuscript books has not shown any evidence of this being a trend of some
                        sort, nor does the excellent <hi rend="italic">Storia della Punteggiatura in
                            Europa </hi>edited by Bice Moratara Garavelli report such use of the
                        hyphen. However, one can also find it in the other autograph copies of works
                        by Doni, such as <hi rend="italic">I Numeri</hi> or <hi rend="italic">Le
                            Nuove Pitture</hi>, for instance. One must therefore conclude that this
                        feature is specific to Doni. Examining the pairs of words connected by these
                        signs does not reveal any particular pattern, either. When we look at
                        the first ten occurrences of the phenomenon in V (Table 8), no obvious grammatical pattern emerges.</p>
                    <table>
                        <head>Table 8</head>
                        <row>
                            <cell>
                                <hi rend="bold">End of line - Beginning of following line</hi>
                            </cell>
                            <cell>
                                <hi rend="bold">POS</hi>
                            </cell>
                        </row>
                        <row>
                            <cell>1. onorati - signori</cell>
                            <cell>adjective - noun</cell>
                        </row>
                        <row>
                            <cell>2. al - mondo</cell>
                            <cell>preposition - noun</cell>
                        </row>
                        <row>
                            <cell>3. come - udirete</cell>
                            <cell>adverb - verb</cell>
                        </row>
                        <row>
                            <cell>4. nata - in</cell>
                            <cell>adjective - preposition</cell>
                        </row>
                        <row>
                            <cell>5. lunga - et</cell>
                            <cell>adjective - conjunction</cell>
                        </row>
                        <row>
                            <cell>6. rubamenti - et</cell>
                            <cell>noun - conjunction</cell>
                        </row>
                        <row>
                            <cell>7. dire - d’esser</cell>
                            <cell>verb - verb</cell>
                        </row>
                        <row>
                            <cell>8. fuori - della</cell>
                            <cell>adverb - preposition</cell>
                        </row>
                        <row>
                            <cell>9. mai - lo</cell>
                            <cell>adverb - pronoun</cell>
                        </row>
                        <row>
                            <cell>10. ti - prego</cell>
                            <cell>pronoun - verb</cell>
                        </row>
                    </table>
                    <p>When we look at words separated by the equals sign, or the occurrences of the
                        phenomenon in R, the situation is the same. So where does this sign come
                        from and what is its meaning? It may have been used as line filler in order
                        to justify the right margin, but in many cases its use makes the line exceed
                        its optimal length; this is the case, for instance, in V f. 4r, in the
                        fourth line from the top, where the hyphen is added after the word "nata."
                        As Figure 6 shows, the letter "a" has been stretched to fill the line, yet
                        the little hyphen extends well into the margin. On the previous line,
                        however, the hyphen after "come" does appear to have been used as a
                        filler.</p>
                    <figure>
                        <head rend="italic"> Figure 6: V f. 4r, end of lines 3, 4, and 5.</head>
                        <graphic url="media/image8.jpg"/>
                    </figure>
                    <p>This fact is even more evident at f. 6v, where the speech of Vincenzo is
                        interrupted by an aside of Caterina, and the equals sign is in the middle
                        of the line, to signify, most probably, that even if the speech is
                        interrupted, the sentence continues.</p>
                    <p>It is of course impossible to give a decisive answer to these questions.
                        However, some hints may come from two domains very close to Doni and to the
                            <hi rend="italic">Stufaiuolo</hi>: reading practices and music
                        performance. Marzia Pieri in her 1992 article focuses on the richness of punctuation
                        in theatrical plays, seeing punctuation as a sort of stage direction, that
                        is, indicating to the actors how to enact a particular speech.<note
                            place="foot" xml:id="ftn30" n="30"> Marzia Pieri<hi rend="italic">,
                                “</hi>Fra scrittura e scena: la cinquecentina teatrale,” in <hi
                                rend="italic">Storia e teoria dell’interpunzione: Atti del Convegno
                                Internazionale di Studi Firenze 19–21 maggio 1988</hi>, ed. E.
                            Cresti, N. Maraschio, and L. Toschi (Roma: Bulzoni, 1992),
                            245–67.</note> Sixteenth-century theoreticians such as Chiantera and
                        Maraschio emphasize that one of the main purposes of punctuation is to
                        support the practice of reading aloud.<note place="foot" xml:id="ftn31"
                            n="31"> Angela Chiantera, “Pubblico e punteggiatura nel Cinquecento,” in
                                <hi rend="italic">Problemi</hi> 4 (1983): 237–49; Nicoletta Maraschio, “Il Secondo Cinquecento,” in Mortara
                            Garavelli, <hi rend="italic">Storia</hi>, 122–37.
                        </note> Could these signs have been for that purpose? Could they be
                        directing the reader not to pause too long at the line break? The hypothesis
                        is tempting and finds support in the musical practice of the time. In
                        Gregorian musical notation it was normal to add a small note at the end of
                        each line to alert the singer to the first note of the following line; this
                        little note is called <hi rend="italic">custos </hi>(“guardian” or “guide”),
                        and although it was a practice falling out of use in Doni’s time, Doni
                        himself used it in his musical manuscripts (see <hi rend="italic">Le Nuove
                            Pitture</hi>). The richness of the punctuation of the <hi rend="italic"
                            >Stufaiuolo</hi>, along with its modernity, seem to suggest that reading
                        aloud was indeed the intended aim for the play. This, and the usage of
                        hyphens, as well as Doni’s musical education and the fact that the V version
                        was supposed to have been accompanied by musical scores, all seem to
                        indicate that we could consider the <hi rend="italic">Stufaiuolo</hi> a sort
                        of score for voice reading.</p>
                </div>
            </div>
            <div type="section">
                <head type="main">Conclusions</head>

                <p>The <hi rend="italic">Stufaiuolo</hi> is certainly not the most beautiful or
                    original play of the Italian Renaissance, yet it holds much to tempt the modern
                    reader. From its unusual plot to the aesthetic value of the manuscripts to the
                    originality of its language and the ingenuity of the punctuation, it seems clear
                    that the <hi rend="italic">Stufaiuolo</hi> has been neglected for too long. The
                    current edition fills this gap and offers its readers the tools for a full
                    appreciation of all aspects of this comedy. Despite being around for more than
                    twenty years, digital editions still seem to need to justify themselves. This
                    edition of the <hi rend="italic">Stufaiuolo</hi> is no exception to that rule,
                    in particular because it is very unusual in the field of Italian Studies to
                    offer the edition of a single work on the web. I can only hope that presenting
                    the text in this way will establish a practice that has so much to offer to
                    editors and readers alike.</p>
            </div>
        </body>
    </text>
</TEI>
