<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<?oxygen RNGSchema="http://www.scholarlyediting.org/scholarlyediting.rng" type="xml"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
    <teiHeader xml:lang="eng">
        <fileDesc>
            <titleStmt>
                <title level="a" type="main">Editors' Introduction to the 2015 Issue of <hi
                        rend="italic">Scholarly Editing: The Annual of the Association for
                        Documentary Editing</hi>
                </title>

                <author>Amanda Gailey</author>
                <author>Andrew Jewell</author>
            </titleStmt>
            <editionStmt>
                <edition>
                    <date>2015</date>
                </edition>
            </editionStmt>
            <publicationStmt>
                <idno type="file">essay.v36intro</idno>
                <authority>Scholary Editing: The Annual of the Association for Documentary
                    Editing</authority>
                <address>
          <addrLine>http://www.scholarlyediting.org</addrLine>
        </address>
                <publisher>Association for Documentary Editing</publisher>
                <publisher>University of Nebraska&#8211;Lincoln</publisher>
                <distributor>
                    <name>Center for Digital Research in the Humanities</name>
                    <address>
            <addrLine>319 Love Library</addrLine>
            <addrLine>University of Nebraska&#8211;Lincoln</addrLine>
            <addrLine>Lincoln, NE 68588-4100</addrLine>
            <addrLine>http://cdrh.unl.edu</addrLine>
          </address>
                </distributor>
                <date>2015</date>
                <availability>
                    <p>Scholary Editing: The Annual of the Association for Documentary Editing is
                        freely distributed by the Association for Documentary Editing and the Center
                        for Digital Research in the Humanities at the University of Nebraska-Lincoln
                        and licensed under a Creative Commons Attribution-NonCommercial-ShareAlike
                        3.0 Unported License</p>
                </availability>
            </publicationStmt>
            <seriesStmt>
                <title level="j">Scholarly Editing: The Annual of the Association for Documentary
                    Editing</title>
                <respStmt>
                    <resp>editor</resp>
                    <name xml:id="aag">Amanda Gailey</name>
                </respStmt>
                <respStmt>
                    <resp>editor</resp>
                    <name xml:id="awj">Andrew Jewell</name>
                </respStmt>
                <idno type="vol">36</idno>
                <idno type="ISSN">2167-1257</idno>
            </seriesStmt>
            <sourceDesc>
                <bibl>
                    <note>Born digital.</note>
                </bibl>
            </sourceDesc>
        </fileDesc>
        <revisionDesc>
            <change when="2015-03-23" who="#aag">markup in TEI XML</change>
        </revisionDesc>
    </teiHeader>
    <text>
        <front>
            <head type="main">Editors' Introduction to the 2015 Issue of <hi rend="italic">Scholarly
                    Editing: The Annual of the Association for Documentary Editing</hi></head>
            <byline>Amanda Gailey</byline>
            <byline>Andrew Jewell</byline>

        </front>

        <body>
            <p>The fourth issue of <hi rend="italic">Scholarly Editing: The Annual of the
                    Association for Documentary Editing</hi> includes two new developments. First,
                we are pleased to introduce a new feature, "Reflections on the Editor's Craft,"
                where we will publish the views of experienced editors on practical aspects of
                editing. In our inaugural essay, <ref type="html"
                    target="../../2015/essays/essay.gordon">"Editing Death: An Element
                    of Craft,"</ref> Ann D. Gordon discusses the challenge editors face in handling
                a subject's death, and offers the case of Elizabeth Cady Stanton as an example.
                Also, this issue of <hi rend="italic">Scholarly Editing: The Annual of the
                    Association for Documentary Editing</hi> includes for the first time an edition
                that eschews the linear presentation of text favored by TEI (Text Encoding
                Initiative) markup. Daniel Carter's <ref type="html"
                    target="../../2015/editions/intro.hejinian">edition of Language poet Lyn
                    Hejinian's autobiographical <hi rend="italic">My Life</hi></ref> uses comma
                separated values, Python, and Javascript to visualize repetition and variation in
                the work. Carter also includes "What's Missing from <hi rend="italic">My Life</hi>,"
                Hejinian's essay that expands upon on the work Carter has edited. We are excited to
                present this experimental method of digital editing.</p>
            <p>Laura L. Mielke and Martha Baldwin have contributed an edition of a play by Kate
                Edwards Swayze, <ref type="html" target="../../2015/editions/intro.swayzedrama"
                        ><hi rend="italic">“a black diamond among thim American wifes”: Kate Edwards
                        Swayze’s Antislavery Adaptation of George Colman’s </hi>Inkle and
                    Yarico</ref>. Swayze's abolitionist play adapted a popular British comic opera
                about an interracial romance by placing it firmly in the context of American
                slavery. The edition makes available a fascinating and neglected antislavery
                document, and even offers a Juxta visualization of the difference between Swayze's
                drama and her British source text.</p>
            <p>Another edition in this year's issue also focuses on an antislavery text. Todd
                Thompson and Jessica Showalter have edited <ref type="html"
                    target="../../2015/editions/intro.lowelledition">a satirical poem by James
                    Russell Lowell</ref> that criticizes the US-Mexico War and was reprinted in
                    several American newspapers. The edition presents the text of "LETTER FROM
                A VOLUNTEER IN SALTILLO," noting all the variants that occurred among the six
                reprints as it was recontextualized in different periodicals, producing, as the
                editors put it, "not just a study of textual variants but also a story about editors
                and their choices."</p>
            <p>We continue to offer editions of texts in languages other than English. Elena
                Pierazzo's <ref type="html" target="../../2015/editions/intro.stufaiuolo">Lo
                    Stufaiuolo <hi rend="italic">by Anton Francesco Doni: A Scholarly
                    Edition</hi></ref> presents the sixteenth-century Italian comedy in a triple
                format, with facsimile, diplomatic, and reading editions of two different manuscript
                versions of the play. The diplomatic editions have been put into Juxta to visualize
                their differences. Pierazzo's careful introduction and detailed editing have
                produced a flexible and robust edition. </p>


            <p>This issue of <hi rend="italic">Scholarly Editing</hi> also offers an essay by Amanda
                Gagel, <ref type="html" target="../../2015/essays/essay.gagel">"Letters as Critical Texts: A Consideration of Mark Twain’s 'Ashcroft-Lyon
                Manuscript,'"</ref> which examines the theoretical difficulties surrounding letters, and
                <ref type="html" target="../../2015/essays/essay.2015presidentialaddress">James P. McClure's address</ref> as the president of the Association for Documentary
                Editing, presented at the annual meeting in 2014. We are also pleased to offer reviews of three
                new scholarly editions and an annotated list of recently published editions. </p>
            <p>All of this material reflects the vibrant and varied world of
                editorial scholarship in both print and digital environments.</p>


        </body>





    </text>
</TEI>
