<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<?oxygen RNGSchema="http://www.scholarlyediting.org/scholarlyediting.rng" type="xml"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xml:lang="eng">
    <teiHeader>
        <fileDesc>
            <titleStmt>
                <title level="a" type="main">Letters as Critical Texts</title>
                <title level="a" type="sub">A Consideration of Mark Twain’s “Ashcroft-Lyon
                    Manuscript”</title>
                <author key="Gagel, Amanda">Amanda Gagel</author>
            </titleStmt>
            <editionStmt>
                <edition>
                    <date>2015</date>
                </edition>
            </editionStmt>
            <publicationStmt>
                <idno type="file">essay.gagel</idno>
                <authority>Scholary Editing: The Annual of the Association for Documentary
                    Editing</authority>
                <address>
 <addrLine>http://www.scholarlyediting.org</addrLine>
</address>
                <publisher>Association for Documentary Editing</publisher>
                <publisher>University of Nebraska&#8211;Lincoln</publisher>
                <distributor>
                    <name>Center for Digital Research in the Humanities</name>
                    <address>
<addrLine>319 Love Library</addrLine>
<addrLine>University of Nebraska&#8211;Lincoln</addrLine>
<addrLine>Lincoln, NE 68588-4100</addrLine>
<addrLine>http://cdrh.unl.edu</addrLine>
 </address>
                </distributor>
                <date>2015</date>
                <availability>
                    <p>Scholary Editing: The Annual of the Association for Documentary Editing is
                        freely distributed by the Association for Documentary Editing and the Center
                        for Digital Research in the Humanities at the University of Nebraska-Lincoln
                        and licensed under a Creative Commons Attribution-NonCommercial-ShareAlike
                        3.0 Unported License</p>
                </availability>
            </publicationStmt>
            <seriesStmt>
                <title level="j">Scholarly Editing: The Annual of the Association for Documentary
                    Editing</title>
                <respStmt>
                    <resp>editor</resp>
                    <name xml:id="ag" key="Gailey, Amanda A.">Amanda Gailey</name>
                </respStmt>
                <respStmt>
                    <resp>editor</resp>
                    <name xml:id="awj" key="Jewell, Andrew W.">Andrew Jewell</name>
                </respStmt>
                <idno type="vol">36</idno>
                <idno type="ISSN">2167-1257</idno>
            </seriesStmt>
            <sourceDesc>
                <bibl>
                    <note>Born digital.</note>
                </bibl>
            </sourceDesc>
        </fileDesc>
        <revisionDesc>
            <change when="2015-01-14"><name xml:id="gk" key="Kirilloff, Gabi">Gabi Kirilloff</name>
                markup in TEI XML</change>
        </revisionDesc>
    </teiHeader>
    <text>
        <front>
            <head type="main">Letters as Critical Texts</head>
            <head type="sub">A Consideration of Mark Twain’s “Ashcroft-Lyon Manuscript”</head>
            <byline>Amanda Gagel</byline>
        </front>
        <body>
            <div type="section"><p>The “Ashcroft-Lyon manuscript” is a 429-page diatribe written in 1909, one year
                before Samuel L. Clemens's (Mark Twain's) death. The text will appear in the third and final volume of
                his <hi rend="italic">Autobiography</hi>, the current publishing endeavor of the
                Mark Twain Project.<ptr target="#note1" xml:id="nr1" n="1"/> The document is Twain’s
                rancorous attack on, and laborious account of, ways that his secretary, Isabel Lyon,
                and business manager, Ralph Ashcroft, allegedly embezzled money from him during the
                years 1907 to 1909, as well as manipulated Twain’s relationship with his youngest
                daughter, Jean, resulting in her needless residence in sanitariums for three
                    years.<ptr target="#note2" xml:id="nr2" n="2"/> There have been monographs
                written about this manuscript as well as a number of articles.<ptr target="#note3"
                    xml:id="nr3" n="3"/> The text itself has never been published but has been
                readily available in the Mark Twain Papers and is often cited as evidence of either
                Lyon’s and Ashcroft’s guilt or Twain’s overzealous persecution of them.</p>
            <p>Putting aside the contextual life of this manuscript, editing the work itself has
                presented unique challenges for the editors, at least in part because it was written
                in the guise of an unsent letter to Twain’s good friend William Dean Howells. The
                editors argue that this device was an autobiographical strategy that
                Twain was experimenting with at the time, that is, writing a letter that would never
                be sent, in order to free himself from the constraints inherent in writing a letter
                (or anything else) that was intended for publication. While Twain was composing the
                final form of his autobiography, from roughly 1905 to 1909, he worked chiefly by
                dictating to a stenographer, a practice that he felt also allowed him a degree of
                freedom to say the (conventionally) unsayable, but after three years of dictating,
                this practice too seemed deficient.<ptr target="#note4" xml:id="nr4"
                    n="4"/></p>
            <p>The letter form of the Ashcroft-Lyon manuscript provides us with an alternative
                approach to crafting an autobiographical narrative, but one the author did not
                continue to use after this composition. Twain did <hi rend="italic">not</hi> intend
                for the manuscript to be a part of his autobiography, because he was meticulous
                about marking which dictations and manuscripts should be included in it. Also, it is
                noted in letters that he meant for the manuscript to be held privately and used only
                if Ashcroft and Lyon ever threatened legal or other action against the
                    Clemenses.<ptr target="#note5" xml:id="nr5" n="5"/> Regardless, he did at
                times view the “letter” as a preferred way to relate a more honest account of an
                event from his life than he could achieve in his dictations. Therefore, including
                this text with the <hi rend="italic">Autobiography</hi> required the editors to
                rethink how the text should be presented, compared to the presentation of the
                dictations. Since it is technically a letter, should it be transcribed in plain text
                as are the letters published by the Mark Twain Project? Or should it be printed in
                clear text as are the dictations of the <hi rend="italic">Autobiography</hi>?</p>
            <p>The editorial deliberation over these questions also raised, at least for me, a
                number of larger questions. How does this manuscript affect our understanding and
                definition of the “letter”? What do we understand letters to be when editing them
                for inclusion in a scholarly edition or elsewhere? Are they text of a conversation?
                Are they literature? Are they notes? Are they a dramatic performance? Are they
                private or public documents or both? Letters are sometimes all these things and
                more, and the expectation of what they accomplish as a textual medium changes
                depending on, among other things, what century of letter writing one is studying
                and the context of their composition. That said, they are a fascinating example of
                how a genre of text can evolve. So what can we learn from deliberations over the
                Ashcroft-Lyon manuscript, since the dynamic nature of letters is something not easy
                to pin down?</p>
            <p>Within this frame of analysis, this article reviews the current thinking on the
                epistolary form and identifies where more nuanced thought is lacking when it comes
                to a critical textual study of letters being presented in different media formats. I
                will use Twain’s Ashcroft-Lyon manuscript and other examples to question various
                long-held assumptions about the “letter.”</p></div>
<div type="section">
<p>The handwritten missive of past centuries,
                the “private conversation of distant friends,”<ptr target="#note6" xml:id="nr6"
                    n="6"/> as Harriet Martineau described it, is typically a text that relies on
                the tension of being both a private and a public document. As Margaretta Jolly and
                Liz Stanley claim, “letters inhabit an interesting ontological as well as
                epistemological ‘space,’ situated as they are <hi rend="italic">on the boundaries of
                    personal</hi> [private] <hi rend="italic">and impersonal</hi> [public].”<ptr
                    target="#note7" xml:id="nr7" n="7"/> In fact, the argument about whether a
                letter is ever completely private or public has been the most pervasive and
                genre-defining in the study of correspondence, including attempts to theorize the
                so-called epistolarium.<ptr target="#note8" xml:id="nr8" n="8"/> Twain’s
                manipulation and use of the letter form is one of many examples, surely, of how it
                can be both. Regardless, theorists and editors often use the private-public binary
                as a point of engagement for discussing letters, and for choosing appropriate
                editorial treatments, most specifically, in deciding whether letters require a
                documentary or a critical approach.</p>
            <p>Due to the perceived “documentary” nature of letters (personal, historically
                significant), D. C. Greetham and Thomas Tanselle, two of the most prolific writers
                on textual theory, devote fewer pages to choosing an appropriate theory or method of
                editing letters than they do to other topics of textual inquiry. However, this is
                very likely because letters editions are not usually considered to consist of
                “critical” texts—that is, texts (such as literary fiction) that require a
                sophisticated practice for emending a copy-text from variant readings. Since letters
                    <hi rend="italic">most often</hi> consist of just one unique manuscript, there
                is usually no need to choose between variants. However, this is not always true,
                because sent letters may sometimes have preliminary drafts to them, as well as
                various public printings, all of which may bear on the establishment of a text for
                an edition.<ptr target="#note9" xml:id="nr9" n="9"/> Taking this into account, one
                could argue that letters <hi rend="italic">are</hi> literary works and should <hi
                    rend="italic">not</hi> be treated strictly as historical documents, if indeed
                there is a difference, for as Tanselle has pointed out, “Any approach to editing
                that attempts to justify differing treatment for ‘literature’ and for other works is
                thus built on an insecure foundation, for the simple reason that ‘literature’ is not
                a fixed body of material and what constitutes ‘literature’ is a matter of
                    judgment.”<ptr target="#note10" xml:id="nr10" n="10"/> Admittedly, in this
                deliberation, Tanselle was discussing literary fiction as compared to philosophical
                works and the like, but the statement stands, I believe, with regard to letters as
                well. Editors do and should engage in judgment in the practice of editing, because
                it is inescapable. Therefore, attempting to assign immutable treatments for genres
                of writing in an attempt to deny subjective judgments about the content is a futile
                practice.</p>
            <p>In fact, discriminating between “literary” and “documentary” letters, and making their
                editorial treatment reflect that, is a distinction rejected by Tanselle: “[T]he real
                distinction is between writings of the kind normally intended for publication and
                those of the kind normally not so intended (critical editions often being most
                appropriate for the former, diplomatic transcriptions for the latter).”<ptr
                    target="#note11" xml:id="nr11" n="11"/> Greetham admits that this is a difficult
                distinction to draw for pre-Gutenberg letters,<ptr target="#note12" xml:id="nr12"
                    n="12"/> but it is also a difficult distinction to draw for a number of letters
                in the modern era. A letter may have been a private communication at its inception,
                but it became public when it entered the postal delivery service, was passed among
                friends, or when it was (perhaps) published in a public forum such as a periodical.
                Also, writers who are well-known figures might well expect their letters to be
                published one day, perhaps even having this in mind at the time of composition.
                Twain, for example, did expect this, and four years before he died he appointed
                specific people to be editors of his letters. Determining an editorial policy based
                on the public-private, literary-documentary binary may actually result in editors
                making compromises to construct a policy that incorporates aspects of both.
                Nonetheless, those ideas about the genre have influenced areas outside literary and
                textual scholarship that are concerned with the epistolary form.</p>
            <p>Interestingly enough, some of the current critical work on epistolary theory and the
                formal aspects of the “letter” are in the fields of social science and history, and
                more specifically genre theory, in which scholars are establishing the
                characteristic parameters of the letter form. Social scientists and historians who
                study “life writing” (diaries, letters, etc.) find that establishing or sometimes
                deconstructing the formal and stylistic attributes of letters helps to codify the
                study of them and of the culture or persons they concern.<ptr target="#note13"
                    xml:id="nr13" n="13"/> However, the conclusions most often drawn have not
                identified any kind of useful categorization, but rather have tended to highlight
                the “‘infinitely malleable features’ of letters, finding that letter writing is a
                social practice that morphs into and across genres and across historical periods in
                spite of (varyingly) prescriptive conventions.”<ptr target="#note14" xml:id="nr14"
                    n="14"/> Then what becomes most useful for social scientists interested in just
                the <hi rend="italic">content</hi> of letters and how the form supports or
                manipulates the writer’s life story is to decipher the “truth value” of an author’s
                writings—that is, how much of what an author describes in letters can be counted on
                as truthful after the reader takes into account, for example, the style, voice, and
                possible performance and manipulation of voice that the author uses. This type of
                study may be, also, how some literature scholars contribute with their interest in
                letters: as a way to unearth points of formation of an author’s creative ideas,
                perhaps, or the identification of influences in the professional lives of writers.
                The most common use of letters, though, has always been to construct the biography
                of a figure. Simply put, a biographer, historian, or social scientist will collect
                details from a primary source to serve a scholarly argument or construct a life
                story.</p>
            <p>Whether it is genre theory, social science, history, literary criticism, or
                biographical work, one area could stand more rigorous questioning of its <hi
                    rend="italic">perception</hi> of letters: that of scholarly editing, which more
                often than not provides other scholars with a text to study. The debate of public
                versus private documents alone leads to confusion, as we have seen. However,
                traditionally, a way for editors to determine policies for editions of any text has
                been to identify the definitional aspects of the text: what makes it a draft,
                manuscript, proofs, and so on, and how we can best, typographically, represent those
                    aspects.<ptr target="#note15" xml:id="nr15" n="15"/> Then what were the author’s
                intentions for the manuscript, or on the other hand, what was the social text
                disseminated to the reading public? Various characteristics have been
                assigned to letters, such as: they have a writer and usually a recipient or at least
                an addressee, they are sent through the postal service or by some other carrier,
                they are thought of as covering distance and inhabiting a geographical space, they
                have attached to them an <hi rend="italic">expectation</hi> of privacy (almost
                always met), they have reciprocity built in, and the writing of them has
                “referential aspects.”<ptr target="#note16" xml:id="nr16" n="16"/> However, in the
                end, many find that letters are still a transitionary form and a “particularly
                difficult text object to define: after all almost anything can be put in the form of
                a letter.”<ptr target="#note17" xml:id="nr17" n="17"/></p>
            <p>An editor may admit that any attempt to assign a formal or genre definition to a text
                is continually challenged by exceptions to that genre—an admission thrown into
                relief when trying to use established characteristics in order to formulate an
                editorial policy. Genre-defining can serve a useful purpose in some areas of
                critical study but with editing it can lead to quick judgments, misunderstandings, and
                confusion as to how a text should be published. An early attempt (within the current
                era of scholarly editing) at defining a methodology for editing correspondence was
                done by Robert Stephen Becker in 1984.<ptr target="#note18" xml:id="nr18" n="18"/>
                He surveyed the field of editions being produced at that time and looked for
                patterns of similar approaches to handling correspondence. In short, he found that
                “fifty percent of the canvassed editors would not recommend any edition of letters
                as a model. In general, they felt that individual problems created by an author’s
                correspondence are too great to be solved or even managed with a formula” (262).
                This survey and study grew from what at the time was a quickly moving current toward
                more diplomatic transcriptions of text. In editing, “diplomatic” can mean different
                things, but here I refer to a very general move away from heavily emended,
                truncated, and censored texts (e.g., in letters editions made in the nineteenth to
                mid-twentieth centuries), to transcriptions that showed in their printed surrogates
                the deletions, additions, and other marks a writer makes, for either deliberate or
                unconscious reasons.</p>
            <p>This shift signaled a kind of crisis for letters editions, as touched on above in the
                literary versus documentary debate. Varying degrees of diplomatic transcription were
                a result, as was a more careful attention to the presentation of a holograph letter
                in a published form. Letters editions can still range from giving very literal,
                documentary texts, to giving clear texts with lists of textual alterations in the
                back of the book, and one might say that this latter approach preserved a kind of
                literary aura around letters editions that critical editions had held for years.</p>
            <p>At this point it is important to remember that the resulting edited text is “already
                something other than what the writers in most cases intended them to be. . . .
                Editions of letters are so much a fixture of literate culture that it is easy to
                forget that in its published state a correspondence leads the second of two distinct
                generic lives.”<ptr target="#note19" xml:id="nr19" n="19"/> The recognition that
                what an editor creates is something different from the actual letter is important,
                and where an editor goes from there in the editing process matters; that is, how do
                the assumptions about letters, which I explained above, lead us astray in editorial
                decisions? Letters editions produced from approximately the late eighteenth through
                the nineteenth centuries were made under the theory that an edition should work
                toward creating one long narrative of the subject’s life, or highlight some aspect
                of it while suppressing others.<ptr target="#note20" xml:id="nr20" n="20"/> This
                coincidentally resulted in page after page<ptr target="#note21" xml:id="nr21" n="21"
                /> of blocks of texts, short excerpts, and all in all an aesthetic experience that
                appeared more like a literary tome or novel (consider the epistolary novel) than
                corresponding letters, which by their very nature are disjointed things: interrupted
                conversations, notes of reply in no context, fleeting invitations, utterances in
                transit sent to someone next door or across the world. In fact, most of the
                canvassed editors of Becker’s survey confirmed “that the regular form and spacing of
                print, its size on the page and the bound page itself, are all intrinsic elements of
                the printed medium that are foreign, even contrary, to the corresponding elements of
                the holograph.”<ptr target="#note22" xml:id="nr22" n="22"/> Could it be that the
                reason scholars edit volumes of letters is that they are influenced by the idea that
                “letters have an intrinsic value, which might indeed raise them to the level of
                    literature”?<ptr target="#note23" xml:id="nr23" n="23"/> If so, as Robert
                Halsband surmised, “they intended their editions to be enjoyed by a reading public
                interested in genuine literature but intolerant of pedantry and dullness.”<ptr
                    target="#note24" xml:id="nr24" n="24"/></p>
            <p>Fortunately, then, letters are never just gossip or informal conversation about
                commonplace domestic matters, nor finely crafted literary prose. They are complex
                textual documents that contemporary editors can only attempt to represent on a
                printed page or in a digital frame. It is not just a matter of representing
                typographically the cancellations and insertions in a letter but also a consideration
                of the purpose and aesthetics of them. Some might wonder why it matters, since we
                are only offering a surrogate to readers anyway. But what the editorial artifact
                gives us, through its very content, is an additional, metatextual framework of
                information, as well as a different aesthetic experience from the actual letter,
                which in turn manipulates our understanding of it and, I argue, distances us even
                further from what the letter accomplished decades and centuries ago. Our editorial
                policy and annotation policy should hope to rely on the reader's conception of the
                social and geographical space that letters inhabit and their varied purposes,
                intentions, and styles, whether it be in print or online.</p></div>
            <div type="section"><p>A number of examples can be found among letters written throughout the centuries that
                challenge the conception of the so-called traditional letter, or that do not fit
                into the genre categories mentioned above. I by no means claim that Twain’s letters
                are the only letters that present challenges to the traditional definitions; rather,
                I imagine many letters by other writers would show the same kind of playful
                genre-bending that his sometimes do.</p>
            <p>The Ashcroft-Lyon manuscript gives us an opportunity to unpack and rethink what the
                letter is. To begin with editorial policy: the dictations included in the three
                volumes of the <hi rend="italic">Autobiography</hi>, with few exceptions, are
                printed in a clear, critical text.<ptr target="#note25" xml:id="nr25" n="25"/> This
                means the editors collated different versions of the dictations (such as one or more
                typed copies made by the stenographer, sometimes holograph manuscript, sometimes
                published text, and often one or more typescripts with Twain’s holograph revisions)
                and used these to establish a text, and a textual apparatus was constructed listing
                variants and emendations. The goal was to get as close as possible to the text Twain
                wanted published after his death. He indeed intended all of it to be published, some
                during his lifetime in modified form in periodicals, and some only long after his
                    death.<ptr target="#note26" xml:id="nr26" n="26"/> In other words, the
                autobiography was “finished” before he died, in that he was done giving dictation,
                had completed some revisions to the typescripts produced, and had written what he
                declared to be the end of the work. That being the case, one’s initial thought could
                be that the Ashcroft-Lyon manuscript should be handled the same way as the
                dictations and published as clear text. However, it is not part of the dictations,
                and was written after most of the dictations were completed. It was crafted as a
                narrative of events in his life, but there is where its similarities to
                the dictations end. First, Twain wrote it himself, in manuscript. It is in more or
                less a rambling informal prose style, which is not uncommon for him, but the
                manuscript does give less appearance than the dictation transcripts do of being
                revised for a purpose beyond drafting. Second, he never intended for the manuscript
                to be <hi rend="italic">formally</hi> published (which I will address further on),
                but he did expect unknown others to read it. Here it begins to inhabit this nebulous
                space of being both a private and public document. Third, it is in the form of a
                letter that he never intended to send. He never used this literary device in his
                dictations, but this form has surfaced elsewhere in his writings. So if it is a
                letter, what kind of a letter is it, and are we justified even calling it that (as
                Twain himself did) when it is first and foremost, by content, autobiographical and
                not “correspondence” in the traditional sense?<ptr target="#note27" xml:id="nr27"
                    n="27"/> Should content or form or both decide our methodology for choosing our
                policy?</p>
            <p>In the end, we opted for plain text rather than clear text for all the reasons given
                above as to how it differed from the autobiographical dictations. However, we soon
                ran into problems when trying to adhere to the specifications of plain text
                transcription. Plain text at the Mark Twain Project is a transcription method that
                was devised by general editor Robert H. Hirst for the editing and printing of Twain’s
                letters and other texts. Through certain typographical elements and symbols (e.g.,
                strikethrough, slash, caret), it represents on the page the cancellations, insertions,
                and other substantive markings that constitute the <hi rend="italic">sent</hi>
                letter. But it is also a <hi rend="italic">faithful</hi> transcription, that is,
                faithful to what is literally on the page but also faithful to the intentions of the
                author. This means that in plain text, editors will also use their best editorial
                judgment <hi rend="italic">not</hi> to transcribe words or phrases in a way that
                will confuse the reader, but rather offer them a transcription that benefits a
                comprehensive reading:<q rend="block">We assume that the purpose of publishing
                    letters is to make them easier to read than they are in the original documents.
                    On that assumption, a successful transcription must include enough of the text
                    to enable someone to rely on <hi rend="italic">it</hi>, rather than the
                    original, and it must exclude enough to make the transcribed text easier to read
                    (or at least not more difficult to read) than the original. Thus, when the
                    documents originally sent are intact and available, we transcribe them as fully
                    and precisely as is compatible with a highly inclusive <hi rend="italic"
                        >critical text</hi>—not a literal, or all-inclusive one, but a typographical
                    transcription that is optimally legible and, at the same time, maximally
                    faithful to the text that Clemens himself transmitted.<ptr target="#note28"
                        xml:id="nr28" n="28"/></q>For the transcription of letters, this makes good
                sense, because as we have found, one of the hallmarks of letters is their
                idiosyncrasy, the nature of a text in the midst of being crafted but not polished,
                and this deserves a critical treatment. For the Ashcroft-Lyon manuscript, the plain
                text retained the integrity of the document: that of a drafted letter, loosely
                composed. Twain’s strikeouts, additions, many inserted documents, and tireless
                repetition of events and facts display quite literally his frustration and mounting
                anger over the period of five months when he wrote the manuscript. Also, Twain
                stipulates in the manuscript itself that “This original Manuscript will be locked up
                &amp; put away, &amp; no copy of it made.” Copies would have introduced other
                witnesses to the text and perhaps made it necessary to collate and emend a
                copy-text, but with a unique manuscript, plain text is all the more called for.
                However, using the plain text rules that were established for editing letters did
                not always allow us to transcribe the manuscript satisfactorily. Much of this challenge
                came from the extraordinarily diverse components of the text. It is a long
                manuscript “letter,” but it also includes newspaper clippings, testimonies written
                by the author’s daughters, Clara and Jean, legal contracts, household bills and accounts,
                and typed documents. Are we justified in treating these as plain text items as well?
                Do we retain the common misspellings that occur in newspaper articles where clearly
                the typesetter was inept? Do we treat Clara’s and Jean’s manuscripts as we treat
                Twain’s? This is where it became difficult to treat this “letter” like other
                letters, relying on preconceived notions. What resulted in this case was using plain
                text but also making allowances for the other types of text included so as to
                produce a faithful text, a historically accurate text, and one that does not obscure
                the author’s intentions.<ptr target="#note29" xml:id="nr29" n="29"/></p>
            <p>Twain’s purpose behind writing this document was the other guiding force for the
                editors in deciding how to treat it. Why did Twain choose to unburden himself of all
                his accusations against Ashcroft and Lyon in an “unsent letter” to Howells? His
                intention was not to publish it, but rather to keep it so that the family or Twain’s
                lawyer would have it at hand in case Ashcroft or Lyon ever tried to take legal
                action against the family. That way, even after his death, Twain’s daughter Clara
                would be protected with the document. But why the letter form? He had been attracted
                for many years to the catharsis of the “unsent letter.” It was a way of unburdening
                himself of a topic that might not be suitable for others to read. He expresses this
                quite well in an actual sent letter to Howells written just a few days before he
                started composing the Ashcroft-Lyon manuscript:<q rend="block">My mind’s present
                    scheme is a good one; I could not like it better if I had invented it myself. It
                    is this: to write letters to friends <hi rend="italic">&amp; not send them</hi>.
                    I will now try it on you as a beginning, &amp; see how it works. Dictating
                    Autobiography has certain irremovable drawbacks. . . . Talking to the same,
                    same, same old one-character stenographer all the time, is talking to the
                    vague—with [unsent letters] there’s no definite target for each letter, &amp;
                    you can choose the target that’s going to be the most sympathetic for what you
                    are hungering and thirsting to say . . . you can talk with a quite unallowable
                    frankness &amp; freedom, because you are not going to send the letter. . . .
                    When you are on fire with a good thing that’s indecent you’ll save it for
                    Howells, who will love it. As he will never see it, you can make it really
                    indecenter than he could stand; &amp; so no harm is done, yet a vast advantage
                    is gained.<ptr target="#note30" xml:id="nr30" n="30"/></q>Twain considered the
                Ashcroft-Lyon affair to be indecent because in his own words, directed toward Lyon
                but written in a letter to his daughter Clara, it was about someone who was “a liar,
                a forger, a thief, a hypocrite, a drunkard, a sneak, a humbug, a traitor, a
                conspirator, a filthy-minded &amp; salacious slut pining for seduction &amp; always
                getting disappointed.”<ptr target="#note31" xml:id="nr31" n="31"/> He chooses
                this “freer” and more honest form of the letter, but throughout the manuscript his
                language toward Ashcroft and Lyon becomes increasingly violent and exaggerated, and
                he begins to utter not a number of honest statements but rather half-truths and
                sometimes complete falsehoods.<ptr target="#note32" xml:id="nr32" n="32"/> He claims
                to be his most honest self in this text, but instead he uses it to give voice to
                his version of truth in whatever language he chooses, which could admittedly be
                another kind of honesty. This in turn lends itself to the “truth value” study that
                social scientists are concerned with in life writing, which also is of concern to
                editors. The interesting part of Twain’s use of the letter form in other instances
                is that he often bends the truth in order to effect a response from the reader, a
                literary device found in several of his writings.</p>
            <p>One example that displays Twain’s use of a letter
                to compose a type of fiction is one he wrote in 1874 to, again, William Dean
                    Howells.<ptr target="#note33" xml:id="nr33" n="33"/> It gives the reader a
                multilayered address through the “correspondence” of a letter addressed to his wife
                (“Dear Livy”) but sent to Howells and dated 1935. It is a “prophecy,” as Twain later
                termed it, a fictional letter to Livy written when Twain would have been one
                hundred, Livy ninety, and Howells ninety-eight. He sent this letter as an exercise
                in “forecasting the Monarchy and imagining what the country would be like when the
                Monarchy should replace the Republic,” revealing his cynical view of how one
                powerful political party in America essentially functioned as a monarchy
                (Autobiographical Dictation for July 16 and September 12, 1908, forthcoming in
                volume 3). He imagines that the Irish have taken over politically on the East Coast
                and have renamed some of the major cities, Boston being named “Limerick.” He and his
                close friend the Reverend Joseph Twichell are visiting Howells in New York and Twain
                reports on the trip to Livy. Most of what he says involves the technological
                advances that will be at their disposal in 1935, such as “air-ships,” and even more
                telling, he gives his thoughts on advances in communication. It is in a sense a
                monologue on what he finds to be the benefits of the “old” written word, transmitted
                through letters and telegraphs, versus the new vogue in 1935 of “thought
                transference,” when people will telepathically transfer their thoughts to one
                another instead of writing:<q rend="block">The gentlemen-in-waiting stare to see me
                    sit here <hi rend="italic">telegraphing</hi> this letter to you, &amp; no doubt
                    they are smiling in their sleeves. But <hi rend="italic">let</hi> them! The slow
                    old fashions are good enough for me, thank God, &amp; I will none other. When I
                    see one of these modern fools sit absorbed, holding the end of a telegraph wire
                    in his hand, &amp; reflect that a thousand miles away there is another fool
                    hitched to the other end of it, it makes me frantic with rage; &amp; then am I
                    more <del type="strikethrough">than</del> implacably fixed &amp; resolved than
                    ever, to continue taking twenty minutes to telegraph you what I might
                    communicate in <del type="strikethrough">thre</del> ten seconds by the new way
                    if I would so debase myself. And when I see a whole silent, solemn drawing-room
                    full of idiots sitting with their hands on each other’s foreheads “communing,” I
                    tug the white hairs from my head &amp; curse till my asthma brings me the
                    blessed relief of suffocation. In our old day<del type="strikethrough">s</del> such a gathering talked <add rend="caret" place="inline">pure</add> drivel &amp; “rot,” mostly, but better that, a thousand times, than these dreary
                    conversational funerals that oppress our spirits in this mad generation.<ptr
                        target="#note34" xml:id="nr34" n="34"/></q>This letter defies many genre
                staples. It serves as a communication to three or more addressees, and is not
                private to Livy. It was sent to Howells, and he in turn “passed it around” to Thomas
                Bailey Aldrich and James R. Osgood.<ptr target="#note35" xml:id="nr35" n="35"/>
                Twain then publishes the letter himself by including it in his <hi rend="italic"
                    >Autobiography</hi>, in one of his dictations, thirty-four years later. It was
                first a creative exercise, in 1874, and then a platform from which to divulge his
                views on the country’s political system, in 1908. It was never just a letter to
                Livy; rather, it displayed Twain’s early fascination with the letter as a malleable
                literary device.</p>
            <p>One other instance of Twain’s rumination over the unsent letter is a humorous sketch
                he wrote but never published, titled “Unmailed Letters,”<ptr target="#note36"
                    xml:id="nr36" n="36"/> advice to a young letter writer. It explains his idea
                that there can be two versions of letters: an honest, bilious unmailed version and a
                truncated, dishonest sent version. Writing these two versions was a practice Twain
                saved for recipients such as reporters, reviewers, and overzealous fans who sent him
                endless obtrusive requests.<q rend="block">When you get an exasperating letter, what
                    happens? If you are young, you answer it, promptly, instantly—&amp; mail the
                    thing you have written. At forty what do you do? By that time you have found out
                    that a letter written in a passion is a mistake, in 99 cases out of a hundred,
                    that it usually wrongs two persons, &amp; always wrongs one—yourself.</q>Instead,
                he gives the young writer advice to lay out all his passionate outrage in a letter
                and stick it in a pigeonhole instead of mailing it, and then write a letter void of
                offense and mail that to the recipient. This advice is followed by amusing examples
                of such versions. Yes, this is a humorous exercise, but it speaks to a larger point,
                that the so-called Ur-text of a letter can have various limbs, expressions, and
                versions, and be used for various purposes.</p>
            <p>By 1909 and the writing of the Ashcroft-Lyon manuscript, Twain is very interested in
                the so-called truthful form of letters, and he engages in a conscious manipulation
                of the form when he writes the manuscript to Howells. His preface to the letter
                (note that the use of a preface blurs the lines between its being a literary
                manuscript or a letter) reads:<q rend="block">I have set this history down in the
                    form of a Letter—a letter to an old &amp; sympathetic friend, a friend of
                    thirty-five years’ standing, the novelist William Dean Howells. This was to give
                    me freedom, utter freedom, limitless freedom, liberty to talk right out of my
                    heart, without reserve. I could not talk like that to the general public, I
                    could not strip myself naked before company.</q>Here and elsewhere he believes
                in the ultimate freedom found in letter writing. In 1905, when Twain and Lyon were
                still close, he spoke to her about the kind of honesty that can only be given in
                letters, and he added the necessary component of an addressee or an interlocutor to
                his theory. A recipient, or at least the concept of a recipient, provided Twain with
                the accepting audience he required in order for his communication to be genuine. In
                her diary entry for June 2, 1905, Lyon recorded that Twain said the following:<q
                    rend="block">People think things—know things, but they don’t dare to say things.
                    If a man pokes his head up over the crowd &amp; dares tell the truth, he has
                    potatoes hurled at him by people who know that what he says is true. . . . [but]
                    he never dared to burst out with the things that he could put into a letter—a
                    letter to a man like Twichell—for Twichell is sympathetic—They wouldn’t be
                    things you could print, except to weave into a volume of letters. Letters would
                    be the best kind of biography any way.<ptr target="#note37" xml:id="nr37" n="37"
                    /></q>Consider this along with the fact that writing a letter is, yes, to
                (sometimes) correspond with someone else, but it is also a performance for an
                interlocutor. For, as Bruce Redford has pointed out, the letter is a text feigning a
                conversation, thus a performance of conversation and rhetoric.<ptr target="#note38"
                    xml:id="nr38" n="38"/></p>
            <p>This is key, because more than anything else it is this feigned interaction that
                attracted Twain to the letter form. Consider what he was doing with his
                autobiographical dictations; he was performing for and interacting with his
                different stenographers, whom he prized for their skills as sounding boards for him.
                (This list includes his first biographer, Albert Bigelow Paine, and the
                later-accused Isabel Lyon, to whom, before their falling out, he would read aloud
                sections from the dictations.) Lyon wrote in her 1906 diary, “Mr. Clemens was saying
                that Mr. Paine and Miss Hobby [the stenographer] make a good audience, and quite
                enough too.”<ptr target="#note39" xml:id="nr39" n="39"/></p>
            <p>They provided him with listeners and acted, in a way, as an audience. However, he
                still found these “audience members” as lacking in certain respects. In the
                previously quoted April 17 letter to Howells, Twain wrote, “A stenographer is a
                lecture-audience; you are always conscious of him; he is a restraint . . . you are
                not talking to yourself; you are not thinking aloud—processes which insure a free
                &amp; unembarrassed delivery—for that petrified audience person is always there, to
                block that game.” With the Ashcroft-Lyon manuscript, however, the correspondent
                (Howells) is not there sitting in front of him, and this fact gives him the best of
                both worlds, a person he can still perform for in the text (in the form of asides he
                writes to Howells throughout) but who isn’t there reacting in person and implicitly
                encouraging Twain to censor himself. Howells, or the concept of Howells, is an
                audience that will “beguile me into dwelling leisurely &amp; lovingly upon it, &amp;
                enjoying the taste of it in my mouth” (ibid.).</p>
            <p>Through the Ashcroft-Lyon “letter,” he gives us a bridge from the traditional letter
                to that of prose autobiography. Twain’s manuscript does not fit into the parameters
                that current scholarship attempts to assign to letters: that the sender writes with
                the thought that the letter will travel through a specific geographical space, and
                that there is an expectation of privacy with one recipient. Twain has both these
                characteristics in mind and works toward a hybrid form. First, he takes away the
                idea of distance and keeps it local, writing to someone who is real but present only
                in his imagination. Second, there is an expectation of privacy to this letter but
                not completely: he is not, albeit imaginatively, just corresponding with Howells,
                because his daughters (Clara and Jean) are also involved in the composition of the
                manuscript by giving him their accounts of events. It is a collaborative, performing
                correspondence that he wants to be kept private for the time being, but that he
                knows one day will be read by others. Consider that his preface to the manuscript is
                addressed “To the Unborn Reader,” for he thinks that one day the text will be read
                by a stranger, be it in a court of law or by the general public. Suffice to say,
                with this statement he is introducing yet another correspondent, an unknown “other”
                that he is likely also performing to. Therefore, we have a three-layered addressee,
                similar to his 1874 letter to Livy and Howells.</p>
            <p>So, to bring us back to where we started, policy: with all of these observations and
                considerations in mind, the editors of the Ashcroft-Lyon manuscript used plain text because it was the truest option for us
                to represent this document, but when we make these decisions we are weighing
                ontological arguments about what form is and how it is considered against the
                significance of the content. This exercise of editing the Ashcroft-Lyon manuscript
                helped me to more closely evaluate what a letter is and what it may accomplish in
                different authors’ hands, and consequently how an editor’s decisions could be
                affected by these conceptions. Editors will, one hopes, continue to weigh
                considerations with regard to form, content, and aesthetics when producing editions of
                letters, whether they be in print or online. Mark Twain as letter writer is only one
                example of an author producing unorthodox “letters”; therefore, there must be a
                considered regard in editorial scholarship for how different kinds of letters look
                and how they are read. One assumes that more options will be available in terms of
                rendering letters digitally as technology advances, but efforts in this vein should
                begin with a closer look at what letters accomplish beyond our preconceived
                notions.</p></div>
        </body>
        <back>
            <div type="notes">
                <note xml:id="note1">Volume 3 is forthcoming in the fall of 2015. All volumes are
                    published simultaneously in print and online at <ref type="url"
                        target="http://www.marktwainproject.org/"
                        >http://www.marktwainproject.org/</ref>. The website also holds
                    editions of more than 2,000 of Mark Twain’s letters and electronic texts of scholarly
                    editions of <hi rend="italic">Adventures of Huckleberry Finn</hi> and <hi
                        rend="italic">Huck Finn and Tom Sawyer among the Indians</hi>, with more
                    titles forthcoming.</note>
                <note xml:id="note2">The author’s youngest daughter, Jean Clemens (1880–1909), suffered
                    from epilepsy most of her adult life. The causes of epilepsy in the late
                    nineteenth century were often misunderstood and the treatments various, but Jean
                    had always lived at home under the watchful and loving eye of her mother,
                    Olivia. When Olivia died in 1904 and Isabel Lyon took over management of the
                    Clemens household, she eventually convinced Twain that Jean’s welfare was too
                    much to handle for her and the other servants. In 1906 Jean was sent to live at
                    a sanitarium and stayed there for fifteen months, after which she moved among
                    different homes with paid caretakers, including a stay in Berlin under the care
                    of a specialist. When Jean was not at home, Lyon controlled her communications
                    with her father, and vice versa, because she wanted to shield Twain from worries
                    about his daughter. Unfortunately, this resulted in Jean feeling abandoned by
                    her family and Twain shut out from her affairs. After Lyon was dismissed from
                    her position, Jean finally returned to her father and lived happily at home with
                    him in Redding, Connecticut, from April 1909 to Christmas Eve of that year, when
                    she died from complications related to a seizure (Ashcroft-Lyon manuscript,
                    45–48, Mark Twain Papers, Bancroft Library, UC Berkeley; Karen Lystra, <hi
                        rend="italic">Dangerous Intimacy: The Untold Story of Mark Twain’s Final
                        Years</hi> [Berkeley: University of California Press, 2004], 223).</note>
                <note xml:id="note3">See Hamlin Hill, <hi rend="italic">Mark Twain: God’s Fool</hi>
                    (New York: Harper &amp; Row, 1973); Lystra, <hi rend="italic">Dangerous
                        Intimacy</hi>; Michael Sheldon, <hi rend="italic">Mark Twain: Man in
                        White</hi> (New York: Random House, 2010); and Laura Skandera Trombley, <hi
                        rend="italic">Mark Twain’s Other Woman: The Hidden Story of His Final
                        Years</hi> (New York: Alfred Knopf, 2010).</note>
                <note xml:id="note4">In letters to friends and family, Twain expressed his
                    frustration with working with stenographers. Usually his complaints involved a
                    need to censor himself depending on to whom he dictated (Twain to Jean
                    Clemens, February 8, 1909, Detroit Public Library; Twain to William Dean
                    Howells, April 17, 1909, Houghton Library, Harvard University).</note>
                <note xml:id="note5">See Clara Clemens to Harriet E. Whitmore, August 5, 1910, Mark
                    Twain Memorial Home, Hartford, CT: “Father left me <hi rend="italic">one</hi>
                    weapon to use in case they troubled me any more &amp; I used it.—He wrote out a
                    full description of their entire story of dishonesty which I was to publish if
                    there was no other way to keep them quiet.” Also, in a preface he wrote for the
                    manuscript, addressed to the “Unborn Reader,” Twain was explicit as to the
                    purpose of the manuscript and who should read it: “In your day, a hundred years
                    hence, this Manuscript will have a distinct value” as documentation of events in
                    his private life. Until then, he instructs, “this original Manuscript will be
                    locked up &amp; put away, &amp; no copy of it made. Your eye, after mine, will
                    be the first to see it.” After Twain’s death, the manuscript was left, along
                    with the author’s other papers, to his literary executors, Albert Bigelow Paine
                    and Clara Clemens. For more on the provenance of the document, see “Editorial
                    Preface” to the Ashcroft-Lyon manuscript in <hi rend="italic">Autobiography of
                        Mark Twain</hi>, vol. 3, forthcoming.</note>
                <note xml:id="note6">Harriet Martineau, <hi rend="italic">Life in the Sick Room:
                        Essays by an Invalid</hi> (London, 1844), 91.</note>
                <note xml:id="note7">Margaretta Jolly and Liz Stanley, “Letters as/not a Genre,” <hi
                        rend="italic">Life Writing</hi> 2, no. 2 (2005): 95.</note>
                <note xml:id="note8">See, for example, David Barton and Nigel Hall, eds., <hi
                        rend="italic">Letter Writing as a Social Practice</hi> (Amsterdam: John
                    Benjamins Publishing Co., 2000); William Merrill Decker, <hi rend="italic"
                        >Epistolary Practices: Letter Writing in America before
                        Telecommunications</hi> (Chapel Hill: University of North Carolina Press,
                    1998); James How, <hi rend="italic">Epistolary Spaces</hi> (London: Ashgate,
                    2003); Sarah Poustie, “Re-Theorising Letters and ‘Letterness,’” Working Papers,
                    Olive Schreiner Letters Project, 2010, <ref type="url"
                        target="http://www.oliveschreinerletters.ed.ac.uk/WorkingPaperSeries.html"
                        >http://www.oliveschreinerletters.ed.ac.uk/WorkingPaperSeries.html</ref>;
                    Carol Poster, “The Case of the Purloined Letter-Manuals: Archival Issues in
                    Ancient Epistolary Theory,” <hi rend="italic">Rhetoric Review</hi> 27, no. 1
                    (2008): 1–19; Liz Stanley, “The Epistolarium: On Theorizing Letters and
                    Correspondences,” <hi rend="italic">Auto/Biography</hi> 12 (2004):
                    201–35.</note>
                <note xml:id="note9">See John A. Walker, “Editing Zola’s Correspondence: When Is a
                    Letter Not a Letter?” in <hi rend="italic">Editing Correspondence</hi>, ed. J.
                    A. Dainard (New York: Garland, 1979), 93–112, for an early deliberation on the
                    challenges editors face when deciding whether drafts of letters and letters
                    revised for publication should be included in printed editions of
                    correspondence.</note>
                <note xml:id="note10">G. Thomas Tanselle, “Literary Editing,” in <hi rend="italic"
                        >Literary and Historical Editing</hi>, ed. George L. Vogt and John Bush
                    Jones (Lawrence: University Press of Kansas, 1981), 36.</note>
                <note xml:id="note11">G. Thomas Tanselle, <hi rend="italic">Textual Criticism Since
                        Greg: A Chronicle, 1950–2000</hi> (Charlottesville: University of Virginia
                    Press, 2005), 113.</note>
                <note xml:id="note12">D. C. Greetham, “Editing the Text: Scholarly Editing,” in <hi
                        rend="italic">Textual Scholarship: An Introduction</hi> (New York: Garland,
                    1994), 350–51.</note>
                <note xml:id="note13">Barton and Hall, <hi rend="italic">Letter Writing</hi>;
                    Rebecca Earle, ed., <hi rend="italic">Epistolary Selves: Letters and
                        Letter-Writers, 1600–1945</hi> (London: Ashgate, 1999); Poustie,
                    “Re-Theorising Letters”; Jolly and Stanley, “Letters as/not a Genre.”</note>
                <note xml:id="note14">Poustie, “Re-Theorising Letters,” 15.</note>
                <note xml:id="note15">This holds true for transcriptions in print as well as digital
                    editions; however, complicated typographical symbols can potentially be rendered
                    in more advanced ways on a digital screen than on the printed page if a very
                    literal transcription is intended.</note>
                <note xml:id="note16">See How, <hi rend="italic">Epistolary Spaces</hi>, and Jolly
                    and Stanley, “Letters as/not a Genre,” 91–118.</note>
                <note xml:id="note17">Barton and Hall, <hi rend="italic">Letter Writing</hi>,
                    1.</note>
                <note xml:id="note18">Robert Stephen Becker, “Challenges in Editing Modern Literary
                    Correspondences,” <hi rend="italic">Text</hi> 1 (1984): 257–70, is an analysis
                    of a useful but limited (in scope) survey of forty-seven letters editions
                    published after 1900.</note>
                <note xml:id="note19">Decker, <hi rend="italic">Epistolary Practices</hi>, 6.</note>
                <note xml:id="note20">See, for example, the picture of the field that Robert
                    Halsband presents in “Editing the Letters of Letter-Writers,” in <hi
                        rend="italic">Art and Error: Modern Textual Editing</hi>, ed. Ronald
                    Gottesman and Scott Bennett (Bloomington: University of Indiana Press, 1970),
                    124–39.</note>
                <note xml:id="note21">A similar aesthetic experience may or may not be replicated on
                    a computer screen, depending on when a digital edition was made and the design
                    of the website. Early digital editions and archives of letters sometimes did
                    display the letter texts one after another in one long frame. Other sites often
                    link to letter texts from index-like entries.</note>
                <note xml:id="note22">Becker, “Challenges,” 266.</note>
                <note xml:id="note23">Mark Storey, “‘Creeping into Print’: Editing the Letters of
                    John Clare,” in <hi rend="italic">The Theory and Practice of Text-Editing</hi>,
                    ed. Ian Small and Marcus Walsh (Cambridge: Cambridge University Press, 1991),
                    67–68.</note>
                <note xml:id="note24">Halsband, “Editing the Letters,” 125.</note>
                <note xml:id="note25">For a complete explanation of the editorial policy used and
                    the critical text established, see <ref type="url"
                        target="http://www.marktwainproject.org/xtf/view?docId=works/MTDP10362.xml;chunk.id=bm0019;style=work;brand=mtp"
                        >http://www.marktwainproject.org/xtf/view?docId=works/MTDP10362.xml;chunk.id=bm0019;style=work;brand=mtp</ref>,
                    or in print, Harriet Elinor Smith et al., eds., <hi rend="italic">Autobiography
                        of Mark Twain</hi> (Berkeley: University of California Press, 2010),
                    1:669–79.</note>
                <note xml:id="note26">For a detailed review of Twain’s intentions for publication
                    and the publication history of the autobiographical dictations, see <hi
                        rend="italic">Autobiography of Mark Twain</hi>, 1:1–4: <ref type="url"
                        target="http://www.marktwainproject.org/xtf/view?docId=works/MTDP10362.xml;chunk.id=fm0100;toc.depth=1;toc.id=fr0011;citations=;style=work;brand=mtp#X"
                        >http://www.marktwainproject.org/xtf/view?docId=works/MTDP10362.xml;chunk.id=fm0100;toc.depth=1;toc.id=fr0011;citations=;style=work;brand=mtp#X</ref>.</note>
                <note xml:id="note27">Incidentally, when the Ashcroft-Lyon manuscript was first
                    discovered in private hands in the late 1960s, it was often referred to in news
                    articles as a “long letter” to William Dean Howells and titled as such (“Newly
                    Found Mark Twain Letter Accuses Business Aide of Theft,” <hi rend="italic">New
                        York Times</hi>, June 25, 1970, 1). That stopped being a common title for
                    it, however, and the current “Ashcroft-Lyon manuscript” was assigned to it out
                    of necessity once scholars understood the events it concerned. The title given
                    to an unpublished document is telling in this instance because once it is termed
                    a “manuscript” instead of just a “letter,” a reader may understand this to mean
                    something lengthy, rare, beautiful, and literary. These are not words
                    immediately impressed upon us when we think of a “letter.” Of course this is
                    wrong, as many manuscripts are not beautiful and literary, and many letters are,
                    but there is an unconscious assigning of meaning and significance given by a
                    title chosen for an unpublished work.</note>
                <note xml:id="note28">Harriet Elinor Smith, Richard Bucci, and Lin Salamo, eds., <hi
                        rend="italic">Mark Twain’s Letters</hi> (Berkeley: University of California
                    Press, 2002), 6; see "Guide to Editorial Practice," by Robert H. Hirst, p. 698.</note>
                <note xml:id="note29">One example of where we had to veer from plain text practice
                    was with marginal notes that Twain wrote on a handful of pages of the
                    manuscript. These notes did not constitute new content, but rather were words,
                    such as “carnelian beads,” that served as reminders Twain wrote to himself to
                    cover that topic in the manuscript, which he always did. In plain text these
                    would have to be transcribed diplomatically where they fell on the page.
                    However, such placement would have been difficult in this case because these
                    notes are not attached “by sense” to any word or sentence on the page, because
                    he might cover that topic of “carnelian beads” two or three pages later. In this
                    way these marginal notes differed from those that an author writes as an
                    elaboration or annotation to the text on a page. Therefore, we opted to take
                    these notes out of the main text and place them in the apparatus with an
                    explanation.</note>
                <note xml:id="note30">Twain to William Dean Howells, April 17, 1909, Houghton
                    Library, Harvard University.</note>
                <note xml:id="note31">Twain to Clara Clemens, March 6, 1910, Special Collections,
                    University of Virginia Library.</note>
                <note xml:id="note32">His mischaracterization of Lyon as being a seductress is one
                    of the more egregious, but other examples include his version of events leading
                    to daughter Jean’s tenure in sanitariums, and false statements as to whether
                    Ralph Ashcroft was a paid employee of his. See Lystra, <hi rend="italic"
                        >Dangerous Intimacy</hi>, for more on the events surrounding the writing of
                    the manuscript and the lives of Isabel Lyon and Ralph Ashcroft.</note>
                <note xml:id="note33">Twain to William Dean Howells, November 20, 1874 (<hi
                        rend="italic">Mark Twain’s Letters</hi>, 6:289–92).</note>
                <note xml:id="note34">The idea of “mental telegraphy” is one that continued to
                    fascinate Twain for years afterward. See “Mental Telegraphy. A Manuscript with
                    a History,” <hi rend="italic">Harper's</hi> 84 (December 1891): 95–104, and a
                    lecture he gave to the Saturday Morning Club (Boston) on April 15, 1882
                    (“Minutes,” Saturday Morning Club, Boston, April 15, 1882, Schlesinger Library
                    Special Collections, Radcliffe College, Harvard University).</note>
                <note xml:id="note35">William Dean Howells to Mark Twain, November 23, 1874,
                    photocopy in Mark Twain Papers, Bancroft Library, UC Berkeley.</note>
                <note xml:id="note36">Mark Twain Papers, Bancroft Library, UC Berkeley.</note>
                <note xml:id="note37">Isabel Lyon’s diary is held in the Mark Twain Papers,
                    Bancroft Library, UC Berkeley.</note>
                <note xml:id="note38">Bruce Redford, <hi rend="italic">The Converse of the Pen</hi>
                    (Chicago: University of Chicago Press, 1986).</note>
                <note xml:id="note39">Isabel Lyon’s diary, entry for February 12, 1906.</note>
            </div>
        </back>
    </text>
</TEI>
