<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<?oxygen RNGSchema="http://www.scholarlyediting.org/scholarlyediting.rng" type="xml"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xml:lang="eng">
    <teiHeader>
        <fileDesc>
            <titleStmt>
                <title level="a" type="main">The Second Story</title>
                <author key="McClure, James P.">James P. McClure</author>
            </titleStmt>
            <editionStmt>
                <edition>
                    <date>2015</date>
                </edition>
            </editionStmt>
            <publicationStmt>
                <idno type="file">essay.2015presidentialaddress</idno>
                <authority>Scholary Editing: The Annual of the Association for Documentary
                    Editing</authority>
                <address>
 <addrLine>http://www.scholarlyediting.org</addrLine>
</address>
                <publisher>Association for Documentary Editing</publisher>
                <publisher>University of Nebraska&#8211;Lincoln</publisher>
                <distributor>
                    <name>Center for Digital Research in the Humanities</name>
                    <address>
<addrLine>319 Love Library</addrLine>
<addrLine>University of Nebraska&#8211;Lincoln</addrLine>
<addrLine>Lincoln, NE 68588-4100</addrLine>
<addrLine>http://cdrh.unl.edu</addrLine>
 </address>
                </distributor>
                <date>2015</date>
                <availability>
                    <p>Scholary Editing: The Annual of the Association for Documentary Editing is
                        freely distributed by the Association for Documentary Editing and the Center
                        for Digital Research in the Humanities at the University of Nebraska-Lincoln
                        and licensed under a Creative Commons Attribution-NonCommercial-ShareAlike
                        3.0 Unported License</p>
                </availability>
            </publicationStmt>
            <seriesStmt>
                <title level="j">Scholarly Editing: The Annual of the Association for Documentary
                    Editing</title>
                <respStmt>
                    <resp>editor</resp>
                    <name xml:id="ag" key="Gailey, Amanda A.">Amanda Gailey</name>
                </respStmt>
                <respStmt>
                    <resp>editor</resp>
                    <name xml:id="awj" key="Jewell, Andrew W.">Andrew Jewell</name>
                </respStmt>
                <idno type="vol">36</idno>
                <idno type="ISSN">2167-1257</idno>
            </seriesStmt>
            <sourceDesc>
                <bibl>
                    <note>Born digital.</note>
                </bibl>
            </sourceDesc>
        </fileDesc>
        <revisionDesc>
            <change when="2015-01-14"><name xml:id="gk" key="Kirilloff, Gabi">Gabi Kirilloff</name>
                markup in TEI XML</change>
        </revisionDesc>
    </teiHeader>
    <text>
        <front>
            <head type="main">The Second Story</head>
            <head type="sub">Presidential Address</head>
            <head type="sub">Association for Documentary Editing Annual Meeting</head>
            <head type="sub">Louisville, Kentucky, 2014</head>
            <byline>James P. McClure</byline>
        </front>
        <body>
            <p>For a long stretch of years, if I had been asked to name an edited text that had made
                a particular impression on me, I would have answered without hesitation, <hi
                    rend="italic">The Murder of Charles the Good</hi>. As some of you may know, that
                is the title of a published translation of an account of events surrounding the
                assassination of the count of Flanders in the year 1127. I still have the Harper
                Torchbooks paperback that was on the syllabus of a class on medieval Europe that I
                took as an undergraduate many years ago. From this account by Galbert of Bruges, I
                saw, almost at first hand, disruption, fierce action, and the restoration of order
                in a world that was supposed to be, in so many respects, about seemingly eternal
                continuities. <hi rend="italic">The Murder of Charles the Good</hi> was not the only
                primary account of historical events that I encountered as a college student, but it
                seems to have made by far the deepest impression on me.<ptr target="#note1"
                    xml:id="nr1" n="1"/></p>
            <p>At some point, I realized that another text from the past had left its mark on me
                even earlier. I remember passing time in the library of Monterey High School in
                Lubbock, Texas, during a study hall period and encountering what, according to my
                hazy recollection, was a primary account of the expedition of Francisco Vázquez de
                Coronado into the southern Great Plains. The Coronado expedition, in the early
                1540s, constituted the earliest venture—in Spanish, the first <hi rend="italic"
                    >entrada</hi>—by Europeans into the corner of the universe that was my home.
                Monterey High School’s fiercest crosstown rival at the time, Coronado High School,
                bore the conquistador’s very name, just as another of Lubbock’s high schools,
                Estacado, took its name from the Llano Estacado, or Staked Plains, the historic and
                geographical designation for that great elevated plain edged by escarpments known as
                the Caprock. Coronado was not just any conquistador, he was <hi rend="italic"
                    >our</hi> conquistador.</p>
            <p>While I cannot be entirely sure what narrative I pulled from the shelf in that school
                library, it was likely a version of the <hi rend="italic">Relación</hi> of Pedro de Castañeda, a member of Coronado’s expedition. My
                recollection is of reading a few pages somewhere in the middle of the book, and it
                was not a very exciting narrative. I think that what I read involved, to be honest,
                some uneventful and seemingly endless trekking across a scruffy plain. Yeah, that’s
                about right for the Llano Estacado. But that was interesting stuff. The route of
                Coronado’s journey across the Llano Estacado has long been a subject of intense
                debate. The expedition, which at its outset included about 300 Spanish soldiers and
                friars, perhaps 1,000 or more Native Americans, and maybe 1,500 horses and mules,
                was truly and actually lost for a while, perhaps somewhere not too far, at least in
                western terms, from my home city.</p>
            <p>The Llano Estacado, with an imperceptibly slight tilt, is one of the flattest regions
                on the planet. Coronado’s people, and many who came after, characterized it like the
                sea, with featureless shortgrass prairie in place of water, stretching to the
                horizon in every direction. Encasing everything is an amazing azure-blue, often
                cloudless bowl of sky that, indifferent to the wanderer’s plight, provides limited
                guidance. Misled by a duplicitous native guide, Coronado and the members of his
                expeditionary force were initially searching for, yes, cities and kingdoms of gold:
                first Cibola and then Quivira, a rumored locale far away over the plains that in the
                end proved to be some Native American communities in the legendary place we now call
                Kansas. Make no mistake, though—this was no silly quest by a bunch of misguided Don
                Quixotes but the first venture by armed agents of an imperial power into the heart
                of a continent they knew nothing about, and this was only a little more than twenty
                years after the invasion of Mexico by Hernan Cortés. This, to me, at the remove of
                four centuries, was amazing material, even if nothing exciting occurred in the pages
                that I perused in the school library.<ptr target="#note2" xml:id="nr2" n="2"/></p>
            <p>In both cases, with Galbert’s narrative of the events in twelfth-century Flanders and
                with the Spanish exploration account, I felt a connection to voices spanning across
                centuries. It is as if I had stumbled into some grand, eternal, continuous stream of
                records of the human experience. Indeed, the first publication of <hi rend="italic"
                    >The Murder of Charles the Good</hi> in 1959 was in a “Records of Civilization”
                series put out by the Columbia University Department of History. That aura of
                continuity and seamlessness can be deceptive, however. As editors know, historical
                records such as Galbert’s and Castañeda’s accounts are constructions. The creation
                of such a primary source could be a process of fits and starts, or of a long,
                energetic flow. All of them are snapshots that capture mere moments of time: even
                the longest letter or narrative is but a succession of grabs at the writer’s
                fleeting thoughts.</p>
            <p>The dynamic quality of <hi rend="italic">The Murder of Charles the Good</hi> that
                appealed to me derives in large part from the segmented, episodic nature of the
                narrative. Thomas Jefferson’s correspondence appears in the Princeton edition as a
                single stream, a seemingly unified tributary to that vast narrative river, but it
                was actually an uneven, off-and-on, unconnected series of dialogues, one-time
                exchanges, and unanswered communications with a great number of individuals and
                entities. There are networks within it, to be sure, but its creation by Jefferson
                and his correspondents in real time was in no sense a unified construction. The
                written record is herky-jerky and full of holes, incomplete even when all the
                component pieces of paper are somehow still extant. In the front matter of the first
                volume of the Jefferson Papers, Julian Boyd quoted a letter from Jefferson to Joel
                Barlow in 1802 about the history of the American Revolution: “a great deal of the
                knolege of things is not on paper,” Jefferson wrote, “but only within
                    ourselves.”<ptr target="#note3" xml:id="nr3" n="3"/></p>
            <p>A year and a half after he wrote that letter, Jefferson attempted to capture fugitive
                moments of spoken communication when a delegation of Choctaw Indians, whose homes
                were in what are now Alabama and Mississippi, called on him in Washington.
                Homastubbee and Puckshunubbee, two senior leaders of the Choctaw nation, addressed
                the president in that meeting. Each of them spoke in turn, in the Choctaw language,
                and, in keeping with the style of their council meetings, each speaker paused after
                each sentence or statement. Judging from an unusual set of notes that Jefferson made
                of the meeting, a translator spoke each sentence in English during the pause and
                Jefferson hastily scrawled an abbreviated version of the translated statement,
                perhaps as the speaker made his next statement in Choctaw. Here is just a sample of
                Jefferson’s record of what was said by Homastubbee, the principal chief of one of
                three major divisions of the Choctaw nation:<quote><lg>
                        <l>the land they now offer is the last they can spare</l>
                        <l rend="indented1">must now turn in to work.</l>
                        <l rend="indented1">begs we will not incroach on land, but protect it</l>
                        <l>this is what he has long wished to say, face to face</l>
                        <l rend="indented1">little land many people hunting done, must work</l>
                        <l rend="indented1">individuals want to buy land.</l>
                        <l>will be reduced to poverty without assistce &amp; protection</l>
                    </lg></quote>
                And these lines from the address of Puckshunubbee, chief of the Choctaws’ Upper
                    Towns:<quote><lg>
                        <l>consider them as poor &amp; love them.</l>
                        <l>are red, surrounded by whites.</l>
                        <l>has no thought of turng eyes but to us.</l>
                        <l>hopes we will extricate from poverty</l>
                        <l>. . .</l>
                        <l>a man loves his chdr. hopes we will love &amp; assist them<ptr
                                target="#note4" xml:id="nr4" n="4"/></l>
                    </lg></quote>We could read it as free verse—<quote><lg>
                        <l rend="italic">This is what he has long wished to say, face to face</l>
                        <l rend="italic">A man loves his children</l>
                        <l rend="italic">Hopes we will love &amp; assist them.</l>
                    </lg></quote>
                Jefferson’s notes of what the visitors said that day were an imperfect,
                extraordinary attempt to catch a transient event, a series of spoken lines that tell
                us not only the gist of what was said, but how it was said and what it could have
                been like to hear it on that day in 1803.</p>
            <p>There is a story of the construction of a document—even if we don’t always know the
                story, or know all of it.</p>
            <p>Galbert of Bruges was a notary, in effect a specialized type of witness and recorder.
                He composed his record of the shocking murder of Count Charles of Flanders in the
                church at Bruges—and of the aftermath of the killing, in which nobles and the
                communities of Bruges and Ghent joined forces against the assassins—in three phases,
                two of which were contemporary with the events they described in 1127 and 1128.
                Significant portions of the manuscript of Galbert’s account are lost, and the
                narrative we have now is a composite of manuscript pieces and old published versions
                of the missing parts.<ptr target="#note5" xml:id="nr5" n="5"/></p>
            <p>We know little about Pedro de Castañeda, but he was no cleric and professional scribe
                such as Galbert. Castañeda lived on the northern frontier of Mexico and enrolled as
                a soldier when Coronado assembled the expedition in 1540. Again unlike Galbert,
                Castañeda did not write his account as events unfolded, but twenty years after the
                end of the expedition. His manuscript has not survived, but a copy from 1596, in the
                collections of the Lenox Library, now in the New York Public Library, is the source
                text of this fundamental narrative of early European exploration of the southern
                    plains.<ptr target="#note6" xml:id="nr6" n="6"/></p>
            <p>To be sure, I did not encounter Castañeda’s and Galbert’s accounts in their original
                manuscript form. I saw published versions, which are products of a second
                construction of a text. There is always a second story about a published primary
                text, and it always involves at least one textual scholar or documentary editor
                (whether or not so-called), plus often a publisher, plus always some means of
                supporting the scholar’s work. Consumers of published primary sources—and I’m not
                specifying a particular medium or delivery system when I say “published”—may not
                know much about the first story I have described. They are all too often oblivious
                to the second story. (At least this tends to be the case with published historical
                sources; scholars and students of literature and classics have customary practices
                that place greater emphasis on textual scholarship than historians do.) As far as
                the users of the texts are concerned, the second story is often invisible, and its
                creators—those who constructed the actual thing being used—are anonymous.</p>
            <p>I have been guilty of this myself. Until recently, I paid no attention to what lay
                behind the text that played such an important role in my encounters with published
                primary sources, <hi rend="italic">The Murder of Charles the Good</hi>. The
                translator and editor of the book wrote extraordinarily helpful annotation to
                explain references in the text and give it context, and furnished maps and plans of
                key locations. That translator-editor was James Bruce Ross, who, judging from that
                name and from the erudition of the introduction, notes, and scholarly apparatus, was
                some tweedy, pipe-smoking Oxford don, or maybe a scholar at Edinburgh. Imagine my
                puzzlement when I finally had the wit to look at the blurbs on the back of my
                paperback copy, where I saw James Bruce Ross referred to as “Miss Ross.” <hi
                    rend="italic">Miss</hi> Ross. So much for assumptions based on forenames. The
                bearer of her father’s name, James Bruce Ross was indeed a woman, and she hailed not
                from Scotland or anywhere in the British Isles, but from Independence, Missouri; her
                older brother became Harry Truman’s press secretary. She was known as “J.B.” to her
                friends but “Miss Ross” to her students and within the academic circles of her day,
                despite the fact that she received a PhD from the University of Chicago in 1934. She
                had a long career as a member of the history faculty at her undergraduate college,
                Vassar. She possessed a formidable background in classics and history along with the
                white-hot language skills needed to do immensely detailed, firmly grounded scholarly
                work on medieval Flanders and Renaissance Florence. She could more than hold her own
                with the tweedy dons.</p>
            <p>There is still more to that second story of Galbert’s narrative. In the summer of
                1936, soon after joining the faculty at Vassar, “J.B.” Ross chanced to be on
                vacation in Spain with a friend from the college’s art department when the Spanish
                Civil War suddenly exploded around them. For nineteen days the two young women
                academics from the United States were trapped in the city of Granada as Nationalist
                forces loyal to General Francisco Franco laid siege. Their hotel was bombed. They
                had no communication with the outside world. They witnessed destruction and death
                and could only get out after the attacking army took the city. As Constance Hoffman
                Berman has noted, although Ross may not have thought in these terms, it is difficult
                to believe that her first-hand experience with the terrible chaos and uncertainty of
                violent conflict in Spain did not influence her translation and annotation of
                Galbert’s account of the events triggered by the assassination of Count Charles in
                the chapel at Bruges in March 1127.<ptr target="#note7" xml:id="nr7" n="7"/></p>
            <p>The second story behind Castañeda’s narrative of Coronado’s journey is less dramatic
                but still compelling in its own right. George Parker Winship stands as the key
                figure. In 1891 the Harvard historian Edward Channing pointed Winship, an
                undergraduate student, toward the 1596 manuscript in the Lenox Library. Winship
                undertook a translation and study of the narrative, receiving support from the
                Smithsonian Institution Bureau of Ethnology. Winship’s work with Castañeda’s account
                laid the foundation for scholarship on Coronado’s expedition. Winship became, at the
                age of twenty-four, the librarian of the then-private John Carter Brown collection,
                and oversaw its transformation into the renowned research institution at Brown
                University. He was subsequently the director of the Widener collection and a rare
                books curator at Harvard, and a significant contributor to rare books and
                manuscripts scholarship. His translation and analysis of Castañeda’s text continue
                to be an important reference, even though others since him have also translated and
                annotated the text. The second story of Castañeda’s narrative continues, for there
                are differences between Winship’s translation and those of other scholars regarding
                Spanish terms in the original that provide essential clues to the route that
                Coronado took across the almost featureless Llano Estacado.<ptr target="#note8"
                    xml:id="nr8" n="8"/></p>
            <p>If Galbert’s and Castañeda’s writings live on as part of a great stream of human
                record, and in a form that modern Americans can access and use, it is due to the
                work that makes up the second story surrounding each text. Without J.B. Ross,
                without Vassar College paying her salary and supporting her research, without
                Columbia University to publish the first edition of <hi rend="italic">The Murder of
                    Charles the Good</hi>, without George Parker Winship and the Bureau of Ethnology
                or other institutionally supported scholars of the Castañeda narrative who followed
                him, this address would be about something else, if I were making it at all.</p>
            <p>For any original text to be published—again, “published” in any medium—and thus made
                available to students, researchers, and readers, the second story is critical.
                Textual editors are essential to that big ongoing stream of the human record.
                Permanence, after all, has been at the foundation of how we frame our work. In the
                original feasibility study for what became the Jefferson Papers edition, which
                served as the model for much of what followed in the editing of historical
                documents, Julian Boyd wrote of the “urgent need . . . for an edition of Jefferson’s
                writings so extensive in the number of documents it embraces and so accurate in
                presentation that the work need never be done again. It is believed that such a body
                of Jefferson’s writings would be of permanent value.” The edition was to be
                “definitive,” Boyd wrote, and “so complete, so accurate, and so dependable that it
                will stand for all time.” The project, Boyd advised, “should be so complete in its
                inclusiveness, so scholarly in its presentation, so carefully edited in all its
                details, and so well presented in physical format as to constitute a worthy and
                enduring memorial” to Jefferson and “a constant beacon for the American people.”<ptr
                    target="#note9" xml:id="nr9" n="9"/> In 1951, Lyman Butterfield, who at the time
                was working under Boyd as an associate editor of the Jefferson Papers, referred to
                “our stated aim of doing this job so well that it will not have to be done
                    again.”<ptr target="#note10" xml:id="nr10" n="10"/></p>
            <p>Contrary to what some may believe, however, knowing that our work needs to stand up
                in the long run does not mean that documentary editors want our work to go on
                forever. Boyd stated early in the life of the Jefferson edition that as much as he
                loved editing Jefferson’s papers, he had “no intention . . . of making this a life
                work” or of becoming mired in an endless quest for what he called “an impossible
                perfection.” He wrote in the front matter to the first volume of <hi rend="italic"
                    >The Papers of Thomas Jefferson</hi> that “‘completeness’ as applied to this or
                any other attempt at an exhaustive edition is a relative term, theoretically
                possible but practically unattainable and in some respects undesirable.”<ptr
                    target="#note11" xml:id="nr11" n="11"/> But as the late Warren Zevon once
                reminded us in a song, “Time treats everybody like a fool.”<ptr target="#note12"
                    xml:id="nr12" n="12"/> The second construction of texts, like their first
                construction, can be an uneven set of events. Boyd could not know at the outset that
                the term “exhaustive edition” would have multiple meanings for his edition.</p>
            <p>The Jefferson editorial project began collecting documents in 1944. Volume 1 appeared
                in 1950, so did Volume 2, and publication then continued at the rate of two volumes
                per year through Volumes 11 and 12 in 1955. Even before the first volumes came out,
                Boyd, who felt under pressure from the edition’s sponsors, tried to institute a plan
                that would produce <hi rend="italic">four</hi> volumes a year and was convinced that
                the project’s team should actually be able to put out <hi rend="italic">five</hi>
                700-page volumes a year. Butterfield, with one foot out the door, warned Boyd that
                he would grind himself and his staff into oblivion and undermine the edition’s
                standards of scholarship. Butterfield feared that if he stayed, he would be like
                Charlie Chaplin on the assembly line in the silent movie classic <hi rend="italic"
                    >Modern Times</hi>.<ptr target="#note13" xml:id="nr13" n="13"/> Butterfield
                left, and Boyd, unable to maintain the pace of two volumes a year, let alone four or
                five, and finding the scope of the endeavor to be much larger than he could have
                foreseen at the beginning, did end up spending the rest of his life on the Jefferson
                edition. Such, perhaps, is the lot of the first conquistador to venture onto
                uncharted, trackless plains.</p>
            <p>Years later, after Butterfield left, Boyd in Princeton and Butterfield, then at the
                Adams Papers, despaired together when federal funding agencies pressed documentary
                editors to, in Butterfield’s words, “lower our sights.” They had begun their
                editions without federal assistance, but by the mid-1970s, documentary editions,
                rather like the Choctaws in Jefferson’s administration, found themselves having to
                negotiate new relationships with the US government. Comprehensive scholarly editions
                on the model that Butterfield and Boyd had created were no longer in favor.
                Apparently “what we need,” Butterfield summarized bitterly, “is not definitive
                editions of last resort but lesser, quicker, and cheaper editorial products for a
                more general readership.” He need hardly have added (but did), “I cannot agree.”<ptr
                    target="#note14" xml:id="nr14" n="14"/></p>
            <p>On the face of it, creating an edition is a straightforward matter of following the
                King’s injunction to the White Rabbit in <hi rend="italic">Alice’s Adventures in
                    Wonderland</hi>: “Begin at the beginning, . . . and go on till you come to the
                end: then stop.”<ptr target="#note15" xml:id="nr15" n="15"/> Of course it is never
                really as simple as that. We must continually educate the world, however, about the
                importance of the second story of a text. No matter how rich its contents, a text is
                not really part of that big, seemingly eternal stream of human narrative without the
                second act of construction, the editors’ part of the formula, which moves the source
                from a state of simple existence to a state of true availability as a resource for
                researchers and students—and for unplanned encounters such as mine with the
                narrative of the Coronado expedition when I was sixteen or seventeen years old.</p>
            <p>Jefferson’s in-the-moment record of what the Choctaw leaders Homastubbee and
                Puckshunubbee said to him in December 1803, as they spoke as their forefathers had
                in the great councils for time immemorial—not reading from notes on paper but saying
                what was in their minds and hearts—is presently, as it has been for more than 200
                years, but a piece of paper in the Jefferson collection now at the Library of
                Congress. An image of the manuscript can be found on the library’s American Memory
                website, but its scrawled lines are overlooked. Only when the text and annotation of
                the document prepared for Volume 42 of <hi rend="italic">The Papers of Thomas
                    Jefferson</hi> appears in 2016 will what the Choctaws spoke to the president on
                that day in 1803 be part of that great meganarrative. Only then, after we have done
                    <hi rend="italic">our</hi> jobs, will someone in a distant future, perhaps a
                young person of Choctaw heritage in Oklahoma, or someone curious about the history
                of the lower Mississippi Valley, or a receptive student in a college class on Native
                American history, experience a connection to the words of a long-gone Choctaw leader
                to the president of the United States:<q rend="block"><hi rend="italic">this is what he has long
                    wished to say, face to face.</hi></q></p>
        </body>
        <back>
            <div type="notes">
                <note xml:id="note1">Galbert of Bruges, <hi rend="italic">The Murder of Charles the
                        Good, Count of Flanders</hi>, trans. with intro. and notes by James Bruce
                    Ross, rev. ed. (New York: Harper &amp; Row, 1967); originally published 1959 by
                    Columbia University Press and Oxford University Press.</note>
                <note xml:id="note2">John Miller Morris, <hi rend="italic">El Llano Estacado:
                        Exploration and Imagination on the High Plains of Texas and New Mexico,
                        1536–1860</hi> (Austin: Texas State Historical Association, 1997), 20–21,
                    43, 46–49; George P. Hammond and Agapito Rey, <hi rend="italic">Narratives of
                        the Coronado Expedition, 1540–1542</hi> (Albuquerque: University of New
                    Mexico Press, 1940), 7–8.</note>
                <note xml:id="note3">Julian P. Boyd et al., eds., <hi rend="italic">The Papers of
                        Thomas Jefferson</hi>, 41 vols. to date (Princeton, NJ: Princeton University
                    Press, 1950– ), 1:vii; 37:401.</note>
                <note xml:id="note4">Notes on speeches of Homastubbee and Puckshunubbee, December
                    13, 1803, Jefferson Papers, Library of Congress (to be included in Vol. 42 of
                    the <hi rend="italic">Papers of Thomas Jefferson</hi>).</note>
                <note xml:id="note5">Galbert of Bruges, <hi rend="italic">Murder of Charles the
                        Good</hi>, 63–75, 321.</note>
                <note xml:id="note6">Morris, <hi rend="italic">Llano Estacado</hi>, 46, 118, 367n3;
                    Hammond and Rey, <hi rend="italic">Narratives</hi>, 191n.</note>
                <note xml:id="note7">Constance Hoffman Berman, “James Bruce Ross (1902–1995) and the
                    Sources for Medieval and Renaissance History,” in <hi rend="italic">Women
                        Medievalists and the Academy</hi>, ed. Jane Chance (Madison: University
                    of Wisconsin Press, 2005), 575–84.</note>
                <note xml:id="note8">Morris, <hi rend="italic">Llano Estacado</hi>, 37–39, 50,
                    70–72, 118, 119, 126, 129; Hammond and Rey, <hi rend="italic">Narratives</hi>,
                    31–33; Kenneth E. Carpenter, “Winship, George Parker,” <hi rend="italic"
                        >American National Biography Online</hi> (February 2000), <ref type="url"
                            target="http://www.anb.org/articles/20/20-01137.html"
                            >http://www.anb.org/articles/20/20-01137.html</ref>.</note>
                <note xml:id="note9">Julian P. Boyd, “Report to the Thomas Jefferson Bicentennial
                    Commission on the Need, Scope, Proposed Method of Preparation, Probable Cost,
                    and Possible Means of Publishing a Comprehensive Edition of the Writings of
                    Thomas Jefferson,” typescript, September 25, 1943 (copy in Seeley G. Mudd
                    Manuscript Library, Princeton University), 10, 14, 16, 31–32.</note>
                <note xml:id="note10">Lyman H. Butterfield to Julian P. Boyd, January 8, 1951, Box
                    12, Julian P. Boyd Papers, Collection C0392, Department of Rare Books and
                    Special Collections, Princeton University Library.</note>
                <note xml:id="note11">Boyd to Butterfield, June 29, 1950, Boyd Papers, Princeton
                    University Library; Boyd et al., <hi rend="italic">Papers of Thomas
                        Jefferson</hi>, 1:xiv.</note>
                <note xml:id="note12">Warren Zevon, “Roll With the Punches,” copyright 1992, Zevon
                    Music (BMI).</note>
                <note xml:id="note13">Boyd to Butterfield, June 29, 1950, Butterfield to Boyd,
                    August 29, 1950, and Butterfield to Boyd, January 8, 1951, Boyd Papers,
                    Princeton University Library.</note>
                <note xml:id="note14">Butterfield to Boyd, March 23, 1976, and Boyd to Butterfield,
                    September 24, 1974, Boyd Papers, Princeton University Library.</note>
                <note xml:id="note15">Lewis Carroll, <hi rend="italic">The Annotated Alice: The
                        Definitive Edition. Alice’s Adventures in Wonderland &amp; Through the
                        Looking-Glass</hi>, intro. and notes by Martin Gardner (New York: W. W.
                    Norton &amp; Company, 2000), 121.</note>
            </div>
        </back>
    </text>
</TEI>
