<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<?oxygen RNGSchema="http://www.scholarlyediting.org/scholarlyediting.rng" type="xml"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xml:lang="eng">
    <teiHeader>
        <fileDesc>
            <titleStmt>
                <title level="a" type="main">Editing Death</title>
                <title level="a" type="sub">An Element of Craft</title>
                <author key="Gordon, Ann D.">Ann D. Gordon</author>
            </titleStmt>
            <editionStmt>
                <edition>
                    <date>2015</date>
                </edition>
            </editionStmt>
            <publicationStmt>
                <idno type="file">essay.gordon</idno>
                <authority>Scholary Editing: The Annual of the Association for Documentary
                    Editing</authority>
                <address>
 <addrLine>http://www.scholarlyediting.org</addrLine>
</address>
                <publisher>Association for Documentary Editing</publisher>
                <publisher>University of Nebraska&#8211;Lincoln</publisher>
                <distributor>
                    <name>Center for Digital Research in the Humanities</name>
                    <address>
<addrLine>319 Love Library</addrLine>
<addrLine>University of Nebraska&#8211;Lincoln</addrLine>
<addrLine>Lincoln, NE 68588-4100</addrLine>
<addrLine>http://cdrh.unl.edu</addrLine>
 </address>
                </distributor>
                <date>2015</date>
                <availability>
                    <p>Scholary Editing: The Annual of the Association for Documentary Editing is
                        freely distributed by the Association for Documentary Editing and the Center
                        for Digital Research in the Humanities at the University of Nebraska-Lincoln
                        and licensed under a Creative Commons Attribution-NonCommercial-ShareAlike
                        3.0 Unported License</p>
                </availability>
            </publicationStmt>
            <seriesStmt>
                <title level="j">Scholarly Editing: The Annual of the Association for Documentary
                    Editing</title>
                <respStmt>
                    <resp>editor</resp>
                    <name xml:id="ag" key="Gailey, Amanda A.">Amanda Gailey</name>
                </respStmt>
                <respStmt>
                    <resp>editor</resp>
                    <name xml:id="awj" key="Jewell, Andrew W.">Andrew Jewell</name>
                </respStmt>
                <idno type="vol">36</idno>
                <idno type="ISSN">2167-1257</idno>
            </seriesStmt>
            <sourceDesc>
                <bibl>
                    <note>Born digital.</note>
                </bibl>
            </sourceDesc>
        </fileDesc>
        <revisionDesc>
            <change when="2015-01-13"><name xml:id="gk" key="Kirilloff, Gabi"> Gabi Kirilloff</name>
                markup in TEI XML</change>
        </revisionDesc>
    </teiHeader>
    <text>
        <front>
            <head type="main">Editing Death</head>
            <head type="sub">An Element of Craft</head>
            <byline>Ann D. Gordon</byline>
        </front>
        <body>
            <p>When it came time to design the sixth and final volume of the <hi rend="italic"
                    >Selected Papers of Elizabeth Cady Stanton and Susan B. Anthony</hi>, I realized
                that I knew nothing at all about how editors handled the deaths of their principal
                subjects and concluded their editions. I had never been on an editorial team at the
                subject’s moment of death; moreover, I had not encountered talks or essays by
                colleagues about editing death. With two deaths upcoming in the volume, I needed
                models for the end of life in editions of a person’s papers. The whole staff set out
                to survey the field. Quite unexpectedly, a query about death opened windows onto
                editorial styles. In their handling of death, editors can only create an ending from
                finite and disparate compilations of sources. But through their varied designs, as
                we read the work, editors manifested decisions about the arts of narrative, claims
                about the significance of their subject’s life, and emotions about ending a long
                partnership and collaboration. This is an attempt to start the conversation we once
                    needed.<ptr target="#note1" xml:id="nr1" n="1"/></p>
            <p>Take a case in point. Elizabeth Cady Stanton died on October 26, 1902, in her
                apartment on Ninety-Fourth Street in New York City. In her last surviving private
                letter, dated September 30, Stanton proposed a long-range plan: “As I was wide awake
                last night for hours, when I should have been asleep, I thought of <hi
                    rend="underline">you</hi>,” she told the journalist Ida Harper, as the person
                best qualified to “give the finishing touch” to a volume of her speeches. “Now tell
                me,” she wrote, “if you think you will be able to edit my book.”<ptr target="#note2"
                    xml:id="nr2" n="2"/> Though Stanton, approaching her eighty-seventh birthday,
                found it extremely difficult to move around and could no longer see, there were few
                indications to people outside her family that her end was nigh. In the public
                sphere, readers of William Randolph Hearst’s <hi rend="italic">New York American and
                    Journal</hi> found Stanton’s byline on articles published in July, August,
                September, and even on October 13.<ptr target="#note3" xml:id="nr3" n="3"/> In other
                words, narrative in Stanton’s own documents runs against the current that carries an
                omniscient editor to the conclusion.</p>
            <p>Had I edited books comprised solely of Stanton’s papers, these would be sources from
                which to construct an ending to my book and Stanton’s life. At the September 30
                missive to Ida Harper, I would wrestle with whether to foreshadow death by noting
                that it was the last known private letter. At the October 13 newspaper article, the
                question of when she wrote it would loom, if it were to be my book’s final text.
                Then what? How would Stanton die? Some editors introduce their subject’s last will
                and testament at this point. Though surely written earlier than its placement
                indicates, the will at its moment of legal activation signifies its author’s
                passing. My sources fail me: Stanton left no will that might become the final text.
                At that point, many editors step forward either to recount the death themselves or
                to introduce historical witnesses. Stanton could die in a footnote, maybe anchored
                awkwardly on the article of October 13: “in thirteen days, she would be dead.” She
                could die in an editorial note that stood apart from the texts. She got married that
                way: in the surviving texts of 1840 she broke off her engagement and then sailed on
                her honeymoon. Editors bridged that gap and made it legal. Here at the end of life,
                when Stanton’s papers omit her life’s turns and endings, the editor might step in to
                put finis to the narrative. As a matter of fact, in a solo edition of Stanton’s
                papers, death and texts cannot be made to reach a common end point. Stanton wrote so
                fast and furiously in 1902 that her papers flowed on seamlessly beyond her death. If
                Stanton’s papers were allowed to run their course—fall into their chronological
                slots until the supply ran out—her death would disappear into an inflexible
                progression of papers. Something should be said.</p>
            <p>At the Stanton and Anthony Papers, we decided to take our questions about editing
                death to a list of completed historical editions. Staff members asked, what is the
                final document and why? How does a reader learn that the subject died and when death
                arrived? Are the circumstances of the death regarded as worthy of description? Are
                the boundaries of what constitute the subject’s “papers” expanded for the occasion
                in order to incorporate new points of view, through memorials, condolences, and
                obituaries? They looked at some two dozen editions, both selective and comprehensive
                in scope. Though it was possible to draw up clear descriptions of what the editors
                put into print, we could only infer what governed their choices.</p>
            <p>From this informal survey, they discovered that readers learn about deaths in a
                variety of ways, sometimes by more than one way in a single volume. It might be that
                the date and cause of death are given in an introductory essay. If the device of a
                chronology is employed, death usually makes its appearance in that list. If the
                volume is conceived as a series of chapters each opened with a preface, death may be
                foreshadowed at the final chapter’s start. What seems the most obvious way—to face
                the fact of death in the book’s core of texts and annotation—is not the most popular
                way. By and large, editors seem to cluster near one of two stylistic poles. On the
                one hand, they end their volumes with the last letter or memorandum or other paper
                of the subject, no matter how long before (or after) its author’s death; on the
                other hand, they admit new witnesses—a wife or daughter, an aide, an official’s
                announcement, a newspaper’s obituary—through which to narrate the final weeks or
                days or moments.</p>
            <p>At one pole, to pick but a single example, the staff observed that the two-volume <hi
                    rend="italic">Selected Letters of Charles Sumner</hi> stops with a letter dated
                March 9, 1874, without explanation. Is this the last known letter by Sumner or the
                last one selected by the editor? How much time passed before Sumner died? In fact,
                the date of Sumner’s death (March 11) is nowhere reported in the volume where texts
                of 1874 appear.<ptr target="#note4" xml:id="nr4" n="4"/> At an extreme of this
                style, not even the editor bears witness to death. At the opposite pole, consider
                the <hi rend="italic">Letters of Eugene V. Debs</hi>. The final book of this three
                volume edition winds down slowly. The last letter by Debs is dated June 3, 1926,
                four and a half months before he died. Rather than stop there, the editors selected
                a series of letters written over the summer by well-wishers and followed them with
                letters of condolence to Eugene’s brother Theodore Debs. With the first letter of
                condolence, a footnote places Eugene’s death at October 20, 1926.<ptr
                    target="#note5" xml:id="nr5" n="5"/> In the middle ground, one could look at <hi
                    rend="italic">The Selected Letters of Louisa May Alcott</hi>. The last selection
                is also Alcott’s last text, written on the morning of her fatal stroke, facts the
                reader learns in a concise footnote.<ptr target="#note6" xml:id="nr6" n="6"/></p>
            <p>Narrative is a word of variable stature and fashion among historians but kind of
                basic to the chronological scholarship of texts and documents and papers. Most
                editors are quite clear that they are not <hi rend="italic">the</hi> narrator of
                their edition but rather work in collaboration with the principal subject of their
                work. The editor’s narrative is more akin to the biographer’s than to the
                    storyteller’s.<ptr target="#note7" xml:id="nr7" n="7"/> There is, first, the
                objective limitation of available material, though that limit is not hard and fast,
                especially in a selective edition or one that admits witnesses. As the <hi
                    rend="italic">Papers of Joseph Henry</hi> draws to a close and the last of his
                letters is placed in the volume, the editors add a text so perfect for the purpose
                that any editor will envy their find. The scientist and college professor Maria
                Mitchell visits Henry in the last weeks of his life and records in her journal their
                conversation about facing death. Their book then closes with a single letter between
                two of Henry’s friends that efficiently recounts Henry’s final days and announces
                plans for a funeral.<ptr target="#note8" xml:id="nr8" n="8"/></p>
            <p>Another influence on an editor’s style of narration emerges from the professional but
                subjective measure of the importance of the life edited. It will surprise no one to
                learn that Arthur S. Link edited death on the grandest scale when he reached the
                conclusion of the <hi rend="italic">Papers of Woodrow Wilson</hi>. The ending is
                consistent with Link’s passionate loyalty to Woodrow Wilson, and it suggests ways
                that rational measures of importance become entangled in the difficult emotions of
                parting company with one’s life work. After all, Wilson dies in the sixty-eighth
                volume, every one of them edited by Link. The former president dictated letters on
                January 25, 1924, and a secretary noted on the carbon copy (and the editors quoted
                in a footnote) that the text was one of the last letters dictated by a man too ill
                to sign the sent copies. The secretary’s notation, augmented perhaps by the exact
                date of death, would conclude many an edition in a concise and graceful way. But
                Link and his team were not content to conclude their work at that anticlimactic
                point. They admit several witnesses and include daily bulletins about Wilson’s
                decline that were sent out to the public until he died on February 3. Befitting the
                importance of the occasion, the story extends to selected letters about the funeral,
                to indicate that President Coolidge will attend and that Wilson’s widow instructed
                Henry Cabot Lodge to stay away.<ptr target="#note9" xml:id="nr9" n="9"/></p>
            <p>Because the <hi rend="italic">Selected Papers of Stanton and Anthony</hi> is a joint
                edition of two friends, one woman was bound to witness the death of the other. As
                things turned out, Susan B. Anthony became the resident witness to the death of her
                friend. Through the papers of Anthony, Stanton’s decline and death are documented as
                a matter of course, as a disturbing event in her own life, without editorial
                intervention or quests for external witnesses. The edition’s narrative style stays
                intact. A letter to Anthony from Stanton’s daughter Harriot Blatch in September 1902
                tempers the hopeful note of Stanton’s own letter in the same week. After describing
                her mother as greatly weakened and in constant need of a daughter’s attention,
                Harriot urges Anthony to visit New York City for Stanton’s birthday in November, “as
                I’m sure there wont be another.”<ptr target="#note10" xml:id="nr10" n="10"/> Readers
                of the <hi rend="italic">Selected Papers</hi> learn of Elizabeth Cady Stanton’s
                death in the same way Susan B. Anthony did, by telegram from Harriot Blatch: “Mother
                passed away today.”<ptr target="#note11" xml:id="nr11" n="11"/> With her arrival in
                New York City on October 27, Anthony becomes the witness to the family’s grief, the
                private funeral in their apartment, and a larger ceremony at Woodlawn Cemetery. As
                an editor, I could not possibly improve upon the witness Anthony became. On the day
                of the funeral, she described her loss in terms of science and human reason. <q
                    rend="block">Well, it is an awful hush—it seems impossible—that the voice is
                    hushed—that I have longed to hear for 50 years—longed to get her opinion of
                    things—before I knew exactly where I stood— It is all at sea—but the Laws of
                    Nature are still going on—with no shadow or turning— What a world it is—it goes
                    right on &amp; on—no matter who lives or who dies!!</q>In the same letter, she
                also directs readers to aspects of the public and political response to Stanton’s
                death, critiquing how poorly journalists understood Stanton’s cause and marveling,
                after telegrams arrived from England, that “The whole world knows of the fact!”<ptr
                    target="#note12" xml:id="nr12" n="12"/></p>
            <p>But what happens when the <hi rend="italic">Selected Papers</hi> reaches the moment
                of Susan B. Anthony’s death on March 13, 1906, at her home on Madison Street in
                Rochester? In this death, the more usual laws of editing apply, and the papers of
                Susan B. Anthony, when narrowly defined, offer nothing to document her death. For
                more than a month, her decline was national news. She reached Baltimore on February
                4 with a terrible cold, and reports of her ill health were incorporated into daily
                coverage of the annual convention of the National-American Woman Suffrage
                Association there. In the care of a private nurse, she managed a trip to Washington
                on February 15 and sat on the stage for her eighty-sixth birthday celebration; a few
                words uttered on that occasion bring an end to her papers.<ptr target="#note13"
                    xml:id="nr13" n="13"/> Traveling north toward home, with a nurse still at her
                side, Anthony broke an engagement to celebrate her birthday again with suffragists
                in New York City. That too made the news. Susan B. Anthony’s silence after leaving
                Washington caught the attention of the national press corps and a crowd of reporters
                gathered on Madison Street. Daily briefings for them in front of her house tracked
                her decline, as these headlines illustrate. <q rend="block"><hi rend="italic">Pawtucket Times</hi>, March
                    6: “Susan B. Anthony May Not Recover”</q>
                <q rend="block"><hi rend="italic">Dallas Morning News</hi>, March 7: “Miss Susan B. Anthony Ill”</q>
                <q rend="block"><hi rend="italic">Albuquerque Journal</hi>, March 11: “Susan B. Anthony Worse”</q> From
                inside the house, a niece kept close friends apprised of her condition in neatly
                typed letters. In the <hi rend="italic">Selected Papers</hi>, we admitted new
                witnesses during Anthony’s month of silent decline. Except insofar as we had
                admitted journalists’ accounts of their speeches and interviews, the concluding
                pages of the sixth volume depart from a strict commitment to using only words sent
                to or authored by Stanton and Anthony. Having decided to open that door, it was a
                matter of selecting texts by women who had access to Anthony’s bedroom, who may have
                written for an effect of their own but who had firsthand information. Two letters by
                the niece trace false hopes of improvement and reveal how family members edited the
                news allowed to reach Anthony. Those are followed by her doctor’s statement to the
                press on March 6, 1906.<ptr target="#note14" xml:id="nr14" n="14"/> And for the
                moment of death, we had an unusual source. In 1981, when the project announced its
                search for the papers of Stanton and Anthony in <hi rend="italic">Yankee
                    Magazine</hi>, a family sent us a letter from a young nurse named Mabel Nichols
                who trained in Massachusetts. While in Rochester visiting friends at the nursing
                school, Nichols was hired as Susan B. Anthony’s night nurse. On the morning of her
                patient’s death, she described the events for her sister back home, ending her
                letter (and our volume) with disputed claims for proximity to the dead. “The paper
                gives the names of the parties that were at the death bed, but to tell the truth
                Maude I was all alone with the dear old soul.”<ptr target="#note15" xml:id="nr15"
                    n="15"/></p>
            <p>When I first wrote a short piece about editing death for the <hi rend="italic"
                    >Project Newsletter</hi> of the Stanton and Anthony Papers, one editor sent me a
                defense of “the abrupt end to the letters” at an edition’s conclusion, meaning to
                end an edition without reference to the fact of death. I inferred that because Clara
                Barton (let’s pretend we speak of her) makes no mention of her own death, the style
                does not permit Barton’s editor to step in with information deemed extraneous to the
                text of each letter or other document. The kind of narrative that frames a life—her
                birth, her death—is segregated into editorial apparatus in essays, chronologies, and
                chapter headings. It is as if Clara Barton wrote one narrative in a life of letters
                and her editor wrote another. Such a bifurcation assumes an impossible distance
                between editor and subject, imagines that an editorial voice is not expressed in the
                arrangement of Clara Barton’s narrative. The editor’s hand and voice is all over the
                editions, working in collaboration with the subject, whether overtly or not. An
                intervention to let the subject die in train seems no more than to extend a slight
                courtesy.</p>
            <p>While I contemplated how to edit the deaths of Stanton and Anthony in ways consistent
                with the edition, I forgot to consult <hi rend="italic">The Letters of Virginia
                    Woolf</hi>, though the six volumes occupy a shelf at eye level near my most
                comfortable chair. Woolf’s dramatic death introduces new considerations. As a
                textual artifact, the suicide note overturns my original premise, that a person’s
                papers are pretty useless for documenting his or her own death. Such a note brings
                the reader closer to the end of the author’s life than whatever random letter or
                note gets the editor’s attention for an ending. In the nearly thirty years since I
                last read the final volume of the <hi rend="italic">Letters</hi>, I forgot how
                tightly the narratives of Woolf and her editors are woven at the end. It happens
                that in the papers of Virginia Woolf, there is not one suicide note but three. For
                Nigel Nicolson and Joanne Trautmann, editing death entailed careful textual
                    scholarship.<ptr target="#note16" xml:id="nr16" n="16"/></p>
            <p>Virginia Woolf had written two notes to her husband, Leonard, and one to her sister,
                Vanessa Bell. None was dated, though two of them indicated (different) days of the
                week. Two different tablets of paper had been used. The family—her husband Leonard
                and Quentin Bell, Virginia’s nephew and biographer—settled on a chronology and
                explanation for the multiple notes that were all found at once. Her editors
                questioned the chronology, assigned three different tentative dates to the notes,
                and in their words “dat[ed] the stages by which she reached her decision” (491). If
                they are correct (and I do not pretend to evaluate their work), their chronology
                introduces evidence of a failed suicide. In the simple act of editing death, the
                editors potentially revised the narrative of death, that most certain of things.</p>
        </body>
        <back>
            <div type="notes">
                <note xml:id="note1">Ann D. Gordon, Michael David Cohen, Sara Rzeszutek Haviland,
                    Andy Bowers, and Katharine Lee, eds., <hi rend="italic">Selected Papers of
                        Elizabeth Cady Stanton and Susan B. Anthony</hi>, vol. 6, <hi rend="italic"
                        >An Awful Hush, 1895 to 1906</hi> (New Brunswick, NJ: Rutgers University
                    Press, 2013). Kathleen E. Manning was also part of the team during this
                    exercise.</note>
                <note xml:id="note2">Gordon, <hi rend="italic">An Awful Hush, 1895 to 1906</hi>,
                    435–37.</note>
                <note xml:id="note3">For her articles of April 20 and October 13, see Gordon, <hi
                        rend="italic">An Awful Hush, 1895 to 1906</hi>, 430–32, 441–46. For all
                    articles published in 1902, see Patricia G. Holland and Ann D. Gordon, eds., <hi
                        rend="italic">Papers of Elizabeth Cady Stanton and Susan B. Anthony</hi>
                    (Wilmington, DE: Scholarly Resources Inc., 1991, microfilm).</note>
                <note xml:id="note4">Beverly Wilson Palmer, ed., <hi rend="italic">The Selected
                        Letters of Charles Sumner</hi>, 2 vols. (Boston: Northeastern University
                    Press, 1990), 2:631.</note>
                <note xml:id="note5">J. Robert Constantine, ed., <hi rend="italic">Letters of Eugene
                        V. Debs</hi>, vol. 3, <hi rend="italic">1919–1926</hi> (Urbana: University
                    of Illinois Press, 1990), 581–82, 601.</note>
                <note xml:id="note6">Joel Myerson and Daniel Shealy, eds., <hi rend="italic">The
                        Selected Letters of Louisa May Alcott</hi> (Boston: Little Brown and
                    Company, 1987), 337.</note>
                <note xml:id="note7">For ideas about biographical narration, see Leon Edel, <hi
                        rend="italic">Literary Biography</hi> (1959; reprint, Bloomington: Indiana
                    University Press, 1973), especially chap. 5, “Time.”</note>
                <note xml:id="note8">Marc Rothenberg et al., eds., <hi rend="italic">The Papers of
                        Joseph Henry</hi>, vol. 11, <hi rend="italic">January 1866–May 1878, The
                        Smithsonian Years</hi> (Washington, DC: Smithsonian Institution, 2007),
                    653–55.</note>
                <note xml:id="note9">Arthur S. Link, John E. Little, and L. Kathleen Amon, eds., <hi
                        rend="italic">The Papers of Woodrow Wilson</hi>, vol. 68, <hi rend="italic"
                        >April 8, 1922–February 6, 1924</hi> (Princeton, NJ: Princeton University
                    Press, 1993), 547ff.</note>
                <note xml:id="note10">September 25, 1902, Gordon, <hi rend="italic">An Awful Hush,
                        1895 to 1906</hi>, 434–35.</note>
                <note xml:id="note11">October 26, 1902, Gordon, <hi rend="italic">An Awful Hush,
                        1895 to 1906</hi>, 452.</note>
                <note xml:id="note12">To Ida H. Harper, October 28, 1902, in Gordon, <hi
                        rend="italic">An Awful Hush, 1895 to 1906</hi>, 455–56.</note>
                <note xml:id="note13">Gordon, <hi rend="italic">An Awful Hush, 1895 to 1906</hi>,
                    xxix–xxx, 577–78.</note>
                <note xml:id="note14">Lucy E. Anthony to Ida H. Harper, February 28, 1906, and to
                    Elizabeth Smith Miller, March 2, 1906, and Statement by Dr. Marcena Sherman
                    Ricker, March 6, 1906, all in Gordon, <hi rend="italic">An Awful Hush, 1895 to
                        1906</hi>, 579–81.</note>
                <note xml:id="note15">Mabel Nichols to Maude Nichols, March 13, 1906, in Gordon, <hi
                        rend="italic">An Awful Hush, 1895 to 1906</hi>, 581–82.</note>
                <note xml:id="note16">“The Dating of Virginia Woolf’s Last Letters,” appendix A in
                        <hi rend="italic">The Letters of Virginia Woolf</hi>, ed. Nigel Nicolson and
                    Joanne Trautmann, vol. 6, <hi rend="italic">1936–1941</hi> (New York: Harcourt
                    Brace Jovanovich, 1980), 489–91.</note>
            </div>
        </back>
    </text>
</TEI>
