<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
    <teiHeader xml:lang="eng">
        <fileDesc>
            <titleStmt>
                <title level="a" type="main"
                    >Documentary Editing in the New Scholarly Ecosystem</title>
                <title level="a" type="sub">Presidential Address, Association for Documentary Editing Annual Meeting, Salt Lake City, Utah, 2011</title>
                <author>Susan H. Perdue</author>
            </titleStmt>
            <editionStmt>
                <edition>
                    <date>2012</date>
                </edition>
            </editionStmt>
            <publicationStmt>
                <idno type="file">essay.2012presidentialaddress</idno>
                <authority>Scholary Editing: The Annual of the Association for Documentary
                    Editing</authority>
                <address>
          <addrLine>http://www.scholarlyediting.org</addrLine>
        </address>
                <publisher>Association for Documentary Editing</publisher>
                <publisher>University of Nebraska&#8211;Lincoln</publisher>
                <distributor>
                    <name>Center for Digital Research in the Humanities</name>
                    <address>
            <addrLine>319 Love Library</addrLine>
            <addrLine>University of Nebraska&#8211;Lincoln</addrLine>
            <addrLine>Lincoln, NE 68588-4100</addrLine>
            <addrLine>http://cdrh.unl.edu</addrLine>
          </address>
                </distributor>
                <date>2012</date>
                <availability>
                    <p>Scholary Editing: The Annual of the Association for Documentary Editing is
                        freely distributed by the Association for Documentary Editing and the Center
                        for Digital Research in the Humanities at the University of Nebraska-Lincoln
                        and licensed under a Creative Commons Attribution-NonCommercial-ShareAlike
                        3.0 Unported License</p>
                </availability>
            </publicationStmt>
            <seriesStmt>
                <title level="j"
                    >Scholarly Editing: The Annual of the Association for Documentary
                    Editing</title>
                <respStmt>
                    <resp>editor</resp>
                    <name xml:id="ag">Amanda Gailey</name>
                </respStmt>
                <respStmt>
                    <resp>editor</resp>
                    <name xml:id="awj">Andrew Jewell</name>
                </respStmt>
                <idno type="vol">33</idno>
                <idno type="ISSN">2167-1257</idno>
            </seriesStmt>
            <sourceDesc>
                <bibl>
                    <note>Born digital.</note>
                </bibl>
            </sourceDesc>
        </fileDesc>
        <revisionDesc>
            <change when="2012-01-30" who="#awj">markup in TEI XML</change>
        </revisionDesc>
    </teiHeader>
    <text>
        <front>
            <head type="main"
                >Documentary Editing in the New Scholarly Ecosystem</head>
            <head type="sub">Presidential Address</head><head type="sub">Association for Documentary Editing Annual Meeting</head><head type="sub">Salt Lake City, Utah, 2011</head>
            <byline>Susan H. Perdue</byline>
        </front>
        <body>

           <div type="section"> <p>I want to start by telling you a
                cautionary tale based on my own experience. I am hoping that through the
                telling of this story I will emerge from the process a braver and stronger
                person; I am hoping that at the end of this talk you will also emerge braver
                and stronger people, and that you will share with me a sense of the importance
                of the task we have before us. I think the time is at hand for those of us
                gathered here tonight, and for all of the ADE membership to take control of our
                collective futures.</p>
            
            <p>At the Virginia Foundation for the
                Humanities where I direct Documents Compass, the program directors undergo an
                annual evaluation. This process entails counting the number of people each
                program reaches through a direct audience (such as a lecture), or a mediated
                event (such as a radio broadcast). We then take the overall cost of the program
                and divide it by our total audience, thus resulting in a cost quotient for the
                program. I have never participated in this kind of evaluation before. You can probably
                guess that this annual exercise gets my colleagues really exercised. Not
                surprisingly, they protest because they believe we are comparing apples and
                oranges. During these often-heated discussions I take a low profile, because my
                own cost quotient is so high. I am unsure of my ability to explain this cost to
                them because what we do is so unfamiliar to them. We are not producing radio
                shows for hundreds of thousands of listeners, nor are we putting on an annual
                book festival for thousands of out-of- town visitors, both of which are
                activities sponsored by the Virginia Foundation. We are neither fish nor fowl,
                apple nor orange. It is very difficult for me to quantify or assess the impact
                and outreach of what I do, but I should be able to express to them the <hi rend="italic">importance</hi>
                of what I do.</p>
            
            <p>The work I do nowadays is part
                documentary editing, part consulting, and part project management. Although
                this is different from what I used to do as an editor of a documentary edition
                devoted to one person, I still hold fast to the basic tenets of our profession.
                These are making documents accessible and understandable, providing those
                documents with a level of authority and trustworthiness, and making them the
                building blocks of scholarly products that will stand the test of time, whether
                they are destined for bookshelves or online.</p>
            
            <p>I know that the pursuit of these
                goals in documentary editing does not come cheap. I know that our work is labor
                intensive and careful, and there is a cost involved. Yet, when faced with my
                cost quotient each year, I become a tad nervous&#8212;a bit fearful. I fear
                that the process of explaining this situation is too complicated or too time
                consuming. What saves me from having to do any of this is that my quotient is
                also factored by the uniqueness of the program, and thus I am saved for another
                year. If I were to hand out advice to myself in addition to handing it out to
                you tonight, I would say that I am missing a valuable opportunity each year to
                educate the folks that I work with about what it is that I do. I promise I will
                do better next year. See, I am already braver and stronger.</p>
            
            <p>I am taking the opportunity I now have
                to use my personal experience as a way to illustrate what I see as a similar behavior
                pattern within the profession of documentary editing. I think that too often we
                shrink from defending the process and product of documentary editing, allowing
                the conversation to be overtaken by others putting antiquated editions online, or
                simply inadequate editions on line. What truly concerns me now is the pervasive
                sense that we as a profession might be overwhelmed by the forces of change. It
                feels as if we are a profession in crisis. But are we? That is the question I
                would like to investigate briefly in my talk. I do not propose to offer
                solutions here, but rather suggest a strategy for coming up with some solutions
                as an organization. I think that this is a bigger task than ADE alone can
                accomplish. I believe that what is needed is a larger initiative that expands
                our borders beyond the comfortable and manageable territory we call documentary
                editing.</p>
            
            <p>Over the last thirty years ADE has
                faced repeated crises in funding. We find ourselves in the same situation year
                after year fighting a familiar battle&#8212;an experience Ray Smock likened to
                the movie <hi rend="italic">Groundhog Day</hi>, wherein the
                protagonist played by Bill Murray awakens each morning to relive the same
                experience of the same day over and over again. Certainly we have matured as a
                profession, and as an organization we are moving ahead on several fronts. Yet,
                we are fighting for funding levels that are reminiscent of the 1970s.</p>
            
            <p>Meanwhile, the monumental shift in
                publishing from print to digital is having an enormous impact on documentary
                editors across the board. The pressure from users, funders, and even sometimes
                publishers to respond to this shift has added one more burden on the shoulders
                of editors. Exacerbating this situation is the fact that funders, facing their
                own pressures, are linking financial support to digital publication. The result
                is that everyone feels that they are in a perpetual crisis mode, moving from
                one defensive posture to another. Expectations are constantly changing. Technology
                is rapidly evolving. Many editors are feeling personal and project-level
                stress. What is an editor to do, or more precisely, what are we to do as
                documentary editors? How do we see this as anything but a crisis?</p>
            
            <p>Let's stop and take a collective
                breath and survey the landscape. We are not alone. Funding organizations and
                academic presses are experiencing the present in much the same way. It is
                pretty obvious what is happening to funders in the current economic climate.
                Money is tighter and therefore funders are under extreme pressure to fight for
                level funding, and lucky to get even that. Academic presses are undergoing similar
                stresses: a decline in print revenues coupled with a push for open access.</p>
            
            <p>I propose to you that we see
                documentary editing not in crisis but as experiencing tectonic-like shifts
                within a larger scholarly ecosystem that we share. All of us are facing a new
                landscape of scholarly communication in which it is imperative that we each stake
                our ground. We should make clear what it is we do best and why. Facing this situation,
                I think we are wise to study the example of our colleagues in academic
                publishing, namely the American Association of University Presses. This year the
                AAUP formed a task force to prepare a report entitled "Economic Models for
                Scholarly Publishing." The report begins by presenting an overview of the
                publishing systems that are, in its words "worth protecting and retaining
                throughout this and future periods of transition."<ptr target="#note1" xml:id="nr1" n="1"/> The
                task force goes on to summarize the central role that academic publishers have
                played in the scholarly ecosystem. I will highlight here a few of the services
                they identified: selectivity, editorial engagement, imprimatur, and long-term
                availability, among others. The remainder of the report looks at new approaches
                to scholarly publishing and some suggestions of new business models. I am
                struck by the parallels between what the task force states as worth protecting
                for academic publishing, and what I think is worth protecting in documentary
                editing.  </p>
            
            <p>As a profession, we too must take this
                critical first step. We must demonstrate that we are not in crisis but rather we
                are strong and constantly creating new scholarly content that is rich and
                varied. What we do has virtue. Now more than ever it is incumbent upon us to
                identify and actively promote the best characteristics of scholarly editing&#8212;to
                demonstrate our virtues&#8212;especially in the new "hyperabundant
                landscape," a phrase used in the AAUP report to describe this new world. We
                now have to think about reaching and interacting with an audience, the size and
                scope of which we never could have anticipated twenty-five years ago. </p>
            
            <p>So let me review for you what we
                already know: the features of documentary editing that make it unique,
                important, and virtuous.  You will of course be able to think of some more, but
                I will limit it to three main categories.</p></div>
            
            <div type="section"><head type="main">Number one: Accessibility</head>
            
            <p>The primary objective of every documentary edition is to make
                documents accessible to users. Whether in print or digital format, this means
                that every document is presented in a uniform fashion according to consistent
                transcription rules and standards that are clearly stated to the end user. The
                inclusion of indexes, tables of contents, and prefaces are the typical devices
                that lead scholars and users of all stripes to the documents. We make documents
                accessible in ways that go beyond text searching alone.</p></div>
            
            <div type="section"><head type="main">Number two: Expertise and authority</head>
            
            <p>An editor's familiarity and comfort level with the material
                is key to the documentary edition. His or her expertise guides the process of
                selection and annotation, both of which confer authority to the finished product.
                While they work, editors keep in mind a sense of the larger document corpus
                that they work from. They can recall similar documents. They can recognize
                recurring themes or verbal quirks. Most importantly, they recognize defining
                moments in documents. Although we may not agree about levels of selectivity, my
                hunch is that everyone in this room believes in his or her heart that he or she
                is the best judge of what each document requires in the way of explanation. You
                have the greatest ability to identify forgeries and misdated documents, for
                example, and you know it. This is the true strength of the profession. This is
                why, whether a document is transcribed by you, your most gifted graduate
                student, or produced via crowdsourcing, ultimately, you will bring your
                expertise and experience as an editor to bear on this document. Let's make this
                point at every opportunity. Authoritative documentary editions will never be
                more valuable than now in the Internet age, during which spurious quotes,
                renegade editions, and Wikipedia-like half truths will only increase in number.</p></div>
            
            <div type="section"><head type="main">Number three: Sustainability</head>
            
            <p>The collective assumption of everyone in this room is that
                the modern documentary editions we produce supersede all editions that have
                come before them. Indeed, modern documentary editing was built upon this "golden
                age" premise that the editions begun in the mid-twentieth century and
                every one thereafter has been built to last for the centuries. In my mind, when
                we talk about sustainability in the print realm, we are generally talking about
                putting volumes on shelves in academic libraries. It is in this category that
                the most dramatic shift has occurred for our profession and where the definitions
                have truly changed. Sustainability in the digital realm is something quite
                different than in the print realm. We now need to think about data curation, data
                updates, and even data migration. The Model Editions Partnership is a case in
                point.</p>
            
            <p>I think we will increasingly be asked
                by funders and sponsors to discuss the sustainability of our editions online. We
                are now being asked to serve as stewards of our content in ways we never have
                been before. I think that in order for us to advance as a profession we need to
                work together to find solutions to this question because our future success
                relies on it. This will require us to work in new ways.</p>
            
            <p>I began with a tale about my
                experience in the hopes that it would serve as an example of what not to do. I
                would like us as a profession to recognize and profess our strengths. We must
                be ready to explain what documentary editing is: the process, the product, and
                its costs. We should be able and willing to explain all of these things as a
                reasonable cost of what we do. But I think we need to do more. We need to think
                in even larger terms and we need to envision the profession as it will exist in
                the future. My aim in this talk was to encourage us as an organization to
                expand our thinking about documentary editing as a single isolated species&#8212;or
                an exceptional enterprise. We are part of a much larger system that includes
                university libraries, university presses, archivists, funders, editors, and IT
                professionals. Just as the AAUP did in forming a task force to address its own
                issues, I think we should define who we are, outline our issues, and suggest
                some solutions. We should get out ahead of the forces
                that we believe threaten us and our existence. This will have to be a collaborative
                enterprise that will involve all of us who are struggling to survive in the new
                scholarly ecosystem.</p></div>
            
            
                
                
                

</body>
        <back>


            <div type="notes">
                
                <note xml:id="note1">The report is available for free
                    online at <ref type="url" target="http://www.aaupnet.org/policy-areas/future-of-scholarly-communications/task-force-on-economic-models-report">http://www.aaupnet.org/policy-areas/future-of-scholarly-communications/task-force-on-economic-models-report</ref></note>
                
            </div>
        </back>
    </text>
</TEI>
