<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
    <teiHeader xml:lang="eng">
        <fileDesc>
            <titleStmt>
                <title level="a" type="main">Editors' Introduction to the First Issue of <hi
                        rend="italic">Scholarly Editing: The Annual of the Association for
                        Documentary Editing</hi>
                </title>

                <author>Amanda Gailey</author>
                <author>Andrew Jewell</author>
            </titleStmt>
            <editionStmt>
                <edition>
                    <date>2012</date>
                </edition>
            </editionStmt>
            <publicationStmt>
                <idno type="file">essay.v33intro</idno>
                <authority>Scholary Editing: The Annual of the Association for Documentary
                    Editing</authority>
                <address>
          <addrLine>http://www.scholarlyediting.org</addrLine>
        </address>
                <publisher>Association for Documentary Editing</publisher>
                <publisher>University of Nebraska&#8211;Lincoln</publisher>
                <distributor>
                    <name>Center for Digital Research in the Humanities</name>
                    <address>
            <addrLine>319 Love Library</addrLine>
            <addrLine>University of Nebraska&#8211;Lincoln</addrLine>
            <addrLine>Lincoln, NE 68588-4100</addrLine>
            <addrLine>http://cdrh.unl.edu</addrLine>
          </address>
                </distributor>
                <date>2012</date>
                <availability>
                    <p>Scholary Editing: The Annual of the Association for Documentary Editing is
                        freely distributed by the Association for Documentary Editing and the Center
                        for Digital Research in the Humanities at the University of Nebraska-Lincoln
                        and licensed under a Creative Commons Attribution-NonCommercial-ShareAlike
                        3.0 Unported License</p>
                </availability>
            </publicationStmt>
            <seriesStmt>
                <title level="j">Scholarly Editing: The Annual of the Association for Documentary
                    Editing</title>
                <respStmt>
                    <resp>editor</resp>
                    <name xml:id="aag">Amanda Gailey</name>
                </respStmt>
                <respStmt>
                    <resp>editor</resp>
                    <name xml:id="awj">Andrew Jewell</name>
                </respStmt>
                <idno type="vol">33</idno>
                <idno type="ISSN">2167-1257</idno>
            </seriesStmt>
            <sourceDesc>
                <bibl>
                    <note>Born digital.</note>
                </bibl>
            </sourceDesc>
        </fileDesc>
        <revisionDesc>
            <change when="2012-01-23" who="#aag">markup in TEI XML</change>
        </revisionDesc>
    </teiHeader>
    <text>
        <front>
            <head type="main">Editors' Introduction to the First Issue of <hi rend="italic"
                    >Scholarly Editing: The Annual of the Association for Documentary
                Editing</hi></head>
            <byline>Amanda Gailey</byline>
            <byline>Andrew Jewell</byline>

        </front>

        <body>

            <p>We are honored to present the inaugural issue of <hi rend="italic">Scholarly Editing:
                    The Annual of the Association for Documentary Editing</hi>. As many readers
                know, this journal has had a long life as a print publication&#8212;<hi
                    rend="italic">Documentary Editing</hi>&#8212;but has now been remade as an
                open-access, digital vehicle for publishing not only essays about the theory and
                practice of editing but also short scholarly editions themselves. The journal will
                be among the first&#8212;if not <hi rend="italic">the</hi> first&#8212;to
                offer a platform for textual editors to publish peer-reviewed short editions. Our
                concept for the remaking of the journal, and particularly for the publication of
                short editions, emerged from a desire to somehow respond to obstacles we see
                emerging for digital scholarly editing, and to provide an incentive to would-be
                editors in the form of technological support, peer review, and publication. We would
                like to offer some background on why we came to remake this journal, and how we see
                    <hi rend="italic">Scholarly Editing: The Annual of the Association for
                    Documentary Editing</hi> as providing an important venue both for editors
                looking for appropriate publication opportunities and for any reader interested in
                the documents comprising the record of cultural history.</p>

            <p>We first, however, want to publicly thank the Association for Documentary Editing,
                which sponsors this journal. The ADE has long supported the editorial work of a
                varied group of scholars, and in embracing the reinvention of this journal, they are
                taking a substantial risk. For over thirty years, the ADE has successfully published
                    <hi rend="italic">Documentary Editing</hi> as a print journal, and, of course,
                the organization could have persisted with that model. True to its mission to
                support the work of scholarly editors, though, the organization embraced a new model
                that would allow for both continued publication of essays about the theory and
                practice of editing and, importantly, editions themselves. By sponsoring <hi
                    rend="italic">Scholarly Editing</hi>, the ADE is dedicating itself to a new
                publication model that will hopefully expand the opportunities for scholars
                undertaking editorial work. It takes a committed and courageous organization to
                embrace a reinvention of its well-established publication, and we wish to thank the
                membership and leadership of the ADE for its gracious support throughout the
                development of this debut issue. </p>

            <p>We undertook to transform this publication because we saw it as a significant
                opportunity to contribute to the fields of both editing and digital humanities. Over
                the last fifteen years or so, scholarly editing has increasingly turned to digital
                environments for their flexibility and potential. Space and financial constraints
                historically have forced print editors to make choices about which texts should be
                considered authoritative, sometimes requiring them to choose one version of a
                complex work to represent in the edition, or to collapse complicated documentary
                histories into an apparatus often so impenetrably condensed that such editions have
                been accused of placing texts behind "barbed wire." Digital editions radically ease
                these concerns, theoretically allowing editors to include any number of drafts and
                competing print variations, and allowing for creative and dynamic interfaces that
                can help readers immediately comprehend the complexity of the text, rather than
                choking it up with an intimidating print apparatus. The digital environment also
                allows for facsimiles of documents to be used in ways that are unimaginable in
                print, sometimes illuminatingly knitted to transcriptions and commentary, and
                sometimes offering a degree of detail that would be prohibitively expensive in print
                volumes. Digital editing also allows editors to reconceive the very basis of
                editions, collecting, studying, and recombining works around different axes than
                what can conform to the strictures of the codex edition. Digital editors find that
                the ongoing nature of their projects allow them to add texts and commentary and
                correct mistakes in ways that their print forbears would have envied. Best of all,
                while an impressive, multi-volume print edition may cost hundreds or even thousands
                of dollars&#8212;often meaning that only research libraries or true devotees can
                buy it, or that lay readers are limited to the narrower offerings of a derived
                reader's edition&#8212;some of the largest digital editions are available free
                online, readable by anyone with a computer and internet connection.</p>

            <p>For these reasons, literary scholars, historians, librarians, musicologists,
                paleographers, philosophers, and many other scholars around the world have taken up
                digital editing as the most promising means of representing and disseminating the
                primary materials in their fields. Mass digitization projects, which typically use
                quick and dirty automated methods to digitize vast quantities of texts, attract a
                lot of attention in the popular press, though editors&#8212;while likely
                availing themselves of the remarkable convenience of such projects&#8212;often
                cringe at the projects' shortcomings in metadata, accuracy, representation of
                compositional and publication complexities, and annotation. Large, scholar-led
                digital editions have also grown up over the past decade, with a handful of usually
                canonical figures receiving comprehensive coverage in online editions. However, we
                have noticed that editions of a smaller scale&#8212;for example, ones that may
                study a single text, a small collection of texts, or a grouping of noncanonical
                texts&#8212;have conspicuously not fared as well.</p>

            <p>Back in the early oughts of this century, when we were working as graduate students
                on the <hi rend="italic">Walt Whitman Archive</hi> (<ref type="url"
                    target="http://www.whitmanarchive.org">www.whitmanarchive.org</ref>), it
                seemed to us that we were about to see a great wave of new digital materials for
                literary study and that those materials would be, first and foremost, digital
                editions. However, while we can point to examples of well-done scholarly editions,
                they have not been produced at the rate that many digital humanists likely expected
                a decade ago. The tremendous promise that excited us as graduate students has not
                been fulfilled, and the traditional anxieties of scholarly editors persist. Digital
                editors still face the old concerns about whether editorial work will be valued by
                hiring and promotion committees, and they must confront the intimidating obstacles
                of undertaking a digital project, including finding server space, technological
                support, and an enduring venue for publication, as well as gambling on work that is
                likely to never earn that most important of academic blessings, peer review.
                Reflecting on these obstacles, we proposed <hi rend="italic">Scholarly Editing: The
                    Annual of the Association of Documentary Editing</hi> in the hope that it could
                offer to small-scale editions a stable publication environment, some technical
                advice, and most importantly, peer review, all of which would be a significant and
                innovative service to both would-be editors and to the general public, who have had
                limited access to so many fascinating documents from cultural history. And, since we
                are partnering with the Center for Digital Research in the Humanities at the
                University of Nebraska-Lincoln (<ref type="url"
                    target="http://cdrh.unl.edu">cdrh.unl.edu</ref>), which is housed in the UNL Libraries, the digital
                journal <hi rend="italic">Scholarly Editing</hi> will benefit from the same
                long-term stewardship as the rest of the digital scholarship published by the
                Center. </p>

            <p>Our publication of these short editions is happening through a fairly straightforward
                system: we gather proposals from editors and select the best proposals for
                graduation to the next step; we then get TEI-XML files and schemas from the editors;
                after the XML is received, we modify our house stylesheets for proper rendering of
                the digital edition on the web (or, in rare cases, implement editor-provided
                interface design). Once all parties&#8212;journal editors and edition
                editors&#8212;are satisfied with the interface, we submit the editions to peer
                reviews. Upon successful review, the editions are published. (Simultaneously, we
                have accepted submissions of essays on the theory and practice of editing that have
                also been peer-reviewed prior to publication.)</p>

            <p>In addition to offering an important venue to editors, we also see this publication
                as providing a balance to certain trends within digital humanities, the nebulous
                umbrella term used to describe any number of humanistic undertakings aided by
                computers. To be blunt, we believe that over the last decade, and especially more
                recently, "digital humanities" has come to be defined more by the digital than by
                the humanities. We suspect that this results from many factors, including a
                broadening of the term "digital humanities" to include such a wide range of
                scholarly pursuits that very little yokes them together, apart from a general
                interest in developing or implementing technology-driven (or, at least,
                technology-enabled) methodologies. Most definitions of the term "digital humanities"
                illustrate this point. For example, in Matt Kirschenbaum's recent essay in the <hi
                    rend="italic">ADE Bulletin</hi>, "What is Digital Humanities and What's It Doing
                in English Departments?," he cites the Wikipedia entry on "Digital Humanities"
                (written by people active in the field), commenting, "as a working definition this
                serves as well as any I've seen"<ptr target="#note1" xml:id="nr1" n="1"/>. That
                definition is appropriately wide: <q rend="block">The digital humanities, also known
                    as humanities computing, is a field of study, research, teaching, and invention
                    concerned with the intersection of computing and the disciplines of the
                    humanities. It is methodological by nature and interdisciplinary in scope. It
                    involves investigation, analysis, synthesis and presentation of information in
                    electronic form. It studies how these media affect the disciplines in which they
                    are used, and what these disciplines have to contribute to our knowledge of
                    computing. </q> Though we do not quibble with this as a working definition of
                the field, it is telling that beyond the co-existence of "humanities" and
                "computing," and perhaps the inclination to interdisciplinary teamwork, there is
                little to unite the varied people who self-identify as digital humanists. </p>

            <p> Most conversations in the "digital humanities" community, then, tend toward the
                technology and the methodology: this is what unites the medievalist and the Western
                American historian, the classicist and the librarian. This has also resulted in a
                professional culture that identifies innovations in technology and methodology as
                paramount, and the most headline-grabbing accomplishments in digital humanities are
                fixated on these innovations. Conspicuously absent from this trend, however, are
                celebrations of content-rich digital humanities projects. The valuing of
                technological innovation has made it a little more difficult for editors to create
                digital editions comfortably within the community of digital humanities, as the base
                technologies for creating digital editions have been fairly stable for nearly a
                decade. It used to be that digital humanities scholars would proclaim mightily about
                the power of new systems of access and distribution. "Imagine," we would shout,
                "what will happen when all of author X's work can be edited and published online,
                for free, allowing unfettered access to senior scholars and students alike!" But, in
                the rhetoric of the last few years, such innovations as these seem to have bored
                people. They've grown so used to the ability to access materials through the web, to
                the results of text markup and interface design, and to the ways in which the web
                has reorganized&#8212;and continues to reorganize&#8212;scholarly
                communication, that there is little enthusiasm for new projects that find their
                bread and butter in such technologies. This shift in focus from content development
                to technological innovation, a trend that sometimes seems driven by innovation for
                innovation's sake, can at its worst seem to posit a "hipster ethos" for the digital
                humanities community&#8212;that the quality of the work you do is not so
                important as staying at the edge of innovation, always one step ahead of the
                unfashionable masses. However, we are concerned that viewing technological
                innovation as a value in itself will have pernicious effects on the development of
                digital humanities, both by estranging the field from scholarly humanities content
                and by asserting to our colleagues that digital humanities is a field open only to
                those few scholars who have the institutional resources to develop tools that are
                technologically cutting edge. It is our contention that what we are doing with <hi
                    rend="italic">Scholarly Editing</hi> is both innovative and, pleasantly, rooted
                in a long scholarly tradition. The innovation is in the details: the nature of the
                publication, the form of the scholarly communication, and the method by which we
                will publish, combined with the technology underlying the editing. The tradition is
                in the value we have placed on scholarly editing as a worthy enterprise, an
                enterprise that need not worry over the vagaries of academic hipness. We are basing
                our editorial vision on a notion that digital tools&#8212;new or
                established&#8212;should be utilized only if they are serving the needs of
                humanistic inquiry.</p>

            <p>In this, our debut issue, we include three small-scale editions that evidence the
                value of combining careful editorial attention, humanistic expertise, and developed
                digital methodologies. <ref type="html"
                    target="../../2012/editions/intro.liveoakwithmoss">"The
                        Inscription of Walt Whitman's 'Live Oak, With Moss' Sequence: A Restorative
                        Edition,"</ref> edited by Steven Olsen-Smith, recovers Whitman's
                revisions to this significant poem about same-sex attachment, revisions that have
                been neglected by print scholarship, and offers suggestions in how these
                restorations might change our understanding of the text. In <ref type="html"
                    target="../../2012/editions/intro.utctopsy">"A Selection from
                        '<hi rend="italic">Uncle Tom's Cabin</hi>: A Critical Edition':
                    'Topsy,'"</ref> Wesley Raabe and Les Harrison present a "fluid text" edition
                of one of the most significant sections of what is perhaps the most important work
                of fiction in nineteenth-century America and a key text in American racial history.
                Five different versions of the text, ranging from the original serial publication to
                a luxury book version, show how the complicated mid-nineteenth-century American
                literary marketplace resulted in textual change. In <ref type="html"
                    target="../../2012/editions/baroness/main.baroness">"The
                        Firstling/Erstling/He Complex,"</ref> Tanya Clement and Gaby Duvay
                present a dizzyingly complicated manuscript cluster by the eccentric Baroness von
                Freytag-Loringhoven, allowing the reader to explore through a sophisticated and
                dynamic interface how the texts relate to one another. </p>

            <p>This issue also offers essays that explore diverse concerns within the field of
                scholarly editing: Ronald Broude discusses the challenges of editing music in <ref
                    type="html" target="../../2012/essays/essay.broude">"Musical Works, Musical
                    Texts, and Musical Editions: A Brief Overview"</ref>; John Fierst describes the
                textual complexities involved in editing a Native American captivity narrative in
                    <ref type="html" target="../../2012/essays/essay.fierst">"A 'Succession of
                    Little Occurrences': Scholarly Editing and the Organization of Time in John
                    Tanner's <hi rend="italic">Narrative</hi>"</ref>; and Paul Grant-Costa, Tobias
                Glaza, and Michael Sletcher discuss the promise of cooperatively editing neglected
                historical documents in <ref type="html" target="../../2012/essays/essay.commonpot"
                    >"The Common Pot: Editing Native American Materials."</ref> Finally, in keeping
                with the tradition of the print journal, we offer reviews of new publications, a
                compilation of recent editions, and President Susan Perdue's <ref type="html"
                    target="../../2012/essays/essay.2012presidentialaddress">2011 address to the
                    Association for Documentary Editing</ref>.</p>

            <p> We hope <hi rend="italic">Scholarly Editing: The Annual of the Association for
                    Documentary Editing</hi> demonstrates to readers the powerful revelations about
                the documents of our shared cultural histories that are made possible through
                editing.</p>


        </body>




        <back>
            <div type="notes">
                <note xml:id="note1">Matt Kirschenbaum, <ref type="url"
                        target="http://mkirschenbaum.files.wordpress.com/2011/01/kirschenbaum_ade150.pdf"
                        >"What Is Digital Humanities and What's It
                    Doing in English Departments?"</ref> <hi rend="italic">ADE Bulletin</hi> 150 (2010):
                    1-7.</note>
            </div>
        </back>
    </text>
</TEI>
