<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
    <teiHeader xml:lang="eng">
        <fileDesc>
            <titleStmt>
                <title level="a" type="main">Table of Published Editions of John Tanner's <hi rend="italic">Narrative</hi></title>
                
                <author>John T. Fierst</author>
            </titleStmt>
            <editionStmt>
                <edition>
                    <date>2012</date>
                </edition>
            </editionStmt>
            <publicationStmt>
                <idno type="file">essay.fierst_table</idno>
                <authority>Scholary Editing: The Annual of the Association for Documentary
                    Editing</authority>
                <address>
          <addrLine>http://www.scholarlyediting.org</addrLine>
        </address>
                <publisher>Association for Documentary Editing</publisher>
                <publisher>University of Nebraska&#8211;Lincoln</publisher>
                <distributor>
                    <name>Center for Digital Research in the Humanities</name>
                    <address>
            <addrLine>319 Love Library</addrLine>
            <addrLine>University of Nebraska&#8211;Lincoln</addrLine>
            <addrLine>Lincoln, NE 68588-4100</addrLine>
            <addrLine>http://cdrh.unl.edu</addrLine>
          </address>
                </distributor>
                <date>2012</date>
                <availability>
                    <p>Scholary Editing: The Annual of the Association for Documentary Editing is
                        freely distributed by the Association for Documentary Editing and the Center
                        for Digital Research in the Humanities at the University of Nebraska-Lincoln
                        and licensed under a Creative Commons Attribution-NonCommercial-ShareAlike
                        3.0 Unported License</p>
                </availability>
            </publicationStmt>
            <seriesStmt>
                <title level="j"
                    >Scholarly Editing: The Annual of the Association for Documentary
                    Editing</title>
                <respStmt>
                    <resp>editor</resp>
                    <name xml:id="ag">Amanda Gailey</name>
                </respStmt>
                <respStmt>
                    <resp>editor</resp>
                    <name xml:id="awj">Andrew Jewell</name>
                </respStmt>
                <idno type="vol">33</idno>
                <idno type="ISSN">2167-1257</idno>
            </seriesStmt>
            <sourceDesc>
                <bibl>
                    <note>Born digital.</note>
                </bibl>
            </sourceDesc>
        </fileDesc>
        <revisionDesc>
            <change when="2012-01-23" who="#awj">markup in TEI XML</change>
        </revisionDesc>
    </teiHeader>
    <text>
        <body>

            <table>
<head type="main">Published Editions of John Tanner's <hi rend="italic">Narrative</hi></head>
                
                <row>
                    <cell role="label">
                        Year
                    </cell>
                    <cell role="label">
                        Title
                    </cell>
                    <cell role="label">
                        Comment
                    </cell>
                </row>
                <row>
                    <cell>
                        1830
                    </cell>
                    <cell>
                        Tanner, John. <hi rend="italic"
                            >A Narrative of the Captivity and Adventures of John Tanner, (U.S. Interpreter at the Saut de Ste. Marie,) during Thirty Years Residence among the Indians in the Interior of North America. Prepared for the press by Edwin James, M. D.</hi>
                            New York: G. &amp; C. &amp; H. Carvill, 1830.
                    </cell>
                    <cell>
                        In the summer of 1828 John Tanner travelled to New York City where he sold his book and the artist Henry Inman painted his portrait. The portrait served as the frontispiece to the <hi
                            rend="italic">Narrative</hi>.
                    </cell>
                </row>
                <row>
                    <cell>
                        1830
                    </cell>
                    <cell>
                        ------. <hi rend="italic"
                            >A Narrative of the Captivity and Adventures of John Tanner, (U.S. Interpreter at the Saut de Ste. Marie,) during Thirty Years Residence among the Indians in the Interior of North America. Prepared for the press by Edwin James, M. D. </hi>London : Baldwin &amp; Cradock, 1830.
                    </cell>
                    <cell>
                        A British edition was published in 1830 as well. The New York and London editions were identical save for the facts of publication on their title pages.
                    </cell>
                </row>
                <row>
                    <cell>
                        1835
                    </cell>
                    <cell>
                        ------. <hi rend="italic"
                            >Memoirs de John Tanner, ou Trente Anees dans les Deserts de l'Amerique du Nord</hi>. Translated by Ernerst de Blosseville. 2 vols. Paris: A. Bertrand, 1835.
                    </cell>
                    <cell>
                        Tocqueville purchased the <hi rend="italic"
                            >Narrative</hi> from Tanner and brought it back to France. His friend Ernest de Blosseville translated it into French.
                    </cell>
                </row>
                <row>
                    <cell>
                        1840
                    </cell>
                    <cell>
                        <hi rend="italic"
                            >------. Des Kentuckier's John Tanner denkw&#252;rdigkeiten &#252;ber seinen dreissigj&#228;hrigen aufenthalt unter den Indianern Nord-Amerika's</hi>. Leipzig : W. Engelmann, 1840.
                    </cell>
                    <cell>
                        The geographer Karl Andree translated the <hi rend="italic"
                            >Narrative </hi>into<hi rend="italic"
                                > </hi>German and published it in 1840.
                        
                    </cell>
                </row>
                <row>
                    <cell>
                        1940
                    </cell>
                    <cell>
                        <hi rend="italic"
                            >------. An Indian Captivity (1789-1822). John Tanner's Narrative of His Captivity among the Ottawa and Ojibwa Indians, ed. Edwin James</hi>. Occasional Papers. Reprint Series No. 20. San Francisco: California State Library, 1940.
                    </cell>
                    <cell>
                        In 1940 anthropologist Paul Radin directed the reprinting of the <hi
                            rend="italic"
                            >Narrative</hi> proper in two parts. Personnel of the Work Projects Administration prepared the typescript. 
                    </cell>
                </row>
                <row>
                    <cell>
                        1956
                    </cell>
                    <cell>
                        ------. <hi rend="italic"
                            >A Narrative of the Captivity and Adventures of John Tanner, (U.S. Interpreter at the Saut de Ste. Marie,) during Thirty Years Residence among the Indians in the Interior of North America. Prepared for the press by Edwin James, M. D.</hi> Minneapolis: Ross &amp; Haines, 1956. 
                    </cell>
                    <cell>
                        In 1956, Ross &amp; Haines reset and republished the <hi rend="italic"
                            >Narrative</hi> in its entirety, and for many years this edition has served as the standard text.
                    </cell>
                </row>
                <row>
                    <cell>
                        1968
                    </cell>
                    <cell>
                        ------. <hi rend="italic"
                            >Dreissig Jahre unter den Indianern. Leben und Abenteuer des John Tanner.</hi> Weimar: Kiepenheuer, 1968. 
                    </cell>
                    <cell>
                        Eva Lips translated into German and edited this volume of the <hi rend="italic"
                            >Narrative.</hi>
                    </cell>
                </row>
                <row>
                    <cell>
                        1975
                    </cell>
                    <cell>
                        ------.<hi rend="italic"
                            >A narrative of the captivity and adventures of John Tanner . . . .</hi> New York : Garland Publishing, 1975. 
                    </cell>
                    <cell>
                        In 1975 the <hi rend="italic">Narrative </hi>was published as volume 46 in <hi
                            rend="italic"
                            >The Garland Library of Narratives of North American Indian Captivities</hi>. 
                    </cell>
                </row>
                <row>
                    <cell>
                        1983
                    </cell>
                    <cell>
                        ------. <hi rend="italic"
                            >Trente Ans de Captivit&#233; chez les Indians Ojibwa</hi>. Paris: Payot, 1983.
                    </cell>
                    <cell>
                        In 1983 Pierrette D&#233;sy published James's introduction and the first part of the <hi
                            rend="italic">Narrative</hi> in French, with ethnographic notes.
                    </cell>
                </row>
                <row>
                    <cell>
                        1994
                    </cell>
                    <cell>
                        ------. <hi rend="italic"
                            >The Falcon: A Narrative of the Captivity &amp; Adventures of John Tanner</hi>. . . . Penguin Nature Library. New York: Penguin Books, 1994.
                    </cell>
                    <cell>
                        In 1994, as part of its Nature Library, Penguin Books reissued the Ross &amp; Haines 1956 typescript. They published it in paperback under a new title, <hi
                            rend="italic"
                            >The Falcon</hi>, adding a five page introduction by Louise Erdrich but leaving off Edwin James's introduction and the<hi
                                rend="italic"> Narrative'</hi>s ethnographic appendices. 
                    </cell>
                </row>
            </table>

</body>
        
        
    </text>
</TEI>
