<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<?xml-model href="http://www.tei-c.org/release/xml/tei/custom/schema/relaxng/tei_all.rng" type="application/xml" schematypens="http://relaxng.org/ns/structure/1.0"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
    <teiHeader xml:lang="eng">
        <fileDesc>
            <titleStmt>
                <title level="m" type="main">Extracts from <hi rend="italics">The Young
                    Idea</hi></title>
                <author>Mary Isbell</author>
                <author>Teresa Navarro</author>
                <author>Katelyn Sahagian</author>
            </titleStmt>
            <publicationStmt>
                <authority>Scholarly Editing: The Annual of the Association for Documentary
                    Editing</authority>
                <address>
                    <addrLine>juxta</addrLine>
                    <addrLine>http://www.scholarlyediting.org</addrLine>
                </address>
                <publisher>Association for Documentary Editing</publisher>
                <publisher>University of Nebraska&#8211;Lincoln</publisher>
                <distributor>
                    <name>Center for Digital Research in the Humanities</name>
                    <address>
                        <addrLine>319 Love Library</addrLine>
                        <addrLine>University of Nebraska&#8211;Lincoln</addrLine>
                        <addrLine>Lincoln, NE 68588-4100</addrLine>
                        <addrLine>http://cdrh.unl.edu</addrLine>
                    </address>
                </distributor>
                <date>2015</date>
                <availability>
                    <p>Scholarly Editing: The Annual of the Association for Documentary Editing is
                        freely distributed by the Association for Documentary Editing and the Center
                        for Digital Research in the Humanities at the University of Nebraska-Lincoln
                        and licensed under a Creative Commons Attribution-NonCommercial-Share Alike
                        3.0 Unported License</p>
                </availability>
                <idno type="file">intro.EDITION_SAMPLE</idno>
                <idno type="edition">EDITION_SAMPLE</idno>
            </publicationStmt>
            <seriesStmt>
                <title level="j">Scholarly Editing: The Annual of the Association for Documentary
                    Editing</title>
                <respStmt>
                    <resp>editor</resp>
                    <name xml:id="ag">Amanda Gailey</name>
                </respStmt>
                <respStmt>
                    <resp>editor</resp>
                    <name xml:id="awj">Andrew Jewell</name>
                </respStmt>
                <idno type="vol">37</idno>
                <idno type="ISSN">2167-1257</idno>
            </seriesStmt>
            <sourceDesc>
                <bibl>
                    <author>Mary Isbell</author>
                    <author>Teresa Navarro</author>
                    <author>Katelyn Sahagian</author>
                    <title level="m" type="main">Extracts from <hi rend="italics">The Young
                            Idea</hi></title></bibl>
            </sourceDesc>
        </fileDesc>
    </teiHeader>
    <text>
        <front>
            <head type="main">Editorial Introduction</head>
            <head type="sub"><title>Extracts from <hi rend="italics">The Young
                Idea</hi></title></head>
            <lb/>
            <byline>Mary Isbell</byline>

        </front>
        <body>
            <div type="section">
                <p>"Newspapers are not generally regarded on board men-of-war with a friendly eye.”
                    So explains A. D. McArthur in his preface to the 1867 lithograph edition of <hi
                        rend="italics">The Young Idea: A Naval Journal edited on board H.M.S. <hi
                            rend="italics">Chesapeake</hi> in 1857, 1858, &amp; 1859</hi>. McArthur
                    edited <hi rend="italics">The Young Idea</hi>, an illustrated weekly paper,
                    while serving as a clerk aboard the <hi rend="italics">Chesapeake</hi> (flagship
                    of the East Indies and China Station); his preface goes on to explain that
                    officers viewed shipboard periodicals as vehicles of insubordination. Along with
                    the insight it provides into contributors’ impressions of the foreign ports they
                    visit (including Calcutta, Trincomalee, Aden, and Singapore), <hi rend="italics"
                        >The Young Idea</hi> offers a detailed account of day-to-day life aboard a
                    British warship. It includes, for example, an editorial remembrance of a sailor
                    killed by a falling piece of rigging and a “letter to the editor” complaining
                    that five gentlemen awakened the inhabitants of “forecastle street” by singing
                    “Annie Laurie” at the top of their lungs. It is tempting, when reading these
                    articles, letters, and riddles, to imagine that we’re joining these sailors
                    aboard a warship in the service of the British Empire. This insight into daily
                    life aboard a naval vessel was very likely one of McArthur’s goals in presenting
                    a formerly private newspaper to the public, but it is important to note that he
                    has curated the particular slice of life that he wants to make public. This
                    digital edition is designed to reveal the complexity of <hi rend="italic">The
                        Young Idea</hi>. It will surely prove useful to scholars interested in
                    nineteenth-century naval history, literature, and culture, but it should first
                    be understood as an artifact in its own right.</p>
                <p>After calling attention to the fact that shipboard newspapers are not popular
                    with officers, McArthur explains in his preface that he is practiced in the art
                    of self-censorship. He writes, “when I took the editorial pen, it was my fixed
                    determination to exclude all such emanations [that might undermine discipline].”
                    He clarifies that the paper “met with much opposition at first,” but eventually
                    became “a great favorite with all.” What McArthur does not disclose in his
                    preface is that beyond his refusal to include material that might anger superior
                    officers aboard the <hi rend="italics">Chesapeake</hi>, he also does not include
                    in his lithograph edition all the material that appeared in the manuscript that
                    circulated aboard the <hi rend="italics">Chesapeake</hi>. This insight into
                    McArthur’s editorial process is possible because we have two witnesses to <hi
                        rend="italics">The Young Idea</hi>. Though the manuscript pages that
                    circulated aboard the ship are not extant, we have McArthur’s 1867 lithograph
                    edition and extracts from <hi rend="italics">The Young Idea</hi> that the ship’s
                    chaplain, J. W. L. Bampfield, transcribed into his diary. Beyond offering a
                    second witness to the manuscript pages, Bampfield’s extracts also provide a
                    partial marked list of the paper’s contributors because he included the author’s
                    initials after almost every contribution he transcribed. <figure>
                        <graphic url="TYI0005.jpg"/>
                        <head>Figure 1: Title page for McArthur's 1867 edition</head>
                        <head>Author's personal collection</head>
                    </figure>
                    <figure>
                        <graphic url="BETYI1021.jpg"/>
                        <head>Figure 2: First page of Bampfield's extracts</head>
                        <head>Bamfield, J. W. L. MSS. Journal kept by the ship's chaplain, the Rev.
                            J. W. L. Bamfield. National Maritime Museum, NWT 3.</head>
                    </figure></p>
                <p>This edition includes notes pointing to significant variation between McArthur’s
                    lithograph edition (the base text for this edition) and Bampfield’s handwritten
                    extracts from the manuscript pages. I have concluded that while lithography
                    could have been used to create a facsimile edition (that is, an edition that
                    reproduces as closely as possible the pages exactly as they appeared in the
                    original manuscript newspaper), McArthur’s lithograph edition is not a
                    facsimile. Though he does not announce it as explicitly as Bampfield does with
                    his title, McArthur did pull extracts from the manuscript newspaper and then
                    re-created the appearance of a handwritten paper with those extracts.</p>
                <p>The editors of a similarly produced edition of <hi rend="italic">the Illustrated
                        Arctic News</hi> (London: Ackermann, 1852) are much more explicit than
                    McArthur about their practice; they apologize in their preface for omitting “a
                    few articles,” fearing the bad taste of the arctic public might lead a more
                    general readership to “object on the score of raciness” (Osborne n.p.). There
                    were likely many shipboard newspapers that we’ll never learn about because the
                    editors were not permitted to publish. As Vanessa Histon Roberts explains in
                        <ref target="#intro1" xml:id="nr1" n="1">“Publishing and Printing on board
                        Ships,”</ref> Clements Markham edited a journal during the Franklin
                    expedition entitled <hi rend="italics">Minavilins</hi>, which was
                    suppressed.</p>

                <p>What prompted McArthur to prepare an edition for the public? He explains in the
                    preface to his 1867 edition that he “yielded to the solicitation of friends” to
                    give <hi rend="italic">The Young Idea</hi> “afresh to the world.” McArthur’s
                    preface also indicates that the lithographed edition was funded through a
                    subscription supported by Harry Edmund Edgell, the commanding officer of the <hi
                        rend="italics">Chesapeake</hi> (and the entire squadron) for the majority of
                    the cruise chronicled in <hi rend="italics">The Young Idea</hi>. The <hi
                        rend="italics">Chesapeake</hi> was sold for parts in 1867, so it seems
                    likely that Admiral Edgell (named as a primary supporter of the lithograph
                    edition in McArthur’s preface) and other officers who served aboard the <hi
                        rend="italics">Chesapeake</hi> would be motivated to contribute to a
                    subscription that would fund a beautiful lithograph edition commemorating their
                    time aboard the vessel.</p>

                <p>Hyperlinked annotations throughout this edition support my contention that
                    McArthur had a heavily edited version of <hi rend="italics">The Young Idea</hi>
                    published in 1867, but the clearest evidence is the fact that McArthur includes
                    an article that he wrote about the arrival of letters from home as the first
                    contribution to the ninth issue of his lithograph edition, though it appears as
                    the first entry of the eighth issue in Bampfield’s extracts. McArthur is the
                    author of the article, so the best explanation for Bampfield including it in his
                    extracts before the date that it appears in McArthur's edition of <hi
                        rend="italic">The Young Idea</hi> is that McArthur selected, rearranged, and
                    edited individual contributions for the lithograph edition. Readers of this
                    digital edition can click on the title of each contribution (or, where there is
                    no title, on the first sentence) to learn how Bampfield’s extracts differ from
                    the base text. Readers will also find hyperlinked lines within particular
                    contributions where significant divergences from Bampfield’s extracts occur (the
                    most notable section of divergence in this edition occurs in the article
                    entitled “Up the Hooghly”).</p>

                <p>Of course, this edition for <hi rend="italics">Scholarly Editing</hi> necessarily
                    provides only a section of McArthur’s full fifty-eight-issue lithograph
                    edition. This edition extracts issues 7 (January 23, 1858) through 13 (March 6,
                    1858), which were written and circulated during the ship's time harbored off the
                    coast of Calcutta. I have also included McArthur’s preface to the lithograph
                    edition because it provides a detailed introduction to this unique example of a
                    handwritten newspaper. Issues 7&#8211;13 document day-to-day life aboard a naval
                    vessel (receiving letters from home, disturbances aboard the ship, cricket
                    matches between the crew of the <hi rend="italics">Chesapeake</hi> and other
                    British vessels, etc.), but they stand alone in the sense that they provide a
                    cohesive narrative of sailors' experiences in Calcutta in the wake of what was
                    then referred to as the <ref target="#intro2" xml:id="nr2" n="2">Indian
                        Mutiny</ref>.</p>
                <p>The seventh issue begins with the editor's reflections on the disappointing
                    announcement that the crew of the <hi rend="italics">Chesapeake</hi> would not
                    fight to put down the Mutiny (other sailors had seen direct combat and the
                    sailors aboard the <hi rend="italics">Chesapeake</hi> knew about these famous
                    naval brigades that fought on land). This issue also includes a detailed
                    contribution on first impressions of Calcutta. The eighth issue begins with an
                    editorial, "Try Again," reflecting on the failure of the first attempt to lay an
                    Atlantic telegraph cable and the crack discovered in Big Ben ("his metal was too
                    thin, his tongue was too thick"), reminding us that when in port these sailors
                    followed with great attention the events back home in England. The tenth issue
                    is probably the richest. Extracts from a narrative of the siege at Lucknow
                    appear alongside reports of a regatta in which the <hi rend="italics"
                        >Chesapeake</hi> competed and a fascinating review of the <hi rend="italics"
                        >Chesapeake</hi> sailor amateurs' debut performance at the Calcutta Lyric
                    Theatre, a theatrical performance mounted to benefit the widows and orphans of
                    those killed during the Mutiny. The sailors were criticized harshly by the drama
                    critic for an English-language newspaper printed in Calcutta (<hi rend="italics"
                        >The Hurkaru</hi>), and officers aboard the <hi rend="italics"
                        >Chesapeake</hi> responded to this affront with an article in <hi
                        rend="italics">The Young Idea</hi> and a letter to the editor of <hi
                        rend="italics">The Englishman</hi>, a rival newspaper to <hi rend="italics"
                        >The Hurkaru</hi>. The twelfth issue begins with an editorial speculating on
                    where the ship will travel next (reports at that time were that the <hi
                        rend="italics">Chesapeake</hi> would convey Lady Canning to Madras), and a
                    detailed account of the wedding of the granddaughter of Rajah Behadoor, with
                    careful attention given to narrating the unfamiliar marriage ceremony. The
                    thirteenth issue reflects back on the experiences in Calcutta, and one
                    contributor revisits the brutal review of the sailors' theatrical performance,
                    including the prologue delivered on that occasion. </p>
                <p>McArthur’s preface makes clear that he published in an effort to chronicle the
                    existence of a handwritten newspaper aboard a naval vessel. This digital edition
                    shares that goal, and in so doing contributes to scholarly conversations about
                    handwritten newspapers, <ref target="#intro3" xml:id="nr3" n="3">a growing field
                        of scholarly inquiry</ref>. While researchers have devoted some attention to
                        <ref target="#intro4" xml:id="nr4" n="4">shipboard publishing and
                        printing</ref>, the only <ref target="#intro5" xml:id="nr5" n="5"
                        >scholarship that mentions <hi rend="italics">The Young Idea</hi></ref>
                    concerns Paul Jerrard, the publisher of the 1867 edition. This critical edition
                    uses the 1867 lithograph edition as its base text. All material in this edition
                    has been double keyed, meaning two people have transcribed the source material
                    and the transcriptions have been collated to locate and correct errors in
                    transcription. Superscript letters have not been presented as superscript:
                    whether written as 19<hi rend="superscript">th</hi> or 19th, this edition
                    displays 19th. Column breaks and the running header (visible in page images)
                    have been transcribed and encoded, but do not appear in the edition. Double
                    hyphens appear frequently in the source texts to indicate that a word has been
                    continued onto a new line, but these double hyphens have not been transcribed.
                    Annotations have been provided to help readers learn about people, places, and
                    ships mentioned in the text. As described above, annotations have also been
                    included to present information gleaned from the analysis of variation between
                    McArthur's lithograph edition and Bampfield's extracts. Where possible, these
                    notes combine information from Bampfield's marked list of contributors with data
                    from the muster books for the <hi rend="italics">Chesapeake</hi> to provide
                    insight into the authorship of individual contributions. Readers can view these
                    notes by clicking on the title of each contribution (or, if there is no title,
                    the first line of the contribution).</p>
            </div>

            <div type="notes">

                <note xml:id="intro1">Roberts, Vanessa Histon. "“Publishing and Printing on board
                    ships.” <hi rend="italics">The Mariner’s Mirror.</hi> 74 (1988): 329-34.</note>
                <note xml:id="intro2">In <hi rend="italics">Rule of Darkness</hi> (Ithaca: Cornell
                    University Press, 1988), Patrick Brantlinger explains that “among both British
                    and Indian historians, debate still focuses on whether the uprising was only an
                    army “mutiny,” or a “civil rebellion” as well, or, as Indian nationalists have
                    held it to be, “the first Indian war of independence” (200-201). I follow
                    Brantlinger and refer to the conflict as “the Mutiny.”</note>
                <note xml:id="intro3">For more on the topic, see: Heiko Droste, “Degrees of
                    Publicity: Handwritten Newspapers in the Seventeenth and Eighteenth Centuries,”
                        <hi rend="italics">LIR.journal</hi> 1, no. 1 (2012): 67–83; Kirsti
                    Salmi-Niklander, "Monologic, Dialogic, Collective: Modes of Writing in
                    Hand-written Newspapers," in <hi rend="italics">White Field, Black Seeds: Nordic
                        Literacy Practices in the Long Nineteenth Century.</hi>, ed. Anna Kuismin
                    and M. J. Driscoll, 76-88 (Helsinki: Finnish Literature Society, 2013); and
                    Michael Ray Smith, Quentin Schultze, and Roy Alden Atwood, <hi rend="italics">A
                        Free Press in Freehand.</hi> (Grand Rapids: Edenridge Press, 2011).</note>
                <note xml:id="intro4">Vanessa Histon Roberts, “Publishing and Printing on board
                    Ships,” <hi rend="italics">Mariner’s Mirror</hi> 74 (1988): 329-34; G.F.
                    Barwick, “Books Printed at Sea,” <hi rend="italics">The Library</hi> 2 no. 2
                    (1899): 163-66; David H. Stam and Deirdre C. Stam, “Bending Time: The Function
                    of Periodicals in Nineteenth-Century Polar Naval Expeditions,” <hi
                        rend="italics">Victorian Periodicals Review</hi> 41 no. 4 (2008): 301-322;
                    Hester Blum and Jason R. Rudy, “First Person Nautical: Poetry and Play at Sea,”
                        <hi rend="italics">J19: The Journal of Nineteenth-Century Americanists</hi>
                    1, no. 1 (2013): 189–194.</note>
                <note xml:id="intro5">Howard Leathlean, “Paul Jerrard: Publisher of ‘Special
                    Presents,’” <hi rend="italics">The Book Collector</hi>. 40 no. 2 (1991):
                    169-96.</note>
            </div>
        </body>
    </text>
</TEI>
