<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink"
  xmlns:xs="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema"
  xmlns:math="http://www.w3.org/1998/Math/MathML"
  xmlns:svg="http://www.w3.org/2000/svg"
  xmlns:xi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XInclude"
  xml:id="xxx.person">
<teiHeader>
<fileDesc>
<titleStmt>
<title type="main">Biographical Information</title>
<author></author>
</titleStmt>
<publicationStmt>
<p/>
</publicationStmt>
<sourceDesc>
<p></p>
</sourceDesc>
</fileDesc>
<encodingDesc>
<editorialDecl>
<correction>
<p></p>
</correction>
<normalization>
<p></p>
</normalization>
</editorialDecl>
</encodingDesc>
<profileDesc>
</profileDesc>
<revisionDesc>
  <change when="3016-10-16"><name xml:id="lkw"></name> Initial encoding</change>
</revisionDesc>
</teiHeader>
<text>
<body>
<div1 type="list">
<listPerson type="other">
  <person xml:id="HI">
<persName type="display">Sir Henry Irving</persName>
<persName type="full"><surname>Broadribb</surname>, <forename type="first">John</forename> <forename type="middle">Henry</forename></persName>
<birth when="1838">1838</birth>
<death when="1905">1905</death>
<sex></sex>
    <note><p>English stage actor Henry Irving was born John Henry Broadribb, the son of a traveling salesman in Somerset. His first professional appearance was as the Duke of Orleans in Bulwer-Lytton's <hi rend="italic">Richilieu</hi> in September 1856 at the New Royal Lyceum Theatre, Sunderland. In 1871 he joined the Lyceum Theatre in London under the management of Hezekiah Bateman, where he won acclaim for his performance in <hi rend="italic">The Bells</hi>, an adaptation of Erckmann-Chatrian's <hi rend="italic">Le Juif Polonais</hi>. He took over the management of the Lyceum Theatre from Batemen in 1878, the beginning of his long stage and personal partnership with Ellen Terry. In 1895 he became the first actor to receive a knighthood. During a provincial farewell tour in Bradford he was taken ill and died of a stroke hours later.</p></note>
</person>
  <person xml:id="FJ">
<persName type="display">Frank Jenkins</persName>
<persName type="full"><surname>Jenkins</surname>, <forename type="first">Frank</forename></persName>
<birth when="1851">1851</birth>
<death when="1913">1913</death>
<sex>male</sex>
    <note><p>Jenkins was born in Boontown, N.J. and graduated from Yale in 1874. He moved to New York, where he boarded with fellow April Fool letter writer Horatio C. King, and through that connection soon became Henry Ward Beecher's secretary. He was connected with the <hi rend="italic">Christian Union</hi> in various capacities, including as publisher from 1878&#x2013;1879, and then joined a banking firm in 1879, advancing to senior partner. However, the firm went into receivership in 1890. After two more failed ventures in managing mines in Minnesota and Cuba, he formed the Jenkins Coal Company. Through his association with Beecher and his memberships in the Lambs and Players Clubs he formed acquaintances with Warner, Hutton, Stedman, and Clemens, as he claims in his letter to the Yale alumni club. Clemens's annotation identifies him as a &#x201C;stranger&#x201D; in 1884. Jenkins never married. He died of Bright's disease at his home in the Hotel Ansonia in 1913.</p></note>
</person>
  <person xml:id="GWS">
<persName type="display">George W. Sheldon</persName>
<persName type="full"><surname>Sheldon</surname>, <forename type="first">George</forename> <forename type="middle">William</forename></persName>
<birth when="1843">1843</birth>
<death when="1914">1914</death>
<sex>male</sex>
<note><p>George William Sheldon, art critic and author, graduated from Princeton University in 1863, and spent a year working as a medic in the Union army. He worked as an instructor of languages and literature for a decade at Princeton and then at Union Theological Seminary. From 1876 to 1882 he was an art critic for the New York <hi rend="italic">Evening Post</hi>, and from 1884 to 1886 the dramatic critic of the New York <hi rend="italic">Commercial Advertiser</hi>. He held a concurrent post on the staff of Appleton &amp; Co., for whom he wrote elaborately illustrated art books such as <hi rend="italic">American Painters</hi> (1879), <hi rend="italic">Hours with Art and Artists</hi> (1882), and <hi rend="italic">Artistic Homes</hi> (1882). A year after the April Fool episode, an unsolicited $300 subscription to the latter was a great cause of consternation to Clemens (see SLC's letters to OLC and CLW, 5 Feb 1885).</p></note>
</person>
  <person xml:id="JHS">
<persName type="display">Rev. J. Hyatt Smith</persName>
<persName type="full"><surname>Smith</surname>, <forename type="first">John</forename> <forename type="middle">Hyatt</forename></persName>
<birth when="1824">1824</birth>
<death when="1886">1886</death>
<sex>male</sex>
<note><p>Born in Saratoga, New York, John Hyatt Smith was educated by his schoolmaster father, then sent to Detroit to work as a clerk. There he was a close friend of Anson Burlingame, who later befriended Clemens in Hawaii. Smith studied for the ministry when he wasn't clerking. After ordination in 1848 he served as a Baptist minister in Poughkeepsie, Cleveland, Buffalo, and Philadelphia before he accepted a position at the Lee Avenue Church in Brooklyn. Smith ran as an independent Republican for a seat in the U. S. House of Representatives, and served from 1881&#x2013;1883. In December 1883 he was called by a Congregational Council presided over by Edward Beecher (brother of Henry Ward Beecher) to fill a temporary pastorship at the East Congregational Church in Brooklyn, where he remained until his death in 1887.</p></note>
</person>
  <person xml:id="CGW">
<persName type="display">Charles G. Whiting</persName>
<persName type="full"><surname>Whiting</surname>, <forename type="first">Charles</forename> <forename type="middle">Goodrich</forename></persName>
<birth when="1842">1842</birth>
<death when="1922">1922</death>
<sex>male</sex>
<note><p>Charles Goodrich Whiting had a long association beginning in 1868 with the Springfield <hi rend="italic">Republican</hi> as a writer of bucolic essays and poems in his Sunday column &#x201C;The Saunterer,&#x201D; and, after 1874, as literary editor. He was elected to the Authors Club of New York in 1888. Cable's first reading of his 1883 tour took place at Springfield, and a very favorable review, possibly written by Whiting, appeared in the <hi rend="italic">Republican</hi> on 22 November.</p></note>
</person>
  <person xml:id="RWR">
<persName type="display">R. W. Raymond</persName>
<persName type="full"><surname>Raymond</surname>, <forename type="first">Rossiter</forename> <forename type="middle">Worthington</forename></persName>
<birth when="1840">1840</birth>
<death when="1918">1918</death>
<sex>male</sex>
<note><p>Rossiter Worthington Raymond was born and raised in Syracuse, New York. After graduating from Brooklyn Polytechnic he enrolled in the Royal Mining Academy at Freiburg, followed by studies at Heidelberg and Munich. He edited <hi rend="italic">The American Journal of Mining</hi> from 1867 to 1890. In 1868 he was appointed United States Commissioner of Mining Statistics, and spent nearly a decade surveying mines in the West. In the early 1870s he also taught Mining Engineering at Lafayette College in Easton, Pennsylvania. He served as secretary of the American Institute of Mining, Metallurgy, and Petroleum Engineers (1884&#x2013;1911). In 1884 he lived in Brooklyn, where he was a member of Beecher's Plymouth Church, and served as the director of the Boy's Sunday School for nearly 50 years.</p></note>
</person>
  <person xml:id="GEW">
<persName type="display">George E. Waring, Jr.</persName>
<persName type="full"><surname>Waring</surname>, <forename type="first">George</forename> <forename type="middle">Edwin</forename></persName>
<birth when="1833">1833</birth>
<death when="1898">1898</death>
<sex>male</sex>
<note><p>George E. Waring, Jr. was an author, agriculturalist, and sanitary engineer, and a close friend of Cable, Clemens and James R. Osgood. In 1855 he managed Horace Greeley's farm at Chappaqua, New York. After the Civil War, where he commanded the 4th Missouri Cavalry, he retired his commission to manage Ogden Farm, a model farm in Newport, R.I. Waring wrote both husbandry manuals and bucolic serialized novels, several of which were published by Osgood. In the late 1870s, Waring designed toilets, and from there moved on to design entire sewer systems to alleviate the cholera epidemic at Memphis. In 1895 he established the first organized street cleaning department in New York City. In 1898 william McKinley sent Waring to Cuba to survey sanitary issues, but he contracted yellow fever, and died at home in October 1898.</p></note>
</person>
  <person xml:id="CLK">
<persName type="display">Clara Louise Kellogg</persName>
<persName type="full"><surname>Kellogg</surname>, <forename type="first">Clara</forename> <forename type="middle">Louise</forename></persName>
<birth when="1842">1842</birth>
<death when="1916">1916</death>
<sex>female</sex>
<note><p>Soprano and musical actress Clara Louise Kellogg was considered the first American prima donna. She made her professional debut as Gilda in <hi rend="italic">Rigoletto</hi> in February 1861 at the new York Academy of Music. Over the next two decades she sang over forty roles in several languages. By the mid-1880s she was reduced to sporadic concert engagements, and retired shortly after marrying her manager, Carl Strakosch, in 1887. She died in New Hartford, Connecticut. She was a close friend of the Gilder family and a frequent participant in the Gilder Friday &#x201C;At Home&#x201D; gatherings. </p></note>
</person>
  <person xml:id="JEK">
<persName type="display">Jane Elizabeth (Crosby) Kellogg</persName>
<persName type="full"><surname>Kellogg</surname>, <forename type="first">Jane</forename> <forename type="middle">Elizabeth</forename> <surname type="maiden">Crosby</surname></persName>
<birth when="1816">1816</birth>
<death when="1892">1892</death>
<sex>femaile</sex>
    <note><p>Born at Simsbury, Connecticut, Jane Elizabeth Crosby was the mother of Clara Louise Kellogg. She became her daughter's constant companion and manager on tour: &#x201C;the sentinel that stood between her daughter and the outside world.&#x201D; Harriet Prescott Spofford, in her &#x201C;Biography of Clara Louise Kellogg&#x201D;, describes Clara's mother as &#x201C;a case of suppressed genius,&#x201D; &#x201C;who &#x201C;might have made a great mark on the artistic world if she had not so forgotten and absorbed herself in her daughter.&#x201D; (<bibl rend="inline">Spofford, <hi rend="italic">Our Famous Women: An Authorized Record of The Lives and Deeds of Distinguished American Women of Our Times</hi>. Hartford, Conn.: A. D. Worthington, 1884. 359&#x2013;385</bibl>))</p></note>
</person>
  <person xml:id="FHS">
<persName type="display">Francis Hopkinson Smith</persName>
<persName type="full"><surname>Smith</surname>, <forename type="first">Francis</forename> <forename type="middle">Hoplinson</forename></persName>
<birth when="1838">1838</birth>
<death when="1915">1915</death>
<sex>male</sex>
<note><p>Civil engineer, artist, and writer Francis Hopkinson Smith was a friend and clubmate of Clemens. At the time of his death he was best known as an author and illustrator of his own works. He was also a successful landscape painter. Among his engineering projects were the construction of Race Rock Lighthouse and the base of the Statue of Liberty. He was a founding member of the Kinsman Club and the Tile Club.</p></note>
</person>
  <person xml:id="DS">
<persName type="display">Dean Sage</persName>
<persName type="full"><surname>Sage</surname>, <forename type="first">Dean</forename> <forename type="middle"></forename></persName>
<birth when="1841">1841</birth>
<death when="1902">1902</death>
<sex></sex>
<note><p>Dean Sage, son of businessman Henry W. Sage, graduated from Albany Law School in 1861, but chose to work in his father's lumber business in Albany. His father was a close friend of the Beecher family, and a longtime member and Trustee of the Plymouth Church. Sage had moved back to Brooklyn from Albany by the time he wrote this April Fool letter to Clemens. He was an avid sportsman who enjoyed writing and collecting books on angling. He died at a fishing camp in Canada in 1902.</p></note>
</person>
  <person xml:id="CDW">
<persName type="display">Charles Dudley Warner</persName>
<persName type="full"><surname>Warner</surname>, <forename type="first">Charles</forename> <forename type="middle">Dudley</forename></persName>
<birth when="1829">1829</birth>
<death when="1900">1900</death>
<sex></sex>
<note><p>Essayist and novelist George Dudley Warner was a neighbor of Clemens at Nook Farm in Hartford, and co-author of <hi rend="italic">The Gilded Age</hi> (1873). In the 1860s he was an editor of the Hartford <hi rend="italic">Press</hi>, and then of the Hartford <hi rend="italic">Courant</hi>, when the two papers merged. He joined the staff of <hi rend="italic">Harper's Magazine</hi> in 1884 and was responsible for The Editor's Drawer feature until 1892, when he took on The Editor's Study.</p></note>
</person>
  <person xml:id="WS">
<persName type="display">Wesley E. Sisson</persName>
<persName type="full"><surname>Sisson</surname>, <forename type="first">Wesley</forename> <forename type="middle"></forename></persName>
<birth when="1855">1855</birth>
<death></death>
<sex></sex>
<note><p>Wesley Sisson practiced law with his brother in Chicago from 1876 until 1881, when he moved to New York to pursue a career in theatrical management. He was the assistant manager of the Madison Square Theatre in the 1880s, with concurrent management interests in the Lyceum and Criterion Theaters. He also managed tours for several companies, including those of Clara Morris, and Thomas and Alessandro Salvini. In 1891 he moved with his family back to Chicago to return to the practice of law, while exploring prospects for building a new theatre on the south side. By 1890 they had moved back east again, to Mt. Vernon, New York, where Sisson is listed in the 1910 census as Secretary of the Postal Life Insurance company, a position which he held until he retired. </p></note>
</person>
 
  <person xml:id="RUJ">
<persName type="display">Robert Underwood Johnson</persName>
<persName type="full"><surname>Johnson</surname>, <forename type="first">Robert</forename> <forename type="middle">Underwood</forename></persName>
<birth when="1853">1853</birth>
<death when="1937">1937</death>
<sex>male</sex>
<note><p>Poet, journalist, and conservationist Robert Underwood Johnson began working for <hi rend="italic">Scribner's Magazine</hi> in 1873, and was named Associate Editor of the <hi rend="italic">Century Magazine</hi> in 1881. He succeeded Richard Watson Gilder as editor, and retired in 1913. Johnson campaigned for International Copyright in the 1880s, and, as the secretary of the American Copyright League, played an important role in passing the copyright law of 1891. He was one of the supporters of the foundation of both Yosemite National Park and, along with  John Muir, of the Sierra Club.</p></note>
</person>
  <person xml:id="JCK">
<persName type="display">John Coddington Kinney</persName>
<persName type="full"><surname>Kinney</surname>, <forename type="first">John</forename> <forename type="middle">Coddington</forename></persName>
<birth when="1839">1839</birth>
<death when="1891">1891</death>
<sex></sex>
    <note><p>John Coddington Kinney was an associate editor of the Hartford <hi rend="italic">Courant</hi> (1872&#x2013;1890), and was appointed U.S. Marshall for the district of Connecticut (1882&#x2013;86). In 1890, the year before he died, he was made postmaster of Hartford. During the Civil War he had been a member of the signal corps on Farragut's ship the <hi rend="italic">Hartford</hi>, and wrote about his experiences in &#x201C;An August Morning with Farragut;" a narrative of the Mobile Bay fight, August 5, 1864,&#x201D; <hi rend="italic">Scribner's Magazine</hi> 22 (June 1881): 199&#x2013;208.</p></note>
  </person>
  <person xml:id="TWK">
<persName type="display">Thomas W. Knox</persName>
<persName type="full"><surname>Knox</surname>, <forename type="first">Thomas</forename> <forename type="middle">Wallace</forename></persName>
<birth when="1835">1835</birth>
<death when="1896">1896</death>
<sex></sex>
<note><p>Thomas Wallace Knox was a Civil War correspondent for the New York <hi rend="italic">Herald</hi> and travel writer, best known for his series of 40 travel adventure books for boys. His war letters were collected in 1866 as <hi rend="italic">Campfire and Cottonfields</hi>. After the war he traveled as a <hi rend="italic">Herald</hi> correspondent with the Russo-American Telegraph Company to build the first telegraph line across Siberia. In 1870 the American Publishing Company published these letters as <hi rend="italic">Overland Through Asia</hi>. In 1877 he traveled around the world, gathering material for his series of travel books. The series list serves as an itinerary for his travels. In 1881 the King of Siam conferred upon him a knighthood in the Order of the White Elephant in return for his service to the country. He was the first American to receive that honor. Knox, who never married, made his home at the Lotos Club and was club secretary from 1880&#x2013;89. He was also a member of the Authors Club.</p></note>
</person>
  <person xml:id="JPL">
<persName type="display">George Parsons Lathrop</persName>
<persName type="full"><surname>Lathrop</surname>, <forename type="first">George</forename> <forename type="middle">Parsons</forename></persName>
<birth when="1851">1851</birth>
<death when="1898">1898</death>
<sex></sex>
    <note><p>George Parsons Lathrop was an editor, poet, critic, and copyright reformer. He served as associate editor of the <hi rend="italic">Atlantic Monthly</hi> (1875&#x2013;77), editor-in-chief of the Boston <hi rend="italic">Courier</hi> (1877&#x2013;79), and literary editor of the New York <hi rend="italic">Star</hi> in the late 1880s. He became secretary of the American Copyright League in 1883. Lathrop married Rose Hawthorne, the daughter of Nathaniel Hawthorne, in 1871. From 1879 to 1883 the couple lived in Concord, Mass. in the Hawthorne homestead, &#x201C;The Wayside.&#x201D; Lathrop wrote <hi rend="italic">A Study of Hawthorne</hi> (1876), and was an editor of the Riverside Edition of <hi rend="italic">The Works of Nathaniel Hawthorne</hi> (1882&#x2013;84). Lathrop was a founding member of the Author's Club and a member of the Player's Club, and of the Papyrus Club in Boston.</p></note>
</person>
  <person xml:id="JBM">
<persName type="display">Brander Matthews</persName>
<persName type="full"><surname>Matthews</surname>, <forename type="first">James</forename> <forename type="middle">Brander</forename></persName>
<birth when="1852">1852</birth>
<death when="1829">1829</death>
<sex></sex>
<note><p>Brander Matthews was a writer on dramatic subjects, novelist, critic, and professor of Dramatic Literature at Columbia University from 1892 to 1924. After earning a law degree from Columbia in 1873 Matthews chose to pursue a literary career. By 1884 he had published <hi rend="italic">The Theatres of Paris</hi> (1880), and <hi rend="italic">French Dramatists of the Nineteenth Century</hi> (1881) as well as two novels. The april fool letter is the first extant piece of correspondence between Clemens and Matthews, whose friendship grew in subsequent decades. They were both members of the Kinsmen Club, the Authors Club, and the American Copyright League.</p></note>
</person>
  <person xml:id="FDM">
<persName type="display">Francis Davis Millet</persName>
<persName type="full"><surname></surname>, <forename type="first"></forename> <forename type="middle"></forename></persName>
<birth when="1848">1846</birth>
<death when="1912">1912</death>
<sex></sex>
    <note><p>Francis Davis Millet was a journalist and artist. After serving as a drummer boy and surgical aide to his father in the Civil War he worked as a reporter for the Boston <hi rend="italic">Courier</hi>, and correspondent for the Boston <hi rend="italic">Advertiser</hi> (1869&#x2013;70). In the 18701 he studied painting at the Royal Academy of Fine Art in Antwerp, and then in Italy, moving between art studios in Rome and Venice. Upon his return to the U.S. in 1876 he worked as chief assistant to John La Farge in the creation of murals for Trinity Church, Boston, with John LaFarge. He completed a portrait of Clemens in January 1877. From 1877&#x2013;88 he was a correspondent for the New York <hi rend="italic">Herald</hi> covering the Russo-Turkish War. He died on the Titanic in 1912. </p></note>
</person>
  <person xml:id="HM">
<persName type="display">Helena Modjeska</persName>
<persName type="full"><surname>Modrzejewska</surname>, <forename type="first">Helena</forename> <forename type="maiden">Opid</forename></persName>
<birth when="1840">1840</birth>
<death when="1909">1909</death>
<sex></sex>
    <note><p>Helena Modjeska, whose name on her birth certificate was Jadwiga Benda, was baptised Helena Opid in Kracow. She took as her stage name a simplied version of the stage name of her first husband, Gustaw Zimajer, who went by &#x201C;Gustaw Modrzejewski.&#x201D; Under his management she solidified her repuation as the leading tragic actress on the Polish stage. In 1875 she emigrated to California with her second husband Karol Bozenta Chlapowski. She eventually made her way to the New York Stage, with the support of the Gilder circle. After three years in London she returned to New York with further accolades. She retired from the stage in 1907 (Modjeska, <hi rend="italic">Memories and Impressions of Helena Modjeska.</hi> (New York: MacMillan, 1910); <hi rend="italic">New York Times</hi>, 9 April 1909).</p></note>
</person>
  <person xml:id="TFP">
<persName type="display">Thomas F. Plunkett</persName>
<persName type="full"><surname>Plunkett</surname>, <forename type="first">Thomas</forename> <forename type="middle">Fitzpatrick</forename></persName>
<birth when="1844">1844</birth>
<death when="1905">1905</death>
<sex></sex>
<note><p>Treasurer of the Union Manufacturing Company and president of the Hartford Silk Company, Thomas Fitzpatrick Plunkett fled to Mexico in 1889 to escape embezzlement charges. He was rumored to have been murdered there shortly after his escape, but apparently lived in Mexico until shortly before he died in Tucson, Arizona, in 1905. The Beach family of Hartford were financial supporters of both companies, and Charles M. Beach was appointed receiver for the Union Mfg Co. Plunkett was a member of the Hartford Club. His father, Massachusetts politician Thomas F. Plunkett (senior), had been a member of the Monday Evening Club.</p></note>
</person>
  <person xml:id="JBP">
<persName type="display">James B. Pond</persName>
<persName type="full"><surname>Pond</surname>, <forename type="first"></forename>James<forename type="middle">Burton</forename></persName>
<birth when="1838">1838</birth>
<death when="1903">1903</death>
<sex></sex>
    <note><p>James Burton Pond was a decorated Civil War officer and lecture manager who fought with John Brown in 1846 in Kansas, and against Quanatrill's gang in Missouri. In 1874 he formed the Pond Lyceum Bureau, having spent some years managing acts on his own in Salt Lake City, followed by a stint with the Redpath Lyceum Bureau. By 1884 he had managed Henry Ward Beecher, Wendell Phillips, Matthew Arnold, and George Washington Cable. Pond wrote several books and articles about his experiences on the lecture circuit, including <hi rend="italic">A Summer in England with Henry Ward Beecher.</hi> (1877), and <hi rend="italic">Eccentricities of Genius.</hi> (1900). </p></note>
</person>
  <person xml:id="NS">
<persName type="display">Napoleon Sarony</persName>
<persName type="full"><surname>Sarony</surname>, <forename type="first">Napoleon</forename> <forename type="middle"></forename></persName>
<birth when="1821">1821</birth>
<death when="1896">1896</death>
<sex></sex>
<note><p>Napoleon Sarony, celebrity photographer, lithographer and sketch artist, was born in Canada and trained as a lithographer in his father's business. In 1833 he moved to New York City, where he worked for Robertson &amp; Co. lithographers. After the death of his wife he traveled to Europe to study fine arts, but financial straits led him to photography, which he learned in his brother's Birmingham studio. He returned to New York in 1865 set up studio at 630 Broadway. In 1871 moved to 37 Union Square. In the fall of 1884 Clemens and George Washington Cable visited Sarony for tour photographs. Sarony belonged to the Lotos Club and was a founding member of the Salmagundi Club.</p></note>
</person>
  <person xml:id="HES">
<persName type="display">Horace E. Scudder</persName>
<persName type="full"><surname>Scudder</surname>, <forename type="first">Horace</forename> <forename type="middle">Elisha</forename></persName>
<birth when="1838">1838</birth>
<death when="1902">1902</death>
<sex></sex>
<note><p>Horace Elisha Scudder was a Boston journalist, children's writer, biographer, and editor of the <hi rend="italic">Riverside Magazine</hi>, and later, of the  <hi rend="italic">Atlantic Monthly,</hi> following Thomas Bailey Aldrich. He had a long association with various publishing partnerships of H. O. Houghton as a minority partner, along with George H. Mifflin, in the 1870s.  He is best known for the <hi rend="italic">Bodley Books</hi> (1875&#x2013;87). <hi rend="italic">The Children's Book</hi> (1881), <hi rend="italic">History of the United States ... for the Use of Schools and Academies</hi> (1884), and  <hi rend="italic">Letters of Bayard Taylor</hi> (1884).</p></note>
</person>
  <person xml:id="ECS">
<persName type="display">Edmund Clarence Stedman</persName>
<persName type="full">Stedman<surname></surname>, <forename type="first">Edmund</forename> <forename type="middle">Clarence</forename></persName>
<birth when="1833">1833</birth>
<death when="1908">1908</death>
<sex></sex>
     <note><p>Poet and critic Edmund Clarence Stedman was born in Hartford and attended Yale. In his youth he worked as a correspondent for the <hi rend="italic">Sun</hi> and the <hi rend="italic">Tribune</hi>. He was a member of the Pfaff's Cellar Bohemians before the Civil War, as were many others in this group.  After the war he became a banker on Wall Street from 1865&#x2013;1890, but continued to write and publish poetry and literary criticism. In 1887 Stedman succeeded in foisting his <hi rend="italic">Library of American Literature</hi> compilation upon Clemens's nephew and business partner, Charles L. Webster, a decision that led to the &#x201C;lingering suicide&#x201D; of the publishing firm (AD of 2 June 1906, <ref type="crossref" target="http://www.marktwainproject.org/xtf/view?docId=works/MTDP10363.xml;query=stedman;chunk.id=dv0017;toc.depth=1;toc.id=;citations=;style=work;brand=mtp#1"><hi rend="italic">AutoMT1</hi></ref>).</p></note>
</person>
  <person xml:id="ET">
<persName type="display">Dame Ellen Terry</persName>
<persName type="full"><surname>Terry</surname>, <forename type="first">Alice</forename> <forename type="middle">Ellen</forename></persName>
<birth when="1847">1847</birth>
<death when="1928">1928</death>
<sex></sex>
    <note><p>Ellen Terry was the leading British stage actress in Shakespearean roles of her day. Her first performance in 1856 was as Mamilius in The Winter's Tale at the Princess Theatre, London, where she remained until the retirement of Charles Kean in 1859. In 1878 Terry joined Irving's company at the Lyceum. She had a long professional and personal relationship with Henry Irving. </p></note>
</person>

  <person xml:id="JHT">
    <persName type="display">Joseph H. Twichell</persName>
    <persName type="full"><surname>Twichell</surname>, <forename type="first">Joseph</forename> <forename type="middle">Hopkins</forename></persName>
    <birth when="1838">1838</birth>
    <death when="1918">1918</death>
    <sex></sex>
    <note><p>Pastor of the Asylum Hill Congregational Church in Hartford, Joseph Hopkins Twichell was one of Clemens's closest friends and advisors for some 40 years. Twichell was often Clemens's traveling companion; he joined SLC in Bermuda in 1877 and again in 1907, and also met him in Germany in 1878, while Clemens was working in fits and starts on <hi rend="italic">A Tramp Abroad</hi>, to serve as a remedy for writer's block.</p></note>
  </person>

 
 <!--<person xml:id="bioHO017">
<persName type="display">Oliver Wendell Holmes</persName>
<persName type="full"><surname></surname>, <forename type="first"></forename> <forename type="middle"></forename></persName>
<birth when="1809">1809</birth>
<death when="1894">1894>1894</death>
<sex></sex>
    <note><p>Poet, essayist, physician, and medical writer Oliver Wendell Holmes was born in Boston and received his M.D. from Harvard. He served as Parkman Professor of Anatomy and Physiology at Harvard Medical School until 1882. Holmes is perhaps best known for his Breakfast Table series of essays: <hi rend="italic">The Autocrat at the Breakfast-Table</hi> (1858) <hi rend="italic">The Professor at the Breakfast-Table</hi> (1860), and <hi rend="italic">The Poet at the Breakfast-Table</hi> (1882). Holmes was a member of the Boston literary cabal of poets consisting of Bryant, Longfellow, Lowell and Whittier. In his speech &#x201C;Unconscious Plagiarism", delivered at <hi rend="italic">Atlantic Monthly</hi> birthday dinner to Holmes on 29 August 1879, Clemens characterized Holmes as &#x201C;the first great man who ever wrote me a letter... He was also the first great literary man I ever stole anything from.&#x201D; The theft referred to was what was considered a plagiarism of Holmes' dedication to his mother in <hi rend="italic">Songs of Many Keys</hi> (1862).</p></note>
</person>-->



  <person xml:id="STK">
<persName type="display">Sara T. Kinney</persName>
<persName type="full"><surname>Kinney</surname>, <forename type="first">Sara</forename> <forename type="middle"></forename> <surname type="maiden">Thomson</surname></persName>
<birth when="1842">1842</birth>
<death when="1922">1922</death>
<sex></sex>
    <note><p>Sara Thomson Kinney, the wife of John Coddington Kinney, was active in the Daughters of the American Revolution and the Women's National Indian Association. In 1884, after attending the second annual Lake Mohonk Conference for Friends of the Indian, she joined the WNIA Home-Building and Loan Committee, whose purpose was to encourage Native American wowen to assimilate into white society.</p></note>
</person>
  <person xml:id="CML">
<persName type="display">charles McKnight Leoser</persName>
<persName type="full"><surname>Leoser</surname>, <forename type="first">Charles</forename> <forename type="middle">McKnight</forename></persName>
<birth when="1839">1839</birth>
<death when="1896">1896</death>
<sex></sex>
    <note><p>Charles McKnight Leoser was born in Reading, Penn. and attended West Point. He commanded the Fire Zouaves during the Civil War and mustered out at the rank of Colonel. He was the publisher of <hi rend="italic">Bonfort's Wine and Spirits Circular</hi>, and president of the Wine and Spirits Traders' Society of New York. He served as president of the Lotos Club from 1872&#x2013;74, and two of his poems appear in <hi rend="italic">Lotos Leaves</hi> (1875) (New York <hi rend="italic">Times</hi>, 26 Feb 1896: 5).</p></note>
</person>
  <person xml:id="EKL">
<persName type="display">Edward K. Lockwood</persName>
<persName type="full"><surname></surname>, <forename type="first"></forename> <forename type="middle">Keeler</forename></persName>
<birth when="1828">1828</birth>
<death when="1887">1887</death>
<sex></sex>
    <note><p>E. K. Lockwood and his wife Harriet were passengers along with Clemens on the <hi rend="italic">Quaker City</hi> excursion. Lockwood started out as a clerk in his father's businesses, and inherited his father's interests in the Winnipauk Woollen Mill in 1869. By 1884 he was primarily, as his letterhead states, a purveyor of house furnishing goods. Like his father, he held the positions of Director of the Norwalk Gas Light Co. and the National Bank of Norwalk.</p></note>
</person>
  <person xml:id="DGM">
    <persName type="display">D. G. MacNeill</persName>
    <persName type="full"><surname>MacNeill</surname>, <forename type="first"></forename> <forename type="middle"></forename></persName>
    <birth></birth>
    <death></death>
    <sex></sex>
    <note><p>All that is known of MacNeill is that he was an employee of The Callender Insulating and Waterproofing Co., a purveyor of insulated cables incorporated in 1883 and owned by W. O. Callender of London, whose son William M. Callender served as President. Macneill may have been brought over from the London office.</p></note>
  </person>
  <person xml:id="EMM">
    <persName type="display">Elizabeth (Lily) Millet</persName>
    <persName type="full"><surname></surname>, <forename type="first"></forename> <forename type="middle"></forename></persName>
    <birth when="1855">1855</birth>
    <death when="1932">1932</death>
    <sex></sex>
    <note><p>Elizabeth Greely Merrill, the daughter of Rev. Horatio Merrill of Springfield, Mass, married artist Frank D. Millet in Paris in 1879, with SLC as best man and sculptor Augustus Saint Gaudens as witness. In 1885 the Millets moved to Broadway, a small village in Worcestershire, which had become an artists' colony attracting the likes of William Morris, John Singer Sargent, and Edward Burne-Jones. </p></note>
  </person>
  <person xml:id="HLP">
    <persName type="display">Henry L. Pierce</persName>
    <persName type="full"><surname></surname>, <forename type="first"></forename> <forename type="middle">Lillie</forename></persName>
    <birth when="1825">1825</birth>
    <death when="1896">1896</death>
    <sex></sex>
    <note><p>Henry Lillie Pierce was a politician and millionaire chocolate magnate, and an intimate friend of Thomas Bailey Aldrich. In 1849 he secured a position as a clerk in the Baker chocolate factory in Dorchester, owned by his uncle. By 1854, on the death of the heir, Walter Baker, the trustees gave Pierce a ten-year lease on the factory. He had organized the company so successfully that not only was he able to serve as member of the U.S. House of Representatives 1873&#x2013;1877 and as Mayor of Boston in 1872 and 1878, but by the end of his second ten-year lease the property was conveyed to him by the trustees. Pierce and Thomas Bailey Aldrich were the closest of friends from around 1873 until Pierce's death. He left the family a life interest in Redman Farm, his house and land at Ponkapog, and a total bequest of $400,000. (James Bugbee &#x201C;Memoir of Henry Lillie Pierce,&#x201D; <hi rend="italic">Proceedings of the Massachusetts Historical Society</hi>, Second Series, Vol. 11, (Boston: Massachuessetts Historical Society, 1896&#x2013;1897), 386&#x2013;410. &#x201C;A Model Citizen,&#x201D; <hi rend="italic">The Critic</hi> 30 (Jan 9, 1897): 22).</p></note>
  </person>
  <person xml:id="OWP">
    <persName type="display">Ozias W. Pond</persName>
    <persName type="full"><surname></surname>, <forename type="first"></forename> <forename type="middle"></forename></persName>
    <birth when="1852">1852**</birth>
    <death when="1892">1892</death>
    <sex></sex>
    <note><p>Ozias Walter Pond was a younger brother of James B. Pond, and a manager of musical acts and lecturers for the Redpath Lyceum Bureau. In 1883 he accompanied <name>Henry Ward Beecher</name> on a farewell lecture tour that extended into the spring of 1884. On 1 April he was with Beecher on the road between platform stops in Harrisburg and Cincinnati. Although in his letter to Clemens he claimed a meager acquaintance, he would soon come to know both Clemens and Cable very well&#x2014;in January 1885 he accompanied the pair on their lecture tour in his brother's place. At the end of the month, however, he was forced to leave the tour due to illness.</p> </note>
  </person>
  <person xml:id="NBP">
    <persName type="display">Nella Brown Pond</persName>
    <persName type="full"><surname>Pond</surname>, <forename type="first">Nella</forename> <forename type="middle"></forename> <surname type="maiden">Brown</surname></persName>
    <birth when="1858">1858</birth>
    <death when="1893">1893</death>
    <sex></sex>
    <note><p>Nella Brown Pond was a dramatic reader, and wife of <name>Ozias W. Pond</name>. Despite early success with the Park Dramatic Company in Boston, she chose not to pursue a life on the stage, but channelled her dramatic talents into the platform by joining <name>James Redpath</name>'s Lyceum company.</p></note>
  </person>
  <person xml:id="HR">
    <persName type="display">H. Robinson</persName>
    <persName type="full"><surname></surname>, <forename type="first"></forename> <forename type="middle"></forename></persName>
    <birth></birth>
    <death></death>
    <sex></sex>
    <note><p>The identity of this letter writer remains a mystery. He or she used the return address of the Gilders' home, and may have been a house guest at the time that the Cable circular arrived. Barring a complete and unlikely transformation of hand and signature it cannot be Clemens's Hartford friend Henry C. Robinson. In addressing the envelope to C. L. Clemens he or she reveals either ignorance of Clemens's first name, or a ruse to further obfuscate his or her own identity by pretending not to know Clemens's first name, or sloppiness.</p></note>
  </person>
  <person xml:id="EDS">
    <persName type="display">Ellen Montague Douglas Stedman</persName>
    <persName type="full">Stedman<surname></surname>, <forename type="first">Ellen</forename> <forename type="middle">Montague</forename><surname type="maiden">Douglas</surname></persName>
    <birth when="1856">1855</birth>
    <death when="1931">1931</death>
    <sex></sex>
    <note><p>Ellen D. Stedman was the wife of recently embroiled broker Frederick Stuart Stedman, son of poet Edmund Clarence Stedman. She and her daughter Laura were Edmund Clarence Stedman's mainstays in his old age.</p></note>
  </person>
  <person xml:id="HBV">
    <persName type="display">Henry B. Vandiver</persName>
    <persName type="full"><surname>Vandiver</surname>, <forename type="first">Henry</forename> <forename type="middle">Beaden</forename></persName>
    <birth when="1865"></birth>
    <death when="1918"></death>
    <sex></sex>
    <note><p>H. B. Vandiver was an autograph applicant from Weaverville, N.C., who fancied himself &#x201C;Nicodemus Dodge.&#x201D; He was the son of Rev. Dr. J. W. Vandiver, a Methodist pastor, and a seedsman of some renown in Weaverville, N.C. Like most of his siblings, Harry Vandiver attended Weaverville College.</p></note>
  </person>
  <person xml:id="EBW">
    <persName type="display">Effie Blunt (&#x201C;Daisy&#x201D;) Waring</persName>
    <persName type="full"><surname>Waring</surname>, <forename type="first">Effie</forename> <forename type="middle">Blunt</forename></persName>
    <birth when="1856">1856</birth>
    <death when="1933">1933</death>
    <sex></sex>
    <note><p>Daughter of Col. George E. Waring, Jr., Effie Blunt Waring was born on Horace Greely's farm. She studied painting with Abbott Thayer in Boston, and lived and painted in the family homestead, the Hypotenuse, in Newport, R. I. In 1904 she founded Aquidneck Cottge Industries, a dharitable organization that taught local working class women domestic skills and crafts, e.g. needlework and embroidery. (Newport <hi rend="italic">Mercury</hi>, 20 Oct 1933, 3)</p></note>
  </person>
  <person xml:id="VW">
    <persName type="display">Virginia Waring</persName>
    <persName type="full"><surname>Waring</surname>, <forename type="first">Virginia</forename> <forename type="middle"></forename></persName>
    <birth when="1835">1835</birth>
    <death when="1891">1891</death>
    <sex></sex>
    <note><p>The first wife of Col. George E. Waring, Jr., and mother of Effie, Virginia Waring died in 1891 in Newport, R.I. (Newport <hi rend="italic:">Mercury</hi>, 12 Dec 1891, 1).</p></note>
  </person>
  <person xml:id="CW">
    <persName type="display">Charles Watrous</persName>
    <persName type="full"><surname>Watrous</surname>, <forename type="first">Charles</forename> <forename type="middle"></forename></persName>
    <birth when="1807">1807</birth>
    <death when="1891">1891</death>
    <sex></sex>
    <note><p>Watrous was a U.S. Mail agent in San Francisco in the 1860s, and a friend of Bret Harte there (see, for instance, Axel Nissen's <hi rend="italic">Bret Harte, Prince and Pauper</hi> (2000), 239.) As such he probably had at least a passing acquaintance with Noah Brooks. He was forced to step down from his position due his involvement in a vote-buying scandal to elect Timothy Guy Phelps U.S. Senator from California (Portland <hi rend="italic">Oregonian</hi>, 10 Feb 1863, 2), and moved to New York, where he went into the lumber business with his brother-in-law. A member of the Union League, he was involved in the purge of the Tweed ring in 1871. In 1891 he returned to San Francisco with a group of capitalists and engineers sent overland to explore the possibility of a canal through Nicaraugua (&#x201C;The Big Canal: One of the Miller Party Talks of It It,&#x201D; San Francisco <hi rend="italic">Chronicle</hi>, 19 May 1891, 2), and died as a result of an illness contracted while inspecting the canal site en route.</p></note>
  </person>
  <person xml:id="VB">
    <persName type="display">Violet Beach</persName>
    <persName type="full"><surname></surname>, <forename type="first"></forename> <forename type="middle"></forename></persName>
    <birth when="1867">1867</birth>
    <death when="1946">1946</death>
    <sex></sex>
    <note><p>Violet Beach was the daughter of Moses Sperry Beach and Chloe Buckingham Beach, but allegely the illegitimate daughter of Henry Ward Beecher. She never married.</p></note>
  </person>

  <person xml:id="EHW">
    <persName type="display">Elizabeth (Lilly) G. Warner</persName>
    <persName type="full"><surname>Warner</surname>, <forename type="first">Elizabeth</forename> <forename type="middle">Hooker</forename> <surname type="maide">Gillette</surname></persName>
    <birth when="1838">1838</birth>
    <death when="1915">1915</death>
    <sex></sex>
    <note><p>Painter Lilly Warner, a close friend of Olivia Clemens, was the wife of George H. Warner, and sister of actor William Gillette.</p></note>
  </person>

  <person xml:id="SLC">
    <persName type="display">Samuel L. Clemens</persName>
    <persName type="full"><surname></surname>, <forename type="first"></forename> <forename type="middle"></forename></persName>
    <birth when="1835"></birth>
    <death when="1910"></death>
    <sex></sex>
    <note></note>
  </person>
  <person xml:id="FBH">
    <persName type="display">Bret Harte</persName>
    <persName type="full"><surname>Harte</surname>, <forename type="first">Francis</forename> <forename type="middle">Bret</forename></persName>
    <birth when="1836"></birth>
    <death when="1902"></death>
    <sex></sex>
     <note><p>Born to a poor family in Albany, New York, Bret Harte moved to California in 1854, pursuing a variety of occupations as tutor, apothecary’s assistant, expressman, and newspaperman before he began to publish his poems and stories in 1857. He became an editor of the <hi rend="ita;ic">Golden Era</hi> in 1860. In 1862 he married Anna Griswold, with whom he had two sons. From 1864 he was a major contributor to the <hi rend="italic">Californian</hi> and sometimes its editor, first soliciting Clemens’s work for it in 1864. He was the first editor of the <hi rend="italic">Overland Monthly</hi>, where he published &#x201C;Plain Language From Truthful James&#x201D; (1870) and most of his most popular stories. Harte edited the manuscript of SLC’s <hi rend="italic">The Innocents Abroad</hi> (1869). He also collaborated with SLC on the unsuccessful play <hi rend="italic">Ah Sin</hi> (1876–77), but as a result of disagreements during its writing and production, the two became permanently estranged. Harte subsequently held consular posts in Germany and Scotland; he spent his last years in London.</p>
</note>
  </person>
  <person xml:id="RWG">
    <persName type="display">Richard Watson Gilder</persName>
    <persName type="full"><surname></surname>, <forename type="first"></forename> <forename type="middle"></forename></persName>
    <birth when="1844">1844</birth>
    <death when="1909">1909</death>
    <sex></sex>
    <note><p>Richard Watson Gilder was a poet, journalist, editor, and one of the founders of the American Copyright League. His editorial career at the helm of the <hi rend="italic">Century Magazine</hi> spanned from the death of his predecessor J. G. Holland in 1881 (when <hi rend="italic">Scribner's Magazine</hi> became <hi rend="italic">The Century Magazine</hi>) to his own death in 1909. He married painter Helena de Kay, founder of the Society of American Artists, and their home, a converted stable named the Studio, was a gathering place for artists, players, and writers. Gilder was a founding member of the Authors Club, which was organized in 1882 and incorporated in 1887.</p></note>
  </person>
  <person xml:id="HCK">
    <persName type="display">Horatio C. King</persName>
    <persName type="full"><surname>King</surname>, <forename type="first">Horatio</forename> <forename type="middle">Collins</forename></persName>
    <birth when="1837"></birth>
    <death when="1918"></death>
    <sex></sex>
    <note><p>Horatio Collins King was a decorated civil war officer, lawyer, publisher of the <hi rend="italic">Christian Union</hi> and the <hi rend="italic">Christian at Work</hi> in the 1870s, and long-time member of Beecher's Plymouth Church, which had been founded by his father-in-law, Joseph Tasker Howard. In 1878 he left publishing and was appointed major of the Thirteenth Regiment of the New York National Guard, of which he was later made Judge Advocate General. He was active in Democratic politics, but was never successful in winning an office.</p></note>
  </person>
  <person xml:id="LH">
    <persName type="display">Laurence Hutton</persName>
    <persName type="full"><surname>Hutton</surname>, <forename type="first">Laurence</forename> <forename type="middle"></forename></persName>
    <birth when="1843">1843</birth>
    <death when="1904">1904</death>
    <sex></sex>
    <note><p>Editor and critic Laurence Hutton, one of a handful of friends whom Clemens addressed in letters by his nickname (&#x201C;Larry&#x201D;), served as drama critic of the <hi rend="italic">Daily Evening Mail</hi> from 1872&#x2013;4 and literary critic of <hi rend="italic">Harpers' Magazine</hi> from 1886&#x2013;98. He compiled several important dramatic compendia, e.g. <hi rend="italic">Actors and Actresses of Great Britain and the United States</hi>, 5 vols. (1886&#x2013;7), which he co-edited with with Brander Matthews. He was a founding member of the Authors and Players Clubs and of the American Copyright League. Hutton was also a notorious collector of death masks and of association copies. </p></note>
  </person>
  <person xml:id="CdK">
    <persName type="display">Charles de Kay</persName>
    <persName type="full"><surname></surname>, <forename type="first"></forename> <forename type="middle">Augustus</forename></persName>
    <birth when="1848">1848</birth>
    <death when="1935">1935</death>
    <sex></sex>
    <note><p>Charles de Kay was a poet, critic, and founder of the New York Fencers' Club. de Kay took a degree at Yale and spent two years in the company of the literary and artistic celebrities who frequented the salon of his aunt Katherine de Kay Bronson in Paris and Venice. He was the art and literary critic for the New York <hi rend="italic">Times</hi> from 1876 to 1894. He was a founding member of the Author's Club in 1882, and of the National Arts Club in 1899. From 1894&#x2013;97 he served as consul-general in Berlin.</p></note>
  </person>
<!--<person xml:id="bio05952">
    <persName type="display">Alexander Wilson Drake</persName>
    <persName type="full"><surname></surname>, <forename type="first"></forename> <forename type="middle"></forename></persName>
    <birth when="1843">1843</birth>
    <death when="1916">1916</death>
    <sex></sex>
   <note><p>Engraver, painter. writer, and collector Alexander Wilson Drake (1843&#x2013;1916) was the art editor for <hi>Scribner's Magazine</hi> from 1870&#x2013;1881, and then held the same position at the <hi>Century</hi> and <hi>St. Nicholas</hi> magazines. He was a founder of the Grolier Club and a member of the Century, Authors, Illustrators, Aldine, and Players clubs.</p></note>
  </person> -->

            <person xml:id="LWA">
                  <persName>
                     <forename type="first">Mary</forename>
                     <forename type="middle">Elizabeth</forename>
                     <forename type="nickname">"Lilian"</forename>
                     <forename type="middle">Woodman</forename>
                     <surname>Aldrich</surname>
                  </persName>
                  <persName type="display">Mary Elizabeth "Lilian" Woodman  Aldrich</persName>
                  <birth when="1841">1841</birth>
                  <death when="1927">1927</death>
                  <note>
                     <p>Mary Elizabeth "Lilian" (nee Woodman) married the writer and editor Thomas
                     Bailey Aldrich in 1865. In 1920 she published a memoir of her late husband
                     entitled, <hi rend="italic">Crowding Memories</hi>. See also
                       Scharnhorst's <hi rend="italic">Mark Twain in his Own Time</hi>, pp. 95–98. Clemens did not have a high opinion of her. For
                     example, in a 27 December 1893 letter to his daughter Susy he fumed about
                     Lilian, "Lord, I loathe that woman so! She is an idiot—an absolute
                     idiot—&amp; does not know it. She is sham, sham, sham—not a genuine
                     fibre in her anywhere—a manifest &amp; transparent humbug—&amp; her
                     husband, the sincerest man that walks, doesn’t seem aware of it. It is a most
                     extraordinary combination: he, fine in heart, fine in mind, fine in every
                     conceivable way, sincere, genuine, &amp; lovable beyond all men save only Joe
                     Jefferson—&amp; tied for life to this vacant hellion, this
                     clothes-rack, this twaddling, blethering, driveling blatherskite!" (MS
                     facsimile in CU-MARK).</p>
                  </note>
               </person>
               
               <person xml:id="TBA">
                  <persName>
                     <forename type="first">Thomas</forename>
                     <forename type="middle">Bailey</forename>
                     <surname>Aldrich</surname>
                  </persName>
                  <persName type="display">Thomas Bailey  Aldrich</persName>
                  <birth when="1836">1836</birth>
                  <death when="1907">1907</death>
                  <note>
                     <p>Thomas Bailey Aldrich met Clemens in 1871. He was best known for his poems and
                        stories about New Hampshire, where he was born and raised, including his novel <hi rend="italic">The Story of a Bad Boy</hi>, which was a forerunner for <hi rend="italic">Tom Sawyer</hi>. He served on the
                     editorial staff of the <hi rend="italic">Evening Mirror</hi>, <hi rend="italic">Home Journal</hi>, and <hi rend="italic">Saturday Press</hi>. From 1861
                     until 1862 he served as Civil War correspondent for the New York <hi rend="italic">Tribune</hi>. In 1865 he married Lilian Woodman and moved to
                     Boston, where James R. Osgood had offered him the editorship of <hi rend="italic">Every Saturday</hi>, a post he held until 1874. He succeeded
                     William Dean Howells as editor of the <hi rend="italic">Atlantic Monthly</hi> in 1881, a position he
                     retained until 1890. While Clemens was not initially enthusiastic about Aldrich's
                     work, he often provided advice (see his 15 and 16, 24, 25 March 1874 letter
                     suggesting changes in his novel <hi rend="italic">Prudence Palfrey</hi>, <hi rend="italic">L6</hi>, 74–82, 89–95). They remained lifelong
                     friends. In his 1904 sketch “Robert Louis Stevenson and Thomas Bailey Aldrich,”
                     Clemens wrote that Aldrich “never had his peer for prompt and pithy and witty
                     and humorous sayings” (<ref target="http://www.marktwainproject.org/xtf/view?docId=works/MTDP10362.xml;doc.view=;chunk.id=d1e9377;toc.id=0;style=work;brand=mtp" type="citeref"><hi rend="italic">AutoMT1</hi>, 229</ref>, 539 n.
                     229.8).</p>
                  </note>
               </person>

               <person xml:id="WSA">
                  <persName>
                     <forename type="first">William</forename>
                     <forename type="middle">S.</forename>
                     <surname>Andrews</surname>
                  </persName>
                  <persName type="display">William S.  Andrews</persName>
                  <birth when="1841">1841</birth>
                  <death when="1912">1912</death>
                  <note>
                     <p>William S. Andrews was an actor and noted public speaker who often used Mark
                     Twain's works to demonstrate "dialect humor." Later in life he was an
                     influential politician (<hi rend="italic">L5</hi>, 209 n. 1).</p>
                  </note>
               </person>               

               <person xml:id="CYB">
                  <persName>
                     <forename type="first">Charles</forename>
                     <forename type="middle">Yale</forename>
                     <surname>Beach</surname>
                  </persName>
                  <persName type="display">Charles Yale  Beach</persName>
                  <birth when="1847">1847</birth>
                  <death when="1917">1917</death>
                  <note>
                     <p>Charles Beach, a real estate investor, was the son of Moses Beach, and older
                     brother of Emma Beach.</p>
                  </note>
               </person>

               <!-- finish -->
               <person xml:id="JWB">
                  <persName>
                     <forename type="first">Joseph</forename>
                     <forename type="middle">Watson</forename>
                     <surname>Beach</surname>
                  </persName>
                  <persName type="display">Joseph Watson  Beach</persName>
                  <birth when="1823">1823</birth>
                  <death when="1887">1887</death>
                  <note>
                     <p>J. W. Beach was a Hartford businessman who co-owned Beach and Company with
                     his brothers George and Charles. It is not known when he met Clemens, but his
                     membership in the Hartford Club suggests that he could have known Clemens, who often socialized there.</p>
                  </note>
               </person>

               <person xml:id="MSB">
                  <persName>
                     <forename type="first">Moses</forename>
                     <forename type="middle">Sperry</forename>
                     <surname>Beach</surname>
                  </persName>
                  <persName type="display">Moses Sperry  Beach</persName>
                  <birth when="1822">1822</birth>
                  <death when="1892">1892</death>
                  <note>
                     <p>Moses S. Beach was a printer and editor of the New York <hi rend="italic">Sun</hi>. He was a long-time member and former trustee of Plymouth Church
                     who, with his daughter Emeline (1850–1924), was among the “most prominent
                     Brooklynites” to meet Clemens on the <hi rend="italic">Quaker City</hi> excursion
                     in 1867. Clemens spoke well of Beach, grateful for the treatment he had 
                     received from him and especially praising his liberality and generosity toward the crew of the Quaker City.</p>
                  </note>
               </person>

               <person xml:id="HWB">
                  <persName>
                     <forename type="first">Henry</forename>
                     <forename type="middle">Ward</forename>
                     <surname>Beecher</surname>
                  </persName>
                  <persName type="display">Henry Ward  Beecher</persName>
                  <birth when="1813">1813</birth>
                  <death when="1887">1887</death>
                  <note>
                     <p>Henry Ward Beecher was the renowned liberal pastor of Plymouth Church in
                       Brooklyn, and the author of several popular books. He was also a social activist who promoted abolition, temperance, and women's rights. Clemens met him in the winter of 1868, and admired his congeniality even when pointing out his flimsy convictions (which would culminate in the Beecher-Tilton adultery trial of 1875). Clemens also published the sketch "Rev. Henry Ward Beecher's Farm," which was published in <hi rend="italic">Sketches</hi> (1872) and <hi rend="italic">A Curious Dream</hi> (1872). They exchanged letters and kept a mostly pleasant acqaintance; Clemens usually saw him when he visited his sister Isabella Hooker, who was Clemens's neighbor in Hartford and a very close friend. A tricky publishing venture at the end of Beecher's life also revealed Clemens's ambivalence to the celebrity pastor. On 3 January 1887 Charles Webster informed Clemens that Beecher was considering an autobiography: “Beecher seemed to think that it might be a pretty good thing to do, and he also seemed to think that other things being equal, he would rather have us publish it than any one else. ... I do not love Beecher any more than you do, but I love his money just as well, and I am certain that that book would sell.” (Beecher had also been advanced a substantial sum by Webster to complete his <hi rend="italic">Jesus, Life of the Christ</hi>, which he also did not finish.) Beecher's death complicated these publishing plans, and in 1888 Clemens settled for the unprofitable biography completed by his son William and son-in-law Samuel Scoville (<hi rend="italic">N&amp;J3</hi>, 272, 276).</p>
                  </note>
               </person>

               <person xml:id="WCB">
                  <persName>
                     <forename type="first">William</forename>
                     <forename type="middle">Constantine</forename>
                     <surname>Beecher</surname>
                  </persName>
                  <persName type="display">William Constantine  Beecher</persName>
                  <birth when="1849">1849</birth>
                  <death when="1928">1928</death>
                  <note>
                     <p>William C. Beecher was Henry Ward Beecher's son. He practiced law, but also
                     wrote a biography of his father, <hi rend="italic">Henry Ward Beecher: A Sketch
                        of His Career</hi> (Hartford: American Publishing Company, 1887).</p>
                  </note>
               </person>

               <person xml:id="JSB">
                  <persName>
                     <forename type="first">John</forename>
                     <forename type="middle">Shaw</forename>
                     <surname>Billings</surname>
                  </persName>
                  <persName type="display">John Shaw  Billings</persName>
                  <birth when="1838">1838</birth>
                  <death when="1913">1913</death>
                  <note>
                     <p>Dr. John S. Billings served as medical inspector of the Army of the Potomac.
                     After the war he was posted to the office of the U.S. Surgeon General as
                     Lieutenant Colonel, where he established the National Library of Medicine
                     within the War Department's Surgeon General's Library, for which he served as
                     librarian until his retirement from active Army service in 1895. In 1896 he
                     became the first chief librarian of the New York Public Library. He was also a
                     founding member of the Cosmos Club in Washington D.C. He probably knew Clemens from
                     their mutual friend Colonel George Waring, with whom Billings worked on several
                     sanitation projects.</p>
                  </note>
               </person>

               <person xml:id="HHB">
                  <persName>
                     <forename type="first">Hjalmar</forename>
                     <forename type="middle">H.</forename>
                     <surname>Boyesen</surname>
                  </persName>
                  <persName type="display">Hjalmar H.  Boyesen</persName>
                  <birth when="1848">1848</birth>
                  <death when="1895">1895</death>
                  <note>
                     <p>Boyesen was a Norwegian novelist, critic, and professor of German at Cornell
                     University. He met Clemens in the late 1870s and got to know him well during his
                     stay in Paris in 1879 while he was finishing <hi rend="italic">A Tramp
                        Abroad</hi>. He also introduced Clemens to Turgenev (see Mark Twain's NB 18, <hi rend="italic">NB&amp;J2</hi>, pp. 285–350).</p>
                  </note>
               </person>
               
               <person xml:id="NB">
                  <persName>
                     <forename>Noah</forename>
                     <surname>Brooks</surname>
                  </persName>
                  <persName type="display">Noah  Brooks</persName>
                  <birth when="1830">1830</birth>
                  <death when="1903">1903</death>
                  <note>
                     <p>Noah Brooks began his newspaper career in Boston at the age of eighteen, but six years later he went west, eventually settling in California, where he founded the Marysville <hi rend="italic">Appeal</hi>. During the Civil War he served as Washington correspondent for the Sacramento <hi rend="italic">Union</hi>, and was the last journalist to interview Abraham Lincoln. After the war he became managing editor of the San Francisco <hi rend="italic">Alta California</hi>, when became acquainted with Clemens, initially through their mutual friend Bret Harte (Brooks contributed short fiction, as did Clemens, to Harte's <hi rend="italic">Overland Monthly</hi>). Brooks was the managing editor of the (San Francisco) Daily <hi rend="italic">Alta California</hi> when Clemens undertook the Quaker City voyage in 1867 as an <hi rend="italic">Alta</hi> correspondent (furnishing the material for <hi rend="italic">Innocents Abroad</hi>). In 1871 he started working for the New York <hi rend="italic">Tribune</hi>, and in 1876 he became the editor of the New York <hi rend="italic">Times</hi>. Retiring in 1892, he spent the rest of his life publishing travel literature and memoirs. In his <hi rend="italic">Autobiography</hi>, Clemens recalled that Brooks was "a man of sterling character and equipped with a right heart, also a good historian where facts were not essential" (<ref target="http://www.marktwainproject.org/xtf/view?docId=works/MTDP10362.xml;chunk.id=d1e9273;toc.depth=1;toc.id=;citations=;style=work;brand=mtp#X">AutoMT1</ref>, 228).</p>
                  </note>
               </person>
               
               <person xml:id="CCB">
                  <persName>
                     <forename>Clarence</forename>
                     <forename>Clough</forename>
                     <surname>Buel</surname>
                  </persName>
                  <persName type="display">Clarence Clough  Buel</persName>
                  <birth when="1850">1850</birth>
                  <death when="1933">1933</death>
                  <note>
                     <p>Buel was an editor and author who worked at the <hi rend="italic">New York Tribune</hi> and <hi rend="italic">Century Magazine</hi>. With Robert Underwood Johnson he co-edited the acclaimed <hi rend="italic">Battles and Leaders of the Civil War</hi> (1887&#8211;88).</p>
                  </note>
               </person>

               <person xml:id="HCB">
                  <persName>
                     <forename type="first">Henry</forename>
                     <forename type="middle">Cuyler</forename>
                     <surname>Bunner</surname>
                  </persName>
                  <persName type="display">Henry Cuyler  Bunner</persName>
                  <birth when="1855">1855</birth>
                  <death when="1896">1896</death>
                  <note>
                     <p>H. C. Bunner was a writer and editor who oversaw <hi rend="italic">Puck</hi>, the influential humor magazine. His novels included <hi rend="italic">The
                           Midge</hi> (1882), and <hi rend="italic">The Story of a New York House</hi> (1883), yet he was best known for short stories and sketches about life in New York City, in particular those collected in <hi rend="italic">Short Sixes</hi> (1891). His collaborations with Brander Matthews also pushed the boundaries of the short story genre. Clemens probably met Bunner in 1883, when both were inducted into the Kinsmen club, and they both attended a dinner for Laurence Hutton at the Tile Club in New York in 1885. Clemens also jotted in his notebook in 1886 to read Bunner's <hi>The Midge</hi> (<hi rend="italic">N&amp;J3</hi>, pp. 105, 115, 240). Clemens was also a frequent houseguest at Bunner's New York City home near Old Battery Park (see NB 33, entry for 9 December 1893, and 8 December 1893 to Olivia Clemens, MS in CU-MARK).</p>
                  </note>
               </person>
               
               <person xml:id="GWC">
                  <persName>
                     <forename type="first">George</forename>
                     <forename type="middle">Washington</forename>
                     <surname>Cable</surname>
                  </persName>
                  <persName type="display">George Washington  Cable</persName>
                  <birth when="1844">1844</birth>
                  <death when="1925">1925</death>
                  <note>
                     <p>George Washington Cable, a writer from New Orleans who fought for the Confederacy, was best known for his realist novels about Creole life such as <hi rend="italic">The Grandissimes: A Story of Creole Life</hi> (1880) and <hi rend="italic">Dr. Sevier</hi> (1882). Having heard about Cable's work from William Dean Howells, Clemens met him in New Orleans in 1882, an encounter he described in chapters 44 and 47 of <hi rend="italic">Life on the Mississippi</hi>. The winter following his April Fool joke he and Clemens went on their tour throughout the U.S. in which they alternated reading from their works. While the tour was a success, Clemens elaborated in a letter to Howells about his and Cable's "curious experience" together: "You will never never know, never divine, guess, imagine, how loathsome a thing the Christian religion can be made until you come to know &amp; study Cable daily &amp; hourly. Mind you, I like him; he is pleasant company; I rage &amp; swear at him sometimes, but we do not quarrel; we get along mighty happily together; but in him &amp; his person I have learned to hate all religions. He has taught me to abhor &amp; detest the Sabbath-day &amp; hunt up new &amp; troublesome ways to dishonor it" (27 February 1885 to William Dean Howells, MS in NN-BGC). Clemens may have been responsible for the rumors about Cable's stinginess during his stay with the Clemenses in the winter of 1884 that appeared in the Boston <hi rend="italic">Herald</hi> on 7 May 1885; Clemens denied knowing anything about the "professional newspaper liar" when Cable asked him to refute the damaging story, and encouraged him to let it go. Cable did succeed in getting a retraction, but Clemens and Cable's relationship soured afterward (<hi rend="italic">N&amp;J3</hi>, 154).</p>
                  </note>
               </person>
               
               <person xml:id="WC">
                  <persName>
                     <forename type="first">William</forename>
                     <surname>Carey</surname>
                  </persName>
                  <persName type="display">William  Carey</persName>
                  <birth when="1858">1858</birth>
                  <death when="1901">1901</death>
                  <note>
                     <p>Wiliam Carey worked on the editorial staff for the <hi rend="italic">Century Magazine</hi> for twenty years, as well as acting as a liaison between editors and production men (Arthur John, <hi rend="italic">The Best Years of the Century</hi>, p. 116). A legendary wit and popular with authors, he was also a member of the Authors Club.</p>
                  </note>
               </person>
               
               <person xml:id="RC">
                  <persName>
                     <forename>Robert</forename>
                     <surname>Collyer</surname>
                  </persName>
                  <persName type="display">Robert  Collyer</persName>
                  <birth when="1823">1823</birth>
                  <death when="1912">1912</death>
                  <note>
                     <p>Collyer was a former blacksmith from Yorkshire and a Methodist lay-preacher who became an ordained Unitarian minister, serving as pastor of Unity Church in Chicago from 1859 until 1879. In 1879 he became the pastor of Church of the Messiah in New York City. In addition to being a popular lecturer, Collyer also published several sermons, lectures, and books such as <hi rend="italic">Life of A. H. Conant</hi> (1868), <hi rend="italic">Father Taylor</hi> (1906), and <hi rend="italic">Clear Grit</hi> (1913).</p>
                  </note>
               </person>

               <person xml:id="SSC">
                  <persName>
                     <forename type="first">Stillman</forename>
                     <forename type="middle">S.</forename>
                     <surname>Conant</surname>
                  </persName>
                  <persName type="display">Stillman S.  Conant</persName>
                  <birth when="1831">1831</birth>
                  <death when="1885">1885</death>
                  <note>
                     <p>Stillman S. Conant was a journalist who contributed to several prominent
                     periodicals of the day, including the <hi rend="italic">Galaxy</hi>, to which
                     Clemens also contributed. He also translated into English (from a German
                     translation) Mikhail Lermontov's poem <hi rend="italic">The Circassian Boy</hi>
                     (Boston: James R. Osgood and Co., 1875). In 1869 he became the managing editor
                     of <hi rend="italic">Harper's Weekly</hi>, a position he held until 1885, when
                     he disappeared off the coast of Coney Island. In 1890 the New York <hi rend="italic">Times</hi> reported the discovery of a skeleton in the dunes
                     near Rockaway Beach that was believed to be Conant, but that was never verified
                     ("A Skeleton in the Dunes. The Disappearance of Stillman S. Conant Recalled,"
                     New York <hi rend="italic">Times</hi>, 14 December 1890, 8).</p>
                  </note>
               </person>
               
               <person xml:id="BHC">
                  <persName>
                     <forename type="first">Bloodgood</forename>
                     <forename type="middle">Haviland</forename>
                     <surname>Cutter</surname>
                  </persName>
                  <persName type="display">Bloodgood Haviland  Cutter</persName>
                  <birth when="1817">1817</birth>
                  <death when="1906">1906</death>
                  <note>
                     <p>Bloodgood Cutter was a farmer and poet from Long Island. At the outset of the <hi rend="italic">Quaker City</hi> voyage Clemens described Cutter in his notebook as “fifty years old, &amp; small of his age. He dresses in homespun, &amp; is a simple minded, honest, old-fashioned farmer, with a strange proclivity for writing rhymes. He writes them on all possible subjects, &amp; gets them printed on slips of paper, with his portrait at the head. These he will give to any man that comes along, whether he has anything against him or not” (<hi rend="italic">N&amp;J1</hi>, 344). Cutter considered himself the Poet Laureate of the excursion. Clemens called him the “Poet Lariat” in <hi rend="italic">Innocents</hi>, adopting Francis Eugene Andrews’s mispronunciation. In 1880 he called him a “mildewed idiot. His friends call him a lunatic&#8212;but that is pretty fulsome flattery; one cannot become a lunatic without first having brains” (30 Apr 1880 to Perkins, CtY-BR, in <ref target="http://www.marktwainproject.org/">MTPO</ref>); 31 Mar and 1 Apr 69 to Fairbanks, <hi rend="italic">L2</hi>, 185). In 1886 Cutter self-published a collection of his poems entitled <hi rend="italic">The Long Island Farmer's Poems</hi>. His poems were never celebrated, yet he was a successful farmer: at his death his estate was worth $900,000.</p>
                  </note>
               </person>
               
              <person xml:id="CCD">
                  <persName>
                     <forename type="first">Charles</forename>
                     <forename type="middle">C.</forename>
                     <surname>Duncan</surname>
                  </persName>
                  <persName type="display">Charles C.  Duncan</persName>
                  <birth when="1821">1821</birth>
                  <death when="1898">1898</death>
                  <note>
                     <p>Charles Duncan was the captain of the <hi rend="italic">Quaker City</hi> when Clemens traveled to Europe and the Levant in 1867. Duncan had gone to sea as a boy and was a ship captain before he was thirty. In 1853 he became a shipping and commission merchant in New York City, operating as Charles C. Duncan and Company. Shortly before the Civil War, he resettled in England and resumed business there while leaving the New York office in the hands of a subordinate, who absconded with the firm’s funds, precipitating its bankruptcy after Duncan’s return in 1865. The <hi rend="italic">Quaker City</hi> excursion was in part a means of recovering from the bankruptcy. Duncan also lectured on the excursion, in New York on 3 and 26 December 1867, in Washington on January 1868, in Cleveland on 10 March 1868, and again in New York on 11 January 1877, when he attacked Clemens by declaring <hi rend="italic">Innocents</hi> was “in no sense” an accurate account of the trip (“About Mark Twain,” New York <hi rend="italic">World</hi>, 12 Jan 1877, 5). Clemens showed his contempt for Duncan in his partial draft of a <hi rend="italic">Quaker City</hi> play, depicting him as the mercenary “Capt. Dusenberry” (see Appendix E of <hi rend="italic">L2</hi>; also the enclosure (note 1) of Clemens's <ref target="http://www.marktwainproject.org/xtf/view?docId=letters/UCCL00160.xml;query=quaker%20city%20play;searchAll=;sectionType1=;sectionType2=;sectionType3=;sectionType4=;sectionType5=;style=letter;brand=mtp#1" type="citeref">25 November 1867 letter to Charles Henry Webb</ref>. Over the years he and Duncan were intermittently contentious, specifically in 1877 and 1883, when Clemens spoke out in support of Elihu Root's corruption investigation (<ref target="http://www.marktwainproject.org/xtf/view?docId=letters/UCCL00174.xml;doc.view=;style=letter;brand=mtp" type="citeref">8 January 68 to Beach</ref>, <ref target="http://www.marktwainproject.org/xtf/view?docId=letters/UCCL00200.xml;doc.view=;style=letter;brand=mtp" type="citeref">10 March 68 to Fairbanks</ref>, L2, 149 n. 6, 203 n. 1; N&amp;J2, 35; N&amp;J3, 18, 24–25). Duncan was dismissed in 1884 as shipping commissioner of the port of New York.</p>
                  </note>
               </person>
               
               
               <person xml:id="ACD">
                  <persName>
                     <forename type="first">Austin</forename>
                     <forename type="middle">Cornelius</forename>
                     <surname>Dunham</surname>
                  </persName>
                  <persName type="display">Austin Cornelius  Dunham</persName>
                  <birth when="1833">1833</birth>
                  <death when="1917">1917</death>
                  <note>
                     <p>Austin Dunham was a wool merchant, inventor, and president of the Hartford Electric Light Company. In 1870 he joined the Monday Evening Club, where Clemens had read before (see <ref target="http://vm149.lib.berkeley.edu:8080/xtf-exp/view?docId=letters/UCCL02497.xml;query=UCCL02497;searchAll=;sectionType1=;sectionType2=;sectionType3=;sectionType4=;sectionType5=;style=letter;brand=mtp#1">11 January 1876 to William Dean Howells</ref> at <hi rend="italic">MTPO</hi>). The Dunhams were also good friends with Clemens's friend and collaborator, Charles Dudley Warner.</p>
                  </note>
               </person>

               <person xml:id="GCE">
                  <persName>
                     <forename type="first">George</forename>
                     <forename type="middle">Cary</forename>
                     <surname>Eggleston</surname>
                  </persName>
                  <persName type="display">George Cary  Eggleston</persName>
                  <birth when="1839">1839</birth>
                  <death when="1911">1911</death>
                  <note>
                     <p>Eggleston was a journalist, historian, and novelist raised in southern Indiana. He was practicing law in Richmond, Virginia, when the Civil War broke out, and served as a Confederate officer (he later witnessed the surrender at Appomattox). From 1871–75 he served as the editor of <hi rend="italic">Hearth and Home</hi> magazine, where he made the acquaintance of William Dean Howells. In 1875 he published a well-regarded memoir of his service entitled <hi rend="italic">A Rebel's Recollections</hi>, which later formed the subject of his majestic two-volume <hi rend="italic">A History of the Confederate War</hi>. He was also known for Southern novels such as <hi rend="italic">Dorothy South</hi>, <hi rend="italic">A Carolina Cavalier</hi> and <hi rend="italic">Irene of the Mountains</hi>.</p>
                  </note>
               </person>

               <person xml:id="CSF">
                  <persName>
                     <forename type="first">Charles</forename>
                     <forename type="middle">S.</forename>
                     <surname>Fairchild</surname>
                  </persName>
                  <persName type="display">Charles S.  Fairchild</persName>
                  <birth when="1838">1838</birth>
                  <death when="1910">1910</death>
                  <note>
                     <p>Charles Fairchild was born and raised in Ohio. After graduating from Harvard in 1858 he served in the Union Army, and briefly attended Harvard Law (without taking a degree) before entering the paper manufacturing business. He was “a close friend and drinking companion of James R. Osgood and his knights of the quill&#8212;Aldrich, Samuel Clemens, and William Dean Howells." He helped Howells to finance his house in Belmont, and for a brief time in the early 1880s they were neighbors. Clemens probably first met him in 1874 at the banquet at the Parker House in Boston for <hi rend="italic">Atlantic Monthly</hi> contributors and supporters. (Fairchild had actually advanced $20,000 to Melancthon Hurd and Henry Houghton to purchase ownership of the magazine from James R. Osgood.) (<hi rend="italic">L6</hi>, p. 319). He was also the brother of General Lucius Fairchild, the Civil War veteran, diplomat, and tenth governor of Wisconsin.</p>
                  </note>
               </person>
               
               <person xml:id="MFF">
                  <persName>
                     <forename type="first">Mary</forename>
                     <forename type="middle">Hewins</forename>
                     <surname type="maiden">Fox</surname>
                     <surname type="married">Fiske</surname>
                  </persName>
                  <persName type="display">Mary Fiske</persName>
                  <birth when="1842">1842</birth>
                  <death when="1889">1889</death>
                  <note>
                     <p>Mary Fiske, a Hartford native, wrote plays and drama criticism under the nom de plume "Giddy Gusher." She married the journalist and dramatist Stephen Fiske in 1875.</p>
                  </note>
               </person>
               
               <person xml:id="SRF">
                  <persName>
                     <forename type="first">Stephen</forename>
                     <forename type="middle">Ryder</forename>
                     <surname>Fiske</surname>
                  </persName>
                  <persName type="display">Stephen Ryder  Fiske</persName>
                  <birth when="1840">1840</birth>
                  <death when="1916">1916</death>
                  <note>
                     <p>Fiske was a journalist, drama critic, and theater manager who started his career working for the New York <hi rend="italic">Herald</hi>. After the Civil War he lived in Rome, where he joined Garibaldi, and then lived in London, where he became the manager of the Royal English Opera Company. Returning to New York in 1874, he managed the Fifth Avenue Theatre in New York (where Madame Modjeska mad her famous debut), contributed dramatic criticism to <hi rend="italic">The Spirit of the Times</hi>, and started the <hi rend="italic">New York Dramatic Mirror</hi>. He was also known for several plays, including <hi rend="italic">Corporeal Cartouche</hi>, <hi rend="italic">Martin Chuzzlewit</hi>, and <hi rend="italic">My Noble Son-in-Law</hi>. He was a noted member of Pfaff's cellar, having established himself during the Civil War as a "Pfaff's bohemian."</p>
                  </note>
               </person>


               <person xml:id="DCF">
                  <persName>
                     <forename type="first">Daniel</forename>
                     <forename type="middle">Chester</forename>
                     <surname>French</surname>
                  </persName>
                  <persName type="display">Daniel Chester  French</persName>
                  <birth when="1850">1850</birth>
                  <death when="1931">1931</death>
                  <note>
                     <p>Daniel Chester French was a prolific sculptor best known for his "Minuteman"
                     at Concord (1874) and statue of Abraham Lincoln at the Lincoln Memorial in
                     Washington D.C. (1920). Louisa May Alcott's sister Mary convinced him to be a
                     sculptor when he was growing up in Concord, Massachusetts. He was also a member of the Boston Author's Club, which included Clemens, William Dean
                     Howells, and Thomas Bailey Aldrich as members.</p>
                  </note>
               </person>
               
               <person xml:id="CF">
                  <persName>
                     <forename>Charles</forename>
                     <surname>Frohman</surname>
                  </persName>
                  <persName type="display">Charles  Frohman</persName>
                  <birth when="1860">1860</birth>
                  <death when="1915">1915</death>
                  <note>
                     <p>Charles Frohman was a theatrical manager and producer, notably of the touring Wallack Theatre Company and the Lyceum. In 1900 he met with Clemens to discuss producing "The End of the Earth," a play he co-wrote with Sydney Rosenfeld. Rosenfeld wrote to the New York <hi rend="italic">Dramatic Mirror</hi> on 22 April 1898 that he had that day concluded an agreement with Mark Twain to collaborate on a play, a rough draft of which he had received. On 22 October 1900 the two men met with Frohman, but nothing came of the meeting. In August 1902 Rosenfeld announced to the press that he would produce the play under contract with Leander Sire, possibly as the maiden play for a projected (but never constructed) new theater. It seems never to have made it to the stage. Frohman was among the passengers who died when the Germans sunk the <hi rend="italic">RMS Lusitania</hi>.</p>
                  </note>
               </person>
               
               <person xml:id="DF">
                  <persName>
                     <forename>Daniel</forename>
                     <surname>Frohman</surname>
                  </persName>
                  <persName type="display">Daniel  Frohman</persName>
                  <birth when="1851">1851</birth>
                  <death when="1940">1940</death>
                  <note>
                     <p>Charles Frohman's older brother, Daniel started his career as an office boy for the New York <hi>Tribune</hi>, and then spent five years as a journalist before managing touring companies for New York theaters. In 1880 he organized the Lyceum theater, which made him (and many other actors, such as E. H. Sothern, Henry Miller, and May Robson), famous. He was also a member of the Players Club, where Clemens would also appear. In 1911 Frohman published his <hi rend="italic">Memoirs of a Manager</hi>. He also played a role in the early film industry with the Famous Players Film Company.</p>
                  </note>
               </person>

               <person xml:id="RSG">
                  <persName>
                     <forename type="first">Robert</forename>
                     <forename type="middle">Swain</forename>
                     <surname>Gifford</surname>
                  </persName>
                  <persName type="display">Robert Swain  Gifford</persName>
                  <birth when="1840">1840</birth>
                  <death when="1905">1905</death>
                  <note>
                     <p>Gifford was an artist best known for his landscape paintings, particularly of the American West, New England, and North Africa. An early member of the Society of American Artists, he was also friends with Clemens's friend the artist Frank Millet, who traveled with him to Germany and Scandinavia in 1882.</p>
                  </note>
               </person>

               <!-- finish -->
               <person xml:id="JLG">
                  <persName>
                     <forename type="first">Jeannette</forename>
                     <forename type="middle">Leonard</forename>
                     <surname>Gilder</surname>
                  </persName>
                  <persName type="display">Jeannette Leonard  Gilder</persName>
                  <birth when="1849">1849</birth>
                  <death when="1916">1916</death>
                  <note>
                     <p>Jeannette Gilder was a journalist who corresponded for the Chicago <hi rend="italic">Tribune</hi> and served as the associate editor of <hi rend="italic">Putnam's Magazine</hi> and <hi rend="italic">The Critic and Good Literature</hi>. She was also the daughter of the clergyman William Henry Gilder, and the sister of the poet and editor Richard Watson Gilder. In 1881–82 Clemens and her had a row about a letter to the editor in the Critic which asked why Clemens had not given credit to the source of his story "A Curious Episode," and Clemens responded by sending an excoriating letter to the editor which assumed the editor was a man (Gilder to Clemens, 6 Dec 1881, ms in CU-MARK; Clemens to Gilder, 12 Dec 1881). Gilder and Clemens were both apologetic for their respective blunders, and Gilder later made a gratuitous gesture by sending Clemens the original manuscript of Holmes's poem to commemorate Clemens's fiftieth birthday in 1885 (Gilder to Clemens, 14 December 1881; Clemens to Boyesen, 11 January 1882; Gilder to Clemens, 9 December 1885, ms in CU-MARK).</p>
                  </note>
               </person>
               
               <person xml:id="JEG">
                  <persName>
                     <forename type="first">John</forename>
                     <forename type="middle">E.</forename>
                     <surname>Gowen</surname>
                  </persName>
                  <persName type="display">John E.  Gowen</persName>
                  <birth when="1825">1825</birth>
                  <death when="1895">1895</death>
                  <note>
                     <p>Colonel John Gowen was an engineer and invester who defined his career by raising the Russian fleet of more than seventy ships after they were sunk at Sevastopol during the Crimean War. He was also an early member of the Lotos Club.</p>
                  </note>
               </person>
               
               <person xml:id="HPG">
                  <persName>
                     <forename type="first">Henry</forename>
                     <forename type="middle">Peters</forename>
                     <surname>Gray</surname>
                  </persName>
                  <persName type="display">Henry Peters Gray, Jr.</persName>
                  <birth when="1844">1844</birth>
                  <death when="1897">1897</death>
                  <note>
                     <p>Henry Peters Gray served for the New York Volunteers as an Assistant Adjutant-General during the Civil War, and after the war was a longstanding employee of Tiffany &amp; Co.</p>
                  </note>
               </person>


               <person xml:id="JPCH">
                  <persName>
                     <forename>Joseph</forename>
                     <forename>Paul</forename>
                     <forename>Christopher</forename>
                     <surname>Hatton</surname>
                  </persName>
                  <persName type="display">Joseph Paul Christopher  Hatton</persName>
                  <birth when="1841">1841</birth>
                  <death when="1907">1907</death>
                  <note>
                     <p>Joseph Hatton was a journalist (notably for the Sunday <hi rend="italic">Times</hi>) and prolific popular writer. In addition to writing over 30 novels and running a popular column called "Cigarette Papers," he published a biography in 1884 of Henry Irving after traveling with him on tour. In Hatton's book on Irving, he also established himself as an ally in Clemens's crusade for improved copyright laws between the U.S. and Great Britain (328-29). Just before he died, Hatton wrote on 7 July 1907 that recently "Mark Twain came to see me. I had got into the garden nicely packed up in blankets, and was asleep—that sort of dreamy sleep when you don't quite know whether you are asleep or awake. He was very kind and sympathetic, and we had a very pleasant chat" (M. A. P., 10 August 1907).</p>
                  </note>
               </person>
               
               <person xml:id="JH">
                  <persName>
                     <forename>Julian</forename>
                     <surname>Hawthorne</surname>
                  </persName>
                  <persName type="display">Julian Hawthorne</persName>
                  <birth when="1846">1846</birth>
                  <death when="1934">1934</death>
                  <note>
                    <p>Julian Hawthorne, the son of Nathaniel Hawthorne and Sophia Peabody, was a noted journalist and writer in his own right (mostly of mystery stories), and Clemens's library eventually included his 1885 novel <hi rend="italic">Noble Blood</hi> and his 1903 study of his father, <hi rend="italic">Hawthorne and his Circle</hi> (Gribben, <hi rend="italic">Mark Twain's Library</hi>, p. 1:301). He met Clemens in the early 1870s, and remained good friends with him until his death. During this time he was also employed as the literary editor of the New York <hi rend="italic">World</hi>. They both belonged to the American Copyright League and the Authors Club. About his friendship with Clemens Hawthorne recalled that "I found him as most people did, delightful and fruitful, and very much as he was in his best writing," adding that "He never seemed to be a very happy man ... his mind was too active, searching out and sincere not to be troubled by the riddle of the Universe" ("Mark Twain as I Knew Him," <hi rend="italic">Overland Monthly and Out West Magazine</hi> 87 [April 1929]: 111).</p>
                  </note>
               </person>
               
               <person xml:id="JMH">
                  <persName>
                     <forename type="first">John</forename>
                     <forename type="middle">Milton</forename>
                     <surname>Hay</surname>
                  </persName>
                  <persName type="display">John Milton Hay</persName>
                  <birth when="1838">1838</birth>
                  <death when="1905">1905</death>
                  <note>
                     <p>John Hay was a writer and statesman who grew up in Warsaw, Illinois, a small
                     town about sixty miles from Clemens's hometown of Hannibal, Missouri, and this
                     common background fostered their long friendship. After graduating from Brown
                     University, Hay began his illustrious career in public service as an assistant
                     private secretary to Abraham Lincoln. Hay met Clemens in the late 1860s, and in 1871 Clemens offered Hay
                     part-ownership of the Buffalo <hi rend="italic">Express</hi>, and to join him
                     in a trip down the Mississippi to furnish material for what would appear in
                     1875 as the "Old Times on the Mississippi" series in the January-June and
                     August issues of the <hi rend="italic">Atlantic Monthly</hi>. Hay declined both
                     offers, but remained appreciative of his work (see
                     also <ref target="http://www.marktwainproject.org/xtf/view?docId=letters/UCCL11849.xml;query=john%20hay;searchAll=;sectionType1=;sectionType2=;sectionType3=;sectionType4=;sectionType5=;style=letter;brand=mtp#1">Clemens to John M. Hay, 6? Jan 1871</ref>). Clemens also appreciated Hay's <hi rend="italic">Pike County Ballads</hi> (1871) for its verisimilitude to
                        their boyhood region. In 1870 Hay accepted an editorial
                     position on the New York <hi rend="italic">Tribune</hi> under Horace Greeley,
                     and then, after Greeley’s death in 1872, assisted the new editor, Whitelaw
                     Reid. He gave up his <hi rend="italic">Tribune</hi> position in 1875 and pursued a literary career as
                     a poet, novelist, and biographer of Lincoln. Until about 1890 Hay's friendship with Clemens was
                     was lukewarm, kept up mostly through mutual friends, but their relationship
                     changed in 1898, when Hay became Secretary of State under the McKinley (and
                     later Rossevelt) administration. Despite Clemens's anti-imperialist polemics (and
                     Hay's support for Clemens's foe Theodore Roosevelt), their affection for each other
                     remained solid until Hay's death in 1905 (see <ref target="http://www.marktwainproject.org/xtf/view?docId=works/MTDP10362.xml;chunk.id=d1e9201;toc.depth=1;toc.id=;citations=;style=work;brand=mtp#X">
                           <hi rend="italic">AutoMT1</hi>, pp.222-24</ref>). In a 27 August 1907
                     autobiographical dictation Clemens reminisced, "Hay was a man of great and varied
                     talents and accomplishments, and was conspicuously well equipped for the
                     several great national and international posts which he had filled in his
                     brilliant career; and he climbed to several of them without the help of wealth,
                     and would doubtless have climbed the rest of the way without that help, and all
                     the public would have approved, and would also have affectionately applauded
                     and rejoiced" (<ref target="http://www.marktwainproject.org/xtf/view?docId=works/MTDP10364.xml;query=%22john%20hay%22;chunk.id=dv0028;toc.depth=1;toc.id=;citations=;style=work;brand=mtp#3">
                           <hi rend="italic">AutoMT3</hi>, p. 112</ref>).</p>
                  </note>
               </person>
               
               
               <person xml:id="JHJr">
                  <persName>
                     <forename>Joseph</forename>
                     <surname>Howard, Jr.</surname>
                  </persName>
                  <persName type="display">Joseph  Howard, Jr.</persName>
                  <birth when="1833">1833</birth>
                  <death when="1908">1908</death>
                  <note>
                     <p>Joseph Howard, Jr., was a prominent journalist who worked for the Brooklyn <hi rend="italic">Eagle</hi>, New York <hi rend="italic">Herald</hi>, and the New York <hi rend="italic">World</hi>. 
                     During the Civil War he was briefly imprisoned for creating a hoax document with Francis Avery Mallison that Lincoln had requested a draft for 400,000 troops (just months after the destruction 
                     of the New York City draft riots). He was a founding member of the New York Press Club; he was also a member of Henry Ward Beecher's Plymouth Church, and published a biography of Beecher in 1887. 
                     In a manuscript fragment discovered in one of Clemens's books, he called Howard a "cesspool-siphon of night-cart journalism" (Item #497, A1911 Auction Catalog facsimile, in CU-MARK).</p>
                  </note>
               </person>
   
<person xml:id="JRO">
    <persName type="display">James R. Osgood</persName>
    <persName type="full">Osgood<surname></surname>, <forename type="first">James</forename> <forename type="middle">Ripley</forename></persName>
    <birth when="1836">1836</birth>
    <death when="1892">1892</death>
    <sex></sex>
   <note><p>James Ripley Osgood's long career in publishing began as a clerk for Ticknor &amp; Fields, which by 1864 became Fields, Osgood &amp; Co. Upon the retirement of Fields in 1871 Osgood formed James Osgood &amp; Co. with two sons of William Ticknor.  As publishers of the Atlantic Monthly and *** of novels of Harte, Ttowe, Howells, ***.   SLC. Prince and the Pauper, the Stolen White Elephant, Life on the Mississippi. In 1885 the firm went bankrupt, and Osgood retired and moveed to London to work for Harper and Brothers.</p></note>
  </person> 

 </listPerson>
 
   <listOrg type="other">
      <org xml:id="AuthC">
         <orgName>Authors Club</orgName>
      </org>
      <org xml:id="Fenc">
         <orgName>Fencers' Club</orgName>
      </org>
      <org xml:id="AmCop">
         <orgName>American Copyright League</orgName>
      </org>
      <org xml:id="Ply">
         <orgName>Plymouth Church</orgName>
      </org>
      <org xml:id="Lot">
         <orgName>Lotos Club</orgName>
      </org>
      <org xml:id="Play">
         <orgName>Players' Club</orgName>
      </org>
      <org xml:id="UnivC">
         <orgName>University Club</orgName>
      </org>
      <org xml:id="HartC">
         <orgName>Hartford Club</orgName>
      </org>
      <org xml:id="bio14242">
         <orgName>Hartford Monday Evening Club</orgName>
      </org>
      <org xml:id="AtlM">
         <orgName><hi rend="italic">Atlantic Monthly</hi>, The</orgName>
         <desc></desc>
      </org>
      <org xml:id="CenC">
         <orgName>Century Club</orgName>
      </org>
      <org xml:id="CenM">
         <orgName><hi rend="italic">Century Magazine</hi>, The</orgName>
      </org>
      <org xml:id="NYT">
         <orgName>New York <hi rend="italic">Times</hi></orgName>
         <desc></desc>
      </org>
      <org xml:id="NYPr">
         <orgName>New York Press Club</orgName>
      </org>
      <org xml:id="Kin">
         <orgName>The Kinsmen</orgName>
      </org>
      <org xml:id="Pap">
         <orgName>Papyrus Club</orgName>
      </org>
      <org xml:id="Til">
         <orgName>Tile Club</orgName>
      </org>
      <org xml:id="CU">
         <orgName><hi>Christian Union</hi>, The</orgName>
      </org>
      <org xml:id="SocAA">
         <orgName>Society of American Artists</orgName>
      </org>
 
   </listOrg>
   <listEvent>
      <event xml:id="evt001">
         <label>Quaker City Excursion</label>
      </event>
   </listEvent>
   
   <bibl>
      <listRelation type="personal">
         <relation name="co-author" mutual="#SLC #CDW"/>
         <relation name="co-author" mutual="#GWC #GEW"/>
         <relation name="co-author" mutual="#HCB #BM"/>
         <relation name="spouse" mutual="#STK #JCK"/>
         <relation name="spouse" mutual="#OWP #NBP"/>
         <relation name="spouse" mutual="#TBA #LWA"/>
         <relation name="spouse" mutual="#GEW #VW"/>
         <relation name="spouse" mutual="#EMM #FDM"/>
         <relation name="spouse" mutual="#SF MFF"/>
         <relation name="sibling" mutual="#RWG #JG"/>
         <relation name="sibling" mutual="#DF #CF"/>
         <relation name="in-law" mutual="#HCK #JHJr"/>
         <relation name="in-law" mutual="#JPG #JH"/>
         <relation name="in-law" mutual="#ECS #EDS"/>
         <relation name="parent" active="#JEK" passive="#CLK"/>
         <relation name="parent" active="#MSB" passive="#CYB"/>
         <relation name="parent" active="#GEW" passive="#EBW"/>
      </listRelation>
      <listRelation type="social">
         <relation name="autograph_seeker" active="#FJ #CSF #SRF #CF #ACD #CYB #RSG #JG #HPG #JPCH #JH #JMH #DF #JWB #CCD #BHC #JHJ #JBM #RC #WC #GWC #HCB #HWB #JSB #HHB #CCB #NB #MSB #CDW #HFG #JHS #CGW #GEW #ET #TBA #ECS #FHS #RWR #WS #HES #TWK #NS #LH #JBP #TFP #GWS #HM #FDM #JPL #JCK #HCK #JEK #CLK #RUJ #HI #DS" passive="#SLC"/>
         <relation name="circ_but_no_letter" active="#EGW #VB #JHT #AWD #HFG" passive="#SLC"/>
         <relation type="business_assoc" mutual="#JBP #SLC"/>
         <relation type="business_assoc" mutual="#DS #SLC"/>
         <relation type="business_assoc" mutual="#GWC #JBP"/>
         <relation type="business_assoc" mutual="#RWG #RUJ"/>
         <relation type="business_assoc" mutual="#WS #CF"/>
         <relation type="business_assoc" mutual="#JSB #GEW"/>
         <relation type="business_assoc" mutual="#JBP #HWB"/>
         <relation type="business_assoc" mutual="#WS #DF"/>
         <relation type="close_friend" mutual="#LH #JBM"/>
         <relation type="close_friend" mutual="#RWR #HWB"/>
         <relation type="close_friend" mutual="#ET #HI"/>
         <relation type="close_friend" mutual="#HCB #JBM"/>
         <relation type="close_friend" mutual="#JG #CLK"/>
         <relation type="close_friend" mutual="#GEW #GWC"/>
         <relation type="close_friend" mutual="#JG #HM"/>
         <relation type="close_friend" mutual="#LH #HCB"/>
         <relation type="close_friend" mutual="#CSF #JRO"/>
         <relation type="close_friend" mutual="#GWC #HHB"/>
         <relation type="close_friend" mutual="#NB #FBH"/>
         <relation type="close_friend" mutual="#GWC #RWG"/>
         <relation type="close_friend" mutual="#HM #JG"/>
         <relation type="close_friend" mutual="#SLC #TBA"/>
         <relation type="close_friend" mutual="#HI #HM"/>
         <relation type="close_friend" mutual="#CCD #HWB"/>
         <relation type="close_friend" mutual="#HM #RWG"/>
         <relation type="close_friend" mutual="#ET #HM"/>
         <relation type="close_friend" mutual="#RWG #ECS"/>
         <relation type="close_friend" mutual="#ACD #CDW"/>
         <relation type="close_friend" mutual="#FJ #LH"/>
         <relation type="close_friend" mutual="#FJ #CDW"/>
         <relation type="close_friend" mutual="#JHT #DS"/>
         <relation type="close_friend" mutual="#CLK #HI"/>
         <relation type="close_friend" mutual="#CLK #ET"/>
         <relation type="close_friend" mutual="#CLK #JG"/>
         <relation type="close_friend" mutual="#RC #TWK"/>
         <relation type="close_friend" mutual="#JBM #LH"/>
         <relation type="close_friend" mutual="#HCB #ECS"/>
         <relation type="close_friend" mutual="#HI #ET"/>
         <relation type="close_friend" mutual="#HCB #LH"/>
         <relation type="close_friend" mutual="#TBA #ECS"/>
         <relation type="close_friend" mutual="#HCK #HWB"/>
         <relation type="close_friend" mutual="#HCK #FJ"/>
         <relation type="close_friend" mutual="#JRO #CSF"/>
         <relation type="close_friend" mutual="#ECS #TBA"/>
         <relation type="close_friend" mutual="#HI #JPCH"/>
         <relation type="close_friend" mutual="#JPCH #HI"/>
         <relation type="close_friend" mutual="#HFG #TWK"/>
         <relation type="close_friend" mutual="#JBM #HCB"/>
         <relation type="close_friend" mutual="#JHT #SLC"/>
         <relation name="clubmates" n="AmCopLeague" mutual="#RUJ #SLC #LH #JPL #RWG #JBM #TWK #HHB #CDW #ECS #RC LH"/>	
         <relation name="clubmates" n="AuthClub" mutual="#RWG #RUJ #HCB #JBM #JPL #GWC #NB #TWK #ECS #CDW #GEW #HHB #FHS #HES #JH #TBA #CCB #SLC #WC #GWS"/>
         <relation name="clubmates" n="Century" mutual="#RWR #RUJ #NB #CCB #TBA #FHS #ECS #RWG #RC"/>
         <relation name="clubmates" n="Fencers" mutual="#WC #GWS #RWG #LH #CCB #HHB #FDM #RUJ #JBM #JPL"/>
         <relation name="clubmates" n="Hartford  #JHT #SLC #TFP #ACD #JWB"/>
         <relation name="clubmates" n="Lotos" mutual="#HFG #SLC #JBP #NS #TWK #NB"/>
         <relation name="clubmates" n="MondayEve" mutual="#SLC #CDW #ACD"/>
         <relation name="clubmates" n="NewYorkPress" mutual="#HFG #JHJr #SLC #HCK #HWB #SRF"/>
         <relation name="clubmates" n="Papyrus" mutual="#GEW #CDW #TBA #CSF"/>
         <relation name="clubmates" n="PlymouthChurch" mutual="#JHJr #DS #MSB #FJ #HWB #HCK #CCD #RWR"/>
         <relation name="clubmates" n="QuakerCity" mutual="BHC #SLC #MSB #CCD"/>
         <relation name="clubmates" n="SocietyAmAss" mutual="#FDM #RSG"/>
         <relation name="clubmates" n="Kinsmen" mutual="#JH #FDM #HCB #JBM #RSG #LH #JRO #JPL #RWG #SLC #HI"/>
         <relation name="clubmates" n="Tile" mutual="#FDM #FHS #NS #RSG"/>
         <relation name="clubmates" n="University" mutual="FJ #CDW"/>
         <relation name="employer" n="#ChrU" active="#HWB" passive="#FJ #HCK"/>
         <relation name="lecture_mgr" active="#OWP" passive="#GWC"/>
         <relation name="lecture_mgr" active="#JBP" passive="#HWB"/>
         <relation name="litigant" mutual="SLC NB CCD NYT"/>
         <relation name="neighbor" mutual="#CDW #SLC #ACD"/>
         <relation name="neighbor" mutual="#HWB #DS #JHS SSC"/>
         <relation name="neighbor" mutual="#TBA #HLP"/>
         <relation name="stage_mgr" active="#SF" passive="#HM"/>
         <relation name="publisher" active="#JRO" passive="#GEW #SLC #GWC #JMH"/>
      </listRelation>
   </bibl>

</div1>
</body>
</text>
</TEI>

