<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<?oxygen RNGSchema="schema/mtp4.rng" type="xml"?><TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink"
     xmlns:xs="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema"
     xmlns:math="http://www.w3.org/1998/Math/MathML"
     xmlns:svg="http://www.w3.org/2000/svg"
     xmlns:xi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XInclude"
     xml:id="UCLC">
   <teiHeader type="CDL-TEI:MTP">
      <fileDesc>
        <titleStmt>
            <title>Letter from George E. Waring, Jr. to Samuel L. Clemens : an electronic text</title>
        </titleStmt>
        <publicationStmt>
            <publisher/>
        </publicationStmt>
        <sourceDesc>
            <bibl n="copy">MS, Mark Twain Papers, The Bancroft Library, University of California,
                Berkeley (CU-MARK).</bibl>
        </sourceDesc>
      </fileDesc>
      <encodingDesc>
        <variantEncoding location="internal" method="double-end-point"/>
      </encodingDesc>
      <profileDesc/>
      <revisionDesc>
         <change/>
      </revisionDesc>
   </teiHeader>
   <text type="letter">
      <body>
         <pb facs="waringg01.jpg" xml:id="pb0001" n="1"/>
         <head type="metadata">
             <name corresp="#GEW">George E. Waring, Jr.</name> to <addressee>
               <name corresp="#SLC">Samuel L. Clemens</name>
            </addressee>
             <date when="1884-03-30">30 March 1884</date> &#x2022; <name type="place">Washington, D. C.</name>
            <sourceline>(MS: CU-MARK, UCLC 41849)</sourceline>
         </head>
         <div1 type="letter" xml:id="lt0001">
            <opener>
               <letterhead>
                  <l rend="center">National Board of Health</l>
                  <l><space extent="22"/>Washington, D. C.</l>
	       </letterhead>
                <dateline rend="indentdateline"><date when="1884-03-30">March 30<hi rend="superscript">th</hi> 1884</date></dateline>
               <salute>My dear Clemens:</salute>
            </opener>
             <p rend="text-indent:3">I have lately fallen into a most unfortunate dispute with our dear old friend and despoiler—<name corresp="#JRO">Osgood</name>.<note xml:id="an0001" place="foot" type="an" n="1">Osgood was the publisher of Waring's <hi rend="italic">Whip and Spur</hi> (1875), <hi rend="italic">The Farmer's Vacation</hi> (1876), <hi rend="italic">Bride of the Rhine</hi> (1878), <hi rend="italic">Vix</hi> (1883), and <hi rend="italic">Ruby</hi> (1883).</note></p>
            <p rend="text-indent:2">It would be too long to tell you how it all came about, nor is my memory clear as to the details. I may have been partaking of his hospitality or I may not. Whether I had or not, as I tell you, my memory is not clear as to details, but of this cardinal fact I am clear in my recollection, and the insult has [been] <pb facs="waringg02.jpg" xml:id="pb0002" n="2"/>rankling in my bosom for more than a month:—he called me a “Cape Cod Turkey.”<note xml:id="an0002" place="foot" type="an" n="2">In nineteenth-century slang this term denoted salt cod. Waring spent many years in Newport, R.I., and maintained a summer home there. Calling him a Cape Codder is something of a stretch.</note></p>
            <p rend="text-indent:2">You know what this means,—it means blood,—blood or an apology.</p>
             <p rend="text-indent:2">Now Osgood—by the way he is a mere Gobbler,<note type="an" place="foot" xml:id="an0003" n="3">This pun plays on the despoiling publisher motif introduced above.</note> as any author with rights to tell knows,<note xml:id="an0004" place="foot" type="an" n="4">Osgood, who was popular with the authors he published, was a poor businessman, and filed for bankrupcy on behalf of J. R. Osgood &amp; Co. in 1885. The first book he published for Mark Twain was <hi rend="italic">A True Story, and The Recent Carnival of Crime</hi> (1872), followed nearly a decade later by <hi rend="italic">The Prince and the Pauper</hi> (1881) and <hi rend="italic">The Stolen White Elephant</hi> (1882). In 1882 he accompanied Clemens on a return trip along the great river to gather material for <hi rend="italic">Life on the Mississippi,</hi> which Osgood marketed so poorly that Clemens never published with him again. At this time Clemens and Osgood were still squabbling about the poor returns from <hi rend="italic">Life on the Mississippi</hi>. See, for instance, Osgood to SLC, 26 March 1884 (MS in CU-MARK). Clemens noted the following book-keeping discrepancies in his notebook: "About middle October, '83,  Osgood owed  me $33,250. T[---] Paid me $5,000 by check. Gave me acceptances at 3 months from Oct 15, for $5,000, $10,000 &amp; $5,000 ($20,000. Leaving $8,250 unprovided for (NB 22)."</note>—Osgood wont make an apology—he never would—and I see only this way out of it: You know him and before now you have spoken for him. Speak for him now and make me his apology <hi rend="italic">over your own name</hi>, and to save his life—or that of Yours Truly,
            </p>
            <closer>
                <signed rend="indentctrsig"><hi rend="paraph">George E. Waring Jr</hi><note type="an" place="foot" xml:id="an005" n="5"> Clemens knew Waring as early as 1875, when they socialized together in Newport (see SLC to Waring, 14 July 1875). Waring's association with Cable began In 1880, when Waring was sent to New Orleans to collect social statistics for the tenth Census. He contacted Cable to help him by adding historical material, having read and enjoyed <hi rend="italic">Creole Days</hi> on the train en route. Waring remained a strong supporter of Cable, both by introducing him to his publisher, Osgood, to whom Cable promised <hi rend="italic">Dr. Sevier</hi> (despite a firm relationship with Scribber's &amp; Sons), and during his first lecture tour in 1883. Waring, along with Gilder, Warner and Clemens, sat on the dais at his Hartford performance.</note></signed>
            </closer>
            <postscript>
               <p rend="text-indent:1">But don’t let him call me a “Cape Cod Turkey” again!</p>
            </postscript>
         </div1>
         <div1 type="post-transmission">
            <div2 type="envelope">
               <pb facs="waringg-env.jpg" xml:id="pb0003" n="0003"/>
    <ab>Samuel L. Clemens, Esq. | Hartford, Conn.
        <note type="pt" xml:id="pt001" place="inline" n="return address:"><hi rend="xs-smallcaps">national board of health | official business.</hi></note>
        <note type="pt" xml:id="pt0002" place="inline" n="postmarked:"><hi rend="xs-smallcaps">washington &#x2022; d.c. mar 31 8 am  1884</hi></note> 
    <note type="ed" place="inline" xml:id="in0002">docketed by SLC, in pencil:</note> Waring | mention
</ab>
            </div2>
         </div1>
         <div1 type="commentary" xml:id="cm0001">
         </div1>
      </body>
   </text>
</TEI>
