<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<?oxygen RNGSchema="http://www.scholarlyediting.org/scholarlyediting.rng" type="xml"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xml:lang="eng">
    <teiHeader>
        <fileDesc>
            <titleStmt>
                <title level="a" type="main">Satire in Circulation: James Russell Lowell's "LETTER
                    FROM A VOLUNTEER IN SALTILLO"</title>
                <author key="Last name, first name">Thompson, Todd</author>
                <author key="Last name, first name">Showalter, Jessica</author>
            </titleStmt>
            <editionStmt>
                <edition>
                    <date>2015</date>
                </edition>
            </editionStmt>
            <publicationStmt>
                <idno type="file">intro.lowelledition</idno>
                <idno type="edition">lowelledition</idno>
                <authority>Scholary Editing: The Annual of the Association for Documentary
                    Editing</authority>
                <address>
                    <addrLine>http://www.scholarlyediting.org</addrLine>
                </address>
                <publisher>Association for Documentary Editing</publisher>
                <publisher>University of Nebraska&#8211;Lincoln</publisher>
                <distributor>
                    <name>Center for Digital Research in the Humanities</name>
                    <address>
                        <addrLine>319 Love Library</addrLine>
                        <addrLine>University of Nebraska&#8211;Lincoln</addrLine>
                        <addrLine>Lincoln, NE 68588-4100</addrLine>
                        <addrLine>http://cdrh.unl.edu</addrLine>
                    </address>
                </distributor>
                <date>2015</date>
                <availability>
                    <p>Scholary Editing: The Annual of the Association for Documentary Editing is
                        freely distributed by the Association for Documentary Editing and the Center
                        for Digital Research in the Humanities at the University of Nebraska-Lincoln
                        and licensed under a Creative Commons Attribution-NonCommercial-ShareAlike
                        3.0 Unported License</p>
                </availability>
            </publicationStmt>
            <seriesStmt>
                <title level="j">Scholarly Editing: The Annual of the Association for Documentary
                    Editing</title>
                <respStmt>
                    <resp>editor</resp>
                    <name xml:id="ag" key="Gailey, Amanda A.">Amanda Gailey</name>
                </respStmt>
                <respStmt>
                    <resp>editor</resp>
                    <name xml:id="awj" key="Jewell, Andrew W.">Andrew Jewell</name>
                </respStmt>
                <idno type="vol">36</idno>
                <idno type="ISSN">2167-1257</idno>
            </seriesStmt>
            <sourceDesc>
                <bibl>
                    <note>Born digital.</note>
                </bibl>
            </sourceDesc>
        </fileDesc>
        <revisionDesc>
            <change when="2014-08-24"><name xml:id="jms" key="Showalter, Jessica">Jessica
                    Showalter</name> markup in TEI XML</change>
        </revisionDesc>
    </teiHeader>
    <text>
        <front>
            <head type="main">Introduction</head>
            <byline>Todd Thompson</byline>
            <byline>Jessica Showalter</byline>
        </front>
        <body>
            <div type="section">
                <p>On August 27, 1847, a poem from the <hi rend="italic">Boston Courier</hi> was
                    reprinted in the <hi rend="italic">National Anti-Slavery Standard</hi> under the
                    headline "LATE FROM MEXICO," situating it as news from the still-raging
                    US-Mexico War. An editorial note stated that the versified letter "is certainly
                    the most valuable document we have yet received from the seat of war." Subheaded
                    "LETTER FROM A VOLUNTEER IN SALTILLO," the poem unmasks the contradictions
                    between recruiting rhetoric and the actual war, a typical subject in similar
                    "letters from the front" then popular in newspapers. But "LETTER FROM A
                    VOLUNTEER IN SALTILLO" was not a real letter; rather, it was one of nine protest
                    poems written pseudonymously by James Russell Lowell (in the guise of
                    farmer-poet Hosea Biglow) between 1846 and 1848 that satirized the war. Each
                    poem was printed initially in either the <hi rend="italic">Boston Courier</hi>
                    or the <hi rend="italic">National Anti-Slavery Standard</hi>, and each was
                    reprinted widely across the nation. Eventually, Lowell collected these poems
                    into book form in 1848. This digital edition offers a comparison of changes in
                    orthography and punctuation as the dialect poem migrated from reprint to
                    reprint, but more importantly, it situates the poem within the context of
                    surrounding newspaper articles. Appearing next to news of the events it targets,
                    Lowell's satire both comments on that news and re-presents it through poetry. As
                    this digital edition demonstrates, the meaning of the poem shifts as its news
                    context shifts from rival northeastern reform newspapers to a cosmopolitan
                    periodical focused on international affairs, to a Democratic newspaper on the
                    Texas frontier, to a Whig newspaper in a small New Hampshire town, then in its
                    dramatically revised book form, and ultimately, to a Pennsylvanian newspaper's
                    remix of that book edition. This digital edition of "LETTER FROM A VOLUNTEER IN
                    SALTILLO" is thus not just a study of textual variants but also a story about
                    editors and their choices.</p>
                <p>Lowell's series of poems protesting the war is "ranked high as a classic of
                    American political satire" and is "perhaps the US-Mexico War text that is most
                    familiar to scholars today." <note n="1">Robert W. Johannsen, <hi rend="italic"
                            >To the Halls of the Montezumas: The Mexican War in the American
                            Imagination</hi> (New York: Oxford University Press, 1985), 218; Shelley
                        Streeby, "1846, June: James Russell Lowell's Biglow Papers Are Cut from the
                        Boston Courier and Pasted onto Workshop Walls All over Boston," in <hi
                            rend="italic">A New Literary History of America</hi>, ed. Greil Marcus
                        and Werner Sollors (Cambridge, MA: Harvard University Press, 2009),
                        260.</note> Of the nine Biglow poems, we chose to present "LETTER FROM A
                    VOLUNTEER IN SALTILLO" for several reasons. First, unlike several other Biglow
                    poems, the poem features interplay between all three of Lowell's main satiric
                    characters: the Massachusetts farmer-poet Hosea Biglow, in whose dialect verse
                    all the poems appear; his parson, editor, and literary patron Homer Wilbur, who
                    occasionally introduces these pieces and is referred to often; and Biglow's
                    friend Birdofredum Sawin, whose letters from the front in Mexico Biglow
                    sometimes transcribes into verse. Second, the poem's persistent allusions to
                    contemporary people, perspectives, and events offer useful historical insight
                    but also require contextualizing annotations for the twenty-first-century
                    reader. Third, more than any other Biglow poem, the "LETTER FROM A VOLUNTEER IN
                    SALTILLO"&#8212;in its title, format, and content&#8212;is presented as a
                    firsthand account from the seat of war and is therefore offered (and treated by
                    editors) as, to a certain extent, news, thus revealing the blurriness of lines
                    between literature and news in mid-nineteenth-century periodicals. Our edition
                    seeks to recreate the multiple contexts in which Lowell's very popular poem was
                    situated and read in newspapers.</p>
                <p>As Kevin G. Barnhurst and John Nerone have argued, "Readers do not read bits of
                    text and pictures. What they read is the paper, the tangible object as a whole.
                    They enter the news environment and interact with its surface textures and
                    deeper shapes. Readers don't read the news; they swim in it." <note n="2">Kevin
                        G. Barnhurst and John Nerone, <hi rend="italic">The Form of News: A
                            History</hi> (New York: Guilford Press, 2001), 7.</note> In viewing the
                    images that depict "LETTER FROM A VOLUNTEER IN SALTILLO" on a full page of
                    newsprint alongside other stories about the war, readers of this digital edition
                    temporarily "enter the news environment." When the reader considers the original
                    poem and six newspaper and periodical reprints presented in this variorum, a
                    story emerges about the power of editors to shape readers' reception of
                    literature as well as news. Editors, in making decisions about the form of a
                    newspaper issue&#8212;that is, which stories to reprint from other sources,
                    whether and how to attribute them, what topical heads to use, layout, order, and
                    so on&#8212;shape the "meaning making" of the content represented on those
                    pages. Again according to Barnhurst and Nerone, "Once readers enter the
                    newspaper, they continue to make choices, but the form imposes tacit rules that
                    allow for certain reading practices and work against others. . . . the form of
                    news constructs the audience's field of vision." <note n="3">Barnhurst and
                        Nerone, <hi rend="italic">Form of News</hi>, 6&#8211;7.</note> In an era
                    that featured rampant reprinting of stories from other papers, newspapers
                    differed not so much in the specific news items they presented as in how they
                    presented them. This edition highlights such re-presentations by identifying the
                    different editorial uses to which one very timely and political poem was put
                    over an eighteen-month span.</p>
            </div>
            <div type="section">
                <head type="sub">Hosea Biglow and the Culture of Reprinting</head>
                <p>The poem in the <hi rend="italic">National Anti-Slavery Standard</hi> was itself
                    reprinted from the <hi rend="italic">Boston Courier</hi>, and was reprinted many
                    times in other newspapers and periodicals across the country. According to
                    Lowell, his Biglow poems were "copied everywhere," and he "saw them pinned up in
                    workshops" and "heard them quoted, and their authorship debated." <note n="4"
                        >James Russell Lowell, <hi rend="italic">The Biglow Papers: Second
                            Series</hi> (Boston: Ticknor and Fields, 1867), vii&#8211;viii.</note>
                    Reviews of the 1848 book edition also tended to mention the Biglow poems'
                    previous popularity and wide circulation in the press. <hi rend="italic"
                        >Holden's Review</hi> in early 1849 claimed the poems "have been copied in
                    every paper of the Union, from Maine to Texas, and . . . have been almost as
                    extensively copied into English periodicals"; the <hi rend="italic">Literary
                        World</hi> referred to the poems as "known to the people of the North
                    through the Boston newspapers"; and <hi rend="italic">Harbinger Review</hi> in
                    its review of the book claimed that the poems "as they first came long detached
                    in newspapers had not a little influence in bringing Massachusetts and the North
                    upon their feet, to take the moral ground, amid wicked political party issues."
                        <note n="5">"Meliboeus Hipponax . . . ," <hi rend="italic">Holden's
                            Review</hi>, January 1, 1849, 50; "New England Satire," <hi
                            rend="italic">Literary World</hi>, December 2, 1848, 872; "Review," <hi
                            rend="italic">Harbinger Review</hi>, December 23, 1848, 62.</note>
                    Indeed, the poems were written and disseminated during a time when a "culture of
                    reprinting" prevailed in the United States. <note n="6">On reprinting in
                        nineteenth-century America, see Richard Brodhead, <hi rend="italic">Culture
                            of Letters: Scenes of Reading and Writing in Nineteenth-Century
                            America</hi> (Chicago: University of Chicago Press, 1995), and Meredith
                        L. McGill, <hi rend="italic">American Literature and the Culture of
                            Reprinting, 1834&#8211;1853</hi> (Philadelphia: University of
                        Pennsylvania Press, 2002).</note> Postal rates for newspapers (the "mammoth
                    weeklies" excepted) remained, even after the Postal Reform Act of 1845, at 1792
                    levels of a maximum of 1.5 cents for delivery anywhere in the country.
                    Additionally, the 1845 act stipulated that newspapers garnered free postage when
                    delivered within thirty miles of the place of publication. Free exchange of
                    newspapers among editors remained in place. <note n="7">Richard B. Kielbowicz,
                            <hi rend="italic">News in the Mail: The Press, Post Office, and Public
                            Information, 1700&#8211;1860s</hi> (New York: Greenwood Press, 1989), 3,
                        58, 84.</note> By one estimate, news accounted for approximately 95 percent
                    of the total weight of US mail by the 1830s. <note n="8">Leonard C. Thomas, <hi
                            rend="italic">News for All: America's Coming-of-Age with the Press</hi>
                        (New York: Oxford University Press, 1995), 13.</note> This statistic reveals
                    the intensity of circulating news in the antebellum United States. As a result,
                    newspapers in the era of the partisan press tended to be amalgams of other
                    newspapers, "all filtered through the editor's voice." <note n="9">Barnhurst and
                        Nerone, <hi rend="italic">Form of News</hi>, 102.</note> This would soon
                    change as use of the electric telegraph&#8212;patented in 1837 by Samuel
                    Morse&#8212;led to the advent of wire services. This shift began during the
                    US-Mexico War but was not particularly widespread at the time of Lowell's
                    writing.</p>
                <p>This culture of reprinting, of course, gave Lowell's poems a much wider audience
                    than they would otherwise have. Lowell pointed out in a letter to Mary Peabody
                    (wife of transcendentalist and education reformer Horace Mann) that "M<hi
                        rend="superscript">r</hi> Biglow has a thousand readers for my one, &amp;
                    that he has raised the laugh at War &amp; Slavery &amp; Doughfaces to some
                    purpose." <note n="10">James Russell Lowell, quoted in Thomas Wortham,
                        introduction to <hi rend="italic">The Biglow Papers</hi> [First Series], by
                        James Russell Lowell (DeKalb: Northern Illinois University Press, 1977),
                        xiv.</note> In fact, without editors' exchanges, his work from the <hi
                        rend="italic">National Anti-Slavery Standard</hi> might not have reached
                    Southern readers at all. In a move emblematic of the power of postal workers as
                    censors, a Baltimore mail clerk in 1843 tore up a copy of the <hi rend="italic"
                        >National Anti-Slavery Standard</hi> in front of its subscriber, saying, "I
                    can't pass this." Postmasters at this time often served a surveillance function,
                    noting who took in abolitionist papers, and they had government support: as
                    president, Andrew Jackson proposed that postal records be published to identify
                    Americans subscribing to "subversive" papers. <note n="11">Thomas, <hi
                            rend="italic">News for All</hi>, 14.</note> But Lowell's antislavery
                    poems did make it into Southern papers (though stripped of their radicalism),
                    thanks in part to the vast network of circulating newspapers and editorial
                    reprinting.</p>
                <p>Lowell certainly recognized the power of reprinting and encouraged it. After
                    publishing his first Biglow poem in the <hi rend="italic">Boston Courier</hi> in
                    1846, Lowell wrote to Sydney H. Gay, editor of the <hi rend="italic">National
                        Anti-Slavery Standard</hi> (where Lowell had recently signed on as
                    corresponding editor), "You will find a squib of mine in this week's <hi
                        rend="italic">Courier</hi>. I wish it to continue anonymous, for I wish
                    Slavery to think it has as many enemies as possible. . . . I suppose you will
                    copy it, and, if so, I wish you would correct a misprint or two." <note n="12"
                        >James Russell Lowell to Sydney H. Gay, June 16, 1846, in <hi rend="italic"
                            >The Letters of James Russell Lowell</hi>, ed. Charles Eliot Norton (New
                        York: Harper and Brothers, 1894), 115&#8211;16.</note> Here Lowell
                    encourages Gay to reprint his Biglow poem, acknowledges the power of anonymity
                    in a publishing environment where his byline and initials commonly appear
                    underneath antislavery essays, and recognizes, cheerfully enough, the
                    instability of a reprinted text. Lowell was also intensely aware of the
                    importance of timeliness to the reception of his Biglow satires. In a letter to
                    Gay on April 27, 1848, Lowell enclosed two poems and wrote, "Both will keep a
                    week, I think." <note n="13">James Russell Lowell to Sydney H. Gay, April 27,
                        1848, in <hi rend="italic">Letters</hi>, 128&#8211;29.</note> Similarly, in
                    explaining to Gay why he sent his fifth Biglow poem, "The Debate in the Sennit,
                    Sot to a Nursery Rhyme," to the <hi rend="italic">Boston Courier</hi> instead of
                    the <hi rend="italic">National Anti-Slavery Standard</hi>, he wrote, "Had I
                    thought of writing it soon enough I should have sent it to you. But it would not
                    have kept so well for a fortnight." <note n="14">James Russell Lowell to Sydney
                        H. Gay, May 5, 1848, in <hi rend="italic">Letters</hi>, 128&#8211;29.</note>
                    In both cases, Lowell implied that his satire had an expiration date and needed
                    to be fresh to be effective. It is interesting, then, that Lowell spent so much
                    time and effort in revising the poems into a book in 1848.</p>
                <p>To an extent, our research verifies Lowell's self-reporting of the popularity of
                    his Biglow poems. We have found reprints of the poems in newspapers printed in
                    Massachusetts, New York, New Hampshire, Vermont, Maine, Pennsylvania, Ohio, New
                    Jersey, South Carolina, Georgia, Texas, and Washington, DC, geographical
                    coverage that encompasses much of the pre-1848 United States. We have even
                    tracked down reprints in newspapers printed in Leeds and Liverpool, England.
                    Access to online databases that in many cases offer advanced full-text searching
                    options has accelerated our search for reprints. To date, we have mined digital
                    databases including <hi rend="italic">Nineteenth Century US Newspapers</hi>; <hi
                        rend="italic">America's Historical Newspapers</hi>; <hi rend="italic"
                        >American Periodicals Series (1740&#8211;1900)</hi>; <hi rend="italic"
                        >American Antiquarian Society Historical Periodicals Collection: Series
                        3</hi>; <hi rend="italic">Accessible Archives</hi>; <hi rend="italic"
                        >Chronicling America</hi>; <hi rend="italic">Nineteenth-Century British
                        Library Newspapers</hi>; <hi rend="italic">British Periodicals</hi>; <hi
                        rend="italic">British Newspapers 1600&#8211;1950</hi>; and the <hi
                        rend="italic">London Times</hi>. Our search strategies were expressly
                    developed with the nineteenth-century "culture of reprinting" in mind. For
                    example, the Biglow poems rarely appeared with attributions, and if they did,
                    the byline was often a pseudonym ("H. B." or "B. Sawin"), so author searches
                    were largely futile. Title searches also proved to be a dead end in that
                    newspapers regularly retitled the reprinted material. Keyword searches based on
                    character and place names were more effective, as were searches for phrases such
                    as first lines or refrains. However, keeping in mind that the dialect poems
                    featured irregular spelling, punctuation, and slang, we often tried several
                    versions of the same line to accumulate results. As of October 2014, our
                    searches harvested almost fifty reprints of the nine Biglow poems, including the
                    first appearance of "LETTER FROM A VOLUNTEER IN SALTILLO" in the August 18,
                    1847, <hi rend="italic">Boston Courier</hi> and the following six newspaper
                    reprints of that poem: <list type="bulleted">
                        <item><hi rend="italic">National Anti-Slavery Standard</hi> (August 26,
                            1847)</item>
                        <item><hi rend="italic">The Liberator</hi> (August 27, 1847)</item>
                        <item><hi rend="italic">Littell's Living Age</hi> (September 11,
                            1847)</item>
                        <item><hi rend="italic">Texas Union</hi> (October 16, 1847)</item>
                        <item><hi rend="italic">New Hampshire Sentinel</hi> (November 11,
                            1847)</item>
                        <item><hi rend="italic">Sunbury American</hi> (December 23, 1848)</item>
                    </list>The original and these six reprints, as well as the 1848 book edition
                        (<hi rend="italic">Meliboeus-Hipponax: The Biglow Papers</hi>), serve as
                    eight witnesses in this edition. While we have identified textual variants from
                    one printing to the next, our main interest lies in how the poem's presentation
                    in various periodicals shifts its reception by news-hungry readers. As this
                    variorum of Lowell's poem shows, editorial decisions ranging from
                    letter-by-letter typesetting to arrangement on the page juxtaposing it against
                    other news alters its meaning.</p>
            </div>
            <div type="section">
                <head type="sub"><hi rend="italic">Boston Courier</hi></head>
                <p>The poem first appeared on the front page of the <hi rend="italic">Boston
                        Courier</hi> under the heading "LETTER FROM A VOLUNTEER IN SALTILLO,"
                    alongside various advertisements and several articles about religion. The <hi
                        rend="italic">Boston Courier</hi> was a "lively and literary" Boston
                    newspaper edited by Joseph T. Buckingham and an organ for Massachusetts
                    politician Daniel Webster. According to newspaper historian Frank Luther Mott,
                    Buckingham was "one of the most respected newspaper men in New England." <note
                        n="15">Mott, <hi rend="italic">American Journalism: A History of Newspapers
                            in the United States through 260 Years: 1690 to 1950</hi>, rev. ed. (New
                        York: Macmillan, 1950), 262.</note> Buckingham generally "applauded the
                    prosecution of the war with Mexico" but seems to have been open to dissenting
                    voices, including those of James Russell Lowell and Henry David Thoreau. <note
                        n="16">See Gary Scharnhorst, "'Conflict of Laws': A Lost Essay by Henry
                        David Thoreau," <hi rend="italic">New England Quarterly</hi> 61 (1988):
                        569&#8211;71.</note> Lowell mentions this divergence of political opinion in
                    a letter to the editor that precedes the poem. Hosea Biglow, who misspells
                    Buckingham's name and addresses the letter to "Mister Buckinum," explains that
                    Parson Wilbur encouraged him to send the anti-war poem specifically to
                    Buckingham despite his pro-war sentiments. According to Hosea, the parson "don't
                    ollers agree" with Buckingham, but he does "like a feller that ain't a
                    Feared."</p>
                <p>The poem's speaker, an enlisted man named Birdofredum Sawin, explains that
                    rhetoricians like former Massachusetts secretary of state John Augustus Bolles
                    inspired him to enlist with jingoistic propaganda. But upon his arrival in
                    Mexico, Sawin quickly learns to separate reality from nationalist banalities.
                    "[S]axons would be handy," he writes, "to do the berryin' down here upon the Rio
                    Grandy," where he is ordered to kill Mexicans, whom, before arriving on the
                    scene of war, he'd thought "worn't huming beans." He has since come to realize
                    that "come to look at 'em, they ain't much diff'rent from wot we be." Sawin
                    describes a harsh reality much different from the Mexico sold to him by
                    unscrupulous recruiters, and he has come to question the morality of his
                    mission. Sawin ultimately decides, "This goin' where glory waits ye, haint one
                    agreeable feetur," thus sapping the romance from the popular press's call to
                    arms. Historian Robert Johannsen writes, "For many [soldiers] the romance of the
                    war was dispelled by the realities of the soldier's life in a strange and often
                    inhospitable environment. . . . The visions of a romantic war in an exotic land,
                    dreams of 'citron groves or perfumed bowers,' quickly evaporated once the
                    volunteers arrived on the Rio Grande." <note n="17">Johannsen, <hi rend="italic"
                            >To the Halls of the Montezumas</hi>, 86&#8211;87.</note> Sawin gives
                    voice to this disenchantment by versifying and fictionalizing the letter from
                    the front genre. Through Sawin's comparisons of the ideality of recruiters' and
                    romanticizing writers' visions of the war with its mundane and vicious
                    realities, Lowell responds <hi rend="italic">in</hi> the popular press to the
                    largely pro-war rhetoric <hi rend="italic">of</hi> the popular press on the
                    front page of a newspaper that featured both sides of the debate.</p>
            </div>
            <div type="section">
                <head type="sub"><hi rend="italic">National Anti-Slavery Standard</hi></head>
                <p>In the <hi rend="italic">National Anti-Slavery Standard</hi>, too, the poem
                    appeared not in the page 4 "Poetry" section but on the front page, interspersed
                    with other news of the day. In an otherwise monolithic block of text on a large
                    sheet, the runover line breaks create extra white space, which attracts the
                    reader's eye, visually announcing it as a poem. But at the same time, it is
                    sandwiched on the front page between editorials and other "news"; its placement
                    among news items lends it textual authority even as it calls into question the
                    accuracy of standard "news" accounts of the war. This differs extensively from
                    how poetry was usually presented in the <hi rend="italic">National Anti-Slavery
                        Standard</hi>&#8212;on the back page. In the August 26, 1847, issue, the
                    poem "Eternal Justice" is separated from the prose, cordoned off in the far left
                    margin under a genre-labeling header (not to mention the fact that it is
                    remanded to the last page). This nonsatirical poetry thus has its poetry-ness,
                    not its newsworthiness, highlighted. With the Biglow poem, both are highlighted
                    simultaneously.</p>
                <p>Similar sentiments to those ironically expressed in Sawin's letter appear in an
                    editorial in the <hi rend="italic">National Anti-Slavery Standard</hi> on page 2
                    titled "The Golden Bracelet," which muses on the difference between false
                    recruiting rhetoric and the realities of the war in Mexico. The author
                    editorializes, <q rend="block">The last winter they were enlisting men in our
                        vicinity for this War with Mexico. . . . What invited them from their New
                        England mountains and shores and sky?&#8212;from their fathers and mothers,
                        their brothers and sisters, and dearer than these? Soulless presses, inhuman
                        voices, of Statesmen and partisans, vociferate patriotism, generous love of
                        their father-land and of freedom; then these same presses and sad voices cry
                        out with immitigable eagerness against tories and traitors: Yes, the Tories,
                        to whom God's truth is holier than a Government's Lie, and the sacred laws
                        of nature are dearer than the situates of Tyranny, and loyalty to Heaven is
                        a deeper reverence than slavery to a nefarious administration and a
                        crouching Congress. <note n="18">"The Golden Bracelet," <hi rend="italic"
                                >National Anti-Slavery Standard</hi>, August 26, 1847,
                        50.</note></q>This, too, is a moral protest against politicians and presses
                    for drawing young men into an immoral war. Both pieces contrast the dictates of
                    national expansion with biblical injunctions and "sacred laws." Though the
                    article is deadly earnest and the poem at points downright silly, both offer the
                    same take on the same topic from different angles in an issue-oriented reform
                    newspaper dedicated to abolishing slavery and to preventing any extension of
                    slavery into Mexico as a result of the war.</p>
            </div>
            <div type="section">
                <head type="sub"><hi rend="italic">The Liberator</hi></head>
                <p>Whereas the page layout of the reprint in the <hi rend="italic">National
                        Anti-Slavery Standard</hi> conflates news and poetry, the poem appeared on
                    the back page in the "Poetry" column in controversial abolitionist editor
                    William Lloyd Garrison's <hi rend="italic">The Liberator</hi> on August 27,
                    1847. But in spite of the layout's separation of Sawin's letter from "news," the
                    contents of that letter connect extremely well to the news items surrounding it.
                    Most jarring in its juxtaposition with the comic poem is a piece entitled
                    "Returning Volunteers," which appears on the same page. Reprinted from the <hi
                        rend="italic">Cambridge Chronicle</hi>, this letter from a woman traveling
                    through Cincinnati to a relative in Cambridge enumerates several encounters with
                    volunteer soldiers returning from the war as she passed through New Orleans,
                    Vicksburg, Louisville, and Cincinnati. She recounts a funeral procession in New
                    Orleans for several officers killed at Buena Vista before detailing with some
                    pathos the crowds on the banks in Vicksburg set to receive returning Mississippi
                    volunteers, "or what was left of them. Out of nine hundred, only three hundred
                    lived to return. Poor fellows, they looked as though they had seen hard
                    services: they were sun burnt, and many appeared as though they were not long
                    for this world." Later in the letter, she writes, "From their appearance one
                    would suppose the volunteers had had enough of Mexico. . . . If you could hear
                    some of them relate their hair breath [<hi rend="italic">sic</hi>] escapes it
                    would make your hair rise on your head." This woman's description offers a
                    chilling counterpoint to Sawin's misadventures just two columns over. Sawin,
                    too, has seen some "hard service," describes a couple close calls, and is
                    certainly sick of Mexico, but he is not yet close to death (though in a later
                    letter he would become a triple amputee), and the ludicrousness of the poem
                    blunts soldiers' disillusionment with considerable levity. Incredibly, the
                    woman's letter goes on to describe the grim irony of a deadly welcome to
                    soldiers in Cincinnati, where a cannon shot meant to "salute" the returning
                    volunteers killed one and blew both arms off another, one day after having
                    killed another soldier on a different boat with the same cannon. <note n="19"
                        >"Returning Volunteers," <hi rend="italic">The Liberator</hi>, August 27,
                        1847, 140.</note></p>
                <p>Also on the same page as Sawin's letter is the piece "Assassination of a
                    Massachusetts Volunteer," reprinted from the <hi rend="italic">Boston Post</hi>.
                    This brief article describes the killing of a soldier traveling "from Monterey
                    to Ceralvo" with several other soldiers. His party "learnt from a straggling
                    Mexican, that one of the Mariner band had caught him with a lasso, and that his
                    throat had been cut, and his body dragged into a chapparal." <note n="20"
                        >"Assassination of a Massachusetts Volunteer," <hi rend="italic">The
                            Liberator</hi>, August 27, 1847, 140.</note> This account offers a more
                    grotesque version of Sawin's statement, "You see a feller peekin' out, and, fust
                    you know, a lariat / If [<hi rend="italic">sic</hi>] round your throat and you a
                    copse, 'fore you can say, 'Wat are ye at?'" Of course, the rest of this issue of
                        <hi rend="italic">The Liberator</hi> also included commentary on the war,
                    including a reprinted item from the <hi rend="italic">St. Louis Republican</hi>
                    titled "More Volunteers Wanted" and two front-page stories: a reprint from the
                        <hi rend="italic">Ashtabula Sentinel</hi> detailing a speech by Congressman
                    C. F. Adams about the war and a report that David Hale, editor of the <hi
                        rend="italic">Journal of Commerce</hi> and previous supporter of President
                    Polk, had "come out over his own signature against the origin and prosecution of
                    the war." <note n="21">Untitled news item, <hi rend="italic">The Liberator</hi>,
                        August 27, 1847, 137.</note> So, even though <hi rend="italic">The
                        Liberator</hi> separated "LETTER FROM A VOLUNTEER IN SALTILLO" into its own
                    "Poetry" column, it still spoke to the rest of the news in the paper, offering a
                    comically distorted mirror of news from the Mexican front.</p>
            </div>
            <div type="section">
                <head type="sub"><hi rend="italic">Littell's Living Age</hi></head>
                <p>The context and reception of "LETTER FROM A VOLUNTEER IN SALTILLO" as it appeared
                    in <hi rend="italic">Littell's Living Age</hi> in September 1847 differs because
                    the medium differs. Unlike the charged, single-minded reform newspapers the <hi
                        rend="italic">National Anti-Slavery Standard</hi> and <hi rend="italic">The
                        Liberator</hi>, <hi rend="italic">Littell's Living Age</hi> was a
                    politically eclectic general interest magazine that, aiming to be a cosmopolitan
                    miscellany for an American audience, mostly reprinted works from European
                    (typically British) sources, thus taking advantage of the absence of an
                    international copyright law. <note n="22">Meredith L. McGill, "Lurking in the
                        Blogosphere of the 1840s," <hi rend="italic">Common-Place</hi> 7.2 (2007),
                        accessed August 15, 2014, <ref type="url"
                            target="http://www.common-place.org/vol-07/no-02/reading/"
                            >http://www.common-place.org/vol-07/no-02/reading/</ref>.</note> In this
                    context, Sawin's letter appears not as a plebian voice in debates about the
                    US-Mexico War, but one of many pieces in the magazine describing exotic foreign
                    lands to American readers. A quick perusal of other titles in the September 11,
                    1847, issue of <hi rend="italic">Littell's Living Age</hi>&#8212;"Protest of the
                    Proceedings of the British Near Canton" (in China), "The Out-Station; Or, Jaunts
                    in the Jungle" (set in Ceylon), "A Chinese Ghost Story," "Elections in England,"
                    "The Prussian Die," "Switzerland," and so on&#8212;attest to this. In keeping
                    with this sense of bringing the news of the world home, editor Eliakim Littell's
                    preface to "LETTER FROM A VOLUNTEER IN SALTILLO," like those in the reform
                    newspapers, sets up the poem as war correspondence. He writes, "Having copied
                    many letters from the army in Mexico, we now add one from a correspondent of the
                        <hi rend="italic">Boston Courier</hi>." <note n="23">"Letter from a
                        Volunteer in Saltillo," <hi rend="italic">Littell's Living Age</hi>,
                        September 11, 1847, 503.</note> In this reprinting, then, Biglow goes
                    international, and is situated as one of many points in a constellation of
                    global affairs mediated by an American editor.</p>
            </div>
            <div type="section">
                <head type="sub"><hi rend="italic">Texas Union</hi></head>
                <p>A month later, Lowell's poems had circulated from these northeastern newspapers
                    published in New York and Boston to a Texas frontier town, San Augustine,
                    situated on the Louisiana border. The reprint in the <hi rend="italic">Texas
                        Union</hi> excerpts only the final fourteen lines of the poem. The heading,
                    "SEEN THE ELEPHANT," makes reference to a common nineteenth-century phrase used
                    to describe disillusionment when the reality of a situation does not correspond
                    with what was imagined. <note n="24">For more on the widespread use of this
                        phrase to describe soldiers' disillusionment, see Johannsen, <hi
                            rend="italic">To the Halls of the Montezumas</hi>, 87.</note> According
                    to the editor's preface, Sawin has "seen the elephant" because he has discovered
                    that the "officers at home and the same officers in Mexico, are just as
                    different as 'sodgering in fun' and 'in earnest.'" In the excerpt, Sawin
                    complains that the accommodating, alcohol-proffering officers at the recruiting
                    rallies at home in Massachusetts become demanding tyrants in the field. He
                    considers desertion, but he acknowledges that he would face capital punishment
                    if caught, and concludes, "wal, tain't no use a jawin', / I'm safe enlisted for
                    the war." Sawin's poem about "seeing the elephant" directly links to another
                    article on the front page of the <hi rend="italic">Texas Union</hi>, titled
                    "Wanted to See the Animal" and credited to the <hi rend="italic">Boston
                        Times</hi>. In this anecdote, a visiting yokel sees a signboard advertising
                        <hi rend="italic">Littell's Living Age</hi>&#8212;interestingly, the home of
                    the aforementioned September reprint of Lowell's poem&#8212;at a print shop. One
                    of the articles in <hi rend="italic">Littell's Living Age</hi> mentions "seeing
                    the elephant," and the yokel, taking the metaphor literally and speaking in
                    dialect akin to Sawin's vernacular, asks to buy a ticket to the circus.
                    Misunderstandings and a near riot ensue before the yokel escapes to the nearest
                    train station to go home to the country. This anecdote preps readers for the
                    title and theme of "SEEN THE ELEPHANT." Significantly, the anecdote about the
                    yokel's mistake is labeled "HUMOROUS," which places it into the category of a
                    joke; on the other hand, Lowell's poem is not labeled as fictional or humorous.
                        <note n="25">"Wanted to See the Animal," <hi rend="italic">Texas Union</hi>,
                        October 16, 1847, 1.</note> In fact, the editor's preface identifies Sawin
                    as a "pretended Yankee poet, writing home from Mexico," treating Sawin as a
                    genuine soldier and an ersatz poet, when in fact the reverse is true.</p>
                <p>Whereas Sawin's disillusionment serves as an opportunity to campaign against the
                    war in the northeastern reform papers, the editor of the <hi rend="italic">Texas
                        Union</hi> uses it for a different purpose. The editor, William N. Harman,
                    is explicit about his support of the war. In an editorial on page 2, Harman
                    announces, "Taking it for granted then, that every true friend of this
                    country&#8212;every patriotic Texan, is a supporter of all those measures
                    growing out of annexation, the <hi rend="italic">Texas Union</hi> will
                    fearlessly enter the lists in defence of those measures, and hold itself in
                    readiness to repel the assaults of the Whig Press." In addition to this outright
                    declaration of the paper's support for the Democrat Party and, concurrently, the
                    war, an ode titled "Hero Portraits," which depicts idealized US generals
                    including Taylor and Scott, appears on page 4. Also, Harman celebrates the
                    success of recruitment rallies in Kentucky, Tennessee, and Indiana in an article
                    titled "Military." The editor praises the "chivalry" of the "brave b'hoys" who
                    volunteered, and he also draws special attention to the Tennessee rallies, in
                    which muster quotas were not only met but surpassed. Harman writes, "Huzza for
                    East Tennessee! She can't be beat in patriotic devotion to country! Her sons are
                    ever foremost when their country calls!" Keeping in mind this fervent praise for
                    volunteers, Harman's decision to excerpt the section of Sawin's poem that
                    mentions his desire to desert may seem contradictory. Yet Harman is careful to
                    point out that Sawin and his flip-flopping officers are from Massachusetts. In
                    this context, Sawin's disillusionment is portrayed as Yankee cowardice in
                    contrast to the Southern volunteers, who do not question "the justice or
                    injustice of the cause—as to the right or wrong of the thing—but only [ask],
                    'does the country need our services? If so, we are ready!'" <note n="26"
                        >"Military," <hi rend="italic">Texas Union</hi>, October 16, 1847,
                    2.</note></p>
                <p>Harman's political leanings were typical of Texan printers during this time
                    period. According to Marilyn McAdams Sibley's study of antebellum Texas
                    newspapers, editors "tied the appreciation in value of [their] land and business
                    to the continued growth of the republic" and as a result "subscribed
                    wholeheartedly not only to the unwritten rule of printing nothing that would
                    hurt the country but also to the corollary of that rule, that what would hurt
                    the country would also hurt them." Editors needed to please local advertisers
                    and subscribers to prosper, and the "predominance of the Democrats and the
                    weakness of other parties" dictated those tastes. <note n="27">Marilyn McAdams
                        Sibley, <hi rend="italic">Lone Stars and State Gazettes: Texas Newspapers
                            before the Civil War</hi> (College Station: Texas A&amp;M University
                        Press, 1983), 9, 153.</note> Situated in San Augustine, a frontier town in
                    which basic institutions such as a library, district court, and school were all
                    still under construction, Harman's newspaper business was tenuous. In addition
                    to this generalized fear of pecuniary pain, Harman may have been further
                    motivated by fear of bodily harm. Harman's predecessor, James Russell, had been
                    murdered in a gunfight with another editor, Henry A. Kendall, who then fled
                    town. <note n="28">Sibley, <hi rend="italic">Lone Stars and State Gazettes</hi>,
                        364&#8211;65.</note> Anxious to put that drama to bed, Harman bought
                    Russell's and Kendall's competing papers and united them under the new title <hi
                        rend="italic">Texas Union</hi>, the first issue of which reprinted the
                    Lowell poem. Harman's pro-Southern, pro-war sentiments, geared to please his
                    local community, shaped his reframing of Lowell's poem from anti-war satire to
                    anti-Yankee propaganda.</p>
            </div>
            <div type="section">
                <head type="sub"><hi rend="italic">New Hampshire Sentinel</hi></head>
                <p>The <hi rend="italic">Texas Union</hi>'s editor rails against the Whig press in
                    the issue in which the excerpt appears. But avowedly Whig newspapers, of course,
                    also reprinted the Sawin poem. For example, in November 1847, the <hi
                        rend="italic">New Hampshire Sentinel</hi> (Keene, NH) reprints "LETTER FROM
                    A VOLUNTEER IN SALTILLO" as well as Hosea Biglow's frame letter under the
                    heading "Miscellaneous." Abutting the poem are several other authentic letters
                    about Mexico. Immediately following it is "A Mexican Letter," which describes
                    the capture of Mexico City. Interestingly, this letter was written by a Mexican
                    citizen, providing a viewpoint that contrasts with the typical "letter from the
                    front" genre. The letter describes the US soldiers as a "patrol of foreigners,
                    who entered triumphant, shedding the blood of our people." <note n="29">"A
                        Mexican Letter," <hi rend="italic">New Hampshire Sentinel</hi>, November 11,
                        1847, 2.</note> Another letter on the same page from an American soldier
                    encamped at the Mexican National Palace gives a detailed description of a battle
                    in which Colonel Ransom and several other US soldiers were killed. Yet another
                    letter written by a Southerner explains that the war is necessary because the
                    South "must have an outlet for our slaves." The editor prints this letter as
                    proof of the immorality of the war, which he deems "unconstitutional" and
                    "unnatural." <note n="30">"The War, and What It Is For," <hi rend="italic">New
                            Hampshire Sentinel</hi>, November 11, 1847, 2.</note> On the same page,
                    in an article titled "War News," the editor writes that since there have been
                    "no official despatches" from Mexico, he must rely on "scattering small official
                    and private letters" for news from the front lines. <note n="31">"War News," <hi
                            rend="italic">New Hampshire Sentinel</hi>, November 11, 1847, 2.</note>
                    In this context, Sawin's letter is treated as one of several letters that give
                    firsthand accounts of the war. In this same issue, the <hi rend="italic">New
                        Hampshire Sentinel</hi> also reprints another Biglow poem; "What Mr.
                    Robinson Thinks" is printed on page 4 under the heading "Orchestra." This poem's
                    critique of Massachusetts politics links to the newspaper's celebration of the
                    recent victories of several Whig politicians, whom the editor champions in part
                    because of their anti-war sentiments.</p>
                <p>The <hi rend="italic">New Hampshire Sentinel</hi> was founded in 1799 by John
                    Prentiss, who passed the editorial torch to his son J. W. Prentiss in 1846, the
                    year before the Biglow poems appeared in the newspaper. Both Prentiss senior and
                    junior shaped the paper to reflect their Whig politics, condemnation of the war,
                    and support for temperance, religious freedom, and education reform. <note
                        n="32">Cornelius Raily Lyle II, "New Hampshire's '<hi rend="italic"
                            >Sentinel</hi>': The Editorial Life of John Prentiss, 1799&#8211;1846"
                        (PhD diss., Northwestern University, 1972), 435&#8211;52 (Proquest).</note>
                    This interest in reform may explain how Prentiss came in contact with the Lowell
                    poems; for instance, Prentiss, like many editors, culled material from exchange
                    papers, and he may have subscribed to reform papers like the <hi rend="italic"
                        >National Anti-Slavery Standard</hi> and <hi rend="italic">The
                        Liberator</hi>. In addition, Prentiss apprenticed in Boston and had been a
                    member of elite literary and printing circles in the city. <note n="33">John W.
                        Moore, <hi rend="italic">Moore's Historical, Biographical, and Miscellaneous
                            Gatherings in the Form of Disconnected Notes Relative to Printers,
                            Printing, Publishing, and Editing of Books, Newspapers, Magazines and
                            Other Literary Productions, Such as the Early Publications of New
                            England, the United States, and the World, from the Discovery of the
                            Art, or from 1420 to 1886</hi> (Concord, NH: Republican Press
                        Association, 1886), 530 (Internet Archive); Lyle, "New Hampshire's '<hi
                            rend="italic">Sentinel</hi>,'" 13&#8211;14.</note> This personal network
                    may help explain the circulation of the Biglow poems to Keene, New Hampshire.
                    This close contextualization of the intertwined personal and political
                    connections between printers and editors evinces the way in which the very local
                    can telescope outward to reveal the dynamics of distribution and the stories
                    behind the links between regional and urban nodes in the antebellum US print
                    network.</p>
            </div>
            <div type="section">
                <head type="sub"><hi rend="italic">Meliboeus-Hipponax: The Biglow Papers</hi></head>
                <p>In 1848, Lowell set out to collect his Biglow poems into a book edition, making
                    copious corrections to the poems. As the comparison of witnesses in this digital
                    edition shows, he tinkered endlessly with Biglow's New England dialect. An even
                    bigger and more time-consuming revision involved a huge expansion of the role of
                    Parson Homer Wilbur, Biglow's fictional editor. Whereas in the <hi rend="italic"
                        >National Anti-Slavery Standard</hi> pieces Wilbur makes only a few brief
                    introductory or explanatory appearances, in the book his role swells egregiously
                    to over half the manuscript, thus overshadowing the more interesting characters
                    of the folksy Biglow and the raucous Sawin. For instance, in the <hi
                        rend="italic">National Anti-Slavery Standard</hi> reprint the editorial
                    framing, including headline, amounts to just over 250 words. In the book
                    version, Wilbur's tiresome introduction and afterword framing the poem add up to
                    over 1,600 words, approximately the same word count as the poem itself. As
                    Lowell later explained this decision, "When I came to collect them and publish
                    them in a volume, I conceived my parson-editor with his pedantry and verbosity,
                    his amiable vanity and superiority to the verses he was editing, as a fitting
                    artistic background and foil. It gave me the chance, too, of glancing obliquely
                    at many things which were beyond the horizon of my other characters." <note
                        n="34">James Russell Lowell to Thomas Hughes, September 13, 1859, in <hi
                            rend="italic">Letters</hi>, 296&#8211;97.</note> But in these dense and
                    highly allusive prose interventions, Lowell as Wilbur prattles wanderingly about
                    poetry, his parishioners, and historical precedents for the invasion of Mexico.
                    Thus Wilbur's interruptions are more a Swiftian satire on the book than a
                    critique of the US-Mexico War. Additionally, the juxtaposition of Wilbur's
                    pedantry to Biglow's unlearned but earnest fervor is quite jarring. Cameron
                    Nickels aptly describes the numbing effect that Wilbur's prominence in the book
                    has on the satire: "Although his [Wilbur's] learned notes do often address the
                    issues raised by the dialect letter-poems, his elaborate, scholarly analyses,
                    abundant with Latin quotations and etymologies, too often undercut the moral
                    thrust of the rustic, ironic speakers and reduce their humorous admissions of
                    guilt to tediously pedantic inconsequentiality." <note n="35">Cameron C.
                        Nickels, <hi rend="italic">New England Humor: From the Revolutionary War to
                            the Civil War</hi> (Knoxville: University of Tennessee Press, 1993),
                        205.</note></p>
                <p>Lowell's wholesale changes also delayed publication of the book. He complained to
                    Gay in early September 1848, "I am as busy as I can be with Mr. Biglow's poems,
                    of which I have got between twenty and thirty pages already printed. It is the
                    hardest book to print that I ever had anything to do with, and, what with
                    corrections and Mr. Wilbur's annotations, keeps me more employed than I care to
                    be." <note n="36">James Russell Lowell to Sydney H. Gay, September 2, 1848, in
                            <hi rend="italic">Letters</hi>, 138.</note> Lowell had hoped to publish
                    it in time to influence the November presidential election, steering antislavery
                    voters away from General Zachary Taylor and toward the Free-Soil Party
                    candidate, Martin Van Buren. But by the time <hi rend="italic"
                        >Meliboeus-Hipponax: The Biglow Papers</hi> was published by Putnam in
                    December 1848, the war was over; Whig Zachary Taylor, a target of two Biglow
                    poems, was elected president; and Lowell's satire was already out of date. <note
                        n="37">For a meticulously edited edition of the Biglow poems in book form,
                        see <hi rend="italic">The Biglow Papers</hi> [First Series], ed. Thomas
                        Wortham (DeKalb: Northern Illinois University Press, 1977). "LETTER FROM A
                        VOLUNTEER IN SALTILLO" appears on pages 57&#8211;68.</note> The once
                    hot-button issues the poems addressed were suddenly old news.</p>
            </div>
            <div type="section">
                <head type="sub"><hi rend="italic">Sunbury American</hi></head>
                <p>Soon after the book's publication, an excerpt of "LETTER FROM A VOLUNTEER IN
                    SALTILLO" appeared in the <hi rend="italic">Sunbury American</hi>, a local
                    weekly newspaper printed in Sunbury, Pennsylvania. Titled "Sogering in Mexico,"
                    the reprint includes sixteen lines from "LETTER FROM A VOLUNTEER," as well as
                    thirty-two lines from "A Second Letter from B. Sawin, Esq.," which was published
                    almost a year after the first Sawin letter. The reprint appears without
                    attribution or any sort of preface, meaning the editor does not explain that the
                    reprint samples two separate poems. Instead, the editor seamlessly weaves the
                    excerpts into a single, cohesive poem that reflects on Sawin's disillusionment
                    about war. In the remixed reprint, Sawin notes that his training was much
                    different from actually killing a man, and the recruiter's promises of gold,
                    glory, and "<hi rend="small caps">Glorious Fun</hi>" never materialized, at
                    least not for the enlisted men; his superior officers, on the other hand, did
                    get to "revel in the halls o' Montezumy." Because this version of the poem was
                    printed after the war had ended, the editor treats it as fiction rather than
                    news from the front. He labels it as "Select Poetry," and it abuts a sentimental
                    Christmas story and anecdotes about two literary figures, John Keats and Sir
                    Walter Scott.</p>
                <p>However, the editor did manage to make his remixed Sawin poem timely in that it
                    accompanies several articles about the discovery of gold in California,
                    territory newly acquired by the United States as a result of the war. Johannsen
                    points out that only "[s]ix weeks after President Polk had declared the Mexican
                    War officially at an end, a letter from a New York volunteer in California . . .
                    [mentioned] that a 'gold mine' had recently been discovered," which led pro-war
                    espousers of manifest destiny to believe that "God had kept the gold hidden
                    until the land came into the possession of the American republic." <note n="38"
                        >Johannsen, <hi rend="italic">To the Halls of the Montezumas</hi>,
                        310&#8211;11.</note> In the <hi rend="italic">Sunbury American</hi>, "The
                    Gold Fever" discusses the costs of different routes to California, one of which
                    traveled through Vera Cruz and Acapulco, sites of previous US-Mexico War
                    battles. Both "California&#8212;Its Commercial Advantages, &amp;c." and
                    "Official&#8212;The Gold Essayed&#8212;Extraordinary Purity" comment on the
                    potential financial opportunities of this spoil of the war. However, the editor
                    tempers these temptations with several reality checks. He reprints
                    "Congressional Proceedings," which reports on Congress's dismissal of a bill
                    requesting the convening of a state constitutional convention to include both US
                    and former Mexican citizens, suggesting that the incorporation of this new
                    territory into the US body politic may be more complicated than it seems. The
                    editor also expresses his skepticism about the Gold Rush in two articles. "The
                    Gold Region" reviews several travel narratives about California and surmises
                    that "we ascribe three fourths to exaggeration, produced by excitement. Each of
                    the narrators seems to have been dazzled, and in no condition to consider sober
                    realities." <note n="39">"The Gold Region," <hi rend="italic">Sunbury
                            American</hi>, December 23, 1848, 2.</note> Likewise, in "California
                    Gold Mines," the editor writes, "The present excitement, in regard to the gold
                    mines in California will result in the speedy settlement of that country by
                    American citizens, but we venture to predict that nine tenths of those who go
                    out to realize fortunes in hunting for gold will be disappointed." <note n="40"
                        >"California Gold Mines," <hi rend="italic">Sunbury American</hi>, December
                        23, 1848, 2.</note> The editor's suggestion that the promise of the gold
                    rush may not match up with the reality thematically connects to his remix of the
                    Sawin poems, in which Sawin laments the disconnect between recruiter's promises
                    and the realities of war.</p>
                <p>This balanced viewpoint fits with the overall tone of the newspaper, which was
                    "generally regarded as the expression of conservative and unbiased opinion,"
                    according to a local historian. So unbiased was the editor, the local history
                    claims, that he occasionally used this Democratic organ in a Democratic county
                    to support non-Democratic candidates. The editor of the <hi rend="italic"
                        >Sunbury American</hi>, Henry B. Masser, was a self-educated
                    lawyer-turned-newspaperman who was "recognized as a trenchant and forcible
                    writer, and a sagacious observer of the political and social movements of the
                    day." Under his tenure, the periodical was "one of the most influential journals
                    in central Pennsylvania" and enjoyed "extensive circulation throughout this
                    section of the State." <note n="41">Herbert C. Bell, <hi rend="italic">History
                            of Northumberland County, Pennsylvania</hi> (Chicago: Brown, Runk and
                        Company, 1891), 282, 807 (HathiTrust).</note> Further expanding the
                    influence of his newspaper, Masser published a German-language version, <hi
                        rend="italic">Der Deutsche Amerikaner</hi>; unfortunately, we have yet to
                    track down a copy of the December 23, 1848, issue of <hi rend="italic">Der
                        Deutsche Amerikaner</hi> to examine if it prints a German translation of the
                    Sawin remix poem. Considering the wide circulation, multilingual editions, and
                    local reputation of Masser, the <hi rend="italic">Sunbury American</hi>
                    demonstrates not only that Lowell's poems infiltrated beyond urban centers but
                    also that local papers were powerful sites for the distribution and
                    dissemination of information in their own right.</p>
                <p>The <hi rend="italic">Sunbury American</hi>'s deployment of Sawin's poem after
                    the war had ended shows how the poem lived on beyond Lowell's original intent as
                    a satirical, anti-war, antislavery protest poem. Later iterations of the poem in
                    reprints further demonstrate its longevity. For instance, fifty years after its
                    first publication, four lines from the poem appeared in a Honolulu newspaper,
                        <hi rend="italic">The Independent</hi>, in an editorial about the US
                    annexation of Hawaii. The editorial takes its title from Lowell's poem and links
                    US colonialism in Hawaii to the US-Mexico War, noting that in both cases "the
                    white men" used the ideology of manifest destiny and the civilizing mission as a
                    cover for "committing the highest crime known in international
                    relations&#8212;stealing from a people their government and their lands." <note
                        n="42">"Scrounging Them Out," <hi rend="italic">The Independent</hi>, March
                        9, 1898, 2.</note> In the early twentieth century, an untitled article in
                    Greenville, Kentucky's <hi rend="italic">The Record</hi> cites the poem. After
                    announcing that "[a]ll the dark-skinned races look alike to the white man," the
                    racist article claims, "It is true that we believe, in our political literature,
                    that all men were created free and equal, but practically we make the
                    qualification of Hosea Biglow during the Mexican war, that 'every man don't mean
                    a nigger or a Mexican.'" <note n="43">Untitled news item, <hi rend="italic">The
                            Record</hi>, June 15, 1911, 2.</note> In its original incarnation, this
                    line parodied the racist pro-Anglo-Saxon rhetoric of one of the war's major
                    military figures, Caleb Cushing. However, in <hi rend="italic">The Record</hi>,
                    the editor misreads the poem's satirical rhetoric, quotes a single line stripped
                    of context, and uses it to defend de facto discrimination in a reversal of
                    Lowell's spirit of protest. Although we do not include these two mentions as
                    witnesses in our digital edition because of their brevity, they evince the
                    malleable afterlife of the poem in the hands of editors across a spectrum of
                    political motivations.</p>
            </div>
            <div type="section">
                <head type="sub">Editorial Approach</head>
                <p>To prepare this digital edition, we began by transcribing each reprint as a
                    separate text file. In these diplomatic transcriptions, we preserved all
                    irregular spelling and punctuation in the original because we wanted to record
                    the dialect as is without correction. We decided to record each line of poetry
                    without arbitrary line breaks or indentation caused by varying column widths. We
                    also did not record stanza breaks because they varied and were often difficult
                    to discern on newspaper pages. Once all the transcriptions were complete, we
                    collated the witnesses with Juxta Commons, an online editorial tool developed by
                    NINES that offers collation of comparison sets, several forms of visualization
                    of variants, the option to export as TEI P5 file, and the option to publish
                    results online. In particular, we chose Juxta Commons because it creates a TEI
                    file that uses parallel segmentation to juxtapose the different witnesses.
                    According to the TEI P5 guidelines, parallel segmentation is "useful where
                    editors do not wish to privilege a text as the 'base' or when editors wish to
                    present parallel texts." <note n="44">To access the TEI P5 guidelines, see <ref
                            type="url" target="http://www.tei-c.org/Guidelines/P5/"
                            >http://www.tei-c.org/Guidelines/P5/</ref>.</note> This element of
                    openness reflects our desire to privilege multiplicity rather than an
                    authoritative text. Web technology, of course, is perfectly suited to such an
                    approach. Whereas traditional print editing identifies different versions of a
                    text, creates a conspectus of various readings, makes a single text through a
                    process of combination, and presents to the reader a single text, digital
                    editing, as Peter Robinson points out in "New Directions in Critical Editing,"
                    allows editors to bypass these last two stages and to "simply present all the
                    accumulated evidence for all the different states of the text." <note n="45"
                        >Peter Robinson, "New Directions in Critical Editing," in <hi rend="italic"
                            >Electronic Text: Investigations in Method and Theory</hi>, ed. Kathryn
                        Sunderland (Oxford: Clarendon Press, 1997), 153, 159.</note> This edition is
                    the embodiment of an argument that circulating texts like Lowell's Biglow poems
                    should not be seen as either going "from bad to worse" <note n="46">William
                        Proctor Williams and Craig S. Abbot, <hi rend="italic">An Introduction to
                            Bibliographical and Textual Studies</hi> (New York: Modern Language
                        Association, 2009), 8.</note> as they appear and reappear or as imperfect
                    instantiations to be collated into an authoritative text representing the
                    author's ultimate intention. Rather, this digital edition invites readers to
                    consider these reprints as separate iterations that shift to fit the needs of
                    different news contexts. Hence, we want to highlight not our own editorial
                    decisions, but those of newspaper editors in 1847&#8211;48, as well as the role
                    that readers&#8212;then and now&#8212;play in making meaning through the reading
                    of the poem as it appears in juxtaposition with the news content it adumbrates.
                    The parallel segmentation structure created by collating our witnesses through
                    Juxta Commons helps us achieve this goal.</p>
                <p>Our first trial run using Juxta Commons proved problematic because of the wide
                    variety in our witnesses: some had extensive prefatory material, while others
                    had none. Also, two of our witnesses, the <hi rend="italic">Texas Union</hi> and
                    the <hi rend="italic">Sunbury American</hi>, were excerpts, which created
                    misalignments when the Juxta collation attempted to match up the texts line by
                    line. Our second run, in which we only included the body of the poem in the
                    witnesses that reprinted the entire poem, was much clearer. Then we manually
                    added any prefatory material, the excerpts, and the concluding prose appended to
                    the poem in the book edition. We structured the XML document to reflect this
                    variety of formats. In the front matter, we listed various titles under the
                    "head," any introductory text penned by the editor as "preface," and Hosea
                    Biglow's framing text as "letter." Then we placed the poem in the "body." One of
                    the reprints, the book edition, included an appendix, which is included in the
                    markup as back matter. To ensure that we had not introduced error or
                    accidentally autocorrected an irregular dialect spelling during this
                    transcription process, we performed a round of double-checking. At this stage,
                    we also manually entered instances of italics or small caps, tagged the markup
                    with "placeName" and "persName," and demarcated uses of Latin and Ancient Greek
                    as foreign languages. We decided not to mark the Spanish words within the poem
                    as foreign because at the time the poem was printed, these words were
                    incorporated into the US vernacular and would not have required translation. As
                    Johannsen points out, the "Mexican War brought many more Spanish words and
                    phrases into American speech. . . . Such words as adobe, ranchero, chaparral,
                    sombrero, lasso, corral, hacienda, peon, calaboose, fandango, and patio (the
                    list could go on) came into common use." <note n="47">Johannsen, <hi
                            rend="italic">To the Halls of the Montezumas</hi>, 205.</note> Several
                    of these specific words&#8212;including "chaparral," "fandango," and
                    "lasso"&#8212;appear in Lowell's poem.</p>
                <p>In the next stage of our editorial process, we marked each site of variance
                    between the witnesses as one of four categories: punctuation, orthographic,
                    alteration, and substantive. This categorization revealed several trends as the
                    poem evolved over time. First, the majority of the variants were due to changes
                    in punctuation and spelling that occurred when Lowell compiled the book edition.
                    He systematically made the dialect more irregular. For instance, the standard
                    "and" in the earlier newspaper reprints is universally changed to "an'" in the
                    book, and the same occurs with "as" to "ez," "was" to "wuz," "that" to "thet,"
                    "had" to "hed," and so on. In the glossary that he created for his <hi
                        rend="italic">Biglow Papers</hi> book, Lowell offered "translations" of
                    these slang spellings into proper English. Categorization of variants by type
                    also revealed that the <hi rend="italic">Sunbury American</hi> tends to follow
                    the book's spelling and punctuation, leading us to believe that the editor of
                    that newspaper used the book, not an exchange paper, as his source. (That the
                        <hi rend="italic">Sunbury American</hi> reprints a later Sawin poem and
                    appeared after the book's publication strengthens this claim of lineage.) In
                    addition to noting instances of orthographic or punctuation changes, we also
                    marked substantive variants in which entire words or phrases were altered. In
                    particular, following line 98, Lowell added four lines to the book version. The
                    other major variation among witnesses has to do with Hosea Biglow's explanatory
                    notes. Four of the newspapers reprints include these notes, interspersing them
                    throughout the poem. The book includes all but one of these notes but locates
                    them beneath the poem as footnotes. The book also includes an explanatory note
                    signed by Homer Wilbur. Two of the witnesses excised the notes. For the
                    witnesses that included them, we transcribed each of these explanatory notes and
                    marked them as "authorial." In a few cases, we also classified a variant as an
                    alteration when the appearance of a word or phrase differed, but largely the
                    appearance stayed the same from edition to edition. Finally, we added
                    annotations to the poem about context such as historical figures, literary
                    allusions, and nineteenth-century slang to help modern readers understand the
                    poem.</p>
                <p>Though, as this introduction shows, we are most interested in investigations of
                    the poem's relationship to the news surrounding it in each edition, we
                    ultimately decided not to transcribe and encode selected articles from each
                    newspaper. Instead, we invite readers to review the images of these pages and,
                    building on the juxtapositions we have elaborated here, to identify their own
                    connections between Lowell's poem and other news content. This, we hope, engages
                    the reader in a receptive process similar to that of news-addicted subscribers
                    reading the poem in 1847 and 1848 and fits with our contention that each
                    separate context offers a horizon fruitful for meaning-making.</p>
            </div>
            <div type="section">
                <head type="sub">Acknowledgments</head>
                <p>Special thanks to Dawn Childress of Penn State Libraries, who generously shared
                    her knowledge of TEI with us in a series of hands-on workshops in spring 2014.
                    We also thank Molly Hardy, Paul Erickson, Ashley Cataldo, Jaclyn Donovan Penny,
                    and the rest of the staff at the American Antiquarian Society, which has
                    supported this project in many ways, including awarding us remote access to
                    their proprietary databases for our reprint searches, providing high-resolution
                    scans, and engaging in productive conversation about creating this digital
                    edition. Finally, we thank Harrison Wick, who provided us with scans of the
                    first edition of <hi rend="italic">Meliboeus-Hipponax: The Biglow Papers</hi>
                    housed in Indiana University of Pennsylvania's Special Collections, research
                    assistant Kaitlin Tonti, and project contributor Erin Guydish.</p>
            </div>
            <div type="section">
                <head type="sub">Image Credits</head>
                <p><hi rend="italic">Boston Courier</hi> (August 18, 1847), <hi rend="italic"
                        >National Anti-Slavery Standard</hi> (August 26, 1847), <hi rend="italic"
                        >The Liberator</hi> (August 27, 1847), <hi rend="italic">Littell's Living
                        Age</hi> (September 11, 1847), <hi rend="italic">Texas Union</hi> (October
                    16, 1847), and <hi rend="italic">New Hampshire Sentinel</hi> (November 11, 1847)
                    all courtesy of the American Antiquarian Society; <hi rend="italic">Sunbury
                        American</hi>, (December 23, 1848), Library of Congress; from <hi
                        rend="italic">Meliboeus-Hipponax: The Biglow Papers</hi>, courtesy of IUP
                    Special Collections and University Archives.</p>
            </div>
        </body>
    </text>
</TEI>
