<?xml-model href="http://www.tei-c.org/release/xml/tei/custom/schema/relaxng/tei_all.rng" type="application/xml" schematypens="http://relaxng.org/ns/structure/1.0"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
<teiHeader xml:lang="eng">
<fileDesc>
<titleStmt>
    <title type="main" level="m">Hannah Whitman Heyde to Louisa Van Velsor Whitman, December 20, 1855</title>
<author>Hannah Whitman Heyde</author>
<editor>Maire Mullins</editor>
<respStmt>
<resp>Transcription and encoding</resp>
<persName xml:id="mp">Madison Perrin</persName>
</respStmt>
<respStmt>
<resp>Editing and proofreading</resp>
<persName xml:id="mm">Maire Mullins</persName>
</respStmt>
</titleStmt>
<editionStmt>
<edition>
<date>2016</date>
</edition>
</editionStmt>
<publicationStmt>

<authority>Scholarly Editing: The Annual of the Association for Documentary Editing</authority>
<address>
                    <addrLine>http://www.scholarlyediting.org</addrLine>
            </address>
<publisher>Association for Documentary Editing</publisher>
<publisher>University of Nebraska&#8211;Lincoln</publisher>
<distributor>
<name>Center for Digital Research in the Humanities</name>
<address>
                        <addrLine>319 Love Library</addrLine>
                        <addrLine>University of Nebraska&#8211;Lincoln</addrLine>
                        <addrLine>Lincoln, NE 68588-4100</addrLine>
                        <addrLine>http://cdrh.unl.edu</addrLine>
                    </address>
</distributor>
<date><!-- Year --></date>
<availability>
<p>Scholarly Editing: The Annual of the Association for Documentary Editing is freely distributed by
the Association for Documentary Editing and the Center for Digital Research in the Humanities at the
University of Nebraska-Lincoln and licensed under a Creative Commons Attribution-NonCommercial-Share
Alike 3.0 Unported License</p>
</availability>
    <idno type="file">LOC005hwhlvvw12201855</idno>
    <idno type="edition">whitmanheydeletters</idno>
</publicationStmt>
<seriesStmt>
<title level="j">Scholarly Editing: The Annual of the Association for Documentary Editing</title>
<respStmt>
<resp>editor</resp>
<name xml:id="ag">Amanda Gailey</name>
</respStmt>
<respStmt>
<resp>editor</resp>
<name xml:id="awj">Andrew Jewell</name>
</respStmt>
<idno type="vol"><!-- The Journal's volume number --></idno>
<idno type="ISSN">2167-1257</idno>
</seriesStmt>
<sourceDesc>
<bibl>
<author>Hannah Whitman Heyde</author>
<title>Hannah Whitman Heyde to Louisa Van Velsor Whitman, December 20 1855</title>
<orgName xml:id="col">Hannah Louisa Whitman Heyde Papers, 1853-1892, Library of Congress,
Washington, D.C.</orgName>
<note type="project">Transcribed and encoded from the original manuscript, then edited and annotated
by Maire Mullins</note>
    <date when="1855-12-20">December 20, 1855</date>
</bibl>
</sourceDesc>
</fileDesc>
<profileDesc>
<particDesc>
<person role="sender">
<persName key="Heyde, Hannah Whitman">Hannah Whitman Heyde</persName>
</person>
<person role="recipient">
<persName key="Van Velsor Whitman, Louisa">Louisa Van Velsor Whitman</persName>
</person>
</particDesc>
</profileDesc>
<revisionDesc>
<change when="2015-09-11" who="#mm">edited and proofread</change>
<change when="2015-07-21" who="#mp">encoded</change>
<change when="2015-09-06" who="#mp">encoded annotations</change>
    <change when="2016-04-01" who="#mm">proofread</change>
</revisionDesc>
</teiHeader>
<text type="letter">
    <body><pb facs="LOC005hwhlvvw12201855.01.jpg"/>
<opener>
<dateline rend="right">
<name type="place">Burlington</name>
<date when="1855-12-20">Thursday, Dec. 20 &#40;1855&#41;</date><note xml:id="n1" type="editorial"
resp="jse">Richard Maurice Bucke dated this letter 1855, confirmed because Hannah, still in mourning
for her father, mentions that she has worn "black all the time." December 20, noted in Hannah's
handwriting, fell on a Thursday in 1855, so the month and the date are confirmed as
well.</note>
</dateline>
<salute>Dear Mother,</salute>
</opener>
<p>Take care of yourself dear Mother tell me about every one of them when you write </p>
<p>Whenever they can send me the Dispatch Mother dear <choice>
<sic>dont</sic>
<corr>don't</corr>
</choice> think strange of my not writing before I never thought so much of you all or wanted to
hear from you more than I do now </p>
<p>I have written a good many letters very many more than you have written to me only I have not
sent them, for many reasons sometimes Charlie would see them, and sometimes ones I would write when
I did not feel good and would not want to send them, this time I shall finish and mail it at once. I
have felt quite <choice>
<sic>disagreable</sic>
<corr>disaggreable</corr>
</choice> about my not writing have minded it probably more than you have I think about you all at
home much more than I ever did, and am always delighted to get a letter. I was glad <hi
rend="underline">very</hi> glad to hear Jeffy<note xml:id="n2" type="editorial" resp="jse">Thomas
Jefferson Whitman (1833-1890),"Jeff", was the eighth child of Walter and Louisa Whitman. Walt's
favorite brother, Jeff played the piano and had a lively sense of humor.</note> was better I thought
of you dear Mother every hour in the day, you must have had your hands full Andrew<note xml:id="n3"
type="editorial" resp="jse">Andrew Jackson Whitman (1827-1863), was the sixth child of Walter and
Louisa Whitman. Like his father and brothers, Andrew was a carpenter; he later served in the Union
Army briefly during the Civil War. See Martin G. Murray, "Bunkum Did Go Sogering," <hi rend="italic"
>Walt Whitman Quarterly Review</hi> 10 [Winter 1993], 142&#8212;148.</note> being sick also, I hope
by this time Andrew is entirely well and tell Jeff to keep a good heart and take care of himself, he
must not get downhearted, I am glad George<note xml:id="n4" type="editorial" resp="jse">George
Washington Whitman (1829-1901) was the seventh child of Walter and Louisa Whitman, and ten years
younger than Walt.</note> is in Brooklyn, again <choice>
<sic>its</sic>
<corr>it's</corr>
</choice> nice for you to have him come up home, I wonder if you feel much lonely do you mammy, I
should like to hear from you all again, we were very glad indeed to get the papers you sent, we
cannot <pb facs="LOC005hwhlvvw12201855.02.jpg"/>get the Dispatch<note xml:id="n5" type="editorial" resp="jse"> The <hi rend="italics">New York
Dispatch </hi> was published from 1854-1861. See The Library of Congress, <hi rend="italic"
>Chronicling America: Historic American Newspapers</hi> (web).</note> here they do not keep it.
Charlie gets the Daily times<note xml:id="n6" type="editorial" resp="jse">This may be a reference to
the <hi rend="italics">New-York Daily Times</hi>, which published under this title from
1851-1857.</note>, papers never get here <choice>
<sic>untill</sic>
<corr>until</corr>
</choice> the day after they are printed. Saturday paper they get Monday. Mother I really want to
see you all. I do not think we will remain here long. I know we will not stay long at this Hotel. <choice>
<sic>its</sic>
<corr>It's</corr>
</choice> possible we may go to the American Hotel<note xml:id="n7" type="editorial" resp="jse">The
American Hotel, known as "the leading hotel in Burlington," was built in 1808 and purchased in 1824
by Cornelius Van Ness, Governor of Vermont. A brick wing was added to the building in 1844. The
Hotel was the site of a deadly fire in 1906. See "Woman Perished in Ruins," <hi rend="italic"
>Burlington Free Press</hi> (Burlington, VT) December 20, 1906, 8.</note> , that is up in the
village more and is even still more fashionable. this place they try very hard to be fashionable as
far as dress goes, I think the people here are <choice>
<sic>some what</sic>
<corr>somewhat</corr>
</choice> different from what one has been used to, they had a ball or as they call it a cotillion
party they made quite a display most of the men wore white vests and gloves the girls ball dresses,
I saw them from one of the sitting rooms I did not dance, if we should remain here I should not even
go in the sitting room again they have them every two weeks, the room we occupy is on the second
floor not very large have no bureau or closes we pay &#36;8 a week, Charlie has only disposed of
three pictures since I have been here, he got a good price for them, you need not neglect writing
thinking we are not here as soon as we make any change I will let you know. I have written such a
great number of letters I forget if I told you I went to Plattsburg<pb facs="LOC005hwhlvvw12201855.03.jpg"/><note xml:id="n8"
type="editorial" resp="jse">Plattsburgh, New York, is on west side of Lake Champlain, north and west
of Burlington.</note> had a pleasant sail on the Lake dinner on <choice>
<sic>bourd</sic>
<corr>board</corr>
</choice> the Steamboat a nice walk and ride about the village visited two of the Hotels the day was
warm enough to be out on the <choice>
<sic>promenad</sic>
<corr>promenade</corr>
</choice> deck on the boat got home a little after dark it was no <choice>
<sic>expence</sic>
<corr>expense</corr>
</choice> to Charlie a boarder in the house invited us we could have gone to a very many places if
we had wished, then it was pleasant weather, now its pretty cold, the Lake is not frozen, there has
not been any snow or not enough to cover the <choice>
<corr>groun</corr>
<corr>ground</corr>
</choice> furs are very much worn here, they are much worn and quite expensive shall not be able to
get any this winter I do not go out much I have nothing new but a silk apron I have worn black all
the time the delaine<note xml:id="n9" type="editorial" resp="jse">Hannah's dress is probably made
out of wool; "delaine" refers to an all-wool dress material.</note> dress is worn out it was very
rotten every time I wear it, it gets torn the gingham dress I wore long as I could <choice>
<sic>untill</sic>
<corr>until</corr>
</choice> it got dirty or messy the flounced dress I wear still and my two silk ones, I have not worn
my cloak I wear that wrapper you gave me altogether and my black bonnet, the old black velvet one
was torn there is quite a number stop here that have just been married. sometimes they are married
here quietly, the last that was married here I was bridesmaid, the bridegroom was very rich the
bride was rather pretty they were married <pb facs="LOC005hwhlvvw12201855.04.jpg"/>in the evening <choice>
<sic>Mr</sic>
<corr>Mr.</corr>
</choice> Blodgett<note xml:id="n10" type="editorial" resp="jse">The name of the hotel is "The
Exchange," in Burlington, Vermont. The Heydes stayed at this hotel intermittently during the 1850s,
and Hannah refers to the Exchange in many of her letters. It was owned by the Blodgett
family.</note> the <choice>
<sic>principle</sic>
<corr>principal</corr>
</choice> owner of this Hotel (a widower, was groomsman we do not have very lively times here now
however Charlie thinks <choice>
<sic>its</sic>
<corr>it's</corr>
</choice> the dullest place he ever saw, he frets very much gets quite discouraged but I do not
think we shall be here very long I <choice>
<sic>dont</sic>
<corr>don't</corr>
</choice> care where he goes if he could only feel more cheerful, I of course would feel contented
anywhere where his <choice>
<sic>buisiness</sic>
<corr>business</corr>
</choice> was good, I have written very many letters and then would feel different and would not
send them, I was glad Walt wrote to me Charlie seemed much pleased with Leaves of Grass<note
xml:id="n11" type="editorial" resp="jse">The first edition of <hi rend="italics">Leaves of
Grass</hi>, published in July 1855.</note> he took it to his room at once, and has read it many
times. &#8212; You must write when you can dear Mother for possibly we may remain here some weeks, I
am perfectly willing to leave here I do not like it so very much there is quite a number of women
boarders they notice <choice>
<sic>ones</sic>
<corr>one's</corr>
</choice> dress so much, Charlie has taken one of his paintings up to the American house to night to
be raffled<note xml:id="n12" type="editorial" resp="jse">Heyde followed the example set by the Art
Unions in the mid-nineteenth century, of holding a lottery (or raffle) to sell his paintings. The
Art Union would charge subscribers to belong to its organization each year, and at the end of the
year a drawing would be held. Winners would receive original works of art that the Art Union had
purchased. More than likely Heyde charged a nominal fee for his raffles. See William H. Gerdts, Jr.
<hi rend="italics">Painting and Sculpture in New Jersey</hi> (New Jersey: D. Van Nostrand, 1964),
84.</note> for there. I want to see you dear Mother very much I have so very much to say to you that
I do not wish to write, I have had some bothers, Charlie is not always very good to me but <choice>
<sic>its</sic>
<corr>it's</corr>
</choice> best to say as little about it as possible Charlie has said many times he has written home
when he was angry at me, if he has written as he says, but I do not think he has written what he
said, because there is not the slightest truth in what he says or writes when he is angry he is
sometimes very violent but I do not mind it much I scarcely ever get the least bit angry at him only
remember Mother to not believe any thing he writes of me in the slightest particular, Dear mother I
will certainly write again soon, write to me, I do not wish Charlie to see this. Give my love to
every single one George, to J, W, M<unclear/><note xml:id="n13" type="editorial" resp="jse">Hannah
is abbreviating the names of her siblings: "J" is Jeff; "W" is Walt, and "M" is Mary.</note>, and
Eddy<note xml:id="n14" type="editorial" resp="jse">Eddy (Edward) Whitman (1835-1892), the youngest
child of Louisa and Walter Whitman, was mentally and physically disabled. He lived with Mother
Whitman until her death in 1873, then with his brother George Washington Whitman and his wife Louisa
Orr Haslam Whitman. Walt Whitman contributed to his support. Eddy was placed in an asylum in
Blackwood, New Jersey, in 1888.</note></p>
<closer>
<salute>Good Bye dear Mother</salute>
</closer>
</body>

</text>
</TEI>
