
<?oxygen RNGSchema="http://www.scholarlyediting.org/scholarlyediting.rng" type="xml"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
   <teiHeader>
      <fileDesc>
         <titleStmt>
            <title>The Trinity Seven Planets</title>
            <respStmt>
               <resp>Transcription, encoding and writing introductory essay</resp>
               <name xml:id="ah">Alpo Honkapohja</name>
            </respStmt>
         </titleStmt>
         <editionStmt>
            <edition>
               <date>2012</date>
            </edition>
         </editionStmt>
         <publicationStmt>
            <idno type="file">intro.sevenplanets</idno>
            <idno type="edition">sevenplanets</idno>
            <authority>Scholarly Editing: The Annual of the Association for Documentary
               Editing</authority>
            <address><addrLine>http://www.scholarlyediting.org</addrLine></address>
            <publisher>Association for Documentary Editing</publisher>
            <publisher>University of Nebraska–Lincoln</publisher>
            <distributor>
               <name>Center for Digital Research in the Humanities</name>
               <address>
		                <addrLine>319 Love Library</addrLine>
		                <addrLine>University of Nebraska–Lincoln</addrLine>
		                <addrLine>Lincoln, NE 68588-4100</addrLine>
		                <addrLine>http://cdrh.unl.edu</addrLine>
		            </address>
            </distributor>
            <date>2012</date>
            <availability>
               <p>Scholary Editing: The Annual of the Association for Documentary Editing is freely
                  distributed by the Association for Documentary Editing and the Center for Digital
                  Research in the Humanities at the University of Nebraska-Lincoln and licensed
                  under a Creative Commons Attribution-NonCommercial-ShareAlike 3.0 Unported
                  License</p>
               <p>The Manuscript images are made available with the kind permission of the Master
                  and Fellows of Trinity College Cambridge</p>
            </availability>
         </publicationStmt>
         <seriesStmt>
            <title level="j">Scholarly Editing: The Annual of the Association for Documentary
               Editing</title>
            <respStmt>
               <resp>editor</resp>
               <name xml:id="ag">Amanda Gailey</name>
            </respStmt>
            <respStmt>
               <resp>editor</resp>
               <name xml:id="awj">Andrew Jewell</name>
            </respStmt>
            <idno type="vol">34</idno>
            <idno type="ISSN">2167-1257</idno>
         </seriesStmt>
         <sourceDesc>
            <p>Converted from a Word document</p>
         </sourceDesc>
      </fileDesc>
      <encodingDesc>
         <appInfo>
            <application ident="TEI_fromDOCX" version="2.15.0">
               <label>DOCX to TEI</label>
            </application>
         </appInfo>
      </encodingDesc>
      <revisionDesc>
         <change when="2012-05-31" who="#ah">Converted from a docx.file, did some formatting, added
            header </change>
         <change when="2012-06-28" who="#awj">added idno elements in publicationStmt to follow
            journal tagging conventions; added seriesStmt for Scholarly Editing in fileDesc</change>
         <change when="2012-08-08" who="#ah">Changed footnotes to conform to house style.</change>
         <change when="2012-08-15" who="#ah">revised the contents slightly, added one reference to
            bibliography</change>
         <change when="2012-08-16" who="#ah">added dimensions in pixels to image files</change>
         <change when="2012-08-17" who="#ah">deleted some empty w and seg elements which were left
            in the conversion</change>
         <change when="2012-09-14" who="#ah">added figure-elements around graphic-elements to enable
            captions and easier formatting</change>
         <change when="2012-09-19" who="#awj">added head elements to figures using the text in
            figDesc to enable caption styling; added @type='enlargeOnClick' to select images for
            styling</change>
         <change when="2012-09-24" who="#awj">Pasted in the style guide written by AH before the
            glossary</change>
         <change when="2012-10-04" who="#ah">changed two punctuation marks from PUA character
            references to ASCII symbols</change>
         <change when="2012-10-10" who="#ah">changed "tilde" to ~</change>
         <change when="2013-01-25" who="#ah">made changes suggested by referee1</change>
         <change when="2013-01-28" who="#ah">made changes suggested by referee1</change>
         <change when="2013-01-29" who="#ah">made changes suggested by referee1</change>
         <change when="2013-01-31" who="#awj">added "media/" to image URLs in a few
            instances</change>
         <change when="2013-02-07" who="#awj">rearranged the order of the notes and bibliography;
            changed the head on the bibliography from "References" to "Bibliography"</change>
         <change when="2013-02-27" who="#ah">copied notes formatted by a copy-editor over the old
            notes and bibliography.</change>
         <change when="2013-02-28" who="#ah">carried out language revisions made by the
            copy-editor</change>
         <change when="2013-03-01" who="#ah">fixed a couple of typos; made changes suggested by
            referee2</change>
         <change when="2013-03-05" who="#ah">fixed one typo</change>
         <change when="2013-03-05" who="#awj">added ref tags to make links out of URLs in
            notes</change>
         <change when="2013-03-06" who="#ah">added acknowledgements</change>
      </revisionDesc>
   </teiHeader>
   <text>
      <body>
         <div>
            <head>The Trinity Seven Planets</head>
            <byline>Alpo Honkapohja</byline>
            <div>
               <head>Introduction</head>
               <p>The late medieval manuscript Trinity College Cambridge O.1.77 (henceforth Trinity
                  O.1.77) contains a Middle English treatise on the Seven Planets, which is located
                  as the final item in a sequence of astrological treatises and is not found in any
                  of the related manuscripts.<ptr target="#note1" xml:id="nr1" n="1"/> The
                  manuscript dates from 1459–1460, or slightly earlier, and shares a number of texts
                  with the so-called Sloane Group of Middle English manuscripts, which have
                  attracted scholarly interest, because they may be evidence of systematic book
                  production in the London metropolitan area prior to Caxton and the first printing
                  press.</p>
               <p>Unlike other Middle English items in the manuscript,<ptr target="#note2"
                     xml:id="nr2" n="2"/> this treatise on Seven Planets has hitherto not appeared
                  in a modern edition. The present edition will remedy the situation, contributing
                  to the growing number of Middle English scientific and medical texts made
                  available in scholarly editions in recent decades. Since the manuscript was
                  connected to commercial book production in the fifteenth century, the edition will
                  also contribute to this thriving area of scholarship.</p>
               <p>The treatise is of interest both from a linguistic point of view, as it contains a
                  unique translation of a Latin work, and from sociohistorical point of view, as it
                  gives us information on which types of texts were available for the newly literate
                  middle classes.<ptr target="#note3" xml:id="nr3" n="3"/></p>
               <p>The edition has two goals:</p>
               <list type="ordered">
                  <item>To present the information faithfully and without editorial intervention, in
                     order to be of maximum use for historical linguistics.</item>
                  <item>To be readable to undergraduates and others interested in late medieval
                     astrology. Thus, the text is also available with a detailed glossary, for the
                     items that require it.</item>
               </list>
            </div>
            <div>
               <head>Background</head>
               <p>The time when the <hi rend="italic">The Trinity Seven Planets</hi> was copied
                  coincides with a period of popularity for astrological medicine, which was in the
                  fourteenth and fifteenth centuries.<ptr target="#note4" xml:id="nr4" n="4"/> I
                  briefly discuss two possible explanations for this, related to catastrophes that
                  affected medieval Europe in general and medieval England in particular.</p>
               <p>First, astrological medicine may have been a reaction to the major epidemic that
                  swept across Europe between 1346 and 1352.<ptr target="#note5" xml:id="nr5" n="5"
                  /> Described in contemporary sources as "plague" or "pestilence," it and the many
                  subsequent epidemics that followed in its wake in the following decades and
                  centuries killed approximately one-third of the population.<ptr target="#note6"
                     xml:id="nr6" n="6"/> Plague was a challenge to contemporary medical theory,
                  since it killed people regardless of their complexion, with no respect for the
                  intricate system of oppositions on which traditional Galenic, Hippocratic, and
                  Aristotelian medicine was based on.<ptr target="#note7" xml:id="nr7" n="7"/></p>
               <p>It is important not to overstate this crisis,<ptr target="#note8" xml:id="nr8"
                     n="8"/> as manuscript sources testify to continuity rather than upheaval.
                  However, it is quite likely that the greater emphasis on astrological phenomena
                  was at least partly caused by the plague<ptr target="#note9" xml:id="nr9" n="9"
                  />. It had become customary to attribute the outbreak of the first epidemic to the
                  conjunction of three planets, Mars, Saturn, and Jupiter, in 1345, which had
                  poisoned the air with a lethal miasma.<ptr target="#note10" xml:id="nr10" n="10"
                  /></p>
               <p>Another explanation, related more specifically to England, was the Hundred Years'
                  War and the Wars of the Roses. Because times were very uncertain, people turned to
                  astrology and other forms of divination for guidance. The 1450s and 1460s saw
                  England losing territories in France, King Henry VI suffering fits of insanity,
                  the rebellion of Jack Cade, and the Wars of the Roses erupting with first blood
                  drawn in St. Albans in 1455.<ptr target="#note11" xml:id="nr11" n="11"/> The
                  thirty-year power struggle between Yorkists and Lancastrians was particularly
                  perilous for higher nobility, who were too important not to get politically
                  involved but, on picking the wrong allegiance, faced the risk of prompt execution,
                  whereas soldiers of lower rank were often pardoned.<ptr target="#note12"
                     xml:id="nr12" n="12"/> Civilian population too had its share of horrors, though
                  neither side in the civil war treated civilians brutally as an intentional
                     policy,<ptr target="#note13" xml:id="nr13" n="13"/> unlike in some other
                  medieval conflicts. It is therefore not surprising to see interest in divination
                  arise in various contexts, not only in the court and the universities, but also
                  among more middle-class audiences, such as merchants, artisans, or members of
                  religious orders.<ptr target="#note14" xml:id="nr14" n="14"/></p>
               <p>It seems quite likely that both plague and war contributed in some degree to the
                  vast body of astrological and astro-medical texts that survives, particularly from
                  the second half of the fifteenth century.<ptr target="#note15" xml:id="nr15"
                     n="15"/> The texts come in many different levels of sophistication, ranging
                  from university treatises that discuss astronomy or theories derived from Greek
                  and Arabic sources, to horoscopes of royalty, both official and unofficial, as
                  well as portable calendars for physicians and popular moon books, which equate
                  each planet with a day of the week.<ptr target="#note16" xml:id="nr16" n="16"/>
                  These manuscripts, more often than not, contain several languages, testifying to a
                  complicated linguistic situation and challenging any simplified notions of clear
                  division between learned Latin and popular vernacular.<ptr target="#note17"
                     xml:id="nr17" n="17"/></p>
               <p>It has to be noted that it is misleading to assume a neat distinction between
                  astronomy, which can with a good reason be called the first empirical science,<ptr
                     target="#note18" xml:id="nr18" n="18"/> and astrology, which we are used to
                  dismissing as a pseudoscience. The terms were used interchangeably, and if a
                  distinction was made, it was between theoretical and applied aspects of the art,
                  following Ptolemy.<ptr target="#note19" xml:id="nr19" n="19"/> Despite being based
                  on premises that from a modern point of view are false, astrology had a logical,
                  self-consistent foundation in Aristotelian physics<ptr target="#note20"
                     xml:id="nr20" n="20"/> and was assumed to follow the principles of cause and
                  effect. As such, it differed from magic and occult, "in which the theoretical
                  basis" was "deliberately kept esoteric."<ptr target="#note21" xml:id="nr21" n="21"
                  /></p>
               <p>Astrology was less a separate discipline than a generally accepted aspect of the
                  medieval worldview.<ptr target="#note22" xml:id="nr22" n="22"/> It was "rarely
                  viewed as unworkable in principle" and was considered relevant for many things,
                  including weather forecasting and agriculture.<ptr target="#note23" xml:id="nr23"
                     n="23"/> Astrology had also been incorporated into the teaching of university-trained physicians. It belonged to the <hi rend="italic">quadrivium</hi>, the
                  higher part of the undergraduate degree. But astronomy played the biggest part in
                  the postgraduate faculty of medicine, and students who specialized in it were
                  expected to have more advanced knowledge of astronomy,<ptr target="#note24"
                     xml:id="nr24" n="24"/> but as mentioned above, much of the surviving
                  astro-medical literature is more utilitarian in its focus, and the theoretical
                  content is simplified.</p>
            </div>
            <div>
               <head>Trinity O.1.77 and the "Sloane" Group of Middle English Manuscripts</head>
               <p>The text edited here survives in Trinity College Cambridge O.1.77, a medical
                  handbook containing texts on medicine, alchemy, and astrology. The manuscript was
                  described by Voigts in relation to what she calls the Sloane Group of Middle
                  English manuscripts.<ptr target="#note25" xml:id="nr25" n="25"/> The reason for
                  the name is that many of the manuscripts were part of the collection of Sir Hans
                  Sloane, one of the three collections on which the British Library was based.</p>
               <p>The Sloane Group, as defined by Voigts,<ptr target="#note26" xml:id="nr26" n="26"
                  /> consists of two groups. Six of the manuscripts share a number of physical
                  similarities. They are all copied on quarto-sized paper,<ptr target="#note27"
                     xml:id="nr27" n="27"/> with a very distinctive <hi rend="italic"
                     >mise-en-page</hi>, characterized by wide margins: the writing frame varies
                  between 120 by 72 mm and 130 (in one instance 143) by 95 mm. Voigts calls these
                  the "core group," featuring a set of recurring hands, most of which use a very
                  compressed form of Secretary script. The six manuscripts she includes in the group are BL
                  Sloane 1118, Sloane 1313, Sloane 2320, Sloane 2567, Sloane 2948 and the BL
                  Additional MS 19674. The core manuscripts do not contain any overlapping texts,
                  but are united by a shared subject matter: medicine, astrology, alchemy, and
                  magic.</p>
               <p>Trinity O.1.77, on the other hand, is part of a latter group, which vary more in
                  terms of their physical appearance but share a number of recurring treatises.
                  These include three "siblings," Trinity O.1.77, Boston Countway Library of
                  Medicine MS 19, and BL Sloane 3566, which are smaller in size than the
                  quarto-manuscripts and two lavish postmedieval (1480s–1490s) deluxe codices, Tokyo
                  Takamiya 33 and Gonville and Caius 336/725, which Voigts calls "the second
                  generation of a family that has grown prosperous."<ptr target="#note28"
                     xml:id="nr28" n="28"/> One of the core group manuscripts, Sloane 2320, forms a
                  link between the two groups, as it also contains shared texts of the sibling
                  group.</p>
               <p>In addition, there are a number of manuscripts that cannot be said to qualify for
                  either group, but do display some resemblance. Oxford Bodleian Library MS
                  Rawlinson C.815, a medical codex written in 1554, contains two leaves in the end
                  that display all the characteristics of the core group. One section in British
                  Library Additional MS 5467, ff. 195–204, has a somewhat similar <hi rend="italic"
                     >mise-en-page</hi>. Wellcome Historical Medical Library MS 784 shares one
                  plague treatise with the sibling manuscripts, and the writing area is of a similar
                  size to the core group. However, the hand and the watermarks are not. Voigts
                  treats these three under the label "some family resemblance."<ptr target="#note29"
                     xml:id="nr29" n="29"/></p>
               <p>The Sloane manuscripts have evoked interest for two reasons: (1) they may be
                  evidence of systematic commercial production of medical texts, in London or its
                  surrounding areas, slightly before Caxton and the first printing press,<ptr
                     target="#note30" xml:id="nr30" n="30"/> and (2) Latin and English seem to be
                  on the same level in them. The English texts do not directly gloss the Latin ones,
                  and the contents in both languages are of equal sophistication.<ptr
                     target="#note31" xml:id="nr31" n="31"/></p>
               <p>There are some external pieces of evidence that connect these manuscripts to the book
                  trade in London or the surrounding suburbs.<ptr target="#note32" xml:id="nr32"
                     n="32"/> The BL Additional MS 5467, although its relevance for the group can be
                  contested, contains items translated by John Shirley, known for his activities as
                  a scribe, translator, and book collector in mid-fifteenth-century London.<ptr
                     target="#note33" xml:id="nr33" n="33"/> The core group manuscript Sloane 2948
                  has a scribal signature stating it was copied in London in July 1462, in the
                  second year in the reign of Edward IV.<ptr target="#note34" xml:id="nr34" n="34"/>
                  In the case of one sibling manuscript, Boston MS 19, both the commissioner and
                  scribe are known. The manuscript was copied by the Westminster scribe William
                  Ebesham for John Paston II.<ptr target="#note35" xml:id="nr35" n="35"/> Moreover,
                  the manuscript can be dated and localized with unusual precision, since it is
                  apparent from the Paston letters that Ebesham undertook the work of copying a
                  "litill booke of pheesyk" during summer 1468, when Paston was in France for the
                  wedding of Princess Margaret of York. Ebesham, at the time, was confined to
                  Westminster on account of his debts.<ptr target="#note36" xml:id="nr36" n="36"
                  /></p>
               <p>Professional book production<ptr target="#note37" xml:id="nr37" n="37"/> is
                  suggested by the fact that in each of the sibling manuscripts the sibling sequence
                  of texts is written by a single scribe, a different scribe for each
                     manuscript,<ptr target="#note38" xml:id="nr38" n="38"/> who is able to maintain
                  consistent quality and clear duct throughout the whole sequence. All the
                  manuscripts have uniform layout throughout the sibling sequence of texts. The
                  quality of workmanship in all of them can be deemed to be on a professional level.
                  Two of them are deluxe items, the rest display good craftsmanship. The material is
                  paper for Trinity O.1.77, Boston MS 19, and Sloane 2320. Sloane 3566 is on
                  parchment, as are the two postmedieval codices Gonville and Caius 336/725 and
                  Tokyo Takamiya 33, which is unusual for medical manuscripts as late as the 1480s
                  or 1490s and points more toward their being upmarket items.</p>
               <p>According to Voigts, the Sloane Group manuscripts are important because "they
                  suggest a uniformity and co-ordination in late medieval English book production
                  that has not hitherto been noted."<ptr target="#note39" xml:id="nr39" n="39"/> She
                  further states that "it appears that an individual or a group co-ordinated and
                  exercised control over the subject matter and presentation of these books. Such a
                  publisher, who seems to have specialized in scientific and medical books in the
                  1450s and 1460s, must have been responsible for the uniformity of the Sloane
                     Group."<ptr target="#note40" xml:id="nr40" n="40"/></p>
               <div>
                  <head>Shared Treatises in Trinity O.1.77 and the Sloane Siblings</head>
                  <p>As mentioned above, the five Sloane sibling manuscripts are united by a kind of
                     "set text" of joint treatises, after which <hi rend="italic">The Trinity Seven
                        Planets</hi> appears as an extra item. The sequence of texts can be found in
                     all the Sloane siblings, even though there may be some minor variation in
                     order, and the two large postmedieval codices omit some texts. The set texts
                     can also be found in one of the core group manuscripts, Sloane 2320, in which
                     it forms an individual booklet at the beginning of the codex.</p>
                  <p>In this section, I discuss this group in some detail. These texts represent
                     standardization and attempts at producing copies of popular texts as
                     efficiently as possible, which is the main reason why the Sloane Group is
                     considered important evidence of organized book production before printing.
                     These texts are also the main context for <hi rend="italic">The Trinity Seven
                        Planets</hi>, which appears integrated into the predominantly Latin
                     astrological section of the manuscript.</p>
                  <p>The collection of texts provides information on how to make a prognosis based
                     on uroscopy or astrology, as well as information on diet, laxative and
                     purgative medicines, and treatments for the plague.<ptr target="#note41"
                        xml:id="nr41" n="41"/> The organization resembles, among others, the
                     commonplace book compiled by John Crophill, bailiff at Wix Priory in Essex from
                     1455 to 1477, which now survives as BL MS Harley 1735, or the astro-medical
                     handbook BL Sloane 1315.<ptr target="#note42" xml:id="nr42" n="42"/> The
                     difference is that in the case of the Sloane siblings, almost identical copies
                     of the same texts are found, in the same order, in several
                     commercially produced manuscripts.</p>
                  <figure type="enlargeOnClick">
                     <head>The figure illustrates this sequence of texts in Trinity O.1.77.</head>
                     <figDesc>The figure illustrates this sequence of texts in Trinity
                        O.1.77.</figDesc>
                     <graphic n="1001" height="600px" url="media/image1.jpg" rend="inline"/>
                  </figure>
                  <p>The anthology starts with a text on laxative, digestive, and purgative remedies
                     (1). It is followed by three uroscopical treatises, two in Middle English (2
                     &amp; 3) and one in Latin (4). Text number 5 is a regimen of health, presented
                     as Aristotle's letter to Alexander the Great (5), after which are two short
                     texts containing instructions for manufacturing "aqua mirabilis" (6 &amp; 7).
                     The next three texts are all different versions of the same plague treatise
                     attributed to John of Burgundy (8–10), and contain essentially the same
                        information.<ptr target="#note43" xml:id="nr43" n="43"/> The anthology
                     concludes with a sequence of astrological texts (11–16).</p>
                  <p>The sequence of set texts includes items that are known only from the Sloane
                     siblings, as well as very common ones that could be termed, rather
                     anachronistically, as "best sellers" among medical texts in late medieval
                     England and are encountered in numerous manuscripts. The former includes the
                     treatise on laxative and purgative remedies (1) and the shorter Latin uroscopy
                     text <hi rend="italic">expositiones urinarum in ordine</hi> (4), which are
                     known only from Sloane siblings.<ptr target="#note44" xml:id="nr44" n="44"/>
                     The latter includes uroscopical treatises <hi rend="italic">Practica
                        Urinarum</hi> (2) and especially the <hi rend="italic">Twenty-Jordan
                        Series</hi> (3), which survives in more than fifty manuscripts.<ptr
                        target="#note45" xml:id="nr45" n="45"/> The plague treatises attributed to
                     John of Burgundy (8–10) are also of a very common type, known to be extant
                     across Europe. The ubiquituous image of zodiac man (13) also has to be counted
                     among these, since it survives in hundreds of astro-medical manuscripts from
                     the eleventh century onward.<ptr target="#note46" xml:id="nr46" n="46"/></p>
                  <p>
                     <hi rend="italic">The Trinity Seven Planets</hi> is an interesting exception to
                     this. All the other Middle English texts are popular items surviving in several
                     manuscripts, but this manuscript, which does not differ so remarkably from the
                     other two similar-sized ones, both of which appear to be the work of a
                     professional scribe, contains a translation of an astrological text that is not
                     known from other sources.</p>
                  <figure type="enlargeOnClick">
                     <head>The figure illustrates how <hi rend="italic">The Trinity Seven
                           Planets</hi> is located within the manuscript. Texts copied in the hand
                        of the main scribe are shown as continuous blocks; independent codicological
                        units are shown as separate ones.</head>
                     <figDesc>The figure illustrates how The Trinity Seven Planets is located within
                        the manuscript; Texts copied in the hand of the main scribe are shown as
                        continuous blocks; independent codicological units are shown as separate
                        ones.</figDesc>
                     <graphic n="1002" height="850px" url="media/image2.jpg" rend="inline"/>
                  </figure>
                  <p>In all the other manuscripts, except Boston MS 19, the treatises are
                     accompanied by additional material. There is more variation in the astrological
                     texts at the end of the shared "set texts" of Sloane siblings than there is in
                     the preceding ones.<ptr target="#note47" xml:id="nr47" n="47"/> The two
                     postmedieval deluxe codices, Takamiya 33 and Gonville and Caius 336/725, do not
                     share with the other four manuscripts the astrological texts at the end, but
                     they share a number of other texts with each other.</p>
                  <p>Trinity O.1.77 differs from the other manuscripts by changing the order
                        slightly,<ptr target="#note48" xml:id="nr48" n="48"/> and by including
                     additional texts. The treatise on <hi rend="italic">Aqua Mirabilis &amp;
                        Preciosa</hi> (7) is placed differently in this manuscript. In the other
                     Sloane siblings it precedes the <hi rend="italic">Tractatus de Regimine
                        Sanitatis</hi> (5).<ptr target="#note49" xml:id="nr49" n="49"/> The
                     additional texts include a longer astrological section and two alchemical
                     texts: the Pseudo-Arnaldian <hi rend="italic">De Vinis</hi> and John of
                     Rupescissa's <hi rend="italic">Book of Quintessence</hi>.<ptr target="#note50"
                        xml:id="nr50" n="50"/></p>
                  <p>However, most importantly, the manuscript includes a longer astrological
                     section than other Sloane sibling manuscripts. It is made of several texts, and
                     the order corresponds roughly to the standard organization of astrological
                     treatises found, for example, in the <hi rend="italic">Speculum
                        Astronomiae</hi> or Nicole Oresme's <hi rend="italic">Livre de
                        Divinacions</hi>, and which was derived from Arabic sources.<ptr
                        target="#note51" xml:id="nr51" n="51"/></p>
               </div>
            </div>
            <div>
               <head>The Seven Planets</head>
               <p>Found in a macaronic manuscript, in the middle of Latin texts, <hi rend="italic"
                     >The Trinity Seven Planets</hi> is an intriguing text. It is neither
                  particularly popular,<ptr target="#note52" xml:id="nr52" n="52"/> nor does it
                  represent the most technical type of astrological literature. It could perhaps be
                  described in the same way as Tavormina describes the <hi rend="italic"
                     >Twenty-Jordan Series</hi> of uroscopies, that is, occupying an intermediate
                     position.<ptr target="#note53" xml:id="nr53" n="53"/> This is also very
                  characteristic of scientific literature of the fifteenth century, which was
                  practically rather than theoretically oriented, and "regarded science primarily as
                  a source of information which would help" to "achieve practical results in the
                     world."<ptr target="#note54" xml:id="nr54" n="54"/></p>
               <p>The treatise begins with a reference to Ptolemy's <hi rend="italic">Almegest</hi>,<ptr target="#note55" xml:id="nr55" n="55"/> and describes the seven planets
                  and the "great circle" of zodiac, which is divided in twelve "even equations"
                  named after "certain beasts and fishes for convenience and likeness in certain
                  properties." The twelve signs are listed. They are followed by a description of
                  how long each planet takes in its orbit. This is based on the standard Ptolemaic
                     cosmology.<ptr target="#note56" xml:id="nr56" n="56"/></p>
               <p>Other authorities referred to in the text, include "moyses", "raby" (f. 134v) and
                  "sidrack" (ff. 134v and 135v). "Moyses" very likely refers to the twelfth-century
                  Jewish scholar Mosheh ben Maimon Maimonides, commonly known as Rabbi Moyses in the
                  Middle Ages. "Raby" is more problematic. It is possible that the scribe mixed the
                  order of the names, and the reference is intended as "raby moyses" instead of
                  "moyses sidrack raby" (f. 134v). Other possibilities are Aaron ben Gershon Abu
                  Al-Rabi of Catania, who was a cabalist and astrologer in Sicilia, in the fifteenth
                  century, which may be too late, or Muhiyuddin Muhammad ibn Arabi (1165–1240), an
                  Andalusian mystic and philosopher. Sidrack is almost certainly a reference to the
                  popular book of knowledge, edited as <hi rend="italic">Sidrak and Bokkus</hi>,<ptr
                     target="#note57" xml:id="nr57" n="57"/> which is an encyclopedic dialogue
                  between the two main characters, Sidrak and Bokkus, extant in numerous manuscripts
                  from Italy to Ireland to Denmark.</p>
               <p>The treatise does not contain detailed instructions on how to calculate the
                  position of each planet (they can be found in the previous treatise). What it does
                  include is information on the different regions whose climate is governed by each
                  sign based on its "property and nature." The locations are in the Mediterranean
                  region: the east party, Antioch, is governed by Cancer, Leo, and Virgo. The west
                  party, Armenia, is governed by Capricorn, Aquarius, and Pisces. The south party,
                  Alexandria, is governed by Libra, Sagittarius, and Scorpio. The north party,
                  Constantinople, is governed by Aries, Taurus and Gemini.</p>
               <p>The main part of the treatise is taken by descriptions of the effects of the
                  various planets, presented in the order of distance from the sun according to
                  Ptolemaic cosmology. Starting from the farthest, Saturn, and ending with the
                  closest, the moon. The information includes the "triplicities" for each of
                     them,<ptr target="#note58" xml:id="nr58" n="58"/> that is, whether they are
                  masculine or feminine, diurnal or nocturnal, and what element they represent: dry,
                  moist, airy, or fiery. It is also stated whether the planet is good, evil, or in
                  between ("mean"). The two evil planets are Saturn and Mars, the two good planets
                  Jupiter and Venus. The remaining three, Sol, Luna, and Mercury, are in between.
                  The evil and good planets lessen or increase the effects of other planets. The
                  description for each planet also includes how long it takes the planet to travel
                  around the earth. Furthermore, it lists which zodiacal signs are the natural
                  houses for each planet (one for Sol and Luna, two for the other five). The
                  descriptions are related to physiognomy, since they include information on what
                  the children of each planet are like, including both inward and outward
                  description (the complexion of the patient: whether someone is choleric,
                  melancholy, and so forth, and what the children look like).</p>
            </div>
            <div>
               <head>Previous Work</head>
               <p>The manuscript Trinity O.1.77 is described in two printed catalogues of
                  manuscripts in possession of the Wren Library: James (1900-1904) and Mooney
                     (1995).<ptr target="#note59" xml:id="nr59" n="59"/> James includes both the
                  Latin and Middle English sections in the manuscript, and is the only catalogue to
                  do so. However, some of the information is not completely accurate. Most
                  importantly, he treats the astrological part as a single block. Mooney is more up
                  to date with secondary research but only describes the Middle English items in the
                  manuscript. In addition, the contents of Trinity O.1.77 are among those listed in
                  the <hi rend="italic">Electronic Voigts and Kurtz</hi> (eVK) and the <hi
                     rend="italic">Electronic Thorndike and Kibre</hi> (eTK); eVK contains the
                  Middle English texts and eTK the Latin ones. Most detailed work on the manuscript
                  has been carried out by Voigts,<ptr target="#note60" xml:id="nr60" n="60"/> who
                  describes Trinity O.1.77 in relation to the Sloane Group of Middle English
                  manuscripts. Kurtz and Voigts list five of the Sloane sibling manuscripts as
                  closely related to the large codex Trinity College Cambridge R.14.52, excluding
                  only Trinity O.1.77.<ptr target="#note61" xml:id="nr61" n="61"/></p>
               <p>Claire Jones treats the Sloane Group in relation to identifiable discourse
                     communities.<ptr target="#note62" xml:id="nr62" n="62"/> She mainly follows
                  Voigts in her description, noting that "[t]he uniformity of the main Sloane Group
                  manuscripts does not point to a Westminster medical discourse community, as
                  Westminster was a centre of book production, and the book producers and stationers
                  based in the area did business with book buyers from a very wide area."<ptr
                     target="#note63" xml:id="nr63" n="63"/> With Boston MS 19, she reasons that
                  "[t]he Paston men spent a great deal of time in London on business, and it is
                  possible that Paston came across the Sloane Group manuscripts whilst in London,
                  and decided to have a similar copy made for his family."<ptr target="#note64"
                     xml:id="nr64" n="64"/> However, Jones also notes connections to other groups of
                  medical manuscripts localized in the area of Norfolk, East Anglia, and
                     Lincolnshire.<ptr target="#note65" xml:id="nr65" n="65"/></p>
               <p>The Sloane manuscripts with a particular interest in Boston MS 19 and the Paston
                  household are also briefly addressed by Green in her article on women's
                     literacy.<ptr target="#note66" xml:id="nr66" n="66"/> She mentions the
                  bilingual Sloane group as a part of a "veritable mass production of volumes of
                  medical and scientific texts that employed English and Latin on an essentially
                  equal basis, suggesting that despite the well-documented explosion of vernacular
                  medical writing in England […] <hi rend="italic">bilingual</hi> […], not
                  monolingual, readers continued to be the targeted audience of most medical
                     books."<ptr target="#note67" xml:id="nr67" n="67"/> With respect to Boston MS
                  19, she wonders whether the Paston women would have "had the skills in logical and
                  dialectic mathematics to absorb and assimilate the technical explanations of the
                  'hidden' causes of disease or the calculation of the positions of the moon in the
                  different houses."<ptr target="#note68" xml:id="nr68" n="68"/></p>
               <p>Pahta mentions the Sloane group of Middle English manuscripts as an example of
                  multilingualism in the fifteenth century. The object of her study, however, is
                  code-switching from Middle English to Latin in texts in which Middle English is
                  the dominant language, using the <hi rend="italic">Middle English Medical
                     Texts</hi> corpus. She draws on Voigts for the description: "a bilingual
                  anthology extant in six fifteenth-century manuscripts related to the Sloane Group
                  displays an equivalent use of Latin and English, containing, for example, texts on
                  uroscopy, plague and a regimen of health."<ptr target="#note69" xml:id="nr69"
                     n="69"/></p>
               <p>Taavitsainen makes use of Trinity O.1.77 and the Sloane group as anchorage points,
                  based on the external evidence connecting them to London, in her dialectological
                  study of the Middle English translations of Guy de Chauliac.<ptr target="#note70"
                     xml:id="nr70" n="70"/> She remarks that the manuscripts are mostly in Latin,
                  "but some texts are written in English" and that the "vernacular material is not
                  very comprehensive, and the scope of the texts varies."<ptr target="#note71"
                     xml:id="nr71" n="71"/> She finds Trinity O.1.77 the most suitable for a
                  dialectological analysis among the group, since it contains more Middle English
                  than the rest,<ptr target="#note72" xml:id="nr72" n="72"/> a fact that mainly
                  results from the additional longer text on the seven planets.</p>
               <p>The shorter treatise on Seven Planets found in all Sloane sibling manuscripts has
                  been edited and published by Harley, who uses the Boston Countway Library MS 19 as
                  a basis for the edition (1982). Two treatises on Seven Planets, which are not
                  textually affiliated with the current one, have been published by Brown (1994) and
                  Carillo-Linares (2006). The former is shorter and more limited than the one in
                  Trinity O.1.77.<ptr target="#note73" xml:id="nr73" n="73"/> It includes
                  descriptions of the properties of the seven planets, physiognomical description of
                  recognizing their "children," and a nativity based on the days of the week on
                  which one is born. It does not contain tables or instructions for making
                  calculations on the positions of the planets. The text edited by Carillo-Linares,
                  on the other hand, is longer and more detailed, presenting information in the
                  vernacular, which is only found in Latin in the Trinity O.1.77. This is in line
                  with the ambitious vernacularization program of Trinity 14.52.<ptr
                     target="#note74" xml:id="nr74" n="74"/> Out of these four vernacular treatises
                  on the Seven Planets, the Trinity O.1.77 is thus the second longest and second
                  most detailed.</p>
               <p>Other texts in the sibling manuscripts that have been edited include the <hi
                     rend="italic">Twenty-Jordan Series</hi>.<ptr target="#note75" xml:id="nr75"
                     n="75"/> Tavormina divides various versions of the treatise into subgroups
                  based on the order in which the urine flasks, jordans, are depicted in them and
                  what additional information they include. According to her, the treatises in the
                  Sloane sibling manuscripts form a category of their own based on the order in
                  which the jordans are presented, called the Rubea group.<ptr target="#note76"
                     xml:id="nr76" n="76"/> The John of Burgundy treatises have also been subjected
                  to thorough recent studies by Matheson,<ptr target="#note77" xml:id="nr77" n="77"
                  /> including an edition of the Middle English version of the text found in Trinity
                  R 14.52.<ptr target="#note78" xml:id="nr78" n="78"/> Out of the texts in the
                  sizeable compendium Gonville and Caius 336/725, <hi rend="italic">The Golden
                     Table of Pythagoras</hi> has been edited by Voigts.<ptr target="#note79"
                     xml:id="nr79" n="79"/></p>
            </div>
            <div>
               <head>Manuscript Description</head>
               <p>Like all manuscripts with the O-designation in the Trinity College, Trinity O.1.77
                  was part of a collection accumulated by Dr. Thomas Gale (1635/6–1702) and his
                  eldest son, Roger (1672–1744), which was donated to the library by the latter in
                     1738.<ptr target="#note80" xml:id="nr80" n="80"/> An older shelfmark for it is
                  394. It is, however, not mentioned in the catalogue published by Bernard some
                  forty years before.<ptr target="#note81" xml:id="nr81" n="81"/></p>
               <p>There are two earlier collections included in the Gale collection that are of
                  potential interest. First are relics of the library of Dr. John Dee, most of which
                  "are alchemical and date from near his own time; but there are also one or two
                  older manuscripts of considerable value."<ptr target="#note82" xml:id="nr82"
                     n="82"/> The catalogue of Dee's library, written in his own hand, is also part
                  of the collections of the Wren Library (R.4.20). However, even though several
                  works by John of Rupescissa and Arnald of Villa Nova are listed in Trinity R.4.20,
                  none of the manuscripts described fully matches Trinity O.1.77. Moreover, since
                  the collections of a figure such as John Dee have evoked considerable interest,
                  many of the manuscripts owned by him have been identified.<ptr target="#note83"
                     xml:id="nr83" n="83"/> If Trinity O.1.77 would have been one of them, it would
                  certainly have become established in second literature, especially considering the
                  fact that it is part of the Gale collection of Trinity College Cambridge, the
                  location of many of the manuscripts, including the catalogue.</p>
               <p>The second possibility is the manuscripts formerly owned by William Dun.
                  According to James, "There are a good many medical note-books of the sixteenth
                  century, mostly the property of one William Dun; while medieval astronomy,
                  astrology and mathematics (especially ecclesiastical arithmetic, or Compotus), are
                  represented by nearly thirty volumes."<ptr target="#note84" xml:id="nr84" n="84"/>
                  The subject matter of Trinity O.1.77 would fit this collection. However, the
                  manuscript originates in the fifteenth not sixteenth century, and there is very
                  little evidence of sixteenth-century provenance. The conclusion to be drawn is
                  therefore that the evidence is not sufficient to link Trinity O.1.77 to either of
                  these collections.</p>
               <figure type="enlargeOnClick">
                  <head>Trinity O.1.77</head>
                  <figDesc>Trinity O.1.77</figDesc>
                  <graphic n="1003" height="600px" url="media/image3.jpg" rend="inline"/>
               </figure>
               <p>The manuscript is bound in a white imitation-vellum spine and purple-gray
                  cardboard boards. This type of fairly rough, seventeenth- or eighteenth-century
                  binding is standard for Gale manuscripts, and could well originate with them.<ptr
                     target="#note85" xml:id="nr85" n="85"/> One of the most striking aspects about
                  the manuscript is its small size. At only 75 by 100 mm, it can best be described
                  as pocket-sized.</p>
               <p>Ff. 204. Paper, with parchment leaves in the beginning and end. 105 by 70 mm.
                  Frame 70 by 50 mm, containing 13–18 lines per folium.</p>
               <p>COLLATION:<ptr target="#note86" xml:id="nr86" n="86"/> quired in eights 3
                  flyleaves (2 parchment, 1 paper) + 1<hi rend="superscript">8</hi>–14<hi
                     rend="superscript">8</hi>, 14<hi rend="superscript">8–1</hi>, 15<hi
                     rend="superscript">8</hi>–18<hi rend="superscript">8</hi>, 19<hi
                     rend="superscript">6 </hi>, 20<hi rend="superscript">1</hi>, 21<hi
                     rend="superscript">8</hi>, 22<hi rend="superscript">8–1</hi>, 23<hi
                     rend="superscript">8</hi>–25<hi rend="superscript">8</hi>, 26<hi
                     rend="superscript">8–1</hi> (the final quire is on parchment).</p>
               <p>The manuscript is mainly written on paper. Parchment can be found in the beginning
                  and end. First two flyleaves are on parchment, as is the final quire (26) in its
                  entirety. In addition, the manuscript contains one paper flyleaf (the third one
                  from the beginning). The foliation runs from 1 to 202. There are two
                  inconsistencies in numbering. Quire 4 is a regular quire of eight, but the
                  foliation jumps from 27 to 29. Quire 23 contains leaves numbered 170a and 170b.
                  The leaves are sextodecimo-sized <ptr target="#note87" xml:id="nr87" n="87"/> as
                  shown by the chain-lines and watermarks in top right corners of the folia.</p>
            </div>
            <div>
               <head>Paleographical Analysis</head>
               <p>This section contains a paleographical analysis of the two main hands in the
                  Trinity O.1.77 manuscript. There are three reasons for carrying it out: <list
                     type="bulleted">
                     <item>There has been a growing interest in commercial production of manuscripts
                        in the metropolitan London area. One of the major contributions is the <hi
                           rend="italic">Late Medieval English Scribes</hi> website,<ptr
                           target="#note88" xml:id="nr88" n="88"/> which is a catalogue of all the
                        hands that appear in the writings of Geoffrey Chaucer, John Gower, John
                        Trevisa, William Langland, and Thomas Hoccleve. Since the Sloane Group
                        manuscripts are also connected to commercial book production, one piece of
                        research that needs to be carried out is comparing the scribal hands in them
                        to the hands that have copied Middle English literary manuscripts. For that
                        reason, I use the same format as for that website.</item>
                     <item>As Hands A and B are very close to each other, this analysis will help
                        the reader of this edition to distinguish them.</item>
                     <item>I find the visual presentation of features more useful than the prose
                        description traditionally used in editions. In order to make use of the
                        possibilities of the digital format, I prefer to show the hands with
                        images.</item>
                  </list>I use the same list of letters employed by the <hi rend="italic">Late
                     Medieval English Scribes</hi> website: <hi rend="italic">a</hi>, <hi
                     rend="italic">d</hi>, <hi rend="italic">g</hi>, <hi rend="italic">h</hi>, <hi
                     rend="italic">r</hi>, <hi rend="italic">s</hi>, <hi rend="italic">w</hi>, <hi
                     rend="italic">y</hi>. They consider these letters as having "the most variable
                  forms in late medieval English scripts" and consequently "the best distinguishing
                  graphs of a scribal hand."</p>
               <div>
                  <head>Hand A</head>
                  <p>The manuscript is, for the most part, written by a single hand, responsible for
                     both Latin and the Middle English texts in the manuscript. James describes Hand
                     A as "roughly written."<ptr target="#note89" xml:id="nr89" n="89"/> Voigts
                     labels it "pointed Anglicana."<ptr target="#note90" xml:id="nr90" n="90"/></p>
                  <p>The strong presence of Anglicana features differs from the most closely related
                     manuscripts. Boston MS 19 and Sloane 2320 are both written in Secretary. Sloane
                     3566 is written in a different hand, whose grade resembles Trinity O.1.77, but
                     it also shows stronger prevalence for Secretary forms of the letters.</p>
                  <table xmlns:html="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml" rend="rules">
                     <head>a</head>
                     <row>
                        <cell>
                           <graphic n="1004" height="90px" url="media/image4.png" rend="inline"/>
                        </cell>
                        <cell>
                           <graphic n="1005" height="90px" url="media/image5.png" rend="inline"/>
                        </cell>
                        <cell>f. 123r</cell>
                     </row>
                     <row>
                        <cell>
                           <graphic n="1006" height="90px" url="media/image6.png" rend="inline"/>
                        </cell>
                        <cell>
                           <graphic n="1007" height="90px" url="media/image7.png" rend="inline"/>
                        </cell>
                        <cell>f. 126r</cell>
                     </row>
                     <row>
                        <cell>
                           <graphic n="1008" height="90px" url="media/image8.png" rend="inline"/>
                        </cell>
                        <cell>
                           <graphic n="1009" height="90px" url="media/image9.png" rend="inline"/>
                        </cell>
                        <cell>f. 136r</cell>
                     </row>
                     <row>
                        <cell>
                           <graphic n="10010" height="90px" url="media/image10.png" rend="inline"/>
                        </cell>
                        <cell>
                           <graphic n="10011" height="90px" url="media/image11.png" rend="inline"/>
                        </cell>
                        <cell>f. 127v</cell>
                     </row>
                     <row>
                        <cell>
                           <graphic n="10012" height="90px" url="media/image12.png" rend="inline"/>
                        </cell>
                        <cell>
                           <graphic n="10013" height="90px" url="media/image13.png" rend="inline"/>
                        </cell>
                        <cell>f. 123r</cell>
                     </row>
                  </table>
                  <p>The main scribe uses two forms of the letter <hi rend="italic">a</hi>, a
                     single-compartment <hi rend="italic">a</hi>, which is used in the running text,
                     and a two-compartment variant, with an upper lobe that extends above the other
                     letters. The former is characteristic of Secretary and the latter of
                        Anglicana.<ptr target="#note91" xml:id="nr91" n="91"/> The Anglicana
                     double-compartment <hi rend="italic">a</hi> is often used as a small capital or
                        <hi rend="italic">littera notabilior</hi>, but sometimes without clear
                     functional explanation. The use of Anglicana letter forms as capitals is common
                     practice in fifteenth-century manuscripts.<ptr target="#note92" xml:id="nr92"
                        n="92"/> It is frequently highlighted by a red stroke by the rubricator.</p>
                  <table xmlns:html="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml" rend="rules">
                     <head>d</head>
                     <row>
                        <cell>
                           <graphic n="10014" height="90px" url="media/image14.png" rend="inline"/>
                        </cell>
                        <cell>
                           <graphic n="10015" height="90px" url="media/image15.png" rend="inline"/>
                        </cell>
                        <cell>f. 122v</cell>
                     </row>
                     <row>
                        <cell>
                           <graphic n="10016" height="90px" url="media/image16.png" rend="inline"/>
                        </cell>
                        <cell>
                           <graphic n="10017" height="90px" url="media/image17.png" rend="inline"/>
                        </cell>
                        <cell>f. 128r</cell>
                     </row>
                     <row>
                        <cell>
                           <graphic n="10018" height="90px" url="media/image18.png" rend="inline"/>
                        </cell>
                        <cell>
                           <graphic n="10019" height="90px" url="media/image19.png" rend="inline"/>
                        </cell>
                        <cell>f. 132v</cell>
                     </row>
                     <row>
                        <cell>
                           <graphic n="10020" height="90px" url="media/image20.png" rend="inline"/>
                        </cell>
                        <cell>
                           <graphic n="10021" height="90px" url="media/image21.png" rend="inline"/>
                        </cell>
                        <cell>f. 133r</cell>
                     </row>
                  </table>
                  <p>The scribe's <hi rend="italic">d</hi> is a round-backed, two-compartment one,
                     with a looped ascender, a type that originates with Anglicana.<ptr
                        target="#note93" xml:id="nr93" n="93"/> The letter is typically written with
                     a heavy left-slant, sometimes considered Secretary influence.<ptr
                        target="#note94" xml:id="nr94" n="94"/></p>
                  <table xmlns:html="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml" rend="rules">
                     <head>g</head>
                     <row>
                        <cell>
                           <graphic n="10022" height="90px" url="media/image22.png" rend="inline"/>
                        </cell>
                        <cell>
                           <graphic n="10023" height="90px" url="media/image23.png" rend="inline"/>
                        </cell>
                        <cell>f. 123r</cell>
                     </row>
                     <row>
                        <cell>
                           <graphic n="10024" height="90px" url="media/image24.png" rend="inline"/>
                        </cell>
                        <cell>
                           <graphic n="10025" height="90px" url="media/image25.png" rend="inline"/>
                        </cell>
                        <cell>f. 130r</cell>
                     </row>
                     <row>
                        <cell>
                           <graphic n="10026" height="90px" url="media/image26.png" rend="inline"/>
                        </cell>
                        <cell>
                           <graphic n="10027" height="90px" url="media/image27.png" rend="inline"/>
                        </cell>
                        <cell>f. 134v</cell>
                     </row>
                  </table>
                  <p>The scribe uses a two-compartment 8-shaped <hi rend="italic">g</hi>, with a
                     closed loop in the descender. This is a typical Anglicana form and differs from
                     the Secretary form of the letter.<ptr target="#note95" xml:id="nr95" n="95"
                     /></p>
                  <table xmlns:html="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml" rend="rules">
                     <head>h</head>
                     <row>
                        <cell>
                           <graphic n="10028" height="90px" url="media/image28.png" rend="inline"/>
                        </cell>
                        <cell>
                           <graphic n="10029" height="90px" url="media/image29.png" rend="inline"/>
                        </cell>
                        <cell>f. 122v</cell>
                     </row>
                     <row>
                        <cell>
                           <graphic n="10030" height="90px" url="media/image30.png" rend="inline"/>
                        </cell>
                        <cell>
                           <graphic n="10031" height="90px" url="media/image31.png" rend="inline"/>
                        </cell>
                        <cell>f. 124v</cell>
                     </row>
                     <row>
                        <cell>
                           <graphic n="10032" height="90px" url="media/image32.png" rend="inline"/>
                        </cell>
                        <cell>
                           <graphic n="10033" height="90px" url="media/image33.png" rend="inline"/>
                        </cell>
                        <cell>f. 128v</cell>
                     </row>
                     <row>
                        <cell>
                           <graphic n="10034" height="90px" url="media/image34.png" rend="inline"/>
                        </cell>
                        <cell>
                           <graphic n="10035" height="90px" url="media/image35.png" rend="inline"/>
                        </cell>
                        <cell>f. 135r</cell>
                     </row>
                  </table>
                  <p>The <hi rend="italic">h</hi> is a typical Anglicana form with a long descender,
                     which developed to distinguish the letter from <hi rend="italic">b</hi><ptr
                        target="#note96" xml:id="nr96" n="96"/> and a looped ascender. In English,
                     in word-final position it often has a horizontal stroke through its ascender.
                     This may sometimes signal a final <hi rend="italic">e</hi>, but may equally
                     well be otiose.</p>
                  <table xmlns:html="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml" rend="rules">
                     <head>r</head>
                     <row>
                        <cell>2-shaped r, with long descender</cell>
                     </row>
                     <row>
                        <cell>
                           <graphic n="10044" height="90px" url="media/image44.png" rend="inline"/>
                        </cell>
                        <cell>
                           <graphic n="10045" height="90px" url="media/image45.png" rend="inline"/>
                        </cell>
                        <cell>f. 135r</cell>
                     </row>
                     <row>
                        <cell>
                           <graphic n="10046" height="90px" url="media/image46.png" rend="inline"/>
                        </cell>
                        <cell>
                           <graphic n="10047" height="90px" url="media/image47.png" rend="inline"/>
                        </cell>
                        <cell>f. 135r</cell>
                     </row>
                     <row>
                        <cell>small r</cell>
                     </row>
                     <row>
                        <cell>
                           <graphic n="10038" height="90px" url="media/image38.png" rend="inline"/>
                        </cell>
                        <cell>
                           <graphic n="10039" height="90px" url="media/image39.png" rend="inline"/>
                        </cell>
                        <cell>f. 122v</cell>
                     </row>
                     <row>
                        <cell>
                           <graphic n="10040" height="90px" url="media/image40.png" rend="inline"/>
                        </cell>
                        <cell>
                           <graphic n="10041" height="90px" url="media/image41.png" rend="inline"/>
                        </cell>
                        <cell>f. 123r</cell>
                     </row>
                     <row>
                        <cell>tall r</cell>
                     </row>
                     <row>
                        <cell>
                           <graphic n="10036" height="90px" url="media/image36.png" rend="inline"/>
                        </cell>
                        <cell>
                           <graphic n="10037" height="90px" url="media/image37.png" rend="inline"/>
                        </cell>
                        <cell>f. 122v</cell>
                     </row>
                     <row>
                        <cell>
                           <graphic n="10042" height="90px" url="media/image42.png" rend="inline"/>
                        </cell>
                        <cell>
                           <graphic n="10043" height="90px" url="media/image43.png" rend="inline"/>
                        </cell>
                        <cell>f. 125r</cell>
                     </row>
                  </table>
                  <p>The scribe uses three variants of the letter <hi rend="italic">r</hi>, a
                     2-shaped one, with a long descender; a small one, resembling the modern
                     minuscule <hi rend="italic">r</hi>; and the tall Anglicana one. The last one is
                     fairly rare.</p>
                  <table xmlns:html="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml" rend="rules">
                     <head>s</head>
                     <row>
                        <cell>tall s</cell>
                     </row>
                     <row>
                        <cell>
                           <graphic n="10052" height="90px" url="media/image52.png" rend="inline"/>
                        </cell>
                        <cell>
                           <graphic n="10053" height="90px" url="media/image53.png" rend="inline"/>
                        </cell>
                        <cell>f. 122v </cell>
                     </row>
                     <row>
                        <cell>
                           <graphic n="10054" height="90px" url="media/image54.png" rend="inline"/>
                        </cell>
                        <cell>
                           <graphic n="10055" height="90px" url="media/image55.png" rend="inline"/>
                        </cell>
                        <cell>f. 136v</cell>
                     </row>
                     <row>
                        <cell>sigma-shaped s</cell>
                     </row>
                     <row>
                        <cell>
                           <graphic n="10048" height="90px" url="media/image48.png" rend="inline"/>
                        </cell>
                        <cell>
                           <graphic n="10049" height="90px" url="media/image49.png" rend="inline"/>
                        </cell>
                        <cell>f. 122v</cell>
                     </row>
                     <row>
                        <cell>
                           <graphic n="10050" height="90px" url="media/image50.png" rend="inline"/>
                        </cell>
                        <cell>
                           <graphic n="10051" height="90px" url="media/image51.png" rend="inline"/>
                        </cell>
                        <cell>f. 123r</cell>
                     </row>
                  </table>
                  <p>A tall <hi rend="italic">s</hi> is used word-initially and -medially. A
                     sigma-shaped <hi rend="italic">s</hi> is used word-finally. This is a
                     characteristic Anglicana form of the letter.<lb/>
                  </p>
                  <table xmlns:html="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml" rend="rules">
                     <head>w</head>
                     <row>
                        <cell>
                           <graphic n="10056" height="90px" url="media/image56.png" rend="inline"/>
                        </cell>
                        <cell>
                           <graphic n="10057" height="90px" url="media/image57.png" rend="inline"/>
                        </cell>
                        <cell>f. 122v</cell>
                     </row>
                     <row>
                        <cell>
                           <graphic n="10058" height="90px" url="media/image58.png" rend="inline"/>
                        </cell>
                        <cell>
                           <graphic n="10059" height="90px" url="media/image59.png" rend="inline"/>
                        </cell>
                        <cell>f. 124v</cell>
                     </row>
                     <row>
                        <cell>
                           <graphic n="10060" height="90px" url="media/image60.png" rend="inline"/>
                        </cell>
                        <cell>
                           <graphic n="10061" height="90px" url="media/image61.png" rend="inline"/>
                        </cell>
                        <cell>f. 136v</cell>
                     </row>
                  </table>
                  <p>The form used for <hi rend="italic">w</hi> is a typical Anglicana form, in
                     which two long initial strokes are completed by bows.<ptr target="#note97"
                        xml:id="nr97" n="97"/></p>
                  <table xmlns:html="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml" rend="rules">
                     <head>y</head>
                     <row>
                        <cell>
                           <graphic n="10062" height="90px" url="media/image62.png" rend="inline"/>
                        </cell>
                        <cell>
                           <graphic n="10063" height="90px" url="media/image63.png" rend="inline"/>
                        </cell>
                        <cell>f. 122v</cell>
                     </row>
                     <row>
                        <cell>
                           <graphic n="10064" height="90px" url="media/image64.png" rend="inline"/>
                        </cell>
                        <cell>
                           <graphic n="10065" height="90px" url="media/image65.png" rend="inline"/>
                        </cell>
                        <cell>f. 128r</cell>
                     </row>
                     <row>
                        <cell>
                           <graphic n="10066" height="90px" url="media/image66.png" rend="inline"/>
                        </cell>
                        <cell>
                           <graphic n="10067" height="90px" url="media/image67.png" rend="inline"/>
                        </cell>
                        <cell>f. 136v</cell>
                     </row>
                  </table>
                  <p>The letter <hi rend="italic">y</hi> has a long diagonal descender.</p>
               </div>
               <div>
                  <head>Hand B</head>
                  <figure>
                     <head>f. 122r</head>
                     <graphic n="10068" height="110px" url="media/image68.png" rend="inline"/>
                     <figDesc>f. 122r</figDesc>
                  </figure>
                  <figure>
                     <head>f. 127v</head>
                     <graphic n="10069" height="500px" url="media/image69.png" rend="inline"/>
                     <figDesc>f. 127v</figDesc>
                  </figure>
                  <figure>
                     <head>f. 200r</head>
                     <graphic n="10070" height="600px" url="media/image70.jpg" rend="inline"/>
                     <figDesc>f. 200r</figDesc>
                  </figure>
                  <p>The parchment flyleaves 1 and 2 are in another hand, which I call Hand B.
                     Letter forms used by Hand B are very similar to Hand A, and it is possible that
                     it belonged to the same individual.<ptr target="#note98" xml:id="nr98" n="98"/>
                     The one exception to this is the form used for word-final <hi rend="italic"
                        >s</hi>. Hand B uses the kidney-shaped <hi rend="italic">s</hi> in word-final position, which is never used by Hand A. The hand is also slightly more
                     current in appearance. Sections written in it lack rubrication, which indicates
                     that they were written after the codex had been decorated; even if they were by
                     the same scribe, they were added later. The following table illustrates letter
                     forms used by Hand B, which can be found in the marginal comments of <hi
                        rend="italic">The Trinity Seven Planets</hi>. I do not include examples of
                        <hi rend="italic">w</hi> and <hi rend="italic">y</hi>, since the passages
                     are in Latin and I could not locate examples of those letters.</p>
                  <div>
                     <table xmlns:html="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml" rend="rules">
                        <head>a</head>
                        <row>
                           <cell>
                              <graphic n="10071" height="90px" url="media/image71.png" rend="inline"
                              />
                           </cell>
                           <cell>
                              <graphic n="10072" height="90px" url="media/image72.png" rend="inline"
                              />
                           </cell>
                           <cell>127v</cell>
                        </row>
                        <row>
                           <cell>
                              <graphic n="10073" height="90px" url="media/image73.png" rend="inline"
                              />
                           </cell>
                           <cell>
                              <graphic n="10074" height="90px" url="media/image74.png" rend="inline"
                              />
                           </cell>
                           <cell>127v</cell>
                        </row>
                        <row>
                           <cell>
                              <graphic n="10075" height="90px" url="media/image75.png" rend="inline"
                              />
                           </cell>
                           <cell>
                              <graphic n="10076" height="90px" url="media/image76.png" rend="inline"
                              />
                           </cell>
                           <cell>127v</cell>
                        </row>
                        <row>
                           <cell>
                              <graphic n="10077" height="90px" url="media/image77.png" rend="inline"
                              />
                           </cell>
                           <cell>
                              <graphic n="10078" height="90px" url="media/image78.png" rend="inline"
                              />
                           </cell>
                           <cell>200</cell>
                        </row>
                     </table>
                     <p>The minuscule single-compartment <hi rend="italic">a</hi> of Hand B
                        resembles Hand A. Some examples of a two-compartment version can also be
                        found, but without the red highlighting strokes.</p>
                  </div>
                  <div>
                     <table xmlns:html="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml" rend="rules">
                        <head>d</head>
                        <row>
                           <cell>
                              <graphic n="10079" height="90px" url="media/image79.png" rend="inline"
                              />
                           </cell>
                           <cell>
                              <graphic n="10080" height="90px" url="media/image80.png" rend="inline"
                              />
                           </cell>
                           <cell>127v</cell>
                        </row>
                        <row>
                           <cell>
                              <graphic n="10081" height="90px" url="media/image81.png" rend="inline"
                              />
                           </cell>
                           <cell>
                              <graphic n="10082" height="90px" url="media/image82.png" rend="inline"
                              />
                           </cell>
                           <cell>127v</cell>
                        </row>
                        <row>
                           <cell>
                              <graphic n="10083" height="90px" url="media/image83.png" rend="inline"
                              />
                           </cell>
                           <cell>
                              <graphic n="10084" height="90px" url="media/image84.png" rend="inline"
                              />
                           </cell>
                           <cell>127v</cell>
                        </row>
                        <row>
                           <cell>
                              <graphic n="10085" height="90px" url="media/image85.png" rend="inline"
                              />
                           </cell>
                           <cell>
                              <graphic n="10086" height="90px" url="media/image86.png" rend="inline"
                              />
                           </cell>
                           <cell>200</cell>
                        </row>
                     </table>
                     <p>Hand B uses a round-backed <hi rend="italic">d</hi> similar to that used by
                        Hand A.</p>
                  </div>
                  <div>
                     <table xmlns:html="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml" rend="rules">
                        <head>g</head>
                        <row>
                           <cell>
                              <graphic n="10087" height="90px" url="media/image87.png" rend="inline"
                              />
                           </cell>
                           <cell><graphic n="10300" height="90px" url="media/regulaB200.jpg"
                                 rend="inline"/></cell>
                           <cell>200</cell>
                        </row>
                        <row>
                           <cell>
                              <graphic n="10088" height="90px" url="media/image88.png" rend="inline"
                              />
                           </cell>
                           <cell><graphic n="10301" height="90px" url="media/gnguB200.jpg"
                                 rend="inline"/></cell>
                           <cell>200</cell>
                        </row>
                        <row>
                           <cell>
                              <graphic n="10089" height="90px" url="media/image89.png" rend="inline"
                              />
                           </cell>
                           <cell>
                              <graphic n="10302" height="90px" url="media/signoB200.jpg"
                                 rend="inline"/>
                           </cell>
                           <cell>200</cell>
                        </row>
                     </table>
                     <p>The minuscule <hi rend="italic">g</hi> contains a closed-loop descender,
                        which is another similarity with Hand A.</p>
                  </div>
                  <div>
                     <table xmlns:html="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml" rend="rules">
                        <head>h</head>
                        <row>
                           <cell>
                              <graphic n="10090" height="90px" url="media/image90.png" rend="inline"
                              />
                           </cell>
                           <cell>
                              <graphic n="10091" height="90px" url="media/image91.png" rend="inline"
                              />
                           </cell>
                           <cell>127v</cell>
                        </row>
                        <row>
                           <cell>
                              <graphic n="10092" height="90px" url="media/image92.png" rend="inline"
                              />
                           </cell>
                           <cell>
                              <graphic n="10093" height="90px" url="media/image93.png" rend="inline"
                              />
                           </cell>
                           <cell>200</cell>
                        </row>
                     </table>
                     <p>Hand B uses an Anglicana <hi rend="italic">h</hi> with a long descender,
                        which is similar to the variant written by the main scribe, even though it
                        is often squeezed or drawn out, which makes it difficult to estimate the
                        actual resemblance.</p>
                  </div>
                  <div>
                     <table xmlns:html="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml" rend="rules">
                        <head>r</head>
                        <row>
                           <cell>
                              <graphic n="10094" height="90px" url="media/image94.png" rend="inline"
                              />
                           </cell>
                           <cell>
                              <graphic n="10095" height="90px" url="media/image95.png" rend="inline"
                              />
                           </cell>
                           <cell>200</cell>
                        </row>
                        <row>
                           <cell>
                              <graphic n="10096" height="90px" url="media/image96.png" rend="inline"
                              />
                           </cell>
                           <cell>
                              <graphic n="10097" height="90px" url="media/image97.png" rend="inline"
                              />
                           </cell>
                           <cell>200</cell>
                        </row>
                     </table>
                     <p>Hand B's <hi rend="italic">r</hi>'s are mostly not written out, but are
                        represented by abbreviations (e.g., p<hi rend="italic superscript"
                           >i</hi>ma<hi rend="italic">rum</hi>, f. 200r, line 10). The few examples
                        that are present are of the small minuscule type.</p>
                  </div>
                  <div>
                     <table xmlns:html="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml" rend="rules">
                        <head>s</head>
                        <row>
                           <cell>tall s</cell>
                        </row>
                        <row>
                           <cell>
                              <graphic n="10400" height="90px" url="media/handBtalls1.jpg"
                                 rend="inline"/>
                           </cell>
                           <cell>
                              <graphic n="10401" height="90px" url="media/signoB200.jpg"
                                 rend="inline"/>
                           </cell>
                           <cell>200r</cell>
                        </row>
                        <row>
                           <cell>
                              <graphic n="10402" height="90px" url="media/handBtalls2.jpg"
                                 rend="inline"/>
                           </cell>
                           <cell>
                              <graphic n="10403" height="90px" url="media/existenteB200.jpg"
                                 rend="inline"/>
                           </cell>
                           <cell>200r</cell>
                        </row>
                        <row>
                           <cell>kidney-shaped s</cell>
                        </row>
                        <row>
                           <cell>
                              <graphic n="10098" height="90px" url="media/image98.png" rend="inline"
                              />
                           </cell>
                           <cell>
                              <graphic n="10099" height="90px" url="media/image99.png" rend="inline"
                              />
                           </cell>
                           <cell>127v</cell>
                        </row>
                        <row>
                           <cell>
                              <graphic n="100100" height="90px" url="media/image100.png"
                                 rend="inline"/>
                           </cell>
                           <cell>
                              <graphic n="100101" height="90px" url="media/image101.png"
                                 rend="inline"/>
                           </cell>
                           <cell/>
                        </row>
                        <row>
                           <cell>
                              <graphic n="100103" height="90px" url="media/image103.png"
                                 rend="inline"/>
                           </cell>
                           <cell>
                              <graphic n="100102" height="90px" url="media/image102.png"
                                 rend="inline"/>
                           </cell>
                           <cell>200</cell>
                        </row>
                     </table>
                     <p>Hand B uses a kidney-shaped <hi rend="italic">s</hi> in word-final position.
                        This letter is never used by Hand A.</p>
                  </div>
               </div>
               <div>
                  <head>Rubrics</head>
                  <figure>
                     <head>f. 137r</head>
                     <graphic n="100104" height="200px" url="media/image104.png" rend="inline"/>
                     <figDesc>f. 137r</figDesc>
                  </figure>
                  <p>A third hand found in the manuscript belongs to the rubricator. The rubricator
                     has imitated the scribe's letter forms and uses the same set of abbreviations
                     with very similar forms. However, the letter forms are more formal, with the
                     minims for <hi rend="italic">n</hi> and <hi rend="italic">m</hi> not running
                     together, that is, <hi rend="italic">formata</hi> grade rather than <hi
                        rend="italic">media</hi>. The <hi rend="italic">m</hi>'s in particular are
                     constructed of independent minims, and have serifs that are very pronounced, as
                     opposed to Hand A, which runs them together. In addition, the rubricator has
                     read the text very closely and corrected scribal mistakes on several occasions.
                     It is quite likely that despite the different grade, the hand belongs to the
                     same person as Hand A. In the closely related Boston manuscript, the scribe
                     William Ebesham handled both. This is evident from his correspondence with Sir
                     John Paston II. The text on how to use the <hi rend="italic">Tabula
                        Signorum</hi> refers to the parts of the table that are in red and black,
                     showing that the different colors were part of the plan all along (ff. 107r–v).
                     It is very unlikely that this type of decoration would have been commissioned
                     from a separate artisan.<ptr target="#note99" xml:id="nr99" n="99"/></p>
                  <figure>
                     <head>f. 100r</head>
                     <graphic n="100105" height="700px" url="media/image105.JPG" rend="inline"/>
                     <figDesc>f. 100r</figDesc>
                  </figure>
               </div>
            </div>
            <div>
               <head>Marginal Comments</head>
               <p>The manuscript contains numerous marginal comments, most of which appear to be
                  near contemporary. The two most common types are recipes and astrological notes.
                  Almost all these comments are in Latin.</p>
               <p>Three comments in <hi rend="italic">The Trinity Seven Planets</hi> deserve closer
                  attention. One of these is a rare gloss in which the "Main scribe or a near
                  contemporary has added 'Almenake' above 'Almegeste' in the incipit."<ptr
                     target="#note100" xml:id="nr100" n="100"/> The mistake is an interesting one,
                  since it is found in a manuscript of such a late date. Medieval use of the word
                     <hi rend="italic">almanack</hi> differed from the astrological calendars that
                  would become one of the most popular genres of early printed books in the
                  following century <ptr target="#note101" xml:id="nr101" n="101"/>: "almanacs gave
                  the conjunctions and opposition of the sun and the moon, whereas calendars listed
                  the days of the week and the months of the year." However, in the fifteenth
                  century it had already become commonplace to combine the two,<ptr
                     target="#note102" xml:id="nr102" n="102"/> and the advent of printing "opened
                  the floodgates" for production of cheap astrological calendars for "semi-educated
                  European populace."<ptr target="#note103" xml:id="nr103" n="103"/> The marginal
                  note may thus give some clues on the readership of the manuscript. On the one
                  hand, in the Middle Ages, almanacs were directed toward medical professionals and
                  students as opposed to the more general calendars,<ptr target="#note104"
                     xml:id="nr104" n="104"/> and the use could still pertain to that. On the other
                  hand, Ptolemaic cosmology was the cornerstone of astronomical education in
                  medieval universities, and the fact that the annotator does not recognize the <hi
                     rend="italic">Almagest</hi> may be a sign that the he did not receive a
                  university education.</p>
               <p>The other one is a note on f. 127v written by Hand B. It is one of two marginal
                  comments containing a year. Hand B has also added a note on flyleaf 200, on how
                  the conjunction of the celestial spheres will occur in 1460. The date of the
                  manuscript has sometimes been stated as 1460.<ptr target="#note105" xml:id="nr105"
                     n="105"/> This originates with James, who dates the manuscript to that year
                  based on the markings on f. 200.<ptr target="#note106" xml:id="nr106" n="106"/>
                  However, their relationship to the rest of the codex is far from clear. The
                  astrological note on the flyleaf 200 is in Hand B rather than in the hand of the
                  main scribe, and in a section of the manuscript that is not connected to the
                  earlier quires by scribal catchwords. It is thus better to take this date as
                  evidence of provenance, concluding that the manuscript was used by someone who
                  made astrological calculations in 1459–60, and that the likely date for its
                  composition may have been somewhat earlier.<ptr target="#note107" xml:id="nr107"
                     n="107"/></p>
               <p>At any rate, the note on f. 127v mentions how the planet Mars has entered its
                  house Aries in 1459, an event that signifies "stryues &amp; discordes batails
                  &amp; war" (f. 128r), and the likelihood of war was something that caused great
                  concern in the 1450s and early 1460s.<ptr target="#note108" xml:id="nr108" n="108"
                  /> The years 1459 to 1461, in particular, saw some of the major battles in the
                  wars, culminating in Towton in 1461, quite possibly the largest and bloodiest
                  battle to be fought on the soil of England to date,<ptr target="#note109"
                     xml:id="nr109" n="109"/> which led to the ascension of Edward IV and a period
                  of Yorkist rule in the 1460s.</p>
               <p>London&#8212;if we presume the manuscript was used where it was copied, which may
                  not be the case, since a small portable codex could easily have ended up
                  anywhere&#8212;was never besieged or sacked during the Wars of the Roses, but
                  there were some close calls. In 1460, a Lancastrian garrison in the Tower of
                  London commanded by Thomas de Scales, a veteran of the French wars, who had fought
                  against Joan of Arc in the Loire campaign in 1422–23, held out against a Yorkish
                  army for a few weeks, firing its cannons on the city, hurting men, women and
                  children in the streets.<ptr target="#note110" xml:id="nr110" n="110"/></p>
               <p>Less than a year later, in the aftermath of a Lancastrian victory at the Battle of
                   Wakefield on December 30, 1460, Queen Margaret of Anjou and a Lancastrian army
                  camped outside the city. The army included many Scots and Northerners, who were
                  feared in London, because they were badly paid and prone to looting. The threat
                  eventually passed as the army returned back north without being admitted to the
                  city or attacking it.<ptr target="#note111" xml:id="nr111" n="111"/></p>
               <p/>
            </div>
            <div>
               <head>Audience</head>
               <p>What we know about the audience for <hi rend="italic">The Trinity Seven
                     Planets</hi> and manuscript O.1.77 can be briefly summarized.</p>
               <p>The physical characteristics of Trinity O.1.77, along with what is known about the
                  origin and provenance of Boston MS 19, and the fact that the same collection of
                  texts can be found in all of the sibling manuscripts, would support the hypothesis
                  that it was commissioned as a single item, a pocket-sized medical handbook, from a
                  professional scribe, related to the professional book trade of fifteenth century,
                  by an outside patron who may have practiced medicine by profession, but not
                  necessarily so, as the Paston connection of Boston MS 19 shows. Marginal comments
                  point to a readership with good functional literacy in Latin and an interest in
                  astrology. The one on f. 127v is a Latin comment in the Middle English part of the
                  text.</p>
               <p>The small size is characteristic of books meant for practical use. Booklets and
                  folded parchment compilations, called <hi rend="italic">vade mecums</hi> or girdle
                  books, survive in considerable numbers from the fourteenth and fifteenth
                  centuries. They contain short medical treatises as well as tables for making
                     diagnoses.<ptr target="#note112" xml:id="nr112" n="112"/> A slightly longer
                  pocket-sized book like Trinity O.1.77 would provide more comprehensive information
                  while still being very portable. "Only the better sort of physician would have
                  been able to afford such a handy and beautiful reference tool as he travelled to
                  visit important patients."<ptr target="#note113" xml:id="nr113" n="113"/></p>
               <p>The texts in the manuscript are fairly practically oriented, containing
                  illustrations such as the zodiac or a set of twenty urine glasses for showing
                  different colors of urine. They are not university texts, but theoretically they
                  belong to the academic medical tradition, in which sickness was cured by means of
                  diet, bloodletting, and various remedies aimed at restoring the balance of
                  elements within the body.<ptr target="#note114" xml:id="nr114" n="114"/> This is
                  in contrast to surgical treatises, in which the cures were made by surgical
                     operations,<ptr target="#note115" xml:id="nr115" n="115"/> or folk remedies
                  such as Margaret Paston's plaster for a sore knee, whose origins are much less
                     clear.<ptr target="#note116" xml:id="nr116" n="116"/></p>
               <p>One thing that sets the manuscript apart from the rest of the Sloane sibling
                  manuscripts is the longer astrological section, which also includes <hi
                     rend="italic">The Trinity Seven Planets</hi>. In addition to the sibling texts
                  described above, it includes <hi rend="italic">Tabula Signorum</hi>, tables for
                  calculating the house of the moon (ff. 99v–101r); <hi rend="italic">De
                     distinctione temporum</hi>, a short treatise on measurements of time (ff.
                  101r–102v); <hi rend="italic">De septem mocione planetarum</hi>, a treatise on the
                  cycles of each planet, which makes use of the units described in the previous text
                  (ff. 103r–122r), followed by the current treatise, <hi rend="italic">The Trinity
                     Seven Planets</hi> (ff. 122r–136v). The medical emphasis of the astrological
                  treatises is evident from a closer reading of them. One of the treatises shared by
                  all Sloane siblings states that it is intended for a <hi rend="italic"
                     >medicus</hi>,<ptr target="#note117" xml:id="nr117" n="117"/> which makes the
                  medical connection explicit. Medicus is a general word for a medical practitioner
                  but is not likely to be a reference to a surgeon, <hi rend="italic"
                     >chirurgicus</hi>. Bloodletting is also mentioned in <hi rend="italic">De
                     septem mocione planetarum</hi>.</p>
               <p>A noteworthy feature of Trinity O.1.77 is the multilingual nature of its contents.
                  This points toward an audience whose linguistic ability is fairly diverse. This
                  linguistic diversity, along with the professional quality of the workmanship of
                  the manuscripts in which the Sloane sibling sequence of texts can be found and
                  what is known about the commissioning of Boston MS 19, is a feature of the group
                  that Pahta and Taavitsainen consider to have had the next highest level of
                  literacy: learned aristocracy.<ptr target="#note118" xml:id="nr118" n="118"/>
                  "Other sources, such as the Paston letters, show how many households, even those
                  of wealthy families, tended to treat their own ills wherever possible, and turned
                  to a doctor as a last resort."<ptr target="#note119" xml:id="nr119" n="119"/>
                  However, it is equally plausible that Trinity O.1.77, or some of the other Sloane
                  sibling manuscripts, would have been commissioned or bought by either full- or
                  part-time medical practitioners.</p>
            </div>
            <div>
               <head>The Editorial Approach</head>
               <p>My editorial aim is twofold: first, to represent the data with as much fidelity
                  and transparency as possible so that the text is useful for historical
                  linguistics, and second, to make the edition readable for nonspecialists in Middle
                  English by encoding the text with expanded abbreviations and including a glossary
                  via hyperlinks in the text.</p>
               <p>Recent decades have seen a good deal of discussion over what is required of edited
                  texts in order for them to be useful data for historical linguistics.<ptr
                     target="#note120" xml:id="nr120" n="120"/> In editions directed to historians,
                  literary scholars, or language learners, the text is often modified in various
                  ways to suit the needs of the intended readership. Modifications may include
                  things such as supplying modern punctuation, normalizing spelling variation or
                  word division, expanding abbreviations, or emending scribal mistakes.<ptr
                     target="#note121" xml:id="nr121" n="121"/> Using these editions as data for
                  historical linguistics is problematic because editorial modifications deny the
                  reader access to information present in the manuscript; they create a hybrid text
                  that is a mixture of scribal or authorial and editorial language.<ptr
                     target="#note122" xml:id="nr122" n="122"/> This has consequences, for instance,
                  for historical dialectology, which is based on examining spelling variation in
                  medieval vernaculars (LAEME, LALME, LAOS).<ptr target="#note123" xml:id="nr123"
                     n="123"/> Lass, who is particularly scathing in his criticism, asserts that
                  "[v]irtually all editorial interventions in early texts represent potential losses
                  of information, or additions of false information” and that [n]o modern (or any)
                  editor can be said to know the language of a scribe better than the scribe
                     did."<ptr target="#note124" xml:id="nr124" n="124"/></p>
               <p>Lass proposes three desiderata that he considers inviolable for an edition or
                  corpus used as a basis for historical linguistics: maximal information
                  preservation, no irreversible editorial interference, and maximal flexibility.<ptr
                     target="#note125" xml:id="nr125" n="125"/> The present edition takes these
                  points into account. The approach aims to keep all editorial interference
                  transparent and to include as much information about the source as possible. In
                  terms of flexibility, the XML-based approach that is applied here actually far
                  surpasses the ASCII-based markup that is used in LAEME and LAOS.</p>
               <p>The approach here is a graphemic transcription. It records spelling variation,
                  taking into account variant letter forms, which are assumed to have phonological,
                  functional, or lexical significance.<ptr target="#note126" xml:id="nr126" n="126"
                  /> It does not record the different variants of the same letter when they are
                  assumed to stand for the same sound, such as the different forms of <hi
                     rend="italic">s</hi> and <hi rend="italic">r</hi>. However, in the case of
                  thorn and <hi rend="italic">th</hi>, which are likely to stand for the same sound,
                  I have retained the distinction. This is because they are known to have
                  dialectological significance.<ptr target="#note127" xml:id="nr127" n="127"/></p>
               <div>
                  <head>Encoding Abbreviations</head>
                  <p>A main focus is encoding abbreviations. Because of its small size, Trinity
                     O.1.77 contains a considerable number of these.</p>
                  <p>In printed editions, the standard practice is to expand the abbreviations,
                     either silently or in italics, which is partly due to the requirements of the
                     printed medium and the difficulty of representing the abbreviation signs in
                     modern typeface, and partly to a philosophy of editing that has favored
                     critical editions and the construction of a single text from several manuscript
                        witnesses.<ptr target="#note128" xml:id="nr128" n="128"/> While the
                     expansion of abbreviations is understandable, and is sufficient for many
                     research questions, particularly ones focusing on literary texts, it has its
                     share of problems when used as data for historical linguistics.<ptr
                        target="#note129" xml:id="nr129" n="129"/></p>
                  <p>For the study of historical language variants, both the sign of abbreviation
                     that is used and how it is expanded may be of importance. First of all, the
                     signs might have dialectal distributions, resembling what was demonstrated by
                     Benskin to be the case for the graphemes &lt;&#254;&gt; and &lt;y&gt;.<ptr
                        target="#note130" xml:id="nr130" n="130"/> The practice of including only
                     the expansion leaves out necessary data for carrying out this type of
                     research.</p>
                  <p>Secondly, supplying the expansion also involves a degree of editorial
                     intervention that may be far from transparent. In vernacular texts, which
                     contain a large amount of spelling variation, the scribe may use several
                     spellings for the same word. If he has written <hi rend="italic">er</hi> three
                     times and <hi rend="italic">ir</hi> once, and otherwise used an abbreviation,
                     standard editorial practice would lead to always expanding the abbreviation to
                        <hi rend="italic">er</hi>, possibly hundreds of times, thus seriously
                     distorting the frequencies of the two forms<ptr target="#note131"
                        xml:id="nr131" n="131"/> and perhaps creating serious consequences for
                     research on historical dialectology. Rogos draws attention to the fact that
                     expanding abbreviations creates a false parallel between something that is
                     represented by graphemes in a writing system, and symbols, whose relationship
                     to the abbreviated content is more complex and subject to interpretation.<ptr
                        target="#note132" xml:id="nr132" n="132"/> Expanding abbreviations thus
                     leads to a form of linguistic hybridity between editorial and scribal
                        language.<ptr target="#note133" xml:id="nr133" n="133"/></p>
                  <p>On the other hand, it is also easy to see the problems with not expanding the
                     abbreviations. At worst, completely diplomatic editions, which reproduce
                     manuscript abbreviations, punctuation, and layout, can require knowledge of
                     paleographic or typographic conventions to be readable.<ptr target="#note134"
                        xml:id="nr134" n="134"/> Attempts at typographic facsimile editions, such as
                        <hi rend="italic">William and the Werwolf</hi> (1832) by Madden, have never
                     achieved much popularity.<ptr target="#note135" xml:id="nr135" n="135"/> A
                     pocket-sized manuscript such as Trinity O.1.77 contains such numerous
                     abbreviations that if not expanded, they would seriously reduce the readability
                     of the text to anyone who is not an expert in fifteenth-century scientific
                     writings.</p>
                  <p>With digital markup systems such as TEI Guidelines P5,<ptr target="#note136"
                        xml:id="nr136" n="136"/> it is possible, for the first time, to encode both
                     the symbol and its expansion.<ptr target="#note137" xml:id="nr137" n="137"/>
                     The encoding includes both the abbreviation symbol and its expansion. This can
                     be achieved by using the &lt;choice&gt;, &lt;abbr&gt;, &lt;expan&gt;,
                     &lt;ab&gt;, and &lt;ex&gt; tags,<ptr target="#note138" xml:id="nr138" n="138"/>
                     allowing the user to decide which one he or she wants to work with.</p>
                  <p>The basic encoding looks like this:</p>
                  <table xmlns:html="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml" rend="rules">
                     <row>
                        <cell>facsimile</cell>
                        <cell>expansion</cell>
                        <cell>encoding</cell>
                     </row>
                     <row>
                        <cell>
                           <graphic n="100106" height="90px" url="media/image106.png" rend="inline"/>
                           <lb/>f. 123r</cell>
                        <cell>de<hi rend="italic">par</hi>tid</cell>
                        <cell>
                           <hi rend="color(000096)">&lt;choice&gt;</hi>
                           <lb/>
                           <hi rend="color(000096)">&lt;abbr&gt;</hi>de<hi rend="color(000096)"
                              >&lt;am&gt;</hi><hi rend="color(969600)">&amp;#42833;</hi><hi
                              rend="color(000096)">&lt;/am&gt;</hi>tid<hi rend="color(000096)"
                              >&lt;/abbr&gt;</hi>
                           <lb/>
                           <hi rend="color(000096)">&lt;expan&gt;</hi>de<hi rend="color(000096)"
                              >&lt;ex&gt;</hi>par<hi rend="color(000096)">&lt;/ex&gt;</hi>tid<hi
                              rend="color(000096)">&lt;/expan&gt;</hi>
                           <lb/>
                           <hi rend="color(000096)">&lt;/choice&gt;</hi>
                        </cell>
                     </row>
                     <row>
                        <cell>
                           <graphic n="100107" height="90px" url="media/image107.png" rend="inline"/>
                           <lb/>f. 123r</cell>
                        <cell>i<hi rend="italic">n</hi>
                        </cell>
                        <cell>
                           <hi rend="color(000096)">&lt;choice&gt; &lt;abbr&gt;</hi>i<hi
                              rend="color(000096)">&lt;am&gt;</hi>&amp;#x305;<hi
                              rend="color(000096)">&lt;/am&gt;&lt;/abbr&gt; &lt;expan&gt;</hi>i<hi
                              rend="color(000096)">&lt;ex&gt;</hi>n<hi rend="color(000096)"
                              >&lt;/ex&gt;&lt;/expan&gt;</hi>
                           <lb/>
                           <hi rend="color(000096)">&lt;/choice&gt;</hi>
                        </cell>
                     </row>
                  </table>
                  <p>The abbreviated content is enclosed in the &lt;abbr&gt; tags, indicating that
                     they enclose "an abbreviation of any sort." The signs of abbreviation are
                     surrounded by &lt;am&gt; tags, which contain "a sequence of letters or signs
                     present in an abbreviation which are omitted or replaced in the expanded form
                     of the abbreviation." The abbreviation itself is represented by the
                     corresponding numeric value in Unicode.</p>
                  <p>The expanded form is included inside the &lt;expan&gt; tags, indicating the
                     tagged content "contains the expansion of the abbreviation" (cf. TEI P5 3.5.5).
                     The expanded content marked by &lt;ex&gt; ones, indicating it "contains a
                     sequence of letters added by an editor or transcriber when expanding an
                     abbreviation" (cf. TEI P5 11.3.1.2). In the examples above, the signs of
                     abbreviation could, in a different context, stand for <hi rend="italic"
                        >per</hi> or <hi rend="italic">por</hi> (first one), or a different nasal or
                     general sign of abbreviation (the second). The system satisfies the requirement
                     stipulated by Lass of keeping editorial interference transparent, since
                     everything inside the &lt;ex&gt; tags is, by definition, editorial
                        interpretation.<ptr target="#note139" xml:id="nr139" n="139"/></p>
               </div>
               <div>
                  <head>Encoding Superscript Abbreviations</head>
                  <p>A different approach has been adopted with superscript abbreviations. It would
                     have been possible to treat each of them as an abbreviation.<ptr
                        target="#note140" xml:id="nr140" n="140"/> However, since they are a
                     productive category and could be used to coin new abbreviations, the number of
                     potential variants would be large. For example, they are frequently used to
                     denote endings in Latin, as in ext<hi rend="superscript">ea</hi> (ext<hi
                        rend="italic">rema</hi>) and ext<hi rend="superscript">etas</hi> = (ext<hi
                        rend="italic">remitas</hi>) <ptr target="#note141" xml:id="nr141" n="141"/>.
                     In the vernacular, they resulted in innovations like &#254;<hi
                        rend="superscript">e</hi> (<hi rend="italic">the</hi>), or &#254;<hi
                        rend="superscript">t</hi> (<hi rend="italic">that</hi>). Thus, the encoding
                     adopted in the edition is the one found in Cummings, who uses the &lt;hi
                     rend="superscript"&gt; tags.<ptr target="#note142" xml:id="nr142" n="142"
                     /></p>
                  <table xmlns:html="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml" rend="rules">
                     <row>
                        <cell>facsimile</cell>
                        <cell>expansion</cell>
                        <cell>encoding</cell>
                     </row>
                     <row>
                        <cell>
                           <graphic n="100108" height="90px" url="media/image108.png" rend="inline"/>
                           <lb/>f. 124v</cell>
                        <cell>ge<hi rend="italic">mi</hi>ni</cell>
                        <cell>
                           <hi rend="color(000096)">&lt;choice&gt;</hi>
                           <lb/>
                           <hi rend="color(000096)">&lt;abbr&gt;</hi>ge<hi rend="color(000096)"
                              >&lt;hi</hi>
                           <hi rend="color(F5844C)"> rend</hi><hi rend="color(FF8040)">=</hi><hi
                              rend="color(993300)">"superscript"</hi>
                           <hi rend="color(000096)">&gt;</hi>i<hi rend="color(000096)"
                              >&lt;/hi&gt;</hi>ni<hi rend="color(000096)">&lt;/abbr&gt;</hi>
                           <lb/>
                           <hi rend="color(000096)">&lt;expan&gt;</hi>ge<hi rend="color(000096)"
                              >&lt;ex&gt;</hi>mi<hi rend="color(000096)">&lt;/ex&gt;</hi>ni<hi
                              rend="color(000096)">&lt;/expan&gt;</hi>
                           <lb/>
                           <hi rend="color(000096)">&lt;/choice&gt;</hi>
                        </cell>
                     </row>
                     <row>
                        <cell>
                           <graphic n="100109" height="90px" url="media/image109.png" rend="inline"/>
                           <lb/>f. 126r</cell>
                        <cell>w<hi rend="italic">ith</hi>yn</cell>
                        <cell>
                           <hi rend="color(000096)">&lt;choice&gt;</hi>
                           <lb/>
                           <hi rend="color(000096)">&lt;abbr&gt;</hi>w<hi rend="color(000096)"
                              >&lt;hi</hi>
                           <hi rend="color(F5844C)"> rend</hi><hi rend="color(FF8040)">=</hi><hi
                              rend="color(993300)">"superscript"</hi>
                           <hi rend="color(000096)">&gt;</hi>t<hi rend="color(000096)"
                              >&lt;/hi&gt;</hi>yn<hi rend="color(000096)">&lt;/abbr&gt;</hi>
                           <lb/>
                           <hi rend="color(000096)">&lt;expan&gt;</hi>w<hi rend="color(000096)"
                              >&lt;ex&gt;</hi>ith<hi rend="color(000096)">&lt;/ex&gt;</hi>yn<hi
                              rend="color(000096)">&lt;/expan&gt;</hi>
                           <lb/>
                           <hi rend="color(000096)">&lt;/choice&gt;</hi>
                        </cell>
                     </row>
                  </table>
               </div>
               <div>
                  <head>List of Abbreviations</head>
                  <p>The following table illustrates all of the special characters found in <hi
                        rend="italic">The Trinity Seven Planets</hi>, and the corresponding unicode
                     or ASCII symbol used to represent them.</p>
                  <table xmlns:html="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml" rend="rules">
                     <row>
                        <cell>Runic characters</cell>
                        <cell>Folio</cell>
                        <cell>Name</cell>
                        <cell>Sign</cell>
                        <cell>Encoding</cell>
                     </row>
                     <row>
                        <cell>
                           <graphic n="100110" height="90px" url="media/image110.png" rend="inline"
                           />
                        </cell>
                        <cell>f. 122v</cell>
                        <cell>Thorn</cell>
                        <cell>&#254;</cell>
                        <cell>&amp;#254;</cell>
                     </row>
                     <row>
                        <cell>
                           <graphic n="100111" height="90px" url="media/image111.png" rend="inline"
                           />
                        </cell>
                        <cell>f. 122v</cell>
                        <cell>Yogh</cell>
                        <cell>&#541;</cell>
                        <cell>&amp;#541;</cell>
                     </row>
                     <row>
                        <cell>Signs of abbreviation</cell>
                     </row>
                     <row>
                        <cell>
                           <graphic n="100114" height="90px" url="media/image114.png" rend="inline"
                           />
                        </cell>
                        <cell>f. 122v</cell>
                        <cell>er/e/re</cell>
                        <cell>&#42864;</cell>
                        <cell>&amp;#42864;</cell>
                     </row>
                     <row>
                        <cell>
                           <graphic n="100115" height="90px" url="media/image115.png" rend="inline"
                           />
                        </cell>
                        <cell>f. 123r</cell>
                        <cell>is/es</cell>
                        <cell>&#42861;</cell>
                        <cell>&amp;#42861;</cell>
                     </row>
                     <row>
                        <cell>
                           <graphic n="100116" height="90px" url="media/image106.png" rend="inline"
                           />
                        </cell>
                        <cell>f. 123r</cell>
                        <cell>per/par</cell>
                        <cell>&#42833;</cell>
                        <cell>&amp;#42833;</cell>
                     </row>
                     <row>
                        <cell>
                           <graphic n="100117" height="90px" url="media/image116.png" rend="inline"
                           />
                        </cell>
                        <cell>f. 123r</cell>
                        <cell>pro</cell>
                        <cell>&#42835;</cell>
                        <cell>&amp;#42835;</cell>
                     </row>
                     <row>
                        <cell>
                           <graphic n="100118" height="90px" url="media/image117.png" rend="inline"
                           />
                        </cell>
                        <cell>f. 123r</cell>
                        <cell>-us/con-</cell>
                        <cell>&#42863;</cell>
                        <cell>&amp;#42863;</cell>
                     </row>
                     <row>
                        <cell>
                           <graphic n="100121" height="90px" url="media/image120.png" rend="inline"
                           />
                        </cell>
                        <cell>f. 122v</cell>
                        <cell>horizontal bar</cell>
                        <cell>&#x305;</cell>
                        <cell>&amp;#x305;</cell>
                     </row>
                     <row>
                        <cell>Otiose signs</cell>
                     </row>
                     <row>
                        <cell>
                           <graphic n="100112" height="90px" url="media/image112.png" rend="inline"
                           />
                        </cell>
                        <cell>f. 122v</cell>
                        <cell>Strike-through h;</cell>
                        <cell>&#295;</cell>
                        <cell>&amp;#295;</cell>
                     </row>
                     <row>
                        <cell>
                           <graphic n="100113" height="90px" url="media/image113.png" rend="inline"
                           />
                        </cell>
                        <cell>f. 122v</cell>
                        <cell>Strike-through l;</cell>
                        <cell>&#322;</cell>
                        <cell>&amp;#322;</cell>
                     </row>
                     <row>
                        <cell>Punctuation</cell>
                     </row>
                     <row>
                        <cell>
                           <graphic n="100119" height="90px" url="media/image118.png" rend="inline"
                           />
                        </cell>
                        <cell>f. 128r</cell>
                        <cell>punctus elevatus</cell>
                        <cell>&#1563;</cell>
                        <cell>&amp;#1563;</cell>
                     </row>
                     <row>
                        <cell>
                           <graphic n="100120" height="90px" url="media/image119.png" rend="inline"
                           />
                        </cell>
                        <cell>f. 124v</cell>
                        <cell>virgula suspensiva</cell>
                        <cell>/</cell>
                        <cell>ASCII</cell>
                     </row>
                     <row>
                        <cell>Other</cell>
                     </row>
                     <row>
                        <cell>
                           <graphic n="100122" height="90px" url="media/image121.png" rend="inline"
                           />
                        </cell>
                        <cell>f. 129v</cell>
                        <cell>One dot over two dots</cell>
                        <cell>
                           <hi rend="color(0E1818)">&#8756;</hi>
                        </cell>
                        <cell>&amp;#8756;</cell>
                     </row>
                     <row>
                        <cell>
                           <graphic n="100123" height="90px" url="media/image122.png" rend="inline"
                           />
                        </cell>
                        <cell>f. 133v</cell>
                        <cell>Dragon's tail/colon with middle comma positura</cell>
                        <cell>:~</cell>
                        <cell>ASCII</cell>
                     </row>
                  </table>
                  <p>Out of these, the strikethrough <hi rend="italic">l</hi> and strikethrough <hi
                        rend="italic">h</hi>, were considered otiose and always tagged with only the
                     unicode entity-number, even though it is possible that in some instances they
                     represent a word-final <hi rend="italic">e</hi>.</p>
                  <p>The Middle English special characters (thorn and yogh) are represented with
                     corresponding Unicode symbols. The scribe's yogh and <hi rend="italic">z</hi>
                     are nearly (if not completely) identical. Ones that have been editorially
                     interpreted as <hi rend="italic">z</hi>'s are reproduced as such (the only
                     instance is in the marginal note on f. 127v). The same was done for thorn and
                     yogh as well as punctuation marks such the <hi rend="italic">virgula
                        suspensiva</hi> and <hi rend="italic">punctus elevatus</hi>. Superscript
                     endings for numerals were also tagged without alternative expansion inside the
                     &lt;choice&gt; tags.</p>
               </div>
               <div>
                  <head>Practical Approach</head>
                  <p>The process of encoding was not as labor-intensive as might first seem, since
                     it is possible to do preformating with a word processor before converting the
                     file into XML.<ptr target="#note143" xml:id="nr143" n="143"/> I used Word for
                     Mac, generated a .docx file and converted it in the web service OxGarage (provided
                     by Oxford University Computing Services, ident = "TEI_fromDOCX" version
                        ="2.15.0").<ptr target="#note144" xml:id="nr144" n="144"/></p>
                  <p>In the transcription, abbreviations were tagged in expanded form in italics,
                     and superscript abbreviations as italic superscripts.</p>
                  <p>The four examples given in the sections "Encoding Abbreviations" and "Encoding
                     Superscript Abbreviations" were thus transcribed as:</p>
                  <table xmlns:html="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml" rend="rules">
                     <row>
                        <cell>de<hi rend="italic">par</hi>tid</cell>
                     </row>
                     <row>
                        <cell>i<hi rend="italic">n</hi>
                        </cell>
                     </row>
                     <row>
                        <cell>ge<hi rend="italic superscript">mi</hi>ni</cell>
                     </row>
                     <row>
                        <cell>w<hi rend="italic superscript">ith</hi>yn</cell>
                     </row>
                  </table>
                  <p>The OxGarage web service converted these to:</p>
                  <table xmlns:html="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml" rend="rules">
                     <row>
                        <cell>de<hi rend="color(000096)">&lt;hi</hi>
                           <hi rend="color(F5844C)"> rend</hi>
                           <hi rend="color(FF8040)">=</hi>
                           <hi rend="color(993300)">"italic"</hi>
                           <hi rend="color(000096)">&gt;</hi>par<hi rend="color(000096)"
                              >&lt;/hi&gt;</hi>tid</cell>
                     </row>
                     <row>
                        <cell>i<hi rend="color(000096)">&lt;hi</hi>
                           <hi rend="color(F5844C)"> rend</hi>
                           <hi rend="color(FF8040)">=</hi>
                           <hi rend="color(993300)">"italic"</hi>
                           <hi rend="color(000096)">&gt;</hi>n<hi rend="color(000096)"
                              >&lt;/hi&gt;</hi>
                        </cell>
                     </row>
                     <row>
                        <cell>ge<hi rend="color(000096)">&lt;hi</hi>
                           <hi rend="color(F5844C)"> rend</hi>
                           <hi rend="color(FF8040)">=</hi>
                           <hi rend="color(993300)">"italic superscript"</hi>
                           <hi rend="color(000096)">&gt;</hi>mi<hi rend="color(000096)"
                              >&lt;/hi&gt;</hi>ni</cell>
                     </row>
                     <row>
                        <cell>w<hi rend="color(000096)">&lt;hi</hi>
                           <hi rend="color(F5844C)"> rend</hi>
                           <hi rend="color(FF8040)">=</hi>
                           <hi rend="color(993300)">"italic superscript"</hi>
                           <hi rend="color(000096)">&gt;</hi>ith<hi rend="color(000096)"
                              >&lt;/hi&gt;</hi>yn</cell>
                     </row>
                  </table>
                  <p>I then used a XSLT scripts to convert them to the more semantically justified
                     ones, and to supply the additional tags, as illustrated by the examples
                     above.</p>
               </div>
               <div>
                  <head>Punctuation</head>
                  <p>Scribal punctuation has been reproduced by Junicode symbols, using both the <hi
                        rend="italic">interpunctus</hi> and the modern full stop. In many cases it
                     is very difficult to interpret whether a certain dot is used as a sign of
                     punctuation or to mark an abbreviation that is placed interlinearly or at the
                     bottom line. Sometimes the placement of the dot has been dictated by where
                     there is room. I have tried to reproduce the scribe's decision using my twofold
                     distinction, even though this means forcing the natural creative variation that
                     is possible with a quill pen into the tight boxes of a binary system. Another
                     alternative would have been to normalize them all either as <hi rend="italic"
                        >interpunctus</hi> or as full stops placed on the bottom line. A third
                     alternative would have been to devise a system based on my interpretation of
                     what the scribe's system has been (for example, <hi rend="italic"
                        >interpunctus</hi> in sentence-medial position and a full stop on the bottom
                     line or <hi rend="italic">punctus elevatus</hi> in sentence-final position).
                     However, neither approach is adopted here.</p>
               </div>
               <div>
                  <head>Uncertain Expansions</head>
                  <p>The manuscript contains a number of cases in which editorial expansion is
                     uncertain. This mainly occurs with the <hi rend="italic">-is</hi> abbreviation,
                     which can be expanded either as <hi rend="italic">-es</hi> or <hi rend="italic"
                        >-is</hi>. These have been encoded with the @cert attribute, following TEI
                     P5 Guidelines 17.3. I used the value @cert="unknown." The agency responsible
                     (in this case, the editor) is indicated by the @resp attribute. The same
                     approach is used for expansions of numerals, for which no spelled-out variant
                     could be found in corpus searches.</p>
                  <p>In order to determine the most likely variant, I performed corpus searches
                     using AntConc software. The transcription included not only the Seven Planets
                     but all sections of the Trinity manuscript that can be safely attributed to
                     Hand A (5,084 words)</p>
                  <p>The following table shows the results.</p>
                  <table xmlns:html="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml" rend="rules">
                     <row>
                        <cell>
                           <hi rend="bold">Voiceless alveolar stops</hi>
                        </cell>
                        <cell>
                           <hi rend="bold">tokens</hi>
                        </cell>
                        <cell>
                           <hi rend="bold">etymology</hi>
                        </cell>
                     </row>
                     <row>
                        <cell>ES</cell>
                     </row>
                     <row>
                        <cell>parties,</cell>
                        <cell>3</cell>
                        <cell>Romance</cell>
                     </row>
                     <row>
                        <cell>clymates</cell>
                        <cell>2</cell>
                        <cell>Latin/Romance</cell>
                     </row>
                     <row>
                        <cell>qualites</cell>
                        <cell>1</cell>
                        <cell>Latin/Romance</cell>
                     </row>
                     <row>
                        <cell>delites</cell>
                        <cell>1</cell>
                        <cell>Romance</cell>
                     </row>
                     <row>
                        <cell>spirites</cell>
                        <cell>2</cell>
                        <cell>Latin/Romance</cell>
                     </row>
                     <row>
                        <cell>facultes</cell>
                        <cell>1</cell>
                        <cell>Latin/Romance</cell>
                     </row>
                     <row>
                        <cell>fruytes</cell>
                        <cell>1</cell>
                        <cell>Latin/Romance</cell>
                     </row>
                     <row>
                        <cell>IS</cell>
                     </row>
                     <row>
                        <cell>planetis</cell>
                        <cell>1</cell>
                        <cell>Latin/Romance</cell>
                     </row>
                     <row>
                        <cell>tretis (treatise, singular)</cell>
                        <cell>1</cell>
                        <cell>Latin/Romance</cell>
                     </row>
                     <row>
                        <cell>YS</cell>
                     </row>
                     <row>
                        <cell>metys</cell>
                        <cell>1</cell>
                        <cell>Old English</cell>
                     </row>
                     <row>
                        <cell>tretys (treatise, singular)</cell>
                        <cell>1</cell>
                        <cell>Latin/Romance</cell>
                     </row>
                     <row>
                        <cell>contentys</cell>
                        <cell>1</cell>
                        <cell>Latin</cell>
                     </row>
                     <row>
                        <cell>*S</cell>
                     </row>
                     <row>
                        <cell>astat*s</cell>
                        <cell>1</cell>
                        <cell>Romance (Lat. "status")</cell>
                     </row>
                     <row>
                        <cell>craft*s</cell>
                        <cell>2</cell>
                        <cell>Old English</cell>
                     </row>
                     <row>
                        <cell>marchunt*s</cell>
                        <cell>1</cell>
                        <cell>Romance</cell>
                     </row>
                     <row>
                        <cell>best*s</cell>
                        <cell>2</cell>
                        <cell>Latin/Romance</cell>
                     </row>
                     <row>
                        <cell>planet*s</cell>
                        <cell>15</cell>
                        <cell>Latin/Romance</cell>
                     </row>
                     <row>
                        <cell>tempest*s</cell>
                        <cell>1</cell>
                        <cell>Latin/Romance</cell>
                     </row>
                     <row>
                        <cell>mynut*s</cell>
                        <cell>1</cell>
                        <cell>Latin/Romance</cell>
                     </row>
                     <row>
                        <cell>
                           <hi rend="bold">Voiced alveolar stops</hi>
                        </cell>
                        <cell>
                           <hi rend="bold">tokens</hi>
                        </cell>
                        <cell>
                           <hi rend="bold">etymology</hi>
                        </cell>
                     </row>
                     <row>
                        <cell>ES</cell>
                     </row>
                     <row>
                        <cell>discordes</cell>
                        <cell>1</cell>
                        <cell>Latin/Romance</cell>
                     </row>
                     <row>
                        <cell>wordes</cell>
                        <cell>1</cell>
                        <cell>Old English</cell>
                     </row>
                     <row>
                        <cell>IS</cell>
                     </row>
                     <row>
                        <cell>thredis</cell>
                        <cell>1</cell>
                        <cell>Old English</cell>
                     </row>
                     <row>
                        <cell>almoundis</cell>
                        <cell>1</cell>
                        <cell>Romance/Arabic</cell>
                     </row>
                     <row>
                        <cell>cloudis</cell>
                        <cell>1</cell>
                        <cell>Old English</cell>
                     </row>
                     <row>
                        <cell>YS</cell>
                     </row>
                     <row>
                        <cell>berdys</cell>
                        <cell>1</cell>
                        <cell>Old English</cell>
                     </row>
                     <row>
                        <cell>*S</cell>
                     </row>
                     <row>
                        <cell>ded*s</cell>
                        <cell>1</cell>
                        <cell>Old English</cell>
                     </row>
                     <row>
                        <cell>hed*s</cell>
                        <cell>1</cell>
                        <cell>Old English</cell>
                     </row>
                     <row>
                        <cell>Emerroud*s</cell>
                        <cell>1</cell>
                        <cell>Latin/Romance</cell>
                     </row>
                     <row>
                        <cell>flowd*s</cell>
                        <cell>1</cell>
                        <cell>Old English</cell>
                     </row>
                  </table>

                  <p>The decision was to encode all the unclear cases as <hi rend="italic">-es</hi>
                     because it is the form with most word types. However, I have expanded the word
                     planetis as is <hi rend="italic">-is</hi> (16) because it is found once in its
                     expanded form; this is standard editorial practice.<ptr target="#note145"
                        xml:id="nr145" n="145"/> But as you can see from the table above, the word
                     is found abbreviated fifteen times, resulting in potential distortion of the
                     data. The single expanded form, on f. 135r, occurs in a context in which the
                     word is split between two lines.</p>
                  <figure>
                     <head>f. 135r</head>
                     <graphic n="100124" height="150px" url="media/image123.png" rend="inline"/>
                     <figDesc>f. 135r</figDesc>
                  </figure>
               </div>
               <div>
                  <head>Scribal Additions and Deletions</head>
                  <p>Scribal additions and deletions are marked using the standard TEI-elements for
                     these, &lt;add&gt; and &lt;del&gt;, denoting "letters, words, or phrases
                     inserted in the text by an author, scribe, annotator, or corrector" or a
                     "letter, word, or passage deleted, marked as deleted, or otherwise indicated as
                     superfluous or spurious in the copy text by an author, scribe, annotator, or
                     corrector," respectively (cf. TEI P5 Guidelines 3.4.3).</p>
                  <p>The practical approach here was to use plain superscript for scribal
                     corrections between lines, which were converted into &lt;add&gt; tags. Scribal
                     deletions were marked as strikethrough, and the web service converted them to
                        <hi rend="color(000096)">&lt;hi</hi>
                     <hi rend="color(F5844C)"> rend</hi>
                     <hi rend="color(FF8040)">=</hi>
                     <hi rend="color(993300)">"strikethrough"</hi>
                     <hi rend="color(000096)">&gt; </hi>and<hi rend="color(000096)"> &lt;hi</hi>
                     <hi rend="color(F5844C)"> rend</hi>
                     <hi rend="color(FF8040)">=</hi>
                     <hi rend="color(993300)">"superscript"</hi>
                     <hi rend="color(000096)">&gt;</hi>. These were then converted to a more
                     semantically justified mark-up.</p>
               </div>
               <div>
                  <head>Decorated Intials</head>
                  <p>There are two types of decorated initials in the manuscript. In addition, the
                     rubricator sometimes highlights words. These have been tagged with @rend using
                     "decorated initial" and "highlighting stroke" as the values.</p>
               </div>
               <div>
                  <head>Word Division</head>
                  <p>All of the words in the manuscript have been tagged with &lt;w&gt; tags, which
                     according to the TEI P5 Guidelines represents "a grammatical (not necessarily
                     orthographic) word" (17.1.)</p>
                  <p>The scribe consistently writes "to be" and "shall be" together.</p>
                  <p>tobe</p>
                  <table xmlns:html="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml" rend="rules">
                     <row>
                        <cell>
                           <graphic n="100125" height="90px" url="media/image124.png" rend="inline"
                           />
                        </cell>
                        <cell>f. 125v</cell>
                     </row>
                     <row>
                        <cell>
                           <graphic n="100126" height="90px" url="media/image125.png" rend="inline"
                           />
                        </cell>
                        <cell>f. 131r</cell>
                     </row>
                     <row>
                        <cell>
                           <graphic n="100127" height="90px" url="media/image126.png" rend="inline"
                           />
                        </cell>
                        <cell>f. 134r</cell>
                     </row>
                     <row>
                        <cell>
                           <graphic n="100128" height="90px" url="media/image127.png" rend="inline"
                           />
                        </cell>
                        <cell>f. 125r</cell>
                     </row>
                     <row>
                        <cell>
                           <graphic n="100129" height="90px" url="media/image128.png" rend="inline"
                           />
                        </cell>
                        <cell>f. 126r</cell>
                     </row>
                  </table>
                  <p>The solution here has been to tag them without a space, but separated by word
                     tags:</p>
                  <p>&lt;w&gt;to&lt;/w&gt;&lt;w&gt;be&lt;/w&gt; and
                     &lt;w&gt;shal&lt;/w&gt;&lt;w&gt;be&lt;/w&gt;</p>
                  <figure>
                     <graphic n="100130" height="150px" url="media/image129.png" rend="inline"/>
                  </figure>
                  <p>&lt;w&gt;neuer &#254;e lees&lt;/w&gt; and &lt;w&gt;a bydynge&lt;/w&gt;, on the
                     other hand, have been tagged as single word, even though the orthographic
                     practice of the scribe is to write them separately.</p>
                  <p>&lt;<ref type="url"
                        target="http://www.tei-c.org/release/doc/tei-p5-doc/en/html/ref-w.html"
                        >http://www.tei-c.org/release/doc/tei-p5-doc/en/html/ref-w.html</ref>&gt;.</p>
                  <p>
                     <hi rend="color(000096)">
                        <graphic n="100131" url="media/image130.png" rend="inline"/>
                     </hi>
                  </p>
                  <p>Numerals are a special case in which the expanded form of the abbreviation may
                     affect word division and the word count. For this reason, the word tags in them
                     are included inside the choice tags rather than outside as in the majority of
                     cases. In the example below, two of the numerals ("thre" five tokens, e.g. f.
                     135r, and "hundred," one token, f. 136r) could be by found corpus searches of
                     the Middle English texts in Trinity O.1.77 written by Hand A. For expanding the
                     other two, I have used the headword given by the <hi rend="italic">Middle
                        English Dictionary</hi>.</p>
                  <p>
                     <hi rend="color(000096)">&lt;abbr&gt;</hi>
                  </p>
                  <p>
                     <hi rend="color(000096)">&lt;w&gt;</hi>cccxxxviij<hi rend="color(000096)"
                        >&lt;/w&gt;</hi>
                  </p>
                  <p>
                     <hi rend="color(000096)">&lt;/abbr&gt;</hi>
                  </p>
                  <p>
                     <hi rend="color(000096)">&lt;expan</hi>
                     <hi rend="color(F5844C)"> cert</hi>
                     <hi rend="color(FF8040)">=</hi>
                     <hi rend="color(993300)">"unknown"</hi>
                     <hi rend="color(F5844C)"> resp</hi>
                     <hi rend="color(FF8040)">=</hi>
                     <hi rend="color(993300)">"#ah"</hi>
                     <hi rend="color(000096)">&gt;</hi>
                  </p>
                  <p>
                     <hi rend="color(000096)">&lt;w&gt;</hi>thre<hi rend="color(000096)"
                        >&lt;/w&gt;&lt;w&gt;</hi>hundred<hi rend="color(000096)"
                        >&lt;/w&gt;&lt;w&gt;</hi>thriti<hi rend="color(000096)">&lt;/w&gt;</hi>
                     <hi rend="color(000096)">&lt;w&gt;</hi>eighte<hi rend="color(000096)"
                        >&lt;/w&gt;</hi>
                  </p>
                  <p>
                     <hi rend="color(000096)">&lt;/expan&gt;</hi>
                  </p>
               </div>
               <div>
                  <head>Style Guide</head>
                  <p>The edition follows the lineation and pagination of the original manuscript
                     page. Manuscript images are available by clicking the small thumbnails between
                     pages on the margin in the right-hand side.</p>
                  <p>Since rubrication is such an important part of the original manuscript, the
                     presentation of decorated initials is represented by larger blue initials with
                     red boxes. Red highlighting strokes in <hi rend="italic">litterae
                        notabiliores</hi> are shown as red background for the letters in question.
                     Scribal deletions are shown as strikethroughs and scribal additions as
                     interlinear superscripts.</p>
                  <p>Uncertain editorial expansions are shown in gray, indicating words not found in
                     an expanded form elsewhere in the manuscript, and thus the expansion is an
                     editorial guess based on knowledge of the scribe's orthography or the forms
                     found in the <hi rend="italic">Middle English Dictionary</hi>.</p>
                  <p>A button in the top left corner allows the user to toggle between views in
                     which the abbreviations are expanded and compressed.</p>
                  <p>Glossed words have yellow underlining, and the gloss will appear in a pop-up
                     window by clicking the word.</p>
               </div>
               <div>
                  <head>Glossary</head>
                  <p>Words that are likely to pose difficulty for modern readers, either because
                     their meaning has changed or because they are related to the specialized field
                     of medieval astrology, have been glossed. Linguistic glosses are given in a
                     separate glossary. Textual and historical notes are given as hyperlinks in the
                     edition.</p>
               </div>
               <div>
                  <head type="main">Acknowledgments</head>
                  <p>The manuscript images are displayed with a kind permission from the Master and
                     the Fellows at the Trinity College Library.</p>
                  <p>I am grateful for the following people. Leena Kahlas-Tarkka and Matti Peikola
                     examined my Licentiate Thesis, on which the codicological and paleographical
                     analysis of this article is based. Olga Timofeeva commented on earlier drafts
                     of this article. Two anonymous reviewers likewise offered several points of
                     constructive criticism. Taking these comments into account makes the article
                     much better than it otherwise would have been.</p>
                  <p>I would also like to thank Karin Dalziel for designing an excellent system in
                     the user interface which allows switching between the expanded and compressed
                     forms of the abbreviations, as well as Lona Dearmont for her diligent work copyediting the article, particularly converting my in-line notes to endnotes. The
                     two editors of the volume, Andrew Jewell and Amanda Gailey, likewise deserve a
                     lot of credit.</p>
               </div>
               <div type="notes">
                  <note xml:id="note1">The treatise cannot be found in standard manuscript
                     catalogues, including the electronic database eVK (an expanded and revised
                     version of Linda Ehrsam Voigts and Patricia Deery Kurtz's <hi rend="italic"
                        >Scientific and Medical Writings in Old and Middle English: An Electronic
                        Reference</hi> [CD] (Ann Arbor: University of Michigan Press, 2000), <ref
                        type="url" target="http://cctr1.umkc.edu/search"
                        >http://cctr1.umkc.edu/search</ref>), or the <hi rend="italic">Indices of
                        Middle English Prose</hi> (IMEP). However, as astrological texts are
                     notoriously badly catalogued (for instance, M. R. James's <hi rend="italic">The
                        Western Manuscripts in the Library of Trinity College, Cambridge: A
                        Descriptive Catalogue</hi> [Cambridge, 1900–1904] typically lumps them in a
                     single entry) and the IMEP project is still incomplete, it is possible that
                     other copies will eventually turn up.</note>
                  <note xml:id="note2">Middle English contents of the closely related Boston MS 19
                     were edited by Martha Powell Harley, "The Middle English Contents of a
                     Fifteenth-Century Medical Handbook," <hi rend="italic">Mediaevalia </hi>8
                     (1982): 171–88.</note>
                  <note xml:id="note3">Sophie Page, "Richard Trewythian and the Uses of Astrology in
                     Late Medieval England," <hi rend="italic">Journal of the Warburg and Courtauld
                        Institutes </hi>64 (2001): 193–95.</note>
                  <note xml:id="note4">Nancy G. Siraisi, <hi rend="italic">Medieval and Early
                        Renaissance Medicine: An Introduction to Knowledge and Practice</hi>
                     (Chicago: University of Chicago Press, 1990), 68.</note>
                  <note xml:id="note5">Steven A. Epstein, <hi rend="italic">An Economic and Social
                        History of Later Medieval Europe, 1000–1500</hi> (New York: Cambridge
                     University Press, 2009), 168.</note>
                  <note xml:id="note6">The common name "Black Death" is anachronistic and not found
                     in contemporary sources (Epstein, <hi rend="italic">An Economic and Social
                        History of Later Medieval Europe</hi>, 171). On the later epidemics, see the
                     list compiled by Brian Williams, available at <ref
                        target="http://urbanrim.org.uk/plague%20list.htm">
                        http://urbanrim.org.uk/plague%20list.htm</ref>, or Epstein, 168. For a good
                     breakdown on the effects of the plague on English society, see Mark Ormrod and
                     Phillip Lindley, <hi rend="italic">The Black Death in England</hi> (Donington:
                     Shaun Tyas, 2003).</note>
                  <note xml:id="note7">Danielle Jacquart, "Medical Scholasticism," ed. Mirko D.
                     Grmek (Cambridge, MA: Harvard University Press, 1998), 234.</note>
                  <note xml:id="note8">Cf. Epstein, <hi rend="italic">An Economic and Social History
                        of Later Medieval Europe</hi>, 169–70; David C. Mengel, "A Plague on
                     Bohemia? Mapping the Black Death," <hi rend="italic">Past and Present</hi>,<hi
                        rend="italic"> </hi>no. 211 (2011).</note>
                  <note xml:id="note9">Siraisi, <hi rend="italic">Medieval and Early Renaissance
                        Medicine</hi>, 68; Epstein, <hi rend="italic">An Economic and Social History
                        of Later Medieval Europe</hi>, 176.</note>
                  <note xml:id="note10">Epstein, <hi rend="italic">An Economic and Social History of
                        Later Medieval Europe</hi>, 176; Jacquart, "Medical Scholasticism,"
                     234.</note>
                  <note xml:id="note11">For an overall account, see, for example, Desmond Seward,
                        <hi rend="italic">A Brief History of Wars of the Roses</hi> (London:
                     Robinson, 2007); and Trevor Royle, <hi rend="italic">The Wars of the Roses:
                        England's First Civil War</hi> (London: Abacus, 2009).</note>
                  <note xml:id="note12">Seward, <hi rend="italic">A Brief History of Wars of the
                        Roses</hi>, 11–12.</note>
                  <note xml:id="note13">Rosemary Horrox, <hi rend="italic">Fifteenth-Century
                        Attitudes: Perceptions of Society in Later Medieval England</hi> (Cambridge:
                     Cambridge University Press, 1994), 10.</note>
                  <note xml:id="note14">Cf. Page, "Richard Trewythian and the Uses of Astrology in
                     Late Medieval England," 194.</note>
                  <note xml:id="note15">Page, "Richard Trewythian and the Uses of Astrology in Late
                     Medieval England," 194.</note>
                  <note xml:id="note16">Cf. Irma Taavitsainen, <hi rend="italic">Middle English
                        Lunaries: A Study of the Genre</hi>, Memoires de la Societe Neophilologique
                     de Helsinki, vol. 47 (Helsinki: Societe Neophilologique, 1988), 5, 45–60; Page,
                     "Richard Trewythian and the Uses of Astrology in Late Medieval England,"
                     193–95.</note>
                  <note xml:id="note17">Linda Ehrsam Voigts, "Scientific and Medical Books," in <hi
                        rend="italic">Book Production and Publishing in Britain, 1375–1475</hi>
                     (Cambridge: Cambridge University Press, 1989), 345–402; Voigts, "What's the
                     Word? Bilingualism in Late-Medieval England," <hi rend="italic"
                     >Speculum </hi>71, no. 4 (1996): 813–26; Page, "Richard Trewythian and the Uses
                     of Astrology in Late Medieval England."</note>
                  <note xml:id="note18">Neolithic monuments like Stonehenge prove that prehistoric
                     people, who have left no written record, were able to calculate the exact
                     position of the sun during summer and winter solstices (see, for example, J.
                     D. North, <hi rend="italic">Cosmos: An Illustrated History of Astronomy and
                        Cosmology</hi> [Chicago: University of Chicago Press, 2008], 6–13).</note>
                  <note xml:id="note19">Sophie Page, <hi rend="italic">Astrology in Medieval
                        Manuscripts</hi> (Toronto: University of Toronto Press, 2002), 7; Hilary M.
                     Carey, "Medieval Latin Astrology and the Cycles of Life: William English and
                     English Medicine in Cambridge, Trinity College Ms O.5.26," in <hi rend="italic"
                        >Astro-Medicine: Astrology and Medicine, East and West</hi>, ed. Anna
                     Akasoy, Charles Burnett, and Ronit Yoeli-Tlalim (Florence: Sismel–Edizione del
                     Galluzo, 2008), 42.</note>
                  <note xml:id="note20">The universe was seen as consisting of spherical shells,
                     some of which carried planets, built layer upon layer (North, <hi rend="italic"
                        >Cosmos</hi>, 83–85). The highest layer, the <hi rend="italic">primum
                        mobile</hi>, was made of unmixed bodies, or the fifth element, ether. It was
                     in slow but constant rotation, which was transmitted to the lower layers,
                     composed of the four elements (cf. North, 83–84; Jacquart, "Medical
                     Scholasticism," 233). As opposed to Plato, the movement was thought of as
                     actual physical movement, which could be studied with the physics of cause and
                     effect (North, 83–84; Carey, "Medieval Latin Astrology and the Cycles of Life,"
                     38).</note>
                  <note xml:id="note21">Cf. Mahmoud Manzalaoui, "Chaucer and Science," in <hi
                        rend="italic">Geoffrey Chaucer</hi>, ed. Derek Brewer (London: Bell and
                     Sons, 1974), 224–25.</note>
                  <note xml:id="note22">Taavitsainen, <hi rend="italic">Middle English
                     Lunaries</hi>, 25.</note>
                  <note xml:id="note23">Page, <hi rend="italic">Astrology in Medieval
                        Manuscripts</hi>, 5.</note>
                  <note xml:id="note24">North, <hi rend="italic">Cosmos</hi>, 251.</note>
                  <note xml:id="note25">Voigts, "Scientific and Medical Books"; Voigts, "The 'Sloane
                     Group': Related Scientific and Medical Manuscripts from the Fifteenth Century
                     in the Sloane Collection," <hi rend="italic">British Library Journal </hi>16
                     (1990): 26–57; Voigts, "What's the Word?"</note>
                  <note xml:id="note26">Voigts, "The 'Sloane Group.'"</note>
                  <note xml:id="note27">Even though some contain individual parchment leaves.</note>
                  <note xml:id="note28">Voigts, "The 'Sloane Group,'" 27.</note>
                  <note xml:id="note29">Voigts, "The 'Sloane Group,'" 27. In my opinion, to be
                     argued in more detail in my forthcoming PhD dissertation, the resemblance in
                     Wellcome 784 and Additional MS 5467 is debatable, but the leaves in MS
                     Rawlinson C.815 are definitely fragments of a core group manuscript.</note>
                  <note xml:id="note30">Voigts, "The 'Sloane Group'"; Monica H. Green, "The
                     Possibilities of Literacy and the Limits of Reading: Women and the Gendering of
                     Medical Literacy," in <hi rend="italic">Women's Healthcare in the Medieval
                        West</hi>, ed. Monica H. Green (Bury St. Edmunds: Ashgate, 2000), 38–39;
                     Claire Jones, "Discourse Communities and Medical Texts," in <hi rend="italic"
                        >Medical Scientific Writing in Late Medieval English</hi>, ed. I.
                     Taavitsainen and P. Pahta (Cambridge: Cambridge University Press, 2004),
                     33–34.</note>
                  <note xml:id="note31">Voigts, "The 'Sloane Group'"; Päivi Pahta, "Code-Switching
                     in Medieval Medical Writing," in <hi rend="italic">Medical and Scientific
                        Writing in Late Medieval English</hi> (Cambridge: Cambridge University
                     Press, 2004), 76; Alpo Honkapohja, "Multilingualism in Trinity College
                     Cambridge Manuscript O.1.77," in <hi rend="italic">Foreign Influences on
                        Medieval English</hi>, ed. Jacek Fisiak and Magdalena Bator (Frankfurt am
                     Main: Peter Lang, 2011), 33.</note>
                  <note xml:id="note32">Voigts, "The 'Sloane Group,'" 37.</note>
                  <note xml:id="note33">A. I. Doyle, "More Light on John Shirley," <hi rend="italic"
                        >Medium Aevum</hi>,<hi rend="italic"> </hi>no. 30 (1961): 93–101; Margaret
                     Connolly, <hi rend="italic">John Shirley: Book Production and the Noble
                        Household in Fifteenth-Century England</hi> (Aldershot: Ashgate,
                     1998).</note>
                  <note xml:id="note34">"London perscripti illud die Veneris Julii, 1462 et r.r.
                     Edwardi 4ti anno secundo" (f. 51r). [London, I wrote this down on Friday, ninth
                     of July 1462, and in the second year of the reign of King Edward IV].</note>
                  <note xml:id="note35">See A. I. Doyle, "The Work of a Late-Fifteenth-Century
                     English Scribe, William Ebesham," <hi rend="italic">Bulletin of the John
                        Rylands Library Manchester</hi> 39 (1956): 298–325.</note>
                  <note xml:id="note36">Doyle, "The Work of a Late-Fifteenth-Century English
                     Scribe," 299.</note>
                  <note xml:id="note37">I am following Linne R. Mooney, "Professional Scribes?
                     Identifying English Scribes Who Had a Hand in More Than One Manuscript," in <hi
                        rend="italic">New Directions in Later Medieval Manuscript Studies</hi>, ed.
                     Derek Pearsall (Bury St. Edmunds: York Medieval Press, 2000), 136–37, who gives
                     the following criteria for identifying a hand as belonging to a professional
                     scribe: the quality of workmanship is high; the scribe writes with "uniform
                     quality", that is, he is able "to write clearly and maintain a duct, aspect and
                     consistent style through a long piece of writing"; the hand survives in more
                     than one manuscript; the scribe is able "to write in more than one style and
                     maintain consistency in letter forms within a style"; "employment of certain
                     details of layout, such as writing headings in a different style from text or
                     accounting for formal glosses or commentary in margins when ruling"; and
                     "evidence of collaboration with other professional scribes and/or with an
                     artist or atelier."</note>
                  <note xml:id="note38">Except for the two large postmedieval codices Gonville and
                     Caius 336/725 and Tokyo Takamiya 33.</note>
                  <note xml:id="note39">Voigts, "The 'Sloane Group,'" 27.</note>
                  <note xml:id="note40">Voigts, "The 'Sloane Group,'" 37.</note>
                  <note xml:id="note41">Cf. Harley, "The Middle English Contents of a
                     Fifteenth-Century Medical Handbook," 172.</note>
                  <note xml:id="note42">Cf. Taavitsainen, <hi rend="italic">Middle English
                        Lunaries</hi>, 66; Peter Brown, "The Seven Planets," in <hi rend="italic"
                        >Popular and Practical Science of Medieval England</hi>, ed. L. M. Matheson
                     (East Lansing: Colleagues Press, 1994), 6.</note>
                  <note xml:id="note43">Cf. Harley, "The Middle English Contents of a
                     Fifteenth-Century Medical Handbook," 174; L. M. Matheson, "Medecin Sans
                     Frontieres?: The European Dissemination of John of Burgundy's Plague
                        Treatise," <hi rend="italic">ANQ </hi>18, no. 3 (2005): 17–28; L. M.
                     Matheson, "John of Burgundy: Treatises on Plague," in <hi rend="italic">Sex,
                        Aging, and Death in a Medieval Medical Compendium: Trinity College Cambridge
                        R.14.52, Its Texts, Language, and Scribe</hi>, ed. M. Teresa Tavormina
                     (Tempe: Arizona Center for Medieval and Renaissance Studies, 2006), 569–602. It
                     is not certain, however, whether contemporary readers would have understood
                     that the texts contained essentially the same information, since the Middle
                     English treatise (9) is attributed to "John of Bordeaux" instead of John of
                     Burgundy, which is almost certainly a translation error resulting from
                     confusing <hi rend="italic">Burgundia </hi>and <hi rend="italic">Burdegalia
                     </hi>(Matheson 2005: 23). The final plague treatise is of a different
                     epistolary form (Matheson 2005: 21) and does not mention the name of the
                     author.</note>
                  <note xml:id="note44">The incipit of (1) "Omne enim corpus humanum" can, according
                     to eTK, be found in five manuscripts: British Library Sloane 3566; Boston
                     Countway Library of Medicine MS 19; Cambridge Gonville and Caius 336/725;
                     Trinity O.1.77; and British Library Sloane 2320 (<hi rend="italic">Electronic
                        Thorndike and Kibre</hi> [eTK], a digital resource based on Lynn Thorndike
                     and Pearl Kibre, <hi rend="italic">A Catalogue of Incipits of Mediaeval
                        Scientific Writings in Latin</hi> and supplements [Cambridge, MA: Mediaeval
                     Academy, 1963], <ref type="url" target="http://cctr1.umkc.edu/search"
                        >http://cctr1.umkc.edu/search</ref>). Tokyo Takamiya 33 is not in the
                     database but can be added as well, which makes it one of the works specific to
                     this group of manuscripts. The third uroscopical text is a short Latin piece,
                     introduced as <hi rend="italic">exposiciones vrinarum in ordine</hi>, which
                     briefly summarizes the colors of urine. eTK finds its incipit "Color rubeus est
                     quasi flamma ignis" in three manuscripts: Cambridge Gonville and Caius 336/725,
                     Cambridge Trinity 1102 (O.1.77), and Countway Library of Medicine 23. eTK lists
                     three with the incipit "Expositiones colorum urinarum in ordine": MSS Trinity
                     O.1.77, Boston Countway MS 19, and Gonville and Caius 336/725. Voigts also
                     mentions Sloane 2320 and Takamiya 33 in "The 'Sloane Group,'" 52–53.</note>
                  <note xml:id="note45">Cf. M. Teresa Tavormina, "The Twenty-Jordan Series: An
                     Illustrated Middle English Uroscopy Text," <hi rend="italic">ANQ </hi>18, no. 3
                     (2005): 40–64.</note>
                  <note xml:id="note46">See, for example, Charles West Clark, "The Zodiac Man in
                     Medieval Medical Astrology" (University of Colorado at Boulder, 1979),
                     iii–iv.</note>
                  <note xml:id="note47">Voigts notes that "astrological tables . . . vary from
                     manuscript to manuscript" ("The 'Sloane Group,'" 32).</note>
                  <note xml:id="note48">Voigts, "The 'Sloane Group,'" 32.</note>
                  <note xml:id="note49">Voigts, "The 'Sloane Group,'" 32.</note>
                  <note xml:id="note50">Medical alchemy like astrology has been seen as a response
                     to the crisis of scholastic medicine caused by the Black Death and the
                     subsequent epidemics (cf. Leah DeVun, <hi rend="italic">Prophecy, Alchemy, and
                        the End of Time: John of Rupescissa in the Late Middle Ages</hi> [New York:
                     Columbia University Press, 2009], 77).</note>
                  <note xml:id="note51">Cf. Carey, "Medieval Latin Astrology and the Cycles of
                     Life," 42.</note>
                  <note xml:id="note52">I am following L. M. Matheson (<hi rend="italic">Popular and
                        Practical Science of Medieval England</hi> [East Lansing: Colleagues Press,
                     1994], xi) and Page ("Richard Trewythian and the Uses of Astrology in Late
                     Medieval England," 194): "the semantically charged, but slippery term 'popular'
                     is not intended to carry any political or derogatory connotations. Many of the
                     texts are representative of the kind of general scientific and medical
                     knowledge available to a reasonably educated but non-specialist audience. Some
                     contain popularizations of academic or 'high' science for the use of
                     non-university professionals. Others, by the fact of their translation into
                     English, were intended to reach wider readership than their Latin originals; if
                     the survival of manuscripts and the choice of texts for early printing, then a
                     number succeeded in this sense of the 'popular' also" (Matheson, xi).</note>
                  <note xml:id="note53">Tavormina, "The Twenty-Jordan Series," 41.</note>
                  <note xml:id="note54">Peter Murray Jones, "Information and Science," in <hi
                        rend="italic">Fifteenth-Century Attitudes: Perceptions of Society in Later
                        Medieval England</hi>, ed. Rosemary Horrox (Cambridge: Cambridge University
                     Press, 1994), 100.</note>
                  <note xml:id="note55">Ptolemy did not include astrology in his main work, the <hi
                        rend="italic">Mathematike Syntaxis</hi>, known in the west after its Arabic
                        title <hi rend="italic">al-majist</hi>, as <hi rend="italic">Almagest</hi>,
                     but he considered it to be a part of the total rational account of the universe
                     (North, <hi rend="italic">Cosmos</hi>, 289) and wrote a later work, the <hi
                        rend="italic">Tetrabiblion</hi>, or <hi rend="italic">Quadripartitum</hi> by
                     its Latin name, on it (North, 120).</note>
                  <note xml:id="note56">Cf. North, <hi rend="italic">Cosmos</hi>, 120.</note>
                  <note xml:id="note57">Cf. T. L. Burton, <hi rend="italic">Sidrak and Bokkus</hi>
                     (Oxford: Oxford University Press, 1998).</note>
                  <note xml:id="note58">Cf. Page, <hi rend="italic">Astrology in Medieval
                        Manuscripts</hi>, 23.</note>
                  <note xml:id="note59">James, <hi rend="italic">The Western Manuscripts in the
                        Library of Trinity College</hi>; Linne R. Mooney, <hi rend="italic">The
                        Index of Middle English Prose: Handlist 11, Manuscripts in the Library of
                        Trinity College, Cambridge</hi> (Woodbridge: Brewer, 1995).</note>
                  <note xml:id="note60">Voigts, "Scientific and Medical Books"; Voigts, "The 'Sloane
                     Group'"; Voigts, "What's the Word?"</note>
                  <note xml:id="note61">Patricia Deery Kurtz and Linda Ehrsam Voigts, "Contents,
                     Unique Treatises, and Related Manuscripts," in <hi rend="italic">Sex, Aging,
                        and Death in a Medieval Medical Compendium</hi>, ed. M. Teresa Tavormina
                     (Tempe: Arizona Center for Medieval and Renaissance Studies, 2006), 40.</note>
                  <note xml:id="note62">C. Jones, "Discourse Communities and Medical Texts."</note>
                  <note xml:id="note63">C. Jones, "Discourse Communities and Medical Texts,"
                     33.</note>
                  <note xml:id="note64">C. Jones, "Discourse Communities and Medical Texts,"
                     33.</note>
                  <note xml:id="note65">C. Jones, "Discourse Communities and Medical Texts," 33–34.
                     British Library Additional MS 19674, which is in the Sloane core layout, shares
                     texts, including recipes, and advice on diet and bloodletting with manuscripts
                     with strong East Anglian, Norfolk, and Lincolnshire provenance (cf. C. Jones,
                     34).</note>
                  <note xml:id="note66">Green, "The Possibilities of Literacy and the Limits of
                     Reading."</note>
                  <note xml:id="note67">Green, "The Possibilities of Literacy and the Limits of
                     Reading," 39.</note>
                  <note xml:id="note68">Green, "The Possibilities of Literacy and the Limits of
                     Reading," 38.</note>
                  <note xml:id="note69">Pahta, "Code-Switching in Medieval Medical Writing,"
                     76.</note>
                  <note xml:id="note70">Irma Taavitsainen, "Scriptorial 'House-Styles' and Discourse
                     Communities," in <hi rend="italic">Medical and Scientific Writing in Late
                        Medieval English</hi>, ed. Irma Taavitsainen and Päivi Pahta (Cambridge:
                     Cambridge University Press, 2004), 209–40.</note>
                  <note xml:id="note71">Taavitsainen, "Scriptorial 'House-Styles' and Discourse
                     Communities," 217.</note>
                  <note xml:id="note72">Taavitsainen, "Scriptorial 'House-Styles' and Discourse
                     Communities," 235.</note>
                  <note xml:id="note73">Brown, "The Seven Planets"; María José Carrillo Linares,
                     "The Seven Planets," in <hi rend="italic">Sex, Aging, and Death in a Medieval
                        Medical Compendium</hi>, ed. M. Teresa Tavormina (Tempe: Arizona Center for
                     Medieval and Renaissance Studies, 2006), 681–99.</note>
                  <note xml:id="note74">M. Teresa Tavormina,  ed.<hi rend="italic">Sex, Aging, and Death in
                        a Medieval Medical Compendium: Trinity College Cambridge MS R.14.52, Its
                        Texts, Language, and Scribe</hi>. (Tempe: Arizona Center for Medieval and
                     Renaissance Studies, 2006); Voigts, "What's the Word?"</note>
                  <note xml:id="note75">Tavormina, "The Twenty-Jordan Series."</note>
                  <note xml:id="note76">Tavormina, "The Twenty-Jordan Series," 44.</note>
                  <note xml:id="note77">Matheson, "Medecin Sans Frontieres?"; Matheson, "John of
                     Burgundy."</note>
                  <note xml:id="note78">Matheson, "John of Burgundy."</note>
                  <note xml:id="note79">Linda Ehrsam Voigts, "The Golden Table of Pythagoras."
                        In <hi rend="italic">Popular and Practical Science of Medieval England</hi>,
                     ed. L. M. Matheson (East Lansing: Colleagues Press, 1994), 123–40.</note>
                  <note xml:id="note80">James, <hi rend="italic">The Western Manuscripts in the
                        Library of Trinity College</hi>, v.</note>
                  <note xml:id="note81">James, <hi rend="italic">The Western Manuscripts in the
                        Library of Trinity College</hi>, xxvi.</note>
                  <note xml:id="note82">James, <hi rend="italic">The Western Manuscripts in the
                        Library of Trinity College</hi>, xi.</note>
                  <note xml:id="note83">Montague Rhodes James, <hi rend="italic">List of Manuscripts
                        Formerly Owned by Dr. John Dee</hi> (Oxford: Bibliographical Society,
                     1921).</note>
                  <note xml:id="note84">James, <hi rend="italic">List of Manuscripts Formerly Owned
                        by Dr. John Dee</hi>, xii.</note>
                  <note xml:id="note85">A. G. Rigg, <hi rend="italic">A Glastonbury Miscellany of
                        the Fifteenth Century: A Descriptive Index of Trinity College, Cambridge,
                        Ms.O.9.38</hi> (London: Oxford University Press, 1968), 1. According to the
                     librarians at the Wren Library, the binding is definitely not a Trinity
                     binding, but almost all, if not all, the Gale manuscripts are bound in a
                     similar way. The description in Rigg is of MS O.9.38.</note>
                  <note xml:id="note86">Voigts, "The 'Sloane Group,'" 51, mentions that the
                     manuscript is quired in 8s without specifying further, emphasizing its
                     regularity. James (<hi rend="italic">The Western Manuscripts in the Library of
                        Trinity College</hi>, 76) gives 202+3 without noting the inconsistencies in
                     numbering.</note>
                  <note xml:id="note87">David C. Greetham, <hi rend="italic">Textual Scholarship: An
                        Introduction</hi>, Garland Reference Library of the Humanities, vol. 1417
                     (New York: Garland, 1994), 127.</note>
                  <note xml:id="note88"><hi rend="italic">Late Medieval English Scribes</hi>, <ref
                        target="http://www.medievalscribes.com/"> http://www.medievalscribes.com/</ref>.</note>
                  <note xml:id="note89">James, <hi rend="italic">The Western Manuscripts in the
                        Library of Trinity College</hi>, 76.</note>
                  <note xml:id="note90">Voigts, "The 'Sloane Group,'" 51.</note>
                  <note xml:id="note91">Cf. Malcolm Beckwith Parkes, <hi rend="italic">English
                        Cursive Book Hands, 1250–1500</hi> (Oxford: Clarendon Press, 1969), xv,
                     xix.</note>
                  <note xml:id="note92">Cf. Jane Roberts, <hi rend="italic">Guide to Scripts Used in
                        English Writings up to 1500</hi> (London: British Library, 2005),
                     211.</note>
                  <note xml:id="note93">Parkes, <hi rend="italic">English Cursive Book Hands</hi>,
                     41.</note>
                  <note xml:id="note94">Cf. Roberts, <hi rend="italic">Guide to Scripts Used in
                        English Writings</hi>, 163–64.</note>
                  <note xml:id="note95">Cf. Parkes, <hi rend="italic">English Cursive Book
                        Hands</hi>, xv.</note>
                  <note xml:id="note96">Parkes, <hi rend="italic">English Cursive Book Hands</hi>,
                     xv.</note>
                  <note xml:id="note97">Roberts, <hi rend="italic">Guide to Scripts Used in English
                        Writings</hi>, 161.</note>
                  <note xml:id="note98">Linne R. Mooney uses the wording "main scribe or a near
                     contemporary" in <hi rend="italic">The Index of Middle English Prose</hi>,
                     85.</note>
                  <note xml:id="note99">I am grateful to Matti Peikola for pointing this out.</note>
                  <note xml:id="note100">Mooney, <hi rend="italic">The Index of Middle English
                        Prose</hi>, 85, f. 122r.</note>
                  <note xml:id="note101">See Taavitsainen, <hi rend="italic">Middle English
                        Lunaries</hi>, 141–45; North, <hi rend="italic">Cosmos</hi>, 292–94. The
                     quote is from Taavitsainen, 141.</note>
                  <note xml:id="note102">Taavitsainen, <hi rend="italic">Middle English
                        Lunaries</hi>, 141.</note>
                  <note xml:id="note103">North, <hi rend="italic">Cosmos</hi>, 292, 293.</note>
                  <note xml:id="note104">Cf. Taavitsainen, <hi rend="italic">Middle English
                        Lunaries</hi>, 41.</note>
                  <note xml:id="note105">Cf. Voigts, "The 'Sloane Group,'" 27; Taavitsainen,
                     "Scriptorial 'House-Styles' and Discourse Communities," 235.</note>
                  <note xml:id="note106">James, <hi rend="italic">The Western Manuscripts in the
                        Library of Trinity College</hi>, 77.</note>
                  <note xml:id="note107">Honkapohja, "Multilingualism in Trinity College Cambridge
                     Manuscript O.1.77."</note>
                  <note xml:id="note108">Page, "Richard Trewythian and the Uses of Astrology in Late
                     Medieval England," 211.</note>
                  <note xml:id="note109">Royle, <hi rend="italic">The Wars of the Roses</hi>,
                     282.</note>
                  <note xml:id="note110">Seward, <hi rend="italic">A Brief History of Wars of the
                        Roses</hi>, 79–80.</note>
                  <note xml:id="note111">Seward, <hi rend="italic">A Brief History of Wars of the
                        Roses</hi>, 87–89.</note>
                  <note xml:id="note112">Voigts, "Scientific and Medical Books," 356; Siraisi, <hi
                        rend="italic">Medieval and Early Renaissance Medicine</hi>, 33.</note>
                  <note xml:id="note113">P. M. Jones, "Information and Science," 108.</note>
                  <note xml:id="note114">See, for example, Epstein, <hi rend="italic">An Economic
                        and Social History of Later Medieval Europe</hi>, 175.</note>
                  <note xml:id="note115">Irma Taavitsainen, "Transferring Classical Discourse
                     Conventions into the Vernacular," in <hi rend="italic">Medical and Scientific
                        Writing in Late Medieval English</hi>, ed. Irma Taavitsainen and Päivi Pahta
                     (Cambridge: Cambridge University Press, 2004), 49.</note>
                  <note xml:id="note116">Green, "The Possibilities of Literacy and the Limits of
                     Reading," 38; C. Jones, "Discourse Communities and Medical Texts," 34.</note>
                  <note xml:id="note117">The statement reads "ut sciat medicus in quo signo zodiaci
                     luna fuerit omni die" [so that the medical practitioner shall now in which sign
                     of the zodiac the moon is all day] (f. 94v).</note>
                  <note xml:id="note118">Päivi Pahta and Irma Taavitsainen, "Vernacularisation of
                     Scientific and Medical Writing in Its Sociohistorical Context," in <hi
                        rend="italic">Medical and Scientific Writing in Late Medieval English</hi>,
                     ed. I. Taavitsainen and P. Pahta (Cambridge: Cambridge University Press),
                     1–18; see also Green, "The Possibilities of Literacy and the Limits of
                     Reading," 39.</note>
                  <note xml:id="note119">C. Jones, "Discourse Communities and Medical Texts," 28;
                     see also Green, "The Possibilities of Literacy and the Limits of Reading,"
                     38–39.</note>
                  <note xml:id="note120">See, for example, Richard W. Bailey, "The Need for Good
                     Texts: The Case of Henry Machyn's Day Book, 1550–1563," in <hi rend="italic"
                        >Studies in the History of the English Language, II: Unfolding
                        Conversations</hi>, Topics in English Linguistics 45, ed. Anne Curzan and
                     Kimberly Emmons (Berlin: Mouton de Gruyter, 2004), 217–28; Anne Curzan and
                     Chris C. Palmer, "The Importance of Historical Corpora, Reliability, and
                     Reading," in <hi rend="italic">Corpus-Based Studies of Diachronic English</hi>,
                     ed. Roberta Facchinetti and Matti Rissanen (Bern: Peter Lang, 2006), 17–34;
                     Peter Grund, "Manuscripts as Sources for Linguistic Research: A Methodological
                     Case Study Based on the Mirror of Lights," <hi rend="italic">Journal of English
                        Linguistics </hi>34, no. 2 (2006): 105–25; Alpo Honkapohja, Samuli
                     Kaislaniemi, and Ville Marttila, "Digital Editions for Corpus Linguistics:
                     Representing Manuscript Reality in Electronic Corpora," in <hi rend="italic"
                        >Corpora: Pragmatics and Discourse: Papers from the 29th International
                        Conference on English Language Research on Computerized Corpora (Icame 29).
                        Ascona, Switzerland, 14–18 May 2008</hi>, ed. Andreas H. Jucker, Daniel
                     Schreier, and Marianne Hundt (Amsterdam: Rodopi, 2009), 451–74.</note>
                  <note xml:id="note121">See, for example, Roger Lass, "Ut Custodiant Litteras:
                     Editions, Corpora and Witnesshood," in <hi rend="italic">Methods and Data in
                        English Historical Dialectology</hi>, ed. Marina Dossena (Bern: Peter Lang,
                     2004), 24; Grund, "Manuscripts as Sources for Linguistic Research,"
                     105–6.</note>
                  <note xml:id="note122">Lass, "Ut Custodiant Litteras," 22.</note>
                  <note xml:id="note123">LAEME: <hi rend="italic">A Linguistic Atlas of Early Middle
                        English, 1150–1325, </hi>comp. Margaret Laing and Roger Lass (Edinburgh: ©
                     2007 The University of Edinburgh), <ref type="url"
                        target="http://www.lel.ed.ac.uk/ihd/laeme1/laeme1.html"
                        >http://www.lel.ed.ac.uk/ihd/laeme1/laeme1.html</ref>; LALME: <hi
                        rend="italic">A Linguistic Atlas of Late Middle English</hi>, ed. Angus
                     McIntosh, M. L. Samuels, and Michael Benskin (Aberdeen: University Press,
                     1986); LAOS: <hi rend="italic">A Linguistic Atlas of Older Scots, Phase 1:
                        1380–1500</hi> (Edinburgh: © 2008 The University of Edinburgh), <ref
                        type="url" target="http://www.lel.ed.ac.uk/ihd/laos1/laos1.html"
                        >http://www.lel.ed.ac.uk/ihd/laos1/laos1.html</ref>.</note>
                  <note xml:id="note124">Lass, "Ut Custodiant Litteras," 26, 25.</note>
                  <note xml:id="note125">Lass, "Ut Custodiant Litteras," 40.</note>
                  <note xml:id="note126">Cf. Peter M. W. Robinson, "Is There a Text in These
                     Variants?," in <hi rend="italic">The Literary Text in the Digital Age</hi>, ed.
                     Richard J. Finneran (Ann Arbor: University of Michigan Press, 1996), 105; M. J.
                     Driscoll, "Levels of Transcription," in <hi rend="italic">Electronic Textual
                        Editing</hi>, ed. Lou Burnard, Katherine O'Brien O'Keeffe, and John Unsworth
                     (New York: Modern Language Association of America, 2006), 255.</note>
                  <note xml:id="note127">Cf. Michael Benskin, "The Letters &lt;&#254;&gt; and
                     &lt;Y&gt; in Later Middle English, and Some Related Matters," <hi rend="italic"
                        >Journal of the Society of Archivists</hi>, no. 7 (1982): 13–30.</note>
                  <note xml:id="note128">A. S. G. Edwards, "Representing the Middle English
                     Manuscript," in <hi rend="italic">New Directions in Later Medieval Manuscript
                        Studies</hi>, ed. Derek Pearsall (Bury St. Edmunds: York Medieval Press,
                     2000), 74–75.</note>
                  <note xml:id="note129">See, for example, Justyna Rogos, "On the Pitfalls of
                     Interpretation: Latin Abbreviations in Mss of the Man of Law's Tale," in <hi
                        rend="italic">Foreign Influences on Medieval English</hi>, ed. Jacek Fisiak
                     and Magdalena Bator (Frankfurt am Main: Peter Lang, 2011), 47–54; Driscoll,
                     "Levels of Transcription"; Driscoll, "Marking Up Abbreviations in Old
                     Norse–Icelandic Manuscripts," in <hi rend="italic">Medieval Texts–Contemporary
                        Media: The Art and Science of Editing in the Digital Age</hi>, ed. M. G.
                     Saibene and M. Buzzoni (Pavia: Ibis, 2009), 13–34.</note>
                  <note xml:id="note130">Benskin, "The Letters &lt;&#254;&gt; and &lt;Y&gt; in Later
                     Middle English."</note>
                  <note xml:id="note131">Cf. Driscoll, "Marking Up Abbreviations in Old
                     Norse–Icelandic Manuscripts," 31–32.</note>
                  <note xml:id="note132">Rogos, "On the Pitfalls of Interpretation," 47.</note>
                  <note xml:id="note133">Cf. Grund, "Manuscripts as Sources for Linguistic
                     Research," 106.</note>
                  <note xml:id="note134">Driscoll, "Levels of Transcription," 254.</note>
                  <note xml:id="note135">Frederick Madden, <hi rend="italic">The Ancient English
                        Romance of William and the Werwolf; Edited from an Unique Copy in King's
                        College Library, Cambridge; with an Introduction and Glossary</hi> (London:
                     Roxburghe Clube, 1832). See Edwards, "Representing the Middle English
                     Manuscript," 66.</note>
                  <note xml:id="note136">TEI: <hi rend="italic">Text Encoding Initiative</hi>, <ref
                        type="url" target="http://www.tei-c.org/index.xml"
                        >http://www.tei-c.org/index.xml</ref>.</note>
                  <note xml:id="note137">See, for example, Driscoll, "Levels of Transcription";
                     Driscoll, "Marking Up Abbreviations in Old Norse–Icelandic Manuscripts"; Jaes
                     Cummings, "Converting Saint Paul: A New Tei P5 Edition of the Conversion of
                     Saint Paul Using Stand-Off Methodology," <hi rend="italic">Literary and
                        Linguistic Computing</hi>, no. 3 (2009): 307–17.</note>
                  <note xml:id="note138">Cf. Driscoll, "Marking Up Abbreviations in Old
                     Norse–Icelandic Manuscripts."</note>
                  <note xml:id="note139">Lass, "Ut Custodiant Litteras."</note>
                  <note xml:id="note140">See Driscoll, "Marking Up Abbreviations in Old
                     Norse–Icelandic Manuscripts."</note>
                  <note xml:id="note141">Adriano Cappelli, <hi rend="italic">Manuali Hoepli: Lexicon
                        Abbreviaturarum Dizionario Di Abbreviature Latine Ed Italiane</hi> (Milan:
                     Editore Ulrico Hoepli Milano, 1990), 132.</note>
                  <note xml:id="note142">Cummings, "Converting Saint Paul."</note>
                  <note xml:id="note143">Cf. Cummings, "Converting Saint Paul."</note>
                  <note xml:id="note144">Oxford University Computing Services, OxGarage Conversion,
                        <ref type="url" target="http://www.tei-c.org/oxgarage/"
                        >http://www.tei-c.org/oxgarage/</ref>.</note>
                  <note xml:id="note145">Cf. Driscoll, "Marking Up Abbreviations in Old
                     Norse–Icelandic Manuscripts," 31–32.</note>
               </div>
            </div>
         </div>
      </body>
   </text>
</TEI>
