<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
  <teiHeader xml:lang="eng">
    <fileDesc>
      <titleStmt>
        <title level="m" type="main">THE MALCOLM X. I KNEW</title>
        <author>Alex Haley</author>
        <editor> Amy E. Earhart et al.</editor>
        <respStmt>
          <resp>Transcription and encoding</resp>
          <name xml:id="wr">Amy E. Earhart et al.</name>
        </respStmt>

      </titleStmt>
      <editionStmt>
        <edition>
          <date>2014</date>
        </edition>
      </editionStmt>
      <publicationStmt>
        <idno type="file">haley.malcolmxfull</idno>
        <idno type="edition">haley</idno>

        <authority>Scholarly Editing: The Annual of the Association for Documentary
          Editing</authority>
        <address>
                    <addrLine>http://www.scholarlyediting.org</addrLine>
                </address>
        <publisher>Association for Documentary Editing</publisher>
        <publisher>University of Nebraska&#8211;Lincoln</publisher>
        <distributor>
          <name>Center for Digital Research in the Humanities</name>
          <address>
                        <addrLine>319 Love Library</addrLine>
                        <addrLine>University of Nebraska&#8211;Lincoln</addrLine>
                        <addrLine>Lincoln, NE 68588-4100</addrLine>
                        <addrLine>http://cdrh.unl.edu</addrLine>
                    </address>
        </distributor>
        <date>2014</date>
        <availability>
          <p>Scholarly Editing: The Annual of the Association for Documentary Editing is freely
            distributed by the Association for Documentary Editing and the Center for Digital
            Research in the Humanities at the University of Nebraska-Lincoln and licensed under a
            Creative Commons Attribution-NonCommercial-ShareAlike 3.0 Unported License</p>
        </availability>
      </publicationStmt>
      <seriesStmt>
        <title level="j">Scholarly Editing: The Annual of the Association for Documentary
          Editing</title>
        <respStmt>
          <resp>editor</resp>
          <name xml:id="ag">Amanda Gailey</name>
        </respStmt>
        <respStmt>
          <resp>editor</resp>
          <name xml:id="awj">Andrew Jewell</name>
        </respStmt>
        <idno type="vol">35</idno>
        <idno type="ISSN">2167-1257</idno>
      </seriesStmt>
      <sourceDesc>
        <bibl>
          <note>Born digital.</note>
        </bibl>
      </sourceDesc>
    </fileDesc>
    <revisionDesc>
      <change when="2012-07-26" who="#awj">Altered the encoding to match practices in the following
        ways: 1. added new idnos in publicationStmt 2. Added ISSN number to header and altered vol
        number and year </change>
      <change when="2012-08-06" who="#aee">Altered the encoding to match practices in the following
        ways: 1. revise title statement changing editor and author 2.changed title to match document
        title 3. changed footers and headers to fw 4. linked images to pb 5. changed unclear to gap
        6. changed note formats </change>
      <change when="2012-09-10" who="#awj">removed the front with head because it repeated
        information in the teiHeader and did not represent a head in the original document</change>
      <change when="2012-09-11" who="#awj">fixed the paragraphing (paragraphs were mistakenly closed
        at the end of each page); adjusted encoding on the fw to allow for styling that mimics
        original; changed the pagebreaks so that they preceded the page content rather than followed
        it</change>
      <change when="2012-12-17" who="#aee">added note regarding materials</change>
      <change when="2014-02-25" who="#aee">copyediting changes</change>
    </revisionDesc>
  </teiHeader>
  <text>

    <body>
      <note type="headnote">Note: Below is the transcription of a manuscript version of Alex Haley's
        essay <emph>"The Malcolm X I Knew,"</emph> originally published by <emph>Saga</emph>
        magazine in November 1965, the same month in which <emph>The Autobiography of Malcolm
          X</emph> was published. <emph>Saga</emph> appears to be a pulp men's magazine published by
        New York's Gambi Publications. Articles such as "Confession of an Auto Spy," "How Sex Can
        Take You to the Top," and "Love Among the Beach Boys" appear in the same issue as Haley's
        essay along with drawings of scantily clad women and ads promising to remedy baldness. The
        manuscript version is substantially longer than the published essay, which we cannot
        reproduce due to copyright restrictions. While some of the scenes contained within the essay
        are echoed in <emph>The Autobiography,</emph> new materials is included, such as Malcolm X's
        interaction with a white couple in New York City. The essay provides one more lens through
        which to examine the working relationship of X and Haley as well as the ways Haley shaped
        the narrative. The manuscript from which these materials are transcribed is housed in the
        Alex Haley Papers held by Cushing Library, Special Collections, at Texas A&amp;M
        University.</note>

      <pb n="1" facs="haley.essay.01"/>
      <head type="main">THE MALCOLM X. I KNEW</head>
      <byline>by Alex Haley</byline>


      <p>Malcolm X. and I rode downstairs in a New York Hilton Hotel elevator and outside a
        revolving door he handed a garage attendant his car check. As we stood chatting, a
        middle-aged white couple came up to also order their car, and the husband pleasantly
        observed to us that New York City's weather was excellent. It certainly was, replied Malcolm
        X. The man, with an open, sincere friendliness, introduced himself and his wife, giving <del
          rend="strikethrough">thi</del> their name and their Florida hometown. Malcolm X., warmly
        responding, shaking the man's extended hand and bowing toward his wife in a courtly manner,
        said, "My name's Shabazz. I'm a native of Michigan." A brief, affable conversation ensued
        before Malcolm X.'s blue Oldsmobile was delivered and with an exchange of smiling goodbyes,
        we got <fw>more</fw>
        <pb n="2" facs="haley.essay.02"/>
        <fw type="header_left">Haley</fw><fw type="header_right">page 2</fw> inside the car. Before
        driving away, Malcolm X. bent his head to wave again at the white couple.</p>

      <p>But we looked into their faces suddenly now as blanched and <del rend="strikethrough"
          >slack</del> slack as if they stared at the devil. The garage attendant obviously had
        identified Malcolm X. The blue Oldsmobile gunned out to the street. "I wish he hadn't done
        that!" Malcolm X. exclaimed bitterly.</p>

      <p>The incident happened only a few weeks before Malcolm X.'s death. Often since I've thought
        how it vividly reflected the contrast between the publicly average impression of a
        one-track, vitriolic black demagogue and the private Malcolm X. whom I came to know during
        working closely with him for two years in the process of writing his autobiography that is
        soon to be published. That private Malcolm X. was a paradox. He was a man who had packed
        into his 39 years more high drama than is seen <del rend="strikethrough">by</del>
        <add place="above">in</add> the average ten men's lifetimes. As is now generally known, the
        father of the boy Malcolm was killed, supposedly by whites; the widow burdened with seven
        children and meager income gradually lost her mind and was institutionalized; Malcolm, as a
          <del rend="strikethrough">state</del> ward of the state of Michigan, was reared by a white
        family through his eighth-grade year, and then went to live <del rend="strikethrough">in
          Boston</del> with his grown half-sister in Boston where he first tasted ghetto life.
          <fw>more</fw>
        <pb n="3" facs="haley.essay.03"/>
        <fw type="header_left">Haley</fw><fw type="header_right">page 3</fw> Faking his age, he got
        a railroad dining car job, traveling to New York City, where, captivated by Harlem,<ptr
          target="#note1" xml:id="nr1" n="1"/> he went to work there as a waiter, then he branched
        out into free-lance hustling, selling dope, women and engaging in various other crimes. When
        eventually caught and imprisoned with a ten-year sentence, Malcolm as a convict first heard
        the Black Muslim philosophies of Elijah Muhammad,<ptr target="#note2" xml:id="nr2" n="2"/>
        whose convert he became, and when freed Malcolm's native talent quickly saw his rise to the
        Black Muslim's chief spokesman. In 1959, a television expose<ptr target="#note3"
          xml:id="nr3" n="3"/> had thrust the militant, fiery figure into the public eye, and
        subsequently he had risen to national and finally international fame.</p>

      <p>I came to know a private man of many facets. He was defiant, suspicious; he was almost
        incredibly self-disciplined; he was also warm, and sensitive, and he was fascinated with
        people. From the man who indeed gave every impression that he truly hated all white people,
        I watched him alter what he believed until in the end he grieved that scarcely anyone would
          <del rend="strikethrough">believe</del> accept his declarations that he wanted to work for
        the brotherhood of all men. <ptr target="#note4" xml:id="nr4" n="4"/>It was hard for me to
        believe since his original stand had been so absolutely convincing. To a white person he
        would not speak a word that he considered of non-business nature. I watched him stare coldly
        and fold his <fw>more</fw>
        <pb n="4" facs="haley.essay.04"/>
        <fw type="header_left">Haley</fw><fw type="header_right">page 4</fw> arms when a white hand
        was offered to shake. I saw him turn his back and walk away from white reporters who had
        either asked or said something of which Malcolm X. disapproved. This was the dramatically
        militant personality which had captured most of Harlem's awed admiration when he led 50-odd
        ominously silent Black Muslim "Fruit of Islam"<ptr target="#note5" xml:id="nr5" n="5"/> men
        to stand in ranks before a police precinct where a brother Muslim, nightsticked by a
          policeman,<ptr target="#note6" xml:id="nr6" n="6"/> had been taken. Malcolm X. had gone
        into the precinct and demanded that the man be taken to Harlem Hospital, which was done, and
        the Black Muslims followed and stood outside the hospital, with an excited crowd swelling
        behind them. A high police official warned Malcolm X. that he had generated a potential
        riot, to which Malcolm X. replied that his men were standing perfectly disciplined. "Yes,
        but those others," said the official, and Malcolm X. said, "Those are your problem." Later
        the official told the press, "No one man should have that much power."</p>

      <p>Negro writers -- if assigned by white-owned publications -- fared no better with Malcolm X.
        in these days. "You're another tool of the white man sent to a spy" he told me levelly when
        I approached him to do an article. He required me to fly to Chicago to obtain the clearance
        of his leader, Elijah Muhammad, <ptr target="#note7" xml:id="nr7" n="7"/><fw>more</fw>
        <pb n="5" facs="haley.essay.05"/>
        <fw type="header_left">Haley</fw><fw type="header_right">page 5</fw> and when this was
        gained, Malcolm X. grudgingly cooperated. After the article was published, Elijah Muhammad
        approved of it as having been "fair" and subsequently somewhat thawed <del
          rend="strikethrough">tod</del> toward me, Malcolm X. cooperated with two more articles for
        other publications.<ptr target="#note8" xml:id="nr8" n="8"/> It was this background of <add
          place="above">my</add> successfully working with Malcolm X. that promoted a book publisher
        to ask me in 1963 if I would try to obtain <del rend="strikethrough">his</del> the exclusive
        autobiography of "the angriest Negro in America," as Malcolm X. liked to term himself.<ptr
          target="#note9" xml:id="nr9" n="9"/></p>

      <p>"A -- <hi rend="underline">book</hi>?" Malcolm X. was taken aback when I put the question
        to him in Harlem's Black Muslim Mosque #7 restaurant. He abruptly quit stirring cream into
        his coffee. ("Coffee's the only thing I like integrated" was then among his favorite
        expressions.) Casting me a sharp look, he said, finally, "I will have to give a book a lot
        of thought."</p>
      <p>I was privately dubious if he would agree, for in the magazine interviews Malcolm X. had
        displayed what seemed almost a physical aversion to talking about himself, or anything else
        except the glories of the Black Muslim organization and its leader Elijah Muhammad. But the
        next weekend, I was highly surprised when Malcolm X. said simply, "I'll agree -- but I don't
        want to get one penny from it, I don't want anybody <fw>more</fw>
        <pb n="6" facs="haley.essay.06"/>
        <fw type="header_left">Haley</fw><fw type="header_right">page 6</fw> misinterpreting my
        motives." Then he said, "Now, my agreement to a book is subject to Mr. Muhammad's agreement,
        you'll have to ask him." I flew this time to Phoenix, Arizona, where Elijah Muhammad had a
        summer home for the dry climate's relief of his severe bronchial condition. He said that he
          <del rend="strikethrough">had</del> felt that "Allah approves," and back in New York
        Malcolm X. read the publisher's contract skeptically, signed it, and looked hard at me. "I
        want a writer -- not an interpreter," he said, and I asked him to personally pledge to me a
        priority quota of his time for the planned 100,000-word as-told-to <hi rend="underline"
          >Autobiography Of Malcolm X.</hi>" that would span his entire life.</p>
      <p>Over the next several weeks, I became ready to return to the publisher with news that I
        couldn't get Malcolm X. to talk of anything but the Black Muslims and their leader. I kept
        trying to impress upon my subject that <hi rend="underline">he</hi> was the subject, until
        he snapped, "Nobody puts words in my mouth." What little rapport between us had been gained
        with the magazine articles seemed <del rend="strikethrough">to have</del> to have
        evaporated. His visiting my Greenwich Village<ptr target="#note10" xml:id="nr10" n="10"/>
        studio three or four nights a week was the only positive note there was. He was skeptical of
        everything. He would walk in the door saying, "Testing! Testing!" for he was convinced
          <fw>more</fw>
        <pb n="7" facs="haley.essay.07"/>
        <fw type="header_left">Haley</fw><fw type="header_right">page 7</fw> that the F.B.I. had my
        studio "bugged." Another time, he arrived about fifteen minutes earlier than he had said he
        would, and he met a white friend of mine leaving; he acted as if it confirmed his worst
        suspicions.</p>
      <p>He would pace the floor, haranguing against whites in general and against the prominent
        Negroes who were attacking the Black Muslims. After having done the same thing all day,
        Malcolm X. was always tired when he arrived. Then my first break came one night when he was
        so fatigued he almost stumbled as he walked -- and for some reason I followed an impulse and
        out of the blue I asked him if he would tell me something about his mother.</p>
      <p>Malcolm X. stopped pacing, looking oddly at me. And incredibly to me he began to describe
        in an almost stream-of-consciousness manner the harrassed, distraught widow of his father
        trying to keep her home and children together on the outskirts of Lansing, Michigan. "--she
        was always standing over the stove, trying to stretch whatever we had to eat. We stayed so
        hungry that we were dizzy. I remember the color of dresses she used to wear -- they were a
        kind of faded-out gray . . ."<ptr target="#note11" xml:id="nr11" n="11"/></p>
      <p>From that night, Malcolm X. began volunteering to me the chronology of the boyhood years of
        his life, speaking grimly, <fw>more</fw>
        <pb n="8" facs="haley.essay.08"/>
        <fw type="header_left">Haley</fw><fw type="header_right">page 8</fw> as if it was a
        distasteful job he had contracted to do. I feared now a leaden narrative, but occasionally
        there would be flashes, glimpses, of some leavening lightness or humor. I remember so well,
        because it meant so much, the first honest laughter from Malcolm, in which I joined him. He
        was telling about how his older brother Philbert became a youthful boxer and he, Malcolm,
        envious, also signed up for an amateur bout. “I was really thirteen, but my height let me
        get away with claiming I was sixteen, the minimum age, and my weight of about 128 pounds got
        me a bantamweight classification.” He recalled that he was matched with “Bill Peterson,” a
        white novice. “The bell came, and I knew I was scared. Bill Peterson told me later on he was
        scared of me, too. He was so scared I was going to hurt him that he knocked me down fifty
        times if he did once.” Humiliated, Malcolm X. trained hard for a rematch with Peterson.
        “This time, the bell rang, I saw a fist, then the canvas coming up, and ten seconds later
        the referee was saying ‘<hi rend="underline">Ten</hi>!’ over me. I lay there, listening to
        the full count. I couldn't move, I'm not sure I wanted to move.” </p>
      <p> Other lightening glimpses into Malcolm X. came, such as that all of his life <del
          rend="strikethrough"><gap reason="illegible"/></del> he had feared dogs. “Every since I
        can remember, if I saw a dog no bigger than your hand, it looks <fw> more </fw>
        <pb n="9" facs="haley.essay.09"/>
        <fw type="header_left">Haley</fw><fw type="header_right">page 9 </fw> to me like a lion.
        Why, when later on I became a burglar, I wouldn't go near a house where I heard a dog.” And,
        on the subject of burglary, “Look, I'll tell you a better <del rend="strikethrough"><gap
            reason="illegible"/></del> thing than a dog to keep any burglars away. I'm talking from
        experience. Keep a light burning. And the best place is in the toilet. See, nobody could
        ever be sure if you were in there or not any time of the night, and a burglar knows if you
        are in there, you're especially quiet and you would hear the slightest unnatural noise he
        might make.” <ptr target="#note12" xml:id="nr12" n="12"/></p>
      <p> Malcolm X. was very difficult to keep confined to any specific area of subject. One thing
        mentioned would spark some other remembrance. He might mention, for instance, how pimps he
        had known had beaten up their women, and he would divert to his own childhood punishments.
        “Right then, from my mother, is where I learned one of the most important <del
          rend="strikethrough"><gap reason="illegible"/></del> lessons, to open my mouth and be
        heard. Whenever my mother even <hi rend="underline">started</hi> to raise her hand to hit
        me, I hollered so loud I alarmed the neighbors and she was so embarrassed she quit hitting
        me.”</p>
      <p>
        <del rend="strikethrough"><gap reason="illegible"/></del> It would appear on some occasions
        that Malcolm X. suddenly realized that he might have talked for a whole hour without once
        having lambasted the white man, and without <fw> more </fw>
        <pb n="10" facs="haley.essay.10"/>
        <fw type="header_left">Haley</fw><fw type="header_right">page 10 </fw> and other evident
        motivation, he would deliver a tirade. Once I asked him if in the world there was just one
        white person whom he favored. “None!” He was implacable. “Anytime a black man trust one, he
        makes a mistake -- look what they have already done to us!”</p>
      <p> Seguing on the subject of whom he trusted, Malcolm X. said he next least trusted women.
        “They are the quickest path to a man’s ruination,” and the downfalls of Adam and Samson he
        cited as examples.<ptr target="#note13" xml:id="n13" n="13"/> He said that he had told his
        wife he trusted her “only seventy-five percent.” He looked at me. "You I trust twenty-five
        percent." I must have looked taken aback and he eased the percentage somewhat by saying,
        “Why, I don't even trust <del rend="strikethrough"><gap reason="illegible"/></del> myself
        completely, I've seen too many men betray <del rend="strikethrough"><gap reason="illegible"
          /></del> themselves." The years in crime, then in prison, then in the closely-watched
        Black Muslims had taken a heavy toll on Malcolm X.'s faith in the human race. Time and again
        when I took notes rapidly as he delivered some verbal broadside, especially if it was
        directed at the white race, he would glower and exclaim, “You know that devil's not going to
        print that!” When I reminded him that a sizeable advance had been paid by the publisher who
        knew Malcolm X.'s philos<subst>
          <del rend="strikethrough">p</del>
          <add>o</add>
        </subst>phies before the book was contracted, he scoffed, “You studied in school
          <fw>more</fw>
        <pb n="11" facs="haley.essay.11"/>
        <fw type="header_left">Haley</fw><fw type="header_right">page 11 </fw> what the white man
        wants you taught to think about him. I studied him in the streets where you see the truth.” </p>
      <p> An overall awkward quality persisted in the interviewing with Malcolm X.'s penchant for
        abrupt changes of subject, and when he suggested that I might accompany him on some of his
        daily rounds, I jumped at the opportunity to talk with him out of the somewhat formal studio
        setting. It was like discovering an entirely different man on the Monday he said I could
        join what he called “my little rounds,” explaining that he physically mingled as often as he
        could with the “downtrodden black man in the slums” whom he talked <hi rend="underline"
          >with</hi> “while the other so-called black leaders just talk <hi rend="underline"
          >about</hi>.” <ptr target="#note14" xml:id="nr14" n="14"/></p>

      <p> Walking in the worst blocks in Harlem, Malcolm X. would exhult to me, “These are the black
        people down in the gutter where I came from,” and he was indeed regarded here as a symbol.
        He stopped and talked with dozens of individuals, usually salting his remarks with some
        subtle Black Muslim proselytizing. “White man wants you drunk, so he can put a club beside
        your head,” he might tell a sodden wino, or to Negro men with shiny “conked” hair. <ptr
          target="#note15" xml:id="n15" n="15"/>“Brother, that white devil has taught you to hate
        yourself so bad that you put hot lye in your hair to look more like <hi rend="underline"
          >his</hi> hair.” (Malcolm X. once had “conked” his hair <fw>more </fw>
        <pb n="12" facs="haley.essay.12"/>
        <fw type="header_left">Haley</fw><fw type="header_right">page 12 </fw> with hot lye for
        years; one night he gave me a graphic description of the intensely painful process.) The
        toothy, boyish grin and the well-known repartee charmed stoopfuls of women to the point that
        probably they would have marched behind <sic>Malcom</sic> X. to City Hall if he had asked
        them. The only ghetto residents whom Malcolm X. tended to avoid were the <del
          rend="strikethrough"><gap reason="illegible"/></del> quasi<subst>
          <del rend="strikethrough">-</del>
          <add>"</add>
        </subst>sharply” dressed hustlers such as he once had been. “I know what's in their heads.
        They figure <hi rend="underline">nobody</hi> can tell them anything, and they’re so ignorant
        that most of them couldn’t write a sentence, just like I couldn’t. They’re the most tragic
        figures in the ghetto -- and the most dangerous. They’ve got these fifteen and twenty dollar
        a day dope habits, they’re too ‘hip’ to do anything legitimate -- where do you think they
        get their livings from? Every human being they see is prey.”</p>

      <p> One day when Malcolm X. had asked me to go with him to Philadelphia, where he was to do a
        radio program, we rode in the <del rend="strikethrough"><gap reason="illegible"/></del>
        parlor car on a train (“I can get into trouble on an open coach,” he had said) and soon he
          <del rend="strikethrough"><gap reason="illegible"/></del> nudged me to notice a
        white-jacketed Negro porter who kept walking through the full car. “I forget his name,”
        whispered Malcolm X., <del rend="strikethrough"><gap reason="illegible"/></del> “but I used
        to work right on this train with him. He knows me -- he’s trying to make up his mind.”
        Shortly, Malcolm <del rend="strikethrough"><gap reason="illegible"/></del> leaned out in
        front of the <fw> more</fw>
        <pb n="13" facs="haley.essay.13"/>
        <fw type="header_left">Haley</fw><fw type="header_right">page 13 </fw> oncoming porter.
        “Why, <hi rend="underline">sure</hi> I know you!” the porter suddenly said very loudly. “You
        washed dishes right on this train. I was just telling some of the fellows you were here in
        my car. We all follow you!” </p>
      <p> In the parlor car filled with white passengers except for the three of us, the tension was
        nearly physical in feeling. After a few moments, the porter returned, introducing Malcolm X.
        to a young white passenger, who said loudly he had studied in the Orient and now was at
        Columbia University. “I admire your oratorical ability, but I don’t agree with everything
        you say,” he told Malcolm X. Malcolm X. was almost benevolent in manner, “Sir, I don't
        believe you could search America and find two men who are in agreement on everything.” </p>
      <p> Newspapers along the length of the car had lowered to just below eye-level when another
        white man, an older businessmen, came and shook Malcolm X.'s hand, and suddenly seemed to
        forget whatever he had intended to say. “Sir, I know how you feel,” Malcolm X. attempted a
        rescue. “It's a hard thing to speak when you are agreeing with so much that I <del
          rend="strikethrough"><gap reason="illegible"/></del> say.” The remainder of the way to New
        York, Malcolm X. and I were under a general open scrutiny.<ptr target="#note16"
          xml:id="nr16" n="16"/>
      </p>
      <p> It is not commonly recognized that some of Malcolm X.'s <fw> more</fw>
        <pb n="14" facs="haley.essay.14"/>
        <fw type="header_left">Haley</fw><fw type="header_right">page 14 </fw> most acid attacks
        were made against Negroes. (“The sickest man needs the strongest medicine,” is how he
        explained this.) His flayings of various Negro figures, and organizations, and some
        prevalent customs were almost daily, but generally he confined this to Negro community
        audiences. He rarely spoke at a Negro College without flinging into the teeth of the faculty
        his criticisms of “the so-called educated Negroes.” He would say flatly, “You have not been
        in the vanguard of helping your poor, ignorant black brothers.” He decried the dearth of
        Negro knowledge of <del rend="strikethrough"><gap reason="illegible"/></del> “the great
        history of the black race, extending back to antiquity. Why, if I was the president of this
        college, I’d hock <del rend="strikethrough"><gap reason="illegible"/></del> the campus if I
        had to, to send students to the Black Continent to dig up more artifacts that <hi
          rend="underline">prove</hi> our great history. You’re sitting here, and the white man is
        waking up -- he’s digging. Why, it's <del rend="strikethrough"><gap reason="illegible"
          /></del> gotten so an African elephant can't stumble without falling over some white man
        with a spade!” <ptr target="#note17" xml:id="nr17" n="17"/></p>
      <p> Exposed to any relatively affluent Negro audience, Malcolm X. would score them for “not
        supporting” <del rend="strikethrough"><gap reason="illegible"/></del> the Negro
        organizations. “You run to the surburbs. You don’t provide the help and leadership your poor
        brothers need, like the Jew does. However rich the Jew is, <del rend="strikethrough"><gap
            reason="illegible"/></del> he never forgets his brothers still in the ghetto. If he
          <fw>more </fw>
        <pb n="15" facs="haley.essay.15"/>
        <fw type="header_left">Haley</fw><fw type="header_right">page 15</fw> can't go and help
        personally, or send his wife, he at least donates money. But <hi rend="underline">you</hi>
        won't! That's why the black man’s organizations are controlled by the white man today,
        because the white man <hi rend="underline">supports</hi> them!"<ptr target="#note18"
          xml:id="nr18" n="18"/></p>
      <p>Traveling about with Malcolm X., more than one time I saw him deliberately goad into anger
        various officials of the ranking <del rend="strikethrough">Negro</del> organizations
        dedicated to Civil Rights. "--black bodies with white heads! The white man supports you and
        thus he controls you because he has your paycheck. The black man is the only group in this
        country who has allowed other people to be at the head of his organization!" I believe I am
        correct that of the major Negro leaders, the two whom Malcolm X. most admired -- one openly
        and the other covertly -- were Congressman Adam Clayton Powell<ptr target="#note19"
          xml:id="nr19" n="19"/> and The Reverend Martin Luther King.<ptr target="#note20"
          xml:id="nr20" n="20"/> Of Congressman Powell, Malcolm X. told me, "He hasn't let Congress
        make him forget what it is to get out and organize on the streets. He knows that to change
        the black man's situation, you've got to give him an example of standing up to the white
        man. Though Malcolm X. often took public digs on Dr. King, he told me "You've got to admire
        his coolness under fire. The only thing I wish is that his hero was some of the old labor
        leaders instead <fw>more</fw>
        <pb n="16" facs="haley.essay.16"/>
        <fw type="header_left">Haley</fw><fw type="header_right">page 16</fw> of Mahatma Gandhi.<ptr
          target="#note21" xml:id="nr21" n="21"/> Look what changes King could bring! Look at how
        labor was being called scum, radicals and anarchists back in the Thirties, but look now,
        what's happened because they weren't non-violent. Today, labor has a lobby building
        overlooking the White House, and labor sits down with management and bargains as
          equals."<ptr target="#note22" xml:id="nr22" n="22"/></p>
      <p>Malcolm X's criticisms <add place="above">/among his own race</add> ranged on one occasion
        to nearly physical assault. His car screeched to a stop one day as we drove along 136th
        Street, between Lenox and Seventh Avenues. Malcolm X. bounded and among about six huddled
        Negro teen-agers like an avenging devil. "You here shooting craps, and <hi rend="underline"
          >inside</hi> these doors whites your age are studying about you!" The teen-agers who were
        cowed thoroughly by the man they <del rend="strikethrough"><gap reason="illegible"/></del>
        instantly recognized had been shooting dice against the doorway of the Countee Cullen public
        library branch which houses the great Schomberg Collection, the largest in the world of
        literature about and by Negroes.<ptr target="#note23" xml:id="nr23" n="23"/> Malcolm X. was
        furious when he returned to the car. He said, "I just saw red when I saw that!"</p>
      <p>Malcolm X. was deeply intrigued with centers of culture of any sort. He had a fetish for
        learning. Especially he favored museums, and several times we walked about in the
          <fw>more</fw>
        <pb n="17" facs="haley.essay.17"/>
        <fw type="header_left">Haley</fw><fw type="header_right">page 17</fw> Egyptian Room of the
        Metropolitan Museum.<ptr target="#note24" xml:id="nr24" n="24"/> "I feel like I'm among my
        ancestors in here," he said. "This is black art that predates Christianity by thousands of
        years. If I could do it, I'd have black schoolchildren in here every day, by the
        busloads."</p>
      <p>The eight-grade cessation of his own education probably was Malcolm X's bitterest single
        reminiscence during his narrative of his entire life story. He had been an outstanding
        student in the Mason, Michigan, High School, where he was the only Negro in his class, and
        he was elected the class president. But a class counselor -- who was fond of him -- advised
        him to forget the desire he expressed to become a lawyer, and to become a carpenter instead.
        "I often think about this, I guess it was the most crucial point in my life," said Malcolm
        X., as wistfully as he ever became. "He wasn't against me, in fact he was thinking he was
        helping me, because all he could see was a black boy, not a mind that wanted to develop. If
        he hadn't said what he did, I probably would have been a lawyer today. Because when I went
        to Boston, as badly as my sister Ella<ptr target="#note25" xml:id="nr25" n="25"/> wanted our
        family to be somebody, why, Ella would have <del rend="strikethrough"><gap
            reason="illegible"/></del> taken in washings if she'd had to, to <del
          rend="strikethrough"><gap reason="illegible"/></del> get me in Harvard Law School and put
        me through there."</p>
      <fw>more</fw>
      <pb n="18" facs="haley.essay.18"/>


      <fw type="header_left">Haley</fw>
      <fw type="header_right">page 18</fw>
      <p>The eventual additional education that equipped the Malcolm X. who brilliantly debated some
        of America's top minds in communications and academic circles was gained through his years
        of reading as a convict in prisons. I think that some of <del rend="strikethrough"><gap
            reason="illegible"/></del><add rend="typed" place="above">the</add> most intimate
        glimpses into himself that <del rend="strikethrough"><gap reason="illegible"/></del> Malcolm
        X. ever presented were in the area of his yearning to be better formally educated. "You can
        believe me," he <del rend="strikethrough"><gap reason="illegible"/></del> says in the last
        chapter of his book, "if I had the time right now, I would not be one bit ashamed to go back
        into any New York City public school and start where I left off at the ninth grade, and go
        on through to a degree. ... I would just like to <hi rend="underline">study</hi>. I mean
        ranging study, because I have a wide-open mind ... I do believe that I might have made a
        good lawyer, I have always loved verbal battle, and challenge ...."</p>
      <p>I particularly remember the occasion of Malcolm X.'s telling me this. I had accompanied him
        to the Kennedy Airport where he took a jet to Los Angeles. Waiting for the plane's
        departure, he had been talking about Shakespeare. "In my opinion, in "Hamlet," Shakespeare
        summed up this whole violence versus non-violence issue today," said Malcolm X.<ptr
          target="#note26" xml:id="nr26" n="26"/> "To be or not to be, that is the question. Whether
        it is noble in the <fw>more</fw>
        <pb n="19" facs="haley.essay.19"/>
        <fw type="header_left">Haley</fw><fw type="header_right">page 19</fw> mind of man to suffer
        the slings and arrows of outrageous fortune, or to take up arms against a sea of
        trouble--"</p>
      <p>I remember that at 4 a.m. in the <del rend="strikethrough">mor</del> next morning, New York
        time, my telephone rang, wakening me, and Malcolm X.'s voice said "I trust you seventy
        percent," and he hung up. It warmed me, knowing Malcolm X. (Neither of us ever again
        mentioned it.)<ptr target="#note27" xml:id="nr27" n="27"/>
      </p>
      <p>Malcolm X.'s attitude toward white people had begun to change within himself, I believe,
        well before his break came with the Black Muslim organization, or his subsequent trip to
        Mecca, which is generally identified with his alteration of previous racist views. I feel
        certain that what brought about the change was his cumulative direct contact with whites,
        chiefly in the communications fields, and in college and university audiences, who exhibited
        their respect for him as a highly intelligent individual, notwithstanding his anti-white
        statements. He said to me once what I knew was a highly significant statement from him,
        speaking of four radio or television program hosts <del rend="strikethrough"><gap
            reason="illegible"/></del> whose shows he had returned to many times, Irv Kupcinet<ptr
          target="#note28" xml:id="nr28" n="28"/> in Chicago and in New York Barry Farber,<ptr
          target="#note29" xml:id="nr29" n="29"/> Barry Gray<ptr target="#note30" xml:id="nr30"
          n="30"/> and Mike Wallace.<ptr target="#note31" xml:id="nr31" n="31"/> "I like them
        because they let me see they respect my mind," Malcolm X. told me <del rend="strikethrough"
            ><gap reason="illegible"/></del>
        <fw>more</fw>
        <pb n="20" facs="haley.essay.20"/>
        <fw type="header_left">Haley</fw><fw type="header_right">page 20</fw> "The way I know that
        is they ask my opinion <del rend="strikethrough"><gap reason="illegible"/></del> on subjects
        off the race issue. You see, most whites, even when they credit a Negro with some
        intelligence, never feel that Negro can contribute something to other areas of thought, and
        ideas. You just notice how rarely you will ever hear whites asking any Negroes what they
        think about the problem of world health, or the space race to land men on the moon." </p>
      <p>And I saw Malcolm X. hugely enjoying question-and-answer session give and take after
        college lectures too many times to ever accept that he nurtured a congenital white hatred.
        He <hi rend="underline">loved</hi>
        <del rend="strikethrough"><gap reason="illegible"/></del> to maneuver the white students
        into his standard verbal traps, then to sting them with his practiced arrows. "You took away
        our names, gave us <hi rend="underline">your</hi> names. You hear somebody say "How are you,
        Murphy?"; Naturally you're expecting a white man. What does some black man look like named
        Murphy?" He <hi rend="underline">loved</hi> it when members of white student <del
          rend="strikethrough"><gap reason="illegible"/></del> audiences stood up and managed to
        maneuver him into tight spots, where he had to call upon all of his arsenal of verbal
        dexterity to extricate himself. And the most familiar tight spot that I heard students get
        him into was queries, variously put, of <hi rend="underline">how</hi> could he, with <hi
          rend="underline">his</hi> mind, <hi rend="underline">believe</hi> all of the things he
        said in the service of Elijah Muhammad? Generally, <sic>Malcom</sic> X. would throw out a
        torrent of words. And <fw>more</fw>
        <pb n="21" facs="haley.essay.21"/>
        <fw type="header_left">Haley</fw><fw type="header_right">page 21</fw> I think that the time
        I ever saw Malcolm X. most "put down" in all of the two years that I knew him was after such
        a peroration of his in response to a question from a small, blonde-haired slip of a co-ed.
        When he finished, she stood up and said clearly, "Mr. Malcolm X., methinks you doth protest
        too much." Malcolm X.'s mouth worked, but no words emerged. He quickly nodded to someone
        else who was waving a hand to ask a question. But the girl's touche hung in the atmosphere,
        and he, and I, and everyone present knew it.<ptr target="#note32" xml:id="nr32" n="32"/>
      </p>
      <lb/>
      <p>When I occasionally made trips involved in writing magazine assignments, Malcolm X., in
        open camaraderie now, would ask me always to telephone him when I would be returning to New
        York. If he could squeeze it into his schedule, he would meet me at the airport. And for my
        part, I always found <del rend="strikethrough"><gap reason="illegible"/></del> myself
        anxious to return, for the whole sweep of the story of his life had become to me
        fascinating, and each next interview seemed to add some little extra.</p>

      <p> Then once when I was thus returning, Malcolm X. asked me as we drove into New York, "Look,
        you get around -- have you heard anything?"<ptr target="#note33" xml:id="nr33" n="33"/></p>
      <p>I had no idea what he was getting at, and I said so, and <fw>more</fw>
        <pb n="22" facs="haley.essay.22"/>
        <fw type="header_left">Haley</fw><fw type="header_right">page 22</fw> instantly he shifted
        the subject, leaving me wondering. But I had learned never to press him on any issue. (Long
        before, some persistence of mine had prompted from him a sharp "If I want you to know
        something, I’ll tell you.") I had learned that my best clue to whatever Malcolm X. had meant
        would likely reveal itself through his scribbling habit.</p>
      <p>For months I had collected paper napkins, edges of newspapers, and other pieces of paper on
        which Malcolm X. compulsively scribbled as he talked, then left lying around. They had
        always given me clues to the stream of his thinking. Here are some examples: "Here lies a
        YM, killed by a BM, fighting for the WM, who killed all the RM." (A decoding wasn't
        difficult, knowing Malcolm X. "YM" was for yellow man; "BM" for black man, "WM" for white
        man, and "RM" was for red man.) Another: "The louder WM yelps, more I know I have struck a
        nerve." Another: "BM took 2nd-class so long WM came to accept it as air he breathes."
        Another: "WM so quick to tell BM 'Look what I have done for you!' No! Look what you have
        done <hi rend="underline">to</hi> us!" Or "BM dealing with WM who put our eyes out, now
        condemns us because we cannot see." Or, "If BM as successful building factories as churches,
        what a difference today!"</p>
      <p>I did not have to wait long before my clue came. On a paper napkin served with coffee,
        Malcolm X. scribbled, "My life has always been one of changes."</p>
      <fw>more</fw>

      <pb n="23" facs="haley.essay.23"/>


      <fw type="header_left">Haley</fw>
      <fw type="header_right">page 23</fw>
      <p>I knew that Malcolm X. had something in mind that was of major consequence to him. But my
        wildest speculation would not have anticipated what was about to happen.</p>
      <p>It is generally well-known that Elijah Muhammad publicly announced the suspension of
        Malcolm X. for his having made the statement that he viewed the assassination of the late
        President J. F. Kennedy as "chickens coming home to roost."<ptr target="#note34"
          xml:id="nr34" n="34"/></p>
      <p>Talking with me about it later, Malcolm X. ranged between bitterness and fury, which he
        managed to keep reasonably guarded in most <del rend="strikethrough"><gap reason="illegible"
          /></del>of his public utterances. "I’ve been a street hustler," he said, the back of his
          <del rend="strikethrough"><gap reason="illegible"/></del> neck and his whole faced flushed
        reddish with his anger, "I know when I’m being set up. I’ve said plenty of hotter things
        than that, <del rend="strikethrough"><gap reason="illegible"/></del> and Chicago never
        objected. And look how the press jumps on me when every commentator in the country has said
        the same thing I said. Or take that book of Victor Lasky's<ptr target="#note35"
          xml:id="nr35" n="35"/> -- it has been called outright lies about Kennedy, but they made
        his book into a best-seller!"</p>
      <p>Suspended from any public appearances or <del rend="strikethrough"><gap reason="illegible"
          /></del> from any utterances in the name of the Black Muslims, Malcolm X. chafed at the
        bit, and it was in this time that he and his wife, "Sister Betty"<ptr target="#note36"
          xml:id="nr36" n="36"/> and their then three children were invited <fw>more</fw>
        <pb n="24" facs="haley.essay.24"/>
        <fw type="header_left">Haley</fw><fw type="header_right">page 24</fw> by Cassius Clay to his
        Miami training camp for the first fight against Sonny Liston.<ptr target="#note37"
          xml:id="nr37" n="37"/> Malcolm X. later told me that he was most grateful -- it was
        something to <hi rend="underline">do</hi>. He and Clay had met over a year before in
        Detroit, and Clay had become one of the few Muslims whom Malcolm X. had ever accepted as a
        close <hi rend="underline">personal</hi> friend. Several times he had spoken of Clay to me
        with a warmth rare for Malcolm X. I got postal cards from Malcolm X. in Miami, and in one
        telephone call he told me "I'm not a betting man, but if you are put some money on Cassius,
        and you can get rich." I read in the papers that Malcolm X. <del rend="strikethrough"><gap
            reason="illegible"/></del> was functioning as Clay’s "spiritual advisor." I heard from a
        friend in Miami that the two had daily walks after Clay’s training day was over. Then, the
        night of the gigantic upset, Malcolm X. telephoned me, his voice all but crowing, "What did
        I tell you?" He said that it had been probably the quietest new-champion party in history,
        that at that moment <del rend="strikethrough"><gap reason="illegible"/></del> "Champion
        Cassius" was asleep on his (Malcolm X.’s) bed, "catching a nap."</p>
      <p>Soon, Malcolm X. was <del rend="strikethrough"><gap reason="illegible"/></del>squiring Clay
        about in New York at the United Nations and other places. I saw Malcolm X. but little during
        this time, but he sounded <del rend="strikethrough">a</del> happy in his role when we talked
        on the telephone. Then, abruptly, something <fw>more</fw>
        <pb n="25" facs="haley.essay.25"/>
        <fw type="header_left">Haley</fw><fw type="header_right">page 25</fw> caused Clay to reject
        Malcolm X., transferring his total allegiance to Elijah Muhammad. I believed that the most
        hurt that I ever saw Malcolm X. revealed to me -- aside from his suspension by the Black
        Muslims -- was regarding Clay. "I felt like a blood big-brother to him," he said slowly. And
        carefully considering the words in advance. "I still do. I'm not against him. He's a fine
        young man. Smart. <ptr target="#note38" xml:id="nr38" n="38"/><del rend="strikethrough">
          <gap reason="illegible"/>
        </del> He's just let himself be used -- led astray." </p>

      <p> Malcolm X. next went to Mecca where he performed the Hajj Pilgrimage,<ptr target="#note39"
          xml:id="nr39" n="39"/> and after visiting in <del rend="strikethrough">
          <gap reason="illegible"/>
        </del> some of the emerging African states, he returned to America, presenting himself as
        now a true orthodox Moslem.<ptr target="#note40" xml:id="nr40" n="40"/> Almost with shock, I
        had received the letter he had written me on blue stationery containing the words so
        incredible for Malcolm X.: "--During the past eleven days here in the Muslim world, I have
        eaten from the same plate, drunk from the same glass, and slept in the same bed (or on the
        same rug) –- while praying to the same God –- with fellow Muslims, whose eyes were the
        bluest of blue, whose hair was the blondest of blond, and whose skin was the whitest of
        white, and we were truly all the same (brothers) . . . ” </p>

      <p> Another copy of the letter had been published across America. And Malcolm X., now calling
        himself “El Hajj El Malik <fw>more</fw>
        <pb n="26" facs="haley.essay.26"/>
        <fw type="header_left">Haley</fw><fw type="header_right">page 26</fw> El Shabazz,” entered
        now, when I reflect upon it, the final trail of problems and harassments that would plague
        him to his death. </p>
      <p> From the first stages of his interviews, he had spoken often about his anticipation of a
        violent death. “All <del rend="strikethrough">
          <gap reason="illegible"/>
        </del> of my father’s brothers but one died violently,” <ptr target="#note41" xml:id="nr41"
          n="41"/>he had said. “I never expect to live to be an old man.” Now, when the first death
        threats to him were publicly reported, one day in the Americana Hotel he leaned forward and
        touched the bed. “If I’m alive when this book is published, it will be a miracle,” he said.
        “I’m not saying that in any distress. I’m just saying it like I say that’s a bedspread.” </p>
      <p> Angered and goaded, Malcolm X. began to speak bitterly and accusingly in public about the
        “immorality” of Elijah Muhammad.<ptr target="#note42" xml:id="nr42" n="42"/> Malcolm X. told
        me once in strictest confidence that he had been to a doctor in Long Island and asked for a
        brain examination, fearing for his sanity, because <del rend="strikethrough">a</del>the
        shock of <del rend="strikethrough">expulsion</del> his “betrayal” by the Muslim leader had
        been so great. Later, Malcolm X. said, “You can go ahead and use that in the book, I want it
        to be the whole story.” </p>
      <p> Causing Malcolm X. not much less worry was the establishment of the new public image that
        he wanted. He had formed two new <fw>more</fw>
        <pb n="27" facs="haley.essay.27"/>
        <fw type="header_left">Haley</fw><fw type="header_right">page 27</fw> organizations, a
        "Muslim Mosque, Inc.", religious in nature, and an Organization for Afro-American " Unity"
        which offered a Black Nationalism program.<ptr target="#note43" xml:id="nr43" n="43"/> But
        both whites and Negroes were either flatly disbelieving that Malcolm X. was any different in
        his beliefs, or they were confused about what he <hi rend="underline">now</hi> believed.
        There is more than a little reason to believe that Malcolm X. himself was confused. "I am
        man enough to admit that I can't put my finger on exactly what my philosophy is now," he
        told one writer in an interview not published until after his death. "But I'm <hi
          rend="underline">flexible</hi>." </p>
      <p> At Kennedy Airport,<ptr target="#note44" xml:id="nr44" n="44"/> waiting with me for my
        plane <del rend="strikethrough">
          <gap reason="illegible"/>
        </del>to an upstate New York city, Malcolm X. told me how he was finding <add place="above"
          >that</add> the "so-called moderate" civil-rights organizations were avoiding him as "too
        militant" and the "so-called militants" shunned him as "too moderate." He exclaimed, "They
        won't let me turn the corner! I'm caught in a trap!" </p>
      <p> When I left Malcolm X. there to drive out of the parking lot when I went to catch my
        plane, we waved at each other--and it was the last time I would ever see him alive. </p>
      <p> The "trap" that Malcolm X. was in kept closing around him tighter. He telephoned me
        upstate, telling me that the court had ordered him to be evicted from the home which he had
        occupied for <fw>more</fw>
        <pb n="28" facs="haley.essay.28"/>
        <fw type="header_left">Haley</fw><fw type="header_right">page 28</fw> years: the home
        legally belonged <del rend="strikethrough">the</del>to the Black Muslim organization, which
        had successfully sued for its return.<ptr target="#note45" xml:id="nr45" n="45"/> "My nerves
        are shot--my brains tired, Haley," Malcolm X. said, the first time I had heard him ever say
        anything like that. He said I had spoken of the quiet town where I lived;<ptr
          target="#note46" xml:id="nr46" n="46"/> he asked if he might visit for a weekend. "Just a
        couple of days of peace and quiet, that's what I need." <del rend="strikethrough">
          <gap reason="illegible"/>
        </del>He said that he would like to read through the full book manuscript once more. I said
        that he knew he was most welcome to visit, but he shouldn't tax himself with another reading
        as only very minor editing changes had been made in the manuscript since he last read it. He
        said "I just want to read it again. I don't expect to be alive to read the finished book." </p>
      <p> The weekend that Malcolm X. said he would like to come and have a restful visit was,
        ironically, the Saturday and Sunday of 21-22 February, 1965. The subsequent bombing of his
          home,<ptr target="#note47" xml:id="nr47" n="47"/> and myriad other nerve-wracking
        complications threw his plans so askew that he couldn't make it. He telephoned me once
        again, that Saturday afternoon. He said he had only $150 and he wondered if the publisher
        could advance him a down payment for a new home<ptr target="#note48" xml:id="nr48" n="48"/>
        for his family. "You know nobody will <hi rend="underline">rent</hi>, not <fw>more</fw>
        <pb n="29" facs="haley.essay.29"/>
        <fw type="header_left">Haley</fw><fw type="header_right">page 29</fw> to <hi
          rend="underline">me</hi>!" he tried to chuckle. I said I would have our agent check on
        Monday, and I <del rend="strikethrough">
          <gap reason="illegible"/>
        </del> would telephone him back Monday night. </p>
      <p> But on Sunday afternoon, the killers got to Malcolm X. as he started to speak to an
        audience in the Audubon Ballroom in Harlem.<ptr target="#note49" xml:id="nr49" n="49"/>
        There ensued a week of the greatest news coverage of a death that America had seen since the
        assassination of a beloved young President.<ptr target="#note50" xml:id="nr50" n="50"/> I
        went and I looked down upon the waxy, dead face surrounded by linen Moslem burial dress. All
        I could seem to think was "Well -- goodbye, Malcolm!" And a policeman on guard <del
          rend="strikethrough">
          <gap reason="illegible"/>
        </del> motioned for me to move on, and I did. </p>

      <fw>-- the end --</fw>





    </body>
    <back>
      <div type="notes">
        <note xml:id="note1">Haley summarizes X's life in this passage. Harlem, New York City, is an
          important black cultural center, rising in fame during the 1920s and '30s, the period of
          the Harlem Renaissance.</note>
        <note xml:id="note2">Elijah Muhammad (1934-1975) was the leader of the Nation of Islam. </note>
        <note xml:id="note3">Malcolm X's notoriety began with the 1959 television documentary
            <emph>The Hate That Hate Produced</emph>. </note>
        <note xml:id="note4">Alex Haley maintained that Malcolm X evolved to have a more inclusive
          understanding of race. Manning Marable, in his biography, <emph>Malcolm X: A Life of
            Reinvention</emph>, takes issue with this representation of X. </note>
        <note xml:id="note5">The all-male military wing of the Nation of Islam.</note>
        <note xml:id="note6">Haley refers to the 1957 Johnson X Hinton incident, during which Hinton
          tried to intercede in a police beating. The police turned on Hinton and he was beaten and
          arrested. Malcolm X led the Fruit of Islam to the police station and demanded medical
          treatment for Hinton. Malcolm X's control over the crowd led to the start of his
          surveillance by the New York Police Department and the rise of his national prominence
          (see Marable, <emph>Malcolm X</emph>, 127-29). </note>
        <note xml:id="note7">Malcolm X insisted that Haley receive permission from Elijah Muhammad
          prior to beginning the book (<emph>The Autobiography</emph>, 386).</note>
        <note xml:id="note8">Haley wrote "Mr. Mohammad Speaks," published in <emph>Reader's
            Digest,</emph> and a joint-authored piece titled "Black Merchants of Hate" for the
            <emph>Saturday Evening Post</emph> (see Marable, <emph>Malcolm X</emph>, 220).</note>
        <note xml:id="note9">The book publisher referenced in this passage was Doubleday, who signed
          a contract with Haley and X for $20,000 on May 27, 1963 (Marable, <emph>Malcolm X</emph>,
          247). </note>
        <note xml:id="note10">Haley was living in an apartment in Greenwich Village, a neighborhood
          in New York City.</note>
        <note xml:id="note11">Haley recounts these events in the epilogue of <emph>The
            Autobiography</emph>.</note>
        <note xml:id="note12">Haley includes this anecdote in both <emph>The Autobiography</emph>
          (144) and "The Malcolm X I Knew."</note>
        <note xml:id="note13">X references the biblical stories of Adam, who is tempted by Eve,
          causing the fall of man, and Samson, who is tricked into betraying the source of his
          strength by Delilah, as examples of women causing the downfall of men.</note>
        <note xml:id="note14">Haley writes of X making "my little daily rounds" in Harlem to focused
          on "the black man down in the gutter where I came from" (<emph>The Autobiography</emph>
          402).</note>
        <note xml:id="note15">Conking is a form of hair straightening that uses lye. </note>
        <note xml:id="note16">Haley references the train ride he took to Philadelphia with Malcolm X
          in both <emph>The Autobiography</emph> (397) and "The Malcolm X I Knew" (12-13).</note>
        <note xml:id="note17">The exclusion and incompleteness of African Americans from U.S.
          history is of great concern to Malcolm X. See the chapter "Saved" in <emph>The
            Autobiography</emph>.</note>
        <note xml:id="note18">X is probably referring to the NAACP (National Association for the
          Advancement of Colored People), an interracial group promoting civil rights. </note>
        <note xml:id="note19">Adam Clayton Powell (1908-1972) was an African American politician and
          preacher who represented New York in the U.S. House of Representatives.</note>
        <note xml:id="note20">Martin Luther King (1929-1968) was a Civil Rights activist often
          contrasted with X due to King's nonviolent strategies.</note>
        <note xml:id="note21">Mahatma Gandhi (1869-1948) was the leader of Indian nationalism who
          advocated nonviolent civil disobedience.</note>
        <note xml:id="note22">X is referring to the Department of Labor building in Washington,
          DC.</note>
        <note xml:id="note23">The Countee Cullen Library is a branch of the New York Public Library.
          Named after Harlem Renaissance author Countee Cullen, the library houses African American
          collections including the Schomburg Collection. </note>
        <note xml:id="note24">The Metropolitan Museum of Art, housed in New York, has an extensive
          Egyptian collection.</note>
        <note xml:id="note25">When asked what he wants to be, X tells his teacher, Mr. Ostrowski,
          that he wants to be a lawyer. His teacher replies, "A lawyer--that's no realistic goal for
          a nigger," instead suggesting carpentry (<emph>The Autobiography</emph>, 36). X says this
          incident changed him. In "The Malcolm X I Knew," X notes that Ella would have taken in
          washing to send him to law school. Ella Collins (1913-1996) was the half-sister of Malcolm
          X.</note>
        <note xml:id="note26">The play <emph>Hamlet</emph>, written by William Shakespeare.</note>
        <note xml:id="note27">Haley references this conversation in <emph>The Autobiography</emph>,
          (400).</note>
        <note xml:id="note28">Irv Kupcinet (1912-2003) was a columnist for the <emph>Chicago Sun
            Times</emph> and a television host. X appeared on <emph>Kup's Show</emph>, a television
          show on Chicago's Channel 7.</note>
        <note xml:id="note29">Barry Farber (1930-) is a radio host who, during X's life, worked in
          New York City. X appeared on the <emph>Barry Farber Show</emph> in 1963.</note>
        <note xml:id="note30">Barry Gray (1916-1996) was the radio host of the <emph>Barry
            Gray Show</emph> on New York's WMCA. He interviewed X on the <emph>Barry Gray
            Show</emph> several times.</note>
        <note xml:id="note31">Mike Wallace (1918-2012) was a radio and later television journalist
          who interviewed X in 1964 on the <emph>Mike Wallace News Program</emph>. </note>
        <note xml:id="note32">Haley discusses X's interest in debating with whites who treated him
          intelligently, as well as the coed's "putdown," in <emph>The Autobiography</emph>, (286). </note>
        <note xml:id="note33">This quote appears in <emph>The Autobiography</emph> (404). Haley attributes
          this question to X's fear of retribution after his break with the Nation of Islam.</note>
        <note xml:id="note34">Malcolm X called John F. Kennedy's 1963 assassination "chickens coming
          home to roost."</note>
        <note xml:id="note35">Lasky wrote the 1963 book <emph>JFK: The Man and the Myth</emph>, a
          negative take on Kennedy. </note>
        <note xml:id="note36">Sister Betty is Betty Shabazz (1934-1997), Malcolm X's wife.</note>
        <note xml:id="note37">Cassius Clay, or Muhammad Ali (1942- ), boxed Sonny Liston (1932-1970)
          on February 25, 1964. Clay was declared the winner by technical knockout.</note>
        <note xml:id="note38">Malcolm X had a close relationship to Cassius Clay (Muhammad Ali).
          When X split with the Nation of Islam, Clay cut off ties with him.</note>
        <note xml:id="note39">The Hajj pilgrimage is a yearly journey to Mecca conducted by
          Muslims.</note>
        <note xml:id="note40">Upon X's return from Mecca he claims that he has converted to Orthodox
          Islam.</note>
        <note xml:id="note41"> X believed that his father and three of his father's brothers were
          killed in racist attacks.</note>
        <note xml:id="note42">X had learned that Elijah Muhammad had extramarital affairs and
          fathered several children, a direct violation of Nation of Islam law. </note>
        <note xml:id="note43">After his break with the Nation of Islam, Malcolm X formed "Muslim
          Mosque, Inc." and the OAAU, the Organization for Afro-American Unity.</note>
        <note xml:id="note44">Kennedy Airport is John F. Kennedy Airport in New York City.</note>
        <note xml:id="note45">The Nation of Islam claimed to own the house that Malcolm X and his
          family lived in, successfully suing for repossession after X's break with the group.</note>
        <note xml:id="note46">X is probably referring to Haley's move to Rome, New York.</note>
        <note xml:id="note47">Malcolm X's home was firebombed February 14, 1965, the night before
          his family was to be evicted. No one was injured.</note>
        <note xml:id="note48">Malcolm X had very few funds after his break from the Nation of Islam. He borrowed
          a downpayment for a house from his sister Ella.</note>
        <note xml:id="note49">The Audubon Ballroom is located in Washington Heights, New York City.
          Malcolm's OAAU held regular meetings at the ballroom.</note>
        <note xml:id="note50">Haley is referring to the assassination of John F. Kennedy.</note>


      </div>
    </back>
  </text>
</TEI>
